<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?><rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.epa.gov/feed/79235/rss.xml" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/" xmlns:og="http://ogp.me/ns#" xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#" xmlns:sioc="http://rdfs.org/sioc/ns#" xmlns:sioct="http://rdfs.org/sioc/types#" xmlns:skos="http://www.w3.org/2004/02/skos/core#" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#">
  <channel>
    <title>EPA Center for Corporate Climate Leadership</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/feed/79235/rss.xml</link>
    <description>Updated EPA Center for Corporate Climate Leadership content from the US Environmental Protection Agency</description>
    <language>en</language>
     <atom:link href="https://www.epa.gov/feed/79235/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      <item>
    <title>Partnership and Technical Assistance Programs</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/climateleadership/partnership-and-technical-assistance-programs</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;Many suppliers, especially smaller ones, are unaware of programs that could help them reduce emissions; suppliers would benefit from learning about such programs from their customers. Various voluntary EPA programs that support companies in reducing GHG emissions have seen suppliers join after being encouraged to do so by their customers who are also active participants. Programs that provide suppliers with public recognition for their achievements in reducing GHG emissions can spur continuous improvement by promoting healthy competition among organizations to differentiate themselves from their competitors based on their environmental performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.energystar.gov/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;ENERGY STAR&lt;/a&gt;: Through its partnerships with more than 20,000 private and public sector organizations, EPA&#039;s ENERGY STAR program delivers the technical information and tools that organizations and consumers need to choose energy-efficient solutions and best management practices.

		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.energystar.gov/buildings&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Buildings &amp;amp; Plants&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.energystar.gov/portfoliomanager&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;ENERGY STAR&#039;s Portfolio Manager&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.energystar.gov/smallbiz&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Small Businesses&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.energystar.gov/index.cfm?fuseaction=find_a_product&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Products&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/greenpower&quot;&gt;EPA&#039;s Green Power Partnership&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span&gt;is a voluntary program that encourages organizations to use green power as a way to reduce the environmental impacts associated with conventional electricity use. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/smartway/index.htm&quot;&gt;EPA&#039;s SmartWay&lt;/a&gt; provides tools, data, and standards for measuring, benchmarking, and improving environmental performance in freight supply chains and shipping.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/e3&quot;&gt;E3: Economy, Energy, Environment&lt;/a&gt; is a technical assistance framework helping communities, manufacturers, and manufacturing supply chains reduce pollution and energy use.
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;/e3/about-e3s-green-suppliers-network&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Green Suppliers Network&lt;/a&gt; conducts customized technical assessment of production processes and small and medium-sized manufacturing facilities to help reduce waste and operate more efficiently.&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/chp&quot;&gt;EPA&#039;s Combined Heat and Power (CHP) Partnership&lt;/a&gt; seeks to reduce emissions from electric power generation by increasing the use of CHP. CHP is on-site electricity generation that captures the heat that would otherwise be wasted in conventional generation to provide useful thermal energy—such as steam or hot water—that can be used for space heating, cooling, domestic hot water and industrial processes.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://energy.gov/eere/amo/advanced-manufacturing-office&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The Department of Energy&#039;s Advanced Manufacturing Office&lt;/a&gt; provides a variety of programs that identify opportunities for integrating energy-efficiency measures into industrial facilities.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;EPA’s Center for Corporate Climate Leadership serves as a resource center for all organizations looking to expand their work in the area of greenhouse gas (GHG) measurement and management. The Center organizes the &lt;a href=&quot;/climateleadership/climate-leadership-awards&quot;&gt;Climate Leadership Awards&lt;/a&gt;, which recognize exemplary corporate, organizational, and individual leadership in addressing climate change by reducing carbon pollution and implementing adaptation planning initiatives.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;CDP provides recognition for suppliers and companies who disclose GHG emissions through the &lt;a href=&quot;https://b8f65cb373b1b7b15feb-c70d8ead6ced550b4d987d7c03fcdd1d.ssl.cf3.rackcdn.com/cms/reports/documents/000/001/228/original/CDP_Climate_Change_Report_2016.pdf?1477993118#page=41&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Climate Change A-List&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://b8f65cb373b1b7b15feb-c70d8ead6ced550b4d987d7c03fcdd1d.ssl.cf3.rackcdn.com/cms/reports/documents/000/000/577/original/CDP-Supply-Chain-Report-2016.pdf?1469807996#page=32&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Supplier A-List.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;In addition, many states and local utilities offer rebate programs that allow suppliers to recoup some of the upfront costs associated with improving energy efficiency and reducing GHG emissions. The &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dsireusa.org/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Database of State Incentives for Renewables &amp;amp; Efficiency&lt;/a&gt; provides a clearinghouse for many of these programs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 08 Nov 2016 18:22:14 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>xsyardle</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">164853 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Scope 3 Inventory Guidance</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/climateleadership/scope-3-inventory-guidance</link>
    <description>&lt;h3&gt;On this page&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Description of Scope 3 Emissions&quot;&gt;Description of Scope 3 Emissions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Scope 3 Resources&quot;&gt;Scope 3 Resources&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Scope 3 Emission Factors&quot;&gt;Scope 3 Emission Factors&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;Description of Scope 3 Emissions&quot; id=&quot;Description of Scope 3 Emissions&quot;&gt;Description of Scope 3 Emissions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scope 3 emissions are the result of activities from assets not owned or controlled by the reporting organization, but that the organization indirectly impacts in its value chain. Scope 3 emissions include all sources not within an organization’s scope 1 and 2 boundary. The scope 3 emissions for one organization are the scope 1 and 2 emissions of another organization. Scope 3 emissions, also referred to as value chain emissions, often represent the majority of an organization’s total GHG emissions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scope 3 emissions fall within 15 categories, though not every category will be relevant to all organizations. Scope 3 emission sources include emissions both upstream and downstream of the organization’s activities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to GHG inventory guidance, quantification of scope 1 and 2 emissions are mandatory for organizations reporting and disclosing GHG emissions, while scope 3 emissions quantification is not required. However, more organizations are reaching into their value chain to understand the full GHG impact of their operations. In addition, because scope 3 emission sources may represent the majority of an organization’s GHG emissions, they often offer emissions reduction opportunities. Although these emissions are not under the organization’s control, the organization may be able to impact the activities that result in the emissions. The organization may also be able to influence its suppliers or choose which vendors to contract with based on their practices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a complete description of all scope 3 categories and quantification methods, see the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ghgprotocol.org/standards/scope-3-standard&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;World Resources Institute / World Business Council for Sustainable Development GHG Protocol Corporate Value Chain (Scope 3) Accounting and Reporting Standard&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-png center view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:928px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;WRI/WBCSD Corporate Value Chain (Scope 3) Accounting and Reporting Standard&quot; height=&quot;595&quot; width=&quot;928&quot; class=&quot;center media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2016-11/scope_3_resource_image.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Source: WRI/WBCSD Corporate Value Chain (Scope 3) Accounting and Reporting Standard, page 5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;Scope 3 Resources&quot; id=&quot;Scope 3 Resources&quot;&gt;Scope 3 Resources&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ghgprotocol.org/standards/scope-3-standard&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;World Resources Institute / World Business Council for Sustainable Development GHG Protocol Corporate Value Chain (Scope 3) Accounting and Reporting Standard&lt;/a&gt; presents details on all scope 3 categories and requirements and guidance on reporting scope 3 emissions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The GHG Protocol also provides the following additional scope 3 resources:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ghgprotocol.org/feature/scope-3-calculation-guidance&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Guidance for Calculating Scope 3 Emissions&lt;/a&gt; for each category, including guidance on required data, data collection methods, and quantification methods&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://quantis-suite.com/Scope-3-Evaluator/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The Scope 3 Evaluator tool &lt;/a&gt;helps organizations screen scope 3 emissions categories to identifying focus areas&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Depending on the source, scope 3 emissions can be quantified using either primary data specific to the activity within a company’s value chain, or using secondary data such as industry averages, proxy data, or other generic data. Primary data must often be collected directly from suppliers through a &lt;a href=&quot;/climateleadership/center-corporate-climate-leadership-how-engage-suppliers&quot;&gt;questionnaire or similar format&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.carbontrust.com/client-services/footprinting/footprint-certification/carbon-trust-standard-for-supply-chain/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The Carbon Trust&lt;/a&gt; provides a certification standard and framework for organizations that are measuring, managing, and reducing GHG emissions in their supply chain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;Scope 3 Emission Factors&quot; id=&quot;Scope 3 Emission Factors&quot;&gt;Scope 3 Emission Factors&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The EPA Center for Corporate Climate Leadership currently provides certain scope 3 emission factors and is planning to expand the list. The sections below discuss the&lt;a href=&quot;#Emission Factors Currently Available&quot;&gt; currently available factors&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;#Emission Factors To Be Included&quot;&gt;the factors to be included in the future&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;#Emission Source Categories Using Scope 1 and 2 Emission Factors&quot;&gt;how to apply scope 1 and 2 factors to calculate scope 3 emissions for certain categories&lt;/a&gt;. The categories listed are those defined in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ghgprotocol.org/standards/scope-3-standard&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;GHG Protocol Scope 3 Standard&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;Emission Factors Currently Available&quot; id=&quot;Emission Factors Currently Available&quot;&gt;Emission Factors Currently Available&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;/climateleadership/center-corporate-climate-leadership-ghg-emission-factors-hub&quot;&gt;GHG Emission Factors Hub&lt;/a&gt; currently contains factors applicable to four scope 3 categories. Below is a list of emission sources and the location of the factors in the GHG Emission Factors Hub.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Business Travel (Category 6)............................................Table 8, Business Travel&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Employee Commuting (Category 7)...................................Table 8, Business Travel&lt;a href=&quot;#1&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Upstream Transportation and Distribution (Category 4)......Table 9, Product Transport&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Downstream Transportation and Distribution (Category 9)..Table 9, Product Transport&lt;a href=&quot;#2&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;Emission Factors To Be Included&quot; id=&quot;Emission Factors To Be Included&quot;&gt;Emission Factors to be Included in the Future&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Emissions Factors to assist with quantification in the following categories are under development and will be included in the next revision of the &lt;a href=&quot;/climateleadership/center-corporate-climate-leadership-ghg-emission-factors-hub&quot;&gt;GHG Emission Factors Hub&lt;/a&gt;, expected at the end of 2016 or early 2017&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Purchased goods and services (Category 1)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Capital goods (Category 2)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Fuel- and energy-related activities (not included in scope 1 or scope 2) (Category 3)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Waste generated in operations (Category 5)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;Emission Source Categories Using Scope 1 and 2 Emission Factors&quot; id=&quot;Emission Source Categories Using Scope 1 and 2 Emission Factors&quot;&gt;Emission Source Categories Using Scope 1 and 2 Emission Factors&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some scope 3 categories do not require specific emission factors, because the emissions-generating activities have associated scope 1 and scope 2 factors already available in the &lt;a href=&quot;/climateleadership/center-corporate-climate-leadership-ghg-emission-factors-hub&quot;&gt;GHG Emission Factors Hub&lt;/a&gt;. These sources include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Upstream leased assets (Category 8)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Processing of sold products (Category 10)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Use of sold products (Category 11)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;End-of-life treatment of sold products (Category 12)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Downstream leased assets (Category 13)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Franchises (Category 14)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Investments (Category 15)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;An organization may first define the GHG generating activity for each relevant source category, and then apply the appropriate factors for stationary combustion, mobile combustion, fugitive emissions, electricity, heat or steam from the &lt;a href=&quot;/climateleadership/center-corporate-climate-leadership-ghg-emission-factors-hub&quot;&gt;GHG Emission Factors Hub&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, assume your organization produces electronic equipment. The downstream use of sold products (Category 11) may likely be a large source of emissions. In order to calculate emissions, estimate the lifetime electricity consumption (kWh) for all products sold in the reporting year. Then calculate emissions the same as for Scope 2 electricity, using &lt;a href=&quot;/energy/emissions-generation-resource-integrated-database-egrid&quot;&gt;eGRID emission factors&lt;/a&gt;. Depending on the data available for the location of product use, eGRID subregion or U.S. national average factors would be applied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;1&quot; id=&quot;1&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;These factors are applicable to employee commuting as well as business travel&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;2&quot; id=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;These factors are applicable to all transportation; upstream or downstream, product-related or not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 08 Nov 2016 17:25:13 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>xsyardle</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">164845 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>F-GHG Emissions Reduction Efforts: 2016 Flat Panel Display Supplier Profiles</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/climateleadership/f-ghg-emissions-reduction-efforts-2016-flat-panel-display-supplier-profiles-0</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;The 2016 Supplier Profiles detail the efforts of large-area flat panel suppliers to reduce their fluorinated greenhouse gas (F-GHG) emissions in manufacturing across key areas. They cover mitigation measures and goals, the extent of reduction efforts (whether they include all processes and gases used), the extent to which abatement technologies are installed on newer fabs that manufacture large area panels, and public disclosure efforts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-317147&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-09/documents/fpd_full_supplier_profiles_2016_508compliant.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=2768219&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;F-GHG Emissions Reduction Efforts: 2016 Flat Panel Display Supplier Profiles (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(57 pp, 3 MB, 
  9/16/16)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 21 Sep 2016 22:41:16 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>mklein02</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">160895 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>F-GHG Emissions Reduction Efforts: 2016 Flat Panel Display Supplier Profiles Summary</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/climateleadership/f-ghg-emissions-reduction-efforts-2016-flat-panel-display-supplier-profiles</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;The 2016 Supplier Profiles detail the efforts of large-area flat panel suppliers to reduce their fluorinated greenhouse gas (F-GHG emissions) in manufacturing across key areas. They cover mitigation measures and goals, the extent of reduction efforts (whether they include all processes and gases used), the extent to which abatement technologies are installed on newer fabs that manufacture large area panels, and public disclosure efforts. This document provides a 5-page summary of the 2016 profiles and findings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-317145&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-09/documents/fpd_supplier_profiles_2016_508compliant.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=266668&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;F-GHG Emissions Reduction Efforts: 2016 Flat Panel Display Supplier Profiles Summary (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(5 pp, 267 K, 
  9/16/16)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 21 Sep 2016 22:34:35 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>xsyardle</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">160893 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Improving Environmental Sustainability in Supply Chains: Best Practices</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/climateleadership/improving-environmental-sustainability-supply-chains-best-practices</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;This EPA webinar highlighted best practices for environmental sustainability in the supply chain. Guest speakers from three leading companies highlighted the importance of engaging and rewarding suppliers to drive sustainability; ways to align and clarify value for suppliers, incentivizing suppliers to meet key environmental, health, and safety criteria; and building internal organizational support for engaging suppliers on sustainability, thereby driving innovation for organizational change. Speakers discussed their initiatives, what’s worked and what hasn’t worked, lessons learned, and more. EPA also presented on supply chain policy work, as well as key findings from a recent dialogue with leading stakeholders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speakers:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Melissa Bouilly, Program Manager, Supply Chain Responsibility, Dell&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Melissa Klein, Communications Lead, Center for Corporate Climate Leadership, U.S. Environmental Protection Agency&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Rick Love, Manager, Environmental Sustainability, United Technologies Corporation&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Verena Radulovic, Product Lead, ENERGY STAR Electronics, U.S. Environmental Protection Agency&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Kathleen Shaver, Director of Sustainability and Risk, Cisco Systems&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Nena Shaw, Director, Integrated Environmental Strategies Division, Office of Policy, U.S. Environmental Protection Agency&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-315729&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-09/documents/improving_sustainability_in_supply_chains_091516.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=2973457&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Presentation Slides: Improving Environmental Sustainability in Supply Chains: Best Practices (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(37 pp, 3 MB, 
  9/15/16)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;field field-name-field-document-description field-type-text field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    Presentation Slides: Improving Environmental Sustainability in Supply Chains: Best Practices (PDF)  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 13 Sep 2016 21:30:41 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>xsyardle</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">160067 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Improving Environmental Sustainability in Supply Chains: Best Practices Webinar</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/climateleadership/improving-environmental-sustainability-supply-chains-best-practices-webinar</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Friday, September 9, 2016&lt;br /&gt;
	2:00-3:00 PM ET&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This EPA webinar highlighted best practices for environmental sustainability in the supply chain. Guest speakers from three leading companies highlighted the importance of engaging and rewarding suppliers to drive sustainability; ways to align and clarify value for suppliers, incentivizing suppliers to meet key environmental, health, and safety criteria; and building internal organizational support for engaging suppliers on sustainability, thereby driving innovation for organizational change. Speakers discussed their initiatives, what’s worked and what hasn’t worked, lessons learned, and more. EPA also presented on supply chain policy work, as well as key findings from a recent dialogue with leading stakeholders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speakers:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Melissa Bouilly, Program Manager, Supply Chain Responsibility, Dell&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Melissa Klein, Communications Lead, Center for Corporate Climate Leadership, U.S. Environmental Protection Agency&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Rick Love, Manager, Environmental Sustainability, United Technologies Corporation&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Verena Radulovic, Product Lead, ENERGY STAR Electronics, U.S. Environmental Protection Agency&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Kathleen Shaver, Director of Sustainability and Risk, Cisco Systems&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Nena Shaw, Director, Integrated Environmental Strategies Division, Office of Policy, U.S. Environmental Protection Agency&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 20 Jul 2016 17:58:56 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>mklein02</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">155353 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>2017 Climate Leadership Awards Webinar: A Review of Categories, Eligibility, Criteria, and the Application Process</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/climateleadership/2017-climate-leadership-awards-webinar-review-categories-eligibility-criteria-0</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;The 2017 Climate Leadership Awards application period opened on June 22, 2016. In this informative webinar, organizers discussed what&#039;s new this year and how your organization can be a competitive applicant for this prestigious recognition program. EPA and its NGO partners — The Climate Registry and Center for Climate and Energy Solutions — provided critical information related to eligibility, evaluation criteria, and application content for each of the award categories, as well as answered questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Presenters:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Chelsea Hasenauer, Program Associate, Technical Services, The Climate Registry&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Tim Juliani, Senior Director, Business Strategy &amp;amp; Partnerships, Center for Climate and Energy Solutions&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Melissa Klein, Communications Lead, Center for Corporate Climate Leadership, U.S. EPA &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Climate Leadership Award recipients are recognized for demonstrating exemplary leadership in response to climate change. To view past recipients, please visit &lt;a href=&quot;/climateleadership/climate-leadership-awards&quot;&gt;https://www.epa.gov/climateleadership/climate-leadership-awards&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-295887&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-06/documents/2017_cla_webinar_062116_508.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=855621&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Presentation Slides: 2017 Climate Leadership Awards: A Webinar Review of Categories, Eligibility, Criteria, and the Application Process (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(50 pp, 856 K, 
  June 21, 2016)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jun 2016 14:09:47 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>xsgunthe</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">152955 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Navigating the Center’s GHG Management Tools &amp; Resources Webinar</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/climateleadership/navigating-centers-ghg-management-tools-resources-webinar</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;The U.S. EPA’s Center for Corporate Climate Leadership offers a variety of free tools and resources for organizations looking to expand their work in the area of greenhouse gas (GHG) measurement and management. In this webinar, speakers provided an overview of the Center’s resources, highlighted recent updates – including three new GHG inventory guidance documents for cross-sector emissions sources – and discussed future Center updates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speakers:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Roger Fernandez, Manager of Corporate and Institutional Engagement, Center for Corporate Climate Leadership, U.S. EPA &lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Eric Christensen, Practice Leader, Sustainability and Energy, WSP | Parsons Brinckerhoff &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-288513&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-05/documents/navigatingcenterresourceswebinar.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=3054870&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Presentation Slides: Navigating the Center’s GHG Management Tools &amp;amp; Resources  (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(14 pp, 3 MB, 
  May 25, 2016)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 26 May 2016 17:01:08 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>xsgunthe</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">150543 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>2017 Climate Leadership Awards: A Webinar Review of Categories, Eligibility, Criteria, and the Application Process</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/climateleadership/2017-climate-leadership-awards-webinar-review-categories-eligibility-criteria-and</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tuesday, June 21, 2016&lt;br /&gt;
	2:00 PM-3:30 PM ET&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2017 Climate Leadership Awards application period will open on June 22, 2016. In this informative webinar, organizers will discuss what&#039;s new this year and how your organization can be a competitive applicant for this prestigious recognition program. EPA and its NGO partners — The Climate Registry and Center for Climate and Energy Solutions — will provide critical information related to eligibility, evaluation criteria, and application content for each of the award categories, as well as answer questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Presenters:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Chelsea Hasenauer, Program Associate, Technical Services, The Climate Registry&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Tim Juliani, Senior Director, Business Strategy &amp;amp; Partnerships, Center for Climate and Energy Solutions&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Melissa Klein, Communications Lead, Center for Corporate Climate Leadership, U.S. EPA &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Climate Leadership Award recipients are recognized for demonstrating exemplary leadership in response to climate change. To view past recipients, please visit &lt;a href=&quot;/climateleadership/climate-leadership-awards&quot;&gt;https://www.epa.gov/climateleadership/climate-leadership-awards&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://attendee.gotowebinar.com/register/3917575697760426753&quot;&gt;Register for this webinar&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 25 May 2016 14:30:25 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>mklein02</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">150391 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  </channel>
</rss>

<!-- Page cached by Boost @ 2017-01-26 11:31:08, expires @ 2017-01-27 11:31:08, lifetime 1 day -->