<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?><rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.epa.gov/feed/17591/rss.xml" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/" xmlns:og="http://ogp.me/ns#" xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#" xmlns:sioc="http://rdfs.org/sioc/ns#" xmlns:sioct="http://rdfs.org/sioc/types#" xmlns:skos="http://www.w3.org/2004/02/skos/core#" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#">
  <channel>
    <title>Bed Bugs</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/feed/17591/rss.xml</link>
    <description>Updated Bed Bugs content from the US Environmental Protection Agency</description>
    <language>en</language>
     <atom:link href="https://www.epa.gov/feed/17591/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      <item>
    <title>Bed Bug Tips Door Hanger</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/bedbugs/bed-bug-tips-door-hanger</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;These tips on bedbug prevention at home and while traveling are in a format designed to be printed for hanging on door knobs as part of an outreach program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-314223&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-09/documents/bed-bug-tips-door-hanger.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=239819&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Bed Bug Tips Door Hanger (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(2 pp, 240 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Fri, 09 Sep 2016 19:44:08 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cgesalma</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">159839 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Collaborative Strategy on Bed Bugs</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/bedbugs/collaborative-strategy-bed-bugs</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;The Federal Bed Bug Workgroup developed the Collaborative Strategy on Bed Bugs (the strategy) to highlight ways that all levels of government, community, academia and private industry can work together within a community to reduce bed bugs across the United States.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#strategy&quot;&gt;Read the Collaborative Strategy on Bed Bugs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Managing bed bugs continues to be a major challenge for many communities. Through collaboration, communities can develop customized training programs, communication materials and treatment plans. Implementing these plans at the local level can reduce costs and achieve a better level of bed bug control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The strategy outlines four priority areas for bed bug control:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Prevention.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Surveillance and Integrated Pest Management [IPM].&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Education and Communication.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Research.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Each of these areas is critical to national bed bug control efforts. However, communities may choose to focus their local strategies on one or more of these items, depending on the needs of each individual area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within each priority area, the goals of the strategy are to help stakeholders by:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Coordinating and guiding federal activities.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Facilitating collaboration among stakeholders and various levels of government.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Raising awareness of the issues surrounding the bed bug problem.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Maximizing efficient and effective use of resources to address high priority needs.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Encouraging realistic appraisal and management of bed bug problems through education and integrated mitigation measures.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The strategy also focuses on the importance of measuring the results of actions taken to control bed bugs and sharing success stories with other communities. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;strategy&quot; name=&quot;strategy&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The Collaborative Strategy on Bed Bugs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-108067&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-02/documents/fed-strategy-bedbug-2015.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=363021&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Collaborative Strategy on Bed Bugs (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(21 pp, 363 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2015 18:03:55 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cgesalma</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">73167 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Bed Bug Prevention, Detection and Control</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/bedbugs/bed-bug-prevention-detection-and-control</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;This EPA brochure provides tips for preventing bed bugs day-to-day and while traveling, plus information about identifying bed bugs and controlling them if you find you have an infestation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-53343&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2014-02/documents/bed-bug-prevention-detection-control.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=665560&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Brochure on prevention, detection and control of bed bugs (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(2 pp, 666 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2014 16:08:44 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cgesalma</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">45731 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Tips for Travel</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/bedbugs/tips-travel</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://espanol.epa.gov/control-de-plagas/consejos-para-el-viaje&quot;&gt;Información relacionada disponible en español&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;When traveling:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;figure image mode-full right&quot; style=&quot;width:200px&quot;&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:200px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Person inspecting a hotel luggage stand for bed bugs&quot; title=&quot;Person inspecting a hotel luggage stand for bed bugs&quot; height=&quot;200&quot; width=&quot;200&quot; class=&quot;media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2013-09/bed-bug-travel-issues.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Inspect any room where you will be staying for the presence of bed bugs. You generally can do this without any extra tools but a flashlight can be useful.
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Check the mattress and headboard before sleeping.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Inspect luggage racks.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;In hotel rooms, use luggage racks to hold your luggage when packing or unpacking rather than setting your luggage on the bed or floor. Try to keep luggage away from bed.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Upon returning home, unpack directly into a washing machine and inspect your luggage carefully. Remember that time in a dryer at high temperatures kills the bed bugs (just washing will generally not kill bed bugs).&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Store suitcases away from your bedroom, such as in the basement or garage. Never store suitcases under your bed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2&gt;More Information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/bedbugs/print-bed-bug-card&quot;&gt;Print a card to carry with you when traveling&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/bedbugs/bed-bug-information-clearinghouse&quot;&gt;View videos and other information on preventing bed bugs while traveling&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/bedbugs/how-find-bed-bugs&quot;&gt;How to find bed bugs&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2014 13:51:32 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>dcoleman</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">45721 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Protecting Your Home from Bed Bugs</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/bedbugs/protecting-your-home-bed-bugs</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://espanol.epa.gov/control-de-plagas/proteja-su-hogar-de-las-chinches&quot;&gt;Información relacionada disponible en español&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;Bed bugs are great hitchhikers. They can move from an infested site to a new home by traveling on furniture, bedding, luggage, boxes, and clothing.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although they typically feed on blood every five to ten days, bed bugs can be quite resilient; they are capable of surviving several months to a year without feeding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;A few simple precautions can help prevent bed bug infestation in your home:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;figure image mode-full right&quot; style=&quot;width:200px&quot;&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:200px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Looking for bed bugs under a cushion&quot; title=&quot;Looking for bed bugs under a cushion&quot; height=&quot;200&quot; width=&quot;200&quot; class=&quot;media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2013-09/protect-home-cushion.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;div class=&quot;figcaption&quot;&gt;Inspect the luggage rack in your hotel room for bed bugs.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Check secondhand furniture, beds, and couches for any &lt;a href=&quot;/bedbugs/how-find-bed-bugs&quot;&gt;signs of bed bug infestation&lt;/a&gt; before bringing them home.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Use a protective cover that encases mattresses and box springs and eliminates many hiding spots. The light color of the encasement makes bed bugs easier to see. Be sure to purchase a high quality encasement that will resist tearing and check the encasement regularly for holes.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Reduce clutter in your home to reduce hiding places for bed bugs.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Vacuum frequently to remove any successful hitchhikers.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Be vigilant when using shared laundry facilities. Transport items to be washed in plastic bags (if you have an active infestation, use a new bag for the journey home). Remove from dryer directly into bag and fold at home. (A dryer on high heat can kill bed bugs.)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;If you live in a multi-family home, try to isolate your unit by:
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Installing door sweeps on the bottom of doors to discourage movement into hallways.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Sealing cracks and crevices around baseboards, light sockets, etc., to discourage movement through wall voids.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Consider purchasing a portable heating chamber to treat any items that you believe may have bed bugs.
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Be sure to read and carefully follow the directions if you use one of these units and be aware that they are not regulated by EPA or other federal agencies. &lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/bedbugs/controlling-bed-bugs-using-integrated-pest-management-ipm&quot;&gt;More information on controlling bed bugs&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2014 19:47:51 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>dcoleman</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">45009 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Print a Bed Bug Card - (Page of Cards)</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/bedbugs/print-bed-bug-card-page-cards</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;The bed bug tips cards are designed to be printed and distributed in larger quantities. Each file contains a page of cards, one for travel tips, the other for general bed bug prevention tips.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;Only need one card? See the&lt;a href=&quot;/bedbugs/print-bed-bug-card-single-cards&quot;&gt; single card&lt;/a&gt; page.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-299803&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-07/documents/bed-bug-tips-10.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=73282&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt; Bed Bug Home and Office Tips (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(2 pp, 73 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-130713&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-05/documents/bed_bug_traveller_card.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=228812&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Bed Bug Card for travel (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(2 pp, 229 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 18 Dec 2013 16:57:43 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>dcoleman</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">43843 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Print a Bed Bug Card - (Single Cards)</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/bedbugs/print-bed-bug-card-single-cards</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;These cards have tips to help you remember how to protect yourself from bed bugs. Print these business-card-sized cards to use when you travel and around the home or office. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Need to hand out cards to others? See the &lt;a href=&quot;/bedbugs/print-bed-bug-card-page-cards&quot;&gt;page of cards&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-299801&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-07/documents/bedbug-tips-1.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=78148&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Bed Bug Home and Office Tips Card (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(2 pp, 78 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-48799&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2013-12/documents/bedbug-tips.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=126761&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Bed Bug Card for Travel (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(2 pp, 127 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 18 Dec 2013 16:39:11 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>dcoleman</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">43837 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Stay Legal and Safe in Treating for Bed Bugs</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/bedbugs/stay-legal-and-safe-treating-bed-bugs</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;Sometimes people promote dangerous or illegal ways to eliminate bed bugs through Internet sites, blogs, or word-of-mouth. Just because something is legal doesn’t mean that it is safe, smart or effective. It’s important to remain patient and level-headed when combating bed bugs and not do something out of desperation that will lead to more dangerous or expensive  problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;What’s Legal?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Buy EPA-registered pesticides labeled for bed bug control (look for EPA Reg. # on label). Read the label carefully and completely before using the products. Follow all the label directions and precautions. It’s that simple.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/bedbugs/find-bed-bug-pesticide-product&quot;&gt;Search for EPA-registered pesticides for bed bug control&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;What’s Not Legal?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many people looking for a quick fix to control bed bugs turn to control methods that are not only illegal but also can be dangerous and ineffective. If you are not careful, the misuse of pesticides or other control methods could be worse than the bed bugs themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA looks at all bed bug pesticides it registers to determine if they work and if they can be used without causing unreasonable adverse effects.  EPA recommends using a registered bed bug product to maximize your odds of safely and successfully treating your infestation. &lt;a href=&quot;/bedbugs/when-treatments-dont-work&quot;&gt;Learn why treatments sometimes don&#039;t work&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some things that people frequently do that are not legal include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Mixing pesticides with other pesticides or ingredients, which can be dangerous and is unlikely to work well.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Using diatomaceous earth that is not a registered pesticide product - this type of diatomaceous earth may harm you when you breathe it in. The pesticide version uses a different sized diatom, which can reduce the hazard.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Using rubbing alcohol – this compound vaporizes quickly, is flammable and has caused numerous house fires when used to control bed bugs.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Using carbon dioxide, propane, helium or other unregistered gases to fumigate bed bugs, even if it&#039;s just in an enclosed bag
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;They are not registered and can lead to dangerous low-oxygen situations or cause an explosion.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Using a pesticide in a way that doesn’t follow the label. For bed bugs, people are sometimes tempted to:
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li class=&quot;indented&quot;&gt;Use a pesticide labeled for outdoor use. This can make your home dangerous and uninhabitable.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li class=&quot;indented&quot;&gt;Buy pesticides from street vendors, flea markets or other unreliable sources. You never know what you’re buying, whether it will work, or if it is safe.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li class=&quot;indented&quot;&gt;Apply pesticides (including mosquito repellents) to their body. EPA has not registered any pesticides or repellents for use on human skin against bed bugs and you could end up poisoning yourself.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li class=&quot;indented&quot;&gt;Use too much or apply more often than the label allows. Some pesticides take time to work, or your bed bugs may be resistant to that type of pesticide. If a pesticide is not working, trying a different one with a different ingredient may work better. &lt;a href=&quot;/bedbugs/pesticides-control-bed-bugs&quot;&gt;Read about pesticides used to control bed bugs&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li class=&quot;indented&quot;&gt;Apply pesticides to a bed, furniture, or clothing if these surfaces are not on the label. You could accidentally poison yourself or your family.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li class=&quot;indented&quot;&gt;Use too many fogger products at once, which could lead to a fire and/or explosion.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li class=&quot;indented&quot;&gt;Use pest strips in a manner not on the label. There have been incidents where people were overexposed and became ill.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2&gt;What’s Legal, but Not Safe?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other control methods may be legal, but aren’t necessarily safe or smart. Some of these include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Spraying over and over, whenever you see a bug. This type of application may not actually violate the label, but it is unlikely to eliminate the infestation and can cause the bugs to become resistant to the pesticide so it will no longer work.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Do-it-yourself heating treatments (such as space heaters and fireplaces) – these have been known to burn down homes.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Do-it-yourself freezing treatments (such as freezers, fire extinguishers or opening the home to cold air) – these methods may not get cold enough to kill bed bugs.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Hiring an applicator who does not follow &lt;abbr title=&quot;Integrated Pest Management&quot;&gt;IPM&lt;/abbr&gt; practices – they may charge less but are far less likely to achieve success. &lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Hiring an applicator with no or little experience in controlling bed bugs.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Hiring an applicator that does not provide a follow-up inspection and repeat treatments if needed. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/bedbugs/hiring-pest-management-professional-bed-bugs&quot;&gt;Learn more about hiring pest control applicators&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 13 Aug 2013 19:40:13 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cgesalma</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">37945 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Bed Bug Laws and Regulations</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/bedbugs/bed-bug-laws-and-regulations</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;EPA regulates pesticides that can be used against bed bugs. Our jurisdiction does not include the kind of reporting and management regulations that states have. The Department of Housing and Urban Development has guidance related to controlling bed bugs in public housing.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/bedbugs/epa-regulation-bed-bug-pesticides&quot;&gt;Regulation of Bed Bug Pesticides&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://portal.hud.gov/hudportal/HUD?src=/program_offices/public_indian_housing/programs/ph/phecc/pestmang&quot;&gt;Public Housing Environmental and Conservation Clearinghouse: Integrated Pest Management&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/bedbugs/stay-legal-and-safe-treating-bed-bugs&quot;&gt;Staying Legal and Safe in Treating for Bed Bugs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;There are 21 states that have some level of law or regulation that applies to bed bugs. Some of these requirements have been on the books for many years. Nine states have enacted laws or regulations since 2005. Requirements focus on hotels and landlords or other property managers for the most part.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Be sure to check with your state and local authorities for any changes in these requirements or to find out if your state or city has enacted a requirement more recently. Chicago is an example of a local government that has regulations related to bed bugs. See &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cityofchicago.org/city/en/depts/bacp/supp_info/bed_bug_information.html&quot;&gt;Chicago&#039;s bed bug information&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-328497&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-11/documents/state-bed-bug-laws.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=317817&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Bed bug laws and regulations  (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(4 pp, 318 K, 
  November 2016)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Mon, 29 Jul 2013 18:08:03 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>ctran</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">37433 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  </channel>
</rss>

<!-- Page cached by Boost @ 2017-01-26 04:20:59, expires @ 2017-01-26 16:20:59, lifetime 12 hours -->