<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0">  
<channel>    
<title>EPA Recent Additions</title>    
<link>http://www.epa.gov/home/recent-additions-epas-website</link>    
<description>This page provides access to a listing of some of the recent additions and new materials made available on the EPA Web site within the past six weeks.</description>	
<language>en-us</language>
<webMaster>internet_support@unixmail.rtpnc.epa.gov</webMaster>	
<image>
<title>EPA Recent Additions</title>
<link>http://www.epa.gov/home/recent-additions-epas-website</link>
<url>http://www.epa.gov/home/recent-additions-epas-website</url>
<width>144</width><height>62</height>
<description>This page provides access to a listing of some of the recent additions and new materials made available on the EPA Web site within the past six weeks.</description>
</image>


<item> 
<date>January 18, 2017</date>
<title>EPA Releases Final Biological Evaluations of Three Chemicals' Impacts on Endangered Species</title>  
<link>https://www.epa.gov/endangered-species/implementing-nas-report-recommendations-ecological-risk-assessment-endangered-and</link>	
<description><![CDATA[EPA has released its final biological evaluations (BEs) for effects of chlorpyrifos, diazinon, and malathion on threatened and endangered species and their designated critical habitat. We have also released a separate document that addresses the comments submitted during the public comment period.  <a href="http://www.epa.gov/pesticides/index.htm">Office of Chemical Safety and Pollution Prevention (OCSPP)</a>]]></description>
<pubDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2017 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>	
</item>	

<item> 
<date>January 18, 2017</date>
<title>Tauber Oil Company Settles Allegations of Selling Unregistered Fuel Additive</title>  
<link>https://www.epa.gov/enforcement/tauber-oil-company-clean-air-act-settlement</link>	   
<description><![CDATA[EPA has announced a settlement with Tauber Oil Company, resolving alleged Clean Air Act violations stemming from the company&rsquo;s sale of a fuel additive that was not registered with the EPA. Tauber stopped selling the unregistered fuel additive and will pay a $700,000 civil penalty. <em>(<a href="http://www.epa.gov/aboutepa/about-office-enforcement-and-compliance-assurance-oeca">Office of Enforcement and Compliance Assurance (OECA)</a>)</em>.]]></description>
<pubDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2017 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>	
</item>

<item> 
<date>January 18, 2017</date>
<title>Bandit Industries, Inc., Settles Alleged Clean Air Act Violations for Manufacturing and Selling Wood Processing Equipment That Failed to Meet Emissions Standards</title>  
<link>https://www.epa.gov/enforcement/bandit-industries-inc-clean-air-act-settlement</link>	   
<description><![CDATA[EPA has announced a settlement with Bandit Industries, Inc., for alleged violations of the Clean Air Act for selling non-road diesel engines and equipment used to process wood and waste that do not meet federal standards. Bandit, based in Remus, Michigan, will pay a $3 million civil penalty. Bandit is a manufacturer of self-powered, industrial-strength wood and waste processing equipment, such as wood chippers. The complaint alleges that Bandit sold non-road diesel-fueled engines and equipment that were neither covered by the certificates of conformity required by the Clean Air Act, nor exempt from that certification requirement under the requirements of the Transition Program for Equipment Manufacturers (TPEM). Additionally, as alleged, Bandit built and sold equipment with engines using older emission standards in exceedance of normal inventory restrictions, commonly referred to as &quot;stockpiling.&quot; <em>(<a href="http://www.epa.gov/aboutepa/about-office-enforcement-and-compliance-assurance-oeca">Office of Enforcement and Compliance Assurance (OECA)</a>)</em>.]]></description>
<pubDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2017 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>	
</item>

<item> 
<date>January 17, 2017</date>
<title>Updated List of Human Health Benchmarks for Pesticides in Drinking Water Available</title>  
<link>https://iaspub.epa.gov/apex/pesticides/f?p=HHBP:home:10911636297819:::::</link>	
<description><![CDATA[EPA has updated its list of human health benchmarks for pesticides (HHBP) in drinking water. A total of 394 HHBPs are now available for pesticides that are currently registered for use on food crops or other use that could result in exposure through food or drinking water. EPA develops these benchmarks as screening levels for use by states and water systems in determining whether the detection of a pesticide in drinking water or a drinking water source may indicate a potential health risk. All benchmarks were calculated with updated exposure assumptions (related to body weight and drinking water intake). Three pesticides previously listed in the table (d-allethrin, S-bioallethrin, and bioallethrin) were removed due to updated exposure pattern information demonstrating that these pesticides are no longer used on food. The available information also indicates they do not have the potential to reach drinking water sources. <a href="http://www.epa.gov/pesticides/index.htm">Office of Chemical Safety and Pollution Prevention (OCSPP)</a>]]></description>
<pubDate>Tue, 17 Jan 2017 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>	
</item>	

<item> 
<date>January 13, 2017</date>
<title>For the First Time in 40 Years EPA to Put in Place a Process to Evaluate Chemicals that May Pose Risk</title>  
<link>https://www.epa.gov/assessing-and-managing-chemicals-under-tsca/frank-r-lautenberg-chemical-safety-21st-century-act-5</link>	
<description><![CDATA[EPA is moving swiftly to propose how it will prioritize and evaluate chemicals, given that the final processes must be in place within the first year of the new law&rsquo;s enactment, or before June 22, 2017. <a href="http://www.epa.gov/pesticides/index.htm">Office of Chemical Safety and Pollution Prevention (OCSPP)</a>]]></description>
<pubDate>Fri, 13 Jan 2017 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>	
</item>	

<item> 
<date>January 13, 2017</date>
<title>EPA Amends Registration for Enlist Duo Herbicide to Add GE Cotton and Additional States</title>  
<link>https://www.epa.gov/ingredients-used-pesticide-products/registration-enlist-duo</link>	
<description><![CDATA[Enlist Duo, a formula containing the choline salt of 2,4-D and glyphosate for use in controlling weeds in genetically engineered (GE) crops, was first registered in 2014 for use in GE corn and soybean crops. EPA is amending the registration to include GE cotton and expand the use to an additional 19 states for GE corn, soybean, and cotton and re-affirming our original decision before the remand. 
EPA did a comprehensive review for the initial registration of Enlist Duo and now again in response to the application to amend the registration. EPA&rsquo;s protective and conservative human health and ecological risk assessments re-confirmed our 2014 safety findings. The pesticide meets the safety standard for the public, agricultural workers, and non-target plants and animal species, including a &quot;no effects&quot; determination for species listed as threatened or endangered under the Endangered Species Act. <a href="http://www.epa.gov/pesticides/index.htm">Office of Chemical Safety and Pollution Prevention (OCSPP)</a>]]></description>
<pubDate>Fri, 13 Jan 2017 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>	
</item>	

<item> 
<date>January 12, 2017</date>
<title>EPA Finalizes Steps to Better Protect Bees from Pesticides</title>  
<link>https://www.epa.gov/pollinator-protection/policy-mitigating-acute-risk-bees-pesticide-products</link>	
<description><![CDATA[EPA's is releasing a final policy which describes methods for addressing acute risks to bees from pesticides. Applications of acutely toxic pesticides would be prohibited under certain conditions when bees are most likely to be present. While the restrictions focus on managed bees, EPA believes that these measures will also protect native bees and other pollinators that are in and around treatment areas. New label language will protect managed bees under contract to provide crop pollination services. <a href="http://www.epa.gov/pesticides/index.htm">Office of Chemical Safety and Pollution Prevention (OCSPP)</a>]]></description>
<pubDate>Thu, 12 Jan 2017 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>	
</item>	

<item> 
<date>January 12, 2017</date>
<title>EPA Provides Two Universities with $4 Million for Drinking Water Quality Research</title>  
<link>https://www.epa.gov/research-grants/water-research-grants</link>	
<description><![CDATA[EPA has announced approximately $4 million in funding to two universities to research water quality issues related to low flow conditions of drinking water in premise plumbing systems. <em>(<a href="http://www.epa.gov/aboutepa/about-office-water">Office of Water (OW)</a>)</em>.]]></description>
<pubDate>Thu, 12 Jan 2017 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>	
</item>	

<item> 
<date>January 12, 2017</date>
<title>EPA Report Shows Air Emissions of Toxic Chemicals from Industrial Facilities Down More Than Half Since 2005</title>  
<link>https://www.epa.gov/trinationalanalysis</link>	   
<description><![CDATA[EPA has released its annual Toxics Release Inventory (TRI) National Analysis, which shows releases of toxic chemicals into the air fell 56% from 2005-2015 at industrial facilities submitting data to the TRI program. <em>(<a href="https://www.epa.gov/aboutepa/about-office-environmental-information-oei">Office of Environmental Information (OEI)</a>)</em>.]]></description>
<pubDate>Thu, 12 Jan 2017 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>	
</item>

<item> 
<date>January 12, 2017</date>
<title>EPA Notifies Fiat Chrysler of Clean Air Act Violations</title>  
<link>https://www.epa.gov/fca</link>	   
<description><![CDATA[EPA has issued a notice of violation to Fiat Chrysler Automobiles N.V. and FCA US LLC (collectively FCA) for alleged violations of the Clean Air Act for installing and failing to disclose engine management software in light-duty model year 2014, 2015 and 2016 Jeep Grand Cherokees and Dodge Ram 1500 trucks with 3.0 liter diesel engines sold in the United States. The undisclosed software results in increased emissions of nitrogen oxides (NOx) from the vehicles. The allegations cover roughly 104,000 vehicles. EPA is working in coordination with the California Air Resources Board (CARB), which has also issued a notice of violation to FCA. EPA and CARB have both initiated investigations based on FCA&rsquo;s alleged actions.  <em>(<a href="http://www.epa.gov/aboutepa/about-office-air-and-radiation-oar">Office of Air and Radiation (OAR)</a>)</em>.]]></description>
<pubDate>Thu, 12 Jan 2017 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>	
</item>

<item> 
<date>January 11, 2017</date>
<title>Volkswagen Agrees to Plead Guilty, Pay $4.3 Billion in Criminal and Civil Penalties</title>  
<link>https://www.epa.gov/enforcement/volkswagen-clean-air-act-civil-settlement</link>	   
<description><![CDATA[Through a series of three partial settlements, the EPA has resolved a civil enforcement case against Volkswagen AG, Audi AG, Dr. Ing. h.c. F. Porsche AG, Volkswagen Group of America, Inc., Volkswagen Group of America Chattanooga Operations, LLC, and Porsche Cars North America, Inc. (collectively &quot;Volkswagen&quot;), subject to reservations set forth in each of the partial settlements. This was achieved through three separate partial settlements. First, on June 28, 2016, the United States lodged with the United States District Court for the District of Northern California the first partial settlement with certain of these Volkswagen entities addressing vehicles containing 2.0 liter diesel engines (the &quot;2.0 liter partial settlement&quot;). On October 25, 2016, the court approved the 2.0 liter partial settlement. Second, on December 20, 2016, the United States lodged with the court the second partial settlement with Volkswagen addressing vehicles containing 3.0 liter diesel engines (the &quot;3.0 liter partial settlement&quot;). Third, on January 11, 2017, the United States lodged with the court the third partial settlement with Volkswagen addressing civil penalties and injunctive relief to prevent future violations (the &quot;third partial settlement&quot;). Subject to their reservations, these settlements resolve allegations that Volkswagen violated the Clean Air Act (&quot;CAA&quot;) by the sale of approximately 590,000 model year 2009 to 2016 diesel motor vehicles equipped with &quot;defeat devices.&quot;  The allegations were set forth in a complaint originally filed by the United States on behalf of the EPA on January 4, 2016, and amended on October 7, 2016, alleging that these vehicles are equipped with defeat devices in the form of computer software designed to cheat on federal emissions tests. The major excess pollutant at issue in this case is oxides of nitrogen (NOx), and is a serious health concern. Concurrent with the third partial settlement, among other resolutions: the United States Department of Justice resolved a criminal case against Volkswagen AG with a plea agreement for the offenses of conspiracy, obstruction of justice, and entry of goods by false statement; and the United States Customs and Border Protection resolved civil fraud claims with Volkswagen arising from the illegal importation of affected vehicles. Details on these resolutions are not included on this page. <em>(<a href="http://www.epa.gov/aboutepa/about-office-enforcement-and-compliance-assurance-oeca">Office of Enforcement and Compliance Assurance (OECA)</a>)</em>.]]></description>
<pubDate>Wed, 11 Jan 2017 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>	
</item>

<item> 
<date>January 6, 2017</date>
<title>EPA Releases Final Analysis of Metals Released from Gold King Mine in the Animas and San Juan Rivers</title>  
<link>https://www.epa.gov/goldkingmine/fate-transport-analysis</link>	   
<description><![CDATA[EPA's Office of Research and Development has finalized the report &quot;Analysis of the Transport and Fate of Metal Released from the Gold King Mine in the Animas and San Juan Rivers.&quot; The report is a scientific analysis that focuses on understanding the river conditions before the GKM release; the movement of the GKM release through the river system; and what has happened to water quality in the river since the time of the GKM release. The research supports EPA&rsquo;s earlier statements that water quality in the affected river system returned to the levels that existed prior to the GKM release and contamination of metals from the release have been moved through the river system to Lake Powell.
  <em>(<a href="https://www.epa.gov/aboutepa/about-office-research-and-development-ord">Office of Research and Development (ORD)</a>)</em>.]]></description>
<pubDate>Thu, 06 Jan 2017 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>	
</item>

<item> 
<date>January 5, 2017</date>
<title>EPA Rebates Will Fund Cleaner School Buses in 88 Communities</title>  
<link>https://www.epa.gov/cleandiesel/clean-diesel-rebates</link>	   
<description><![CDATA[EPA has awarded more than $7.7 million to replace or retrofit 401 older diesel school buses. The funds are going to 88 school bus fleets in 27 states, each of which will receive rebates through EPA&rsquo;s Diesel Emissions Reduction Act (DERA) funding. The new and retrofitted buses will reduce pollutants that are linked to health problems such as asthma and lung damage.  <em>(<a href="http://www.epa.gov/aboutepa/about-office-air-and-radiation-oar">Office of Air and Radiation (OAR)</a>)</em>.]]></description>
<pubDate>Thu, 05 Jan 2017 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>	
</item>


<item> 
<date>January 5, 2017</date>
<title>EPA Gives $3.8M to Help 19 Communities Plan New Uses for Former Brownfield Sites</title>  
<link>https://www.epa.gov/brownfields/national-brownfields-area-wide-planning-grant-selected-proposal-descriptions</link>	
<description><![CDATA[EPA has selected 19 communities for approximately $3.8 million in funding to assist with planning for cleanup and reuse of Brownfield sites as part of the Brownfields Area-Wide Planning (AWP) program. Each recipient will receive up to $200,000 to engage their community and conduct planning activities for brownfield site reuse. The grants will help communities plan improvements such as housing, transportation options, recreation and open space, education and health facilities, social services, renewed infrastructure, increased commerce and employment opportunities. <em>(<a href="http://www.epa.gov/aboutepa/about-office-land-and-emergency-management-olem">Office of Land and Emergency Management (OLEM)</a>)</em>.]]></description>
<pubDate>Thu, 05 Jan 2017 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>	
</item>	

<item> 
<date>December 28, 2016</date>
<title>2016 Recycling Economic Information (REI) Report</title>  
<link>https://www.epa.gov/smm/recycling-economic-information-rei-report</link>	
<description><![CDATA[The Recycling Economic Information (REI) Report aims to increase the understanding of the economic implications of material reuse and recycling. How our society uses materials is fundamental to our economic and environmental future. Global competition for finite resources will intensify as world population and economies grow. More productive and less impactful use of materials helps our society remain economically competitive, contributes to our prosperity and protects the environment in a resource-constrained future. By converting waste materials into valuable raw materials, recycling creates jobs, builds more competitive manufacturing industries and significantly contributes to the U.S. economy. <em>(<a href="http://www.epa.gov/aboutepa/about-office-land-and-emergency-management-olem">Office of Land and Emergency Management (OLEM)</a>)</em>.]]></description>
<pubDate>Wed, 28 Dec 2016 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>	
</item>

<item> 
<date>December 20, 2016</date>
<title>EPA Prohibits 72 Inert Ingredients from Use in Pesticides</title>  
<link>https://www.epa.gov/pesticide-registration/inert-ingredients-overview-and-guidance</link>	
<description><![CDATA[EPA is taking action to remove 72 ingredients from its list of ingredients approved for use in pesticide products. Manufacturers wishing to use these ingredients in the future will have to provide EPA with studies or information to demonstrate their safety. EPA will then consider whether to allow their use. <a href="http://www.epa.gov/pesticides/index.htm">Office of Chemical Safety and Pollution Prevention (OCSPP)</a>]]></description>
<pubDate>Tue, 20 Dec 2016 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>	
</item>	


<item> 
<date>December 20, 2016</date>
<title>Volkswagen to Recall 83,000 3.0 Liter Diesel Vehicles, Fund Mitigation Projects</title>  
<link>https://www.epa.gov/enforcement/volkswagen-clean-air-act-partial-settlements</link>	   
<description><![CDATA[In a second partial settlement, the EPA, the Department of Justice (DOJ), and the State of California, automakers Volkswagen AG, Audi AG, Porsche AG and related entities (collectively referred to as Volkswagen), have agreed to recall 83,000 model year 2009 through 2016 3.0 liter diesel vehicles sold or leased in the U.S. that are alleged to be equipped with &quot;defeat devices&quot; to cheat emissions tests, in violation of the Clean Air Act and California law. For the older vehicles, Volkswagen is required to offer to buy back the vehicles or terminate leases, and must also offer an emissions modification to substantially reduce emissions if one is proposed by Volkswagen and approved by regulators. For the newer vehicles, if Volkswagen demonstrates it can make the vehicles compliant with the certified exhaust emission standards, it will have to fix the vehicles and will not be required to buy the vehicles back. Volkswagen is also required to spend $225 million to fund projects that will reduce emissions of nitrogen oxide (NOx). <em>(<a href="http://www.epa.gov/aboutepa/about-office-enforcement-and-compliance-assurance-oeca">Office of Enforcement and Compliance Assurance (OECA)</a>)</em>.]]></description>
<pubDate>Tue, 20 Dec 2016 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>	
</item>

<item> 
<date>December 19, 2016</date>
<title>2016 Annual Environmental Enforcement Results</title>  
<link>https://www.epa.gov/enforcement/enforcement-annual-results-fiscal-year-2016</link>	   
<description><![CDATA[EPA's 2016 annual enforcement and compliance results demonstrate continued progress implementing Next Generation Compliance technologies and creative solutions in high-impact enforcement cases to reduce pollution, level the playing field for responsible companies and protect public health in communities across the country, including those disproportionately affected by pollution. <em>(<a href="http://www.epa.gov/aboutepa/about-office-enforcement-and-compliance-assurance-oeca">Office of Enforcement and Compliance Assurance (OECA)</a>)</em>.]]></description>
<pubDate>Mon, 19 Dec 2016 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>	
</item>

<item> 
<date>December 15, 2016</date>
<title>EPA Takes Action to Prevent Poisonings from Herbicide</title>  
<link>https://www.epa.gov/ingredients-used-pesticide-products/paraquat-dichloride</link>	
<description><![CDATA[EPA is finalizing safety measures to stop poisonings caused by ingestion of the herbicide paraquat, which can also cause severe injuries or death from skin or eye exposure. <a href="http://www.epa.gov/pesticides/index.htm">Office of Chemical Safety and Pollution Prevention (OCSPP)</a>]]></description>
<pubDate>Thu, 13 Dec 2016 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>	
</item>	

<item> 
<date>December 13, 2016</date>
<title>EPA Releases Final Report on Impacts from Hydraulic Fracturing Activities on Drinking Water Resources </title>  
<link>https://www.epa.gov/hfstudy</link>	
<description><![CDATA[EPA is releasing its scientific report on the impacts from hydraulic fracturing activities on drinking water resources, which provides states and others the scientific foundation to better protect drinking water resources in areas where hydraulic fracturing is occurring or being considered. The report, done at the request of Congress, provides scientific evidence that hydraulic fracturing activities can impact drinking water resources in the United States under some circumstances. As part of the report, EPA identified conditions under which impacts from hydraulic fracturing activities can be more frequent or severe. The report also identifies uncertainties and data gaps. These uncertainties and data gaps limited EPA&rsquo;s ability to fully assess impacts to drinking water resources both locally and nationally. These final conclusions are based upon review of over 1,200 cited scientific sources; feedback from an independent peer review conducted by EPA&rsquo;s Science Advisory Board; input from engaged stakeholders; and new research conducted as part of the study.  <em>(<a href="http://www.epa.gov/aboutepa/about-office-water">Office of Water (OW)</a>)</em>.]]></description>
<pubDate>Tue, 13 Dec 2016 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>	
</item>	


<item> 
<date>December 12, 2016</date>
<title>EPA Requires Stronger Standards for Applying the Riskiest Pesticides </title>  
<link>https://www.epa.gov/pesticide-worker-safety/revised-certification-standards-pesticide-applicators</link>	
<description><![CDATA[EPA has finalized stronger standards for people who apply restricted use pesticides (RUPs). These revisions to the Certification of Pesticide Applicators rule will reduce the likelihood of harm from the misapplication of toxic pesticides. Pesticide use will be safer with increased supervision and oversight. These revisions will help ensure that RUPs are used safely.  <a href="http://www.epa.gov/pesticides/index.htm">Office of Chemical Safety and Pollution Prevention (OCSPP)</a>]]></description>
<pubDate>Mon, 12 Dec 2016 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>	
</item>	

<item> 
<date>December 8, 2016</date>
<title>EPA's National Lakes Assessment Finds Nutrient Pollution is Widespread in Lakes</title>  
<link>https://www.epa.gov/national-aquatic-resource-surveys/nla</link>	
<description><![CDATA[EPA has released the results of a national assessment showing that nutrient pollution is widespread in the nation&rsquo;s lakes, with 4 in 10 lakes suffering from too much nitrogen and phosphorus. Excess nutrients can cause algae blooms, lower oxygen levels, degraded habitat for fish and other life, and lower water quality for recreation. The National Lakes Assessment also found an algal toxin – microcystin – in 39 percent of lakes but below levels of concern. Low concentrations of the herbicide atrazine were found in 30 percent of lakes. <em>(<a href="http://www.epa.gov/aboutepa/about-office-water">Office of Water (OW)</a>)</em>.]]></description>
<pubDate>Thu, 08 Dec 2016 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>	
</item>	

<item> 
<date>December 8, 2016</date>
<title>EPA Clarifies Placement of Required First Aid Statements on Pesticide Product Labels</title>  
<link>https://www.epa.gov/pesticide-registration/label-review-manual</link>	
<description><![CDATA[EPA is clarifying where first aid statements must be placed on pesticide product labels. First aid statements provide important information concerning appropriate first aid in the event of accidental exposure to a pesticide. First aid statements must be immediately visible on a pesticide product when the product is sold or distributed. It should not require opening a booklet or other manipulation of the label to read the first aid statement. <a href="http://www.epa.gov/pesticides/index.htm">Office of Chemical Safety and Pollution Prevention (OCSPP)</a>]]></description>
<pubDate>Thu, 08 Dec 2016 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>	
</item>	

<item> 
<date>December 7, 2016</date>
<title>EPA Moves to Ban Certain Aerosol Degreasers and Dry Cleaning Spot Removers</title>  
<link>https://www.epa.gov/assessing-and-managing-chemicals-under-tsca/evaluating-risk-existing-chemicals-under-tsca</link>	
<description><![CDATA[EPA is proposing to ban certain uses of the toxic chemical trichloroethylene (TCE) due to health risks when used as a degreaser and a spot removal agent in dry cleaning. EPA identified serious risks to workers and consumers associated with TCE uses in a 2014 assessment that concluded that the chemical can cause a range of adverse health effects, including cancer, development and neurotoxicological effects, and toxicity to the liver. Specifically, EPA is proposing to prohibit manufacture (including import), processing, and distribution in commerce of TCE for use in aerosol degreasing and for use in spot cleaning in dry cleaning facilities.  EPA is also proposing to require manufacturers, processors, and distributors to notify retailers and others in their supply chains of the prohibitions.
 <a href="http://www.epa.gov/pesticides/index.htm">Office of Chemical Safety and Pollution Prevention (OCSPP)</a>]]></description>
<pubDate>Wed, 07 Dec 2016 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>	
</item>	

<item> 
<date>December 2, 2016</date>
<title>EPA Proposes Financial Responsibility Requirements for Hardrock Mining Industry</title>  
<link>https://www.epa.gov/superfund/superfund-financial-responsibility</link>	
<description><![CDATA[EPA has proposed financial responsibility requirements for the hardrock mining and mineral processing industry. Learn about the proposed rulemaking. <em>(<a href="http://www.epa.gov/aboutepa/about-office-land-and-emergency-management-olem">Office of Land and Emergency Management (OLEM)</a>)</em>.]]></description>
<pubDate>Thu, 2 Dec 2016 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>	
</item>	

<item> 
<date>December 2, 2016</date>
<title>Slawson to Make System Upgrades and Undertake Projects to Reduce Air Pollution in ND</title>  
<link>https://www.epa.gov/enforcement/slawson-exploration-company-inc-clean-air-act-settlement</link>	   
<description><![CDATA[A settlement with Slawson Exploration Company, Inc., resolving alleged Clean Air Act violations stemming from the company&rsquo;s oil and gas production activities in North Dakota, including on the Fort Berthold Indian Reservation resolves claims that Slawson failed to adequately design, operate, and maintain vapor control systems on its storage tanks at its approximately 170 oil and natural gas well pads in North Dakota, resulting in emissions of volatile organic compounds (VOCs). VOCs are a key component in the formation of smog or ground-level ozone, a pollutant that irritates the lungs, exacerbates diseases such as asthma, and can increase susceptibility to respiratory illnesses, such as pneumonia and bronchitis. As part of this settlement, Slawson&rsquo;s total expenditures on system upgrades, monitoring and inspections are estimated to be $4.1 million. These improvements will significantly reduce VOC emissions and include the use of advanced technology such as infrared cameras and electronic pressure monitors to better detect and respond to air emissions. In addition, Slawson will spend at least an estimated $2 million to fund environmental mitigation projects and pay a $2.1 million civil penalty. <em>(<a href="http://www.epa.gov/aboutepa/about-office-enforcement-and-compliance-assurance-oeca">Office of Enforcement and Compliance Assurance (OECA)</a>)</em>.]]></description>
<pubDate>Thu, 2 Dec 2016 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>	
</item>

<item> 
<date>November 30, 2016</date>
<title>Robust Technical Analysis Supports Leaving Carbon Pollution Standards for Cars and Light Trucks in Place Through 2025, EPA Administrator Finds </title>  
<link>https://www.epa.gov/regulations-emissions-vehicles-and-engines/midterm-evaluation-light-duty-vehicle-greenhouse-gas-ghg</link>	   
<description><![CDATA[EPA Administrator has proposed to determine that the MY 2022-2025 standards remain appropriate and that a rulemaking to change them is not warranted. This proposed determination is based on the robust technical record including the draft TAR, input from the auto industry and other stakeholders, and updated analyses.  <em>(<a href="http://www.epa.gov/aboutepa/about-office-air-and-radiation-oar">Office of Air and Radiation (OAR)</a>)</em>.]]></description>
<pubDate>Thu, 30 Nov 2016 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>	
</item>

<item> 
<date>November 30, 2016</date>
<title>New EPA Guidance for Testing Pesticides Will Reduce Animal Testing </title>  
<link>https://www.epa.gov/pesticide-registration/bridging-or-waiving-data-requirements</link>	
<description><![CDATA[EPA is issuing guidance for requesting waivers of acute dermal toxicity testing requirements for pesticide formulations, which will lead to fewer animal tests for acute dermal toxicity for pesticides. Last March, EPA released a &quot;Draft Retrospective Analysis for Waiving Acute Dermal Toxicity Tests for Pesticide Formulations,&quot; which included guidance for pesticide manufacturers to request waivers of acute dermal toxicity studies for formulations.  <a href="http://www.epa.gov/pesticides/index.htm">Office of Chemical Safety and Pollution Prevention (OCSPP)</a>]]></description>
<pubDate>Thu, 30 Nov 2016 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>	
</item>	

<item> 
<date>November 30, 2016</date>
<title>EPA Names First Chemicals for Review Under New TSCA Legislation</title>  
<link>https://www.epa.gov/assessing-and-managing-chemicals-under-tsca/evaluating-risk-existing-chemicals-under-tsca</link>	
<description><![CDATA[EPA has announced the first 10 chemicals it will evaluate for potential risks to human health and the environment under the Toxic Substances Control Act (TSCA) as amended by the Frank R. Lautenberg Chemical Safety for the 21st Century Act. Under TSCA EPA is now required to evaluate existing chemicals to determine whether they &quot;present an unreasonable risk of injury to health or the environment.&quot; The Agency will start the risk evaluation process for these first 10 chemicals and within six months release a scoping document for each chemical which includes the hazard(s), exposure(s), conditions of use, and the potentially exposed or susceptible subpopulation(s) the Agency plans to consider for the evaluation. TSCA requires these chemical risk evaluations be completed within three years. If EPA determines that a chemical presents an unreasonable risk, EPA must mitigate the risk(s) within two years. <a href="http://www.epa.gov/pesticides/index.htm">Office of Chemical Safety and Pollution Prevention (OCSPP)</a>]]></description>
<pubDate>Thu, 30 Nov 2016 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>	
</item>	

<item> 
<date>November 25, 2016</date>
<title>Guidance on Criteria for Extension of Exclusive Data Use and Minor Use Designation </title>  
<link>https://www.epa.gov/pesticide-registration/details-exclusive-use-data-protection-minor-use-registrations</link>	
<description><![CDATA[EPA has added a document to our website to assist registrants with applying for an extension of the exclusive data use period*. This guidance is intended to help pesticide registrants or applicants for registration by clarifying the criteria for a minor use to qualify for the extension. The guidance answers questions that a registrant may have during the application process. <a href="http://www.epa.gov/pesticides/index.htm">Office of Chemical Safety and Pollution Prevention (OCSPP)</a>]]></description>
<pubDate>Fri, 25 Nov 2016 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>	
</item>	

<item> 
<date>November 23, 2016</date>
<title>EPA Finalizes Increase in Renewable Fuel Volumes</title>  
<link>https://www.epa.gov/renewable-fuel-standard-program/final-renewable-fuel-standards-2017-and-biomass-based-diesel-volume</link>	   
<description><![CDATA[EPA has finalized increases in renewable fuel volume requirements across all categories of biofuels under the Renewable Fuel Standard (RFS) program. In a required annual rulemaking, this action finalizes the volume requirements and associated percentage standards for cellulosic biofuel, advanced biofuel, and total renewable fuel for 2017, and for biomass-based diesel for 2018. <em>(<a href="http://www.epa.gov/aboutepa/about-office-air-and-radiation-oar">Office of Air and Radiation (OAR)</a>)</em>.]]></description>
<pubDate>Tue, 23 Nov 2016 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>	
</item>

<item> 
<date>November 10, 2016</date>
<title>Updated Human Health Risk Analyses for Chlorpyrifos</title>  
<link>https://www.epa.gov/ingredients-used-pesticide-products/proposal-revoke-chlorpyrifos-food-residue-tolerances</link>	
<description><![CDATA[EPA has revised the human health hazard assessment and drinking water exposure assessment for chlorpyrifos that supported our October 2015 proposal to revoke all food residue tolerances for chlorpyrifos. EPA has further analyzed watershed data from across the United States and characterized dietary exposure risk from drinking water residues in order to better understand the risk of chlorpyrifos exposure. EPA will make a final decision by March 31, 2017.  <a href="http://www.epa.gov/pesticides/index.htm">Office of Chemical Safety and Pollution Prevention (OCSPP)</a>]]></description>
<pubDate>Thu, 10 Nov 2016 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>	
</item>	

<item> 
<date>November 17, 2016</date>
<title>U.S. Food Loss and Waste 2030 Champions</title>  
<link>https://www.epa.gov/sustainable-management-food/united-states-food-loss-and-waste-2030-champions</link>	
<description><![CDATA[The U.S. Department of Agriculture (USDA) and EPA have announced the formation of the U.S. Food Loss and Waste 2030 Champions group and presented the first set of 2030 Champions. U.S. Food Loss and Waste 2030 Champions are businesses and organizations that have made a public commitment to reduce food loss and waste in their own operations in the United States by 50 percent by the year 2030. <em>(<a href="http://www.epa.gov/aboutepa/about-office-land-and-emergency-management-olem">Office of Land and Emergency Management (OLEM)</a>)</em>.]]></description>
<pubDate>Thu, 17 Nov 2016 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>	
</item>	

<item> 
<date>November 10, 2016</date>
<title>Registration of Dicamba for Use on Genetically Engineered Crops</title>  
<link>https://www.epa.gov/ingredients-used-pesticide-products/registration-dicamba-use-genetically-engineered-crops</link>	
<description><![CDATA[EPA is registering a dicamba formulation, Xtendimax™ with Vapor Grip™ Technology, which is specifically designed to have lower volatility, to control weeds in cotton and soybean crops genetically engineered to tolerate dicamba.  <a href="http://www.epa.gov/pesticides/index.htm">Office of Chemical Safety and Pollution Prevention (OCSPP)</a>]]></description>
<pubDate>Thu, 10 Nov 2016 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>	
</item>	

<item> 
<date>November 3, 2016</date>
<title>Automakers Outperform Greenhouse Gas Emissions Standards for 4th Consecutive Year</title>  
<link>https://www.epa.gov/regulations-emissions-vehicles-and-engines/greenhouse-gas-ghg-emission-standards-light-duty</link>	   
<description><![CDATA[Passenger vehicles achieved record-high fuel economy while outperforming greenhouse gas emission standards in model year 2015, according to two new reports released by EPA. The GHG Manufacturer Performance Report for 2015 Model Year finds automakers went beyond the model year (MY) 2015 standards by an average 7 grams of CO2 per mile, equivalent to 0.9 miles per gallon (mpg), even as the fleet-wide standard became more stringent by 13 grams of CO2 per mile. All large manufacturers have met the standards through MY 2015. <em>(<a href="http://www.epa.gov/aboutepa/about-office-air-and-radiation-oar">Office of Air and Radiation (OAR)</a>)</em>.]]></description>
<pubDate>Thu, 03 Nov 2016 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>	
</item>

<item> 
<date>October 28, 2016</date>
<title>EPA Issues Rule Finalizing Changes to Existing Hazardous Waste Export and Import Regulations</title>  
<link>https://www.epa.gov/hwgenerators/final-rule-hazardous-waste-export-import-revisions</link>	
<description><![CDATA[EPA has finalized a rule to improve the nation&rsquo;s hazardous waste regulations to protect public health and the environment. The updated Hazardous Waste Import and Export Regulations streamline the hazardous waste export and import process, implement mandatory electronic reporting for international shipments and electronically linking export information.  <em>(<a href="http://www.epa.gov/aboutepa/about-office-land-and-emergency-management-olem">Office of Land and Emergency Management (OLEM)</a>)</em>.]]></description>
<pubDate>Fri, 28 Oct 2016 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>	
</item>	

<item> 
<date>October 27, 2016</date>
<title>EPA Launches New Guide for Long-Term Stormwater Planning</title>  
<link>https://www.epa.gov/npdes/stormwater-planning</link>	
<description><![CDATA[On October 27, 2016, EPA announced a draft guide, toolkit, and technical assistance to promote comprehensive, community-wide planning approaches to manage stormwater. EPA considers this guide a draft that will be supplemented with an integrated online tool to assist communities in implementing the planning process, piloted through community-based technical assistance efforts, and updated over time with feedback from users. <em>(<a href="http://www.epa.gov/aboutepa/about-office-water">Office of Water (OW)</a>)</em>.]]></description>
<pubDate>Thu, 27 Oct 2016 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>	
</item>	

<item> 
<date>October 27, 2016</date>
<title>EPA Releases the EJ 2020 Action Agenda, the Agency's Environmental Justice Strategic Plan for 2016-2020</title>  
<link>https://www.epa.gov/environmentaljustice/ej-2020-action-agenda-epas-environmental-justice-strategy</link>	   
<description><![CDATA[EPA has released the Environmental Justice 2020 Action Agenda (EJ 2020), the Agency&rsquo;s environmental justice strategic plan for 2016 to 2020. EJ 2020 will further integrate environmental justice considerations in all of the Agency&rsquo;s programs, strengthen EPA&rsquo;s collaboration with partners, and demonstrate progress on significant national challenges facing minority and low-income communities.  <em>(<a href="http://www.epa.gov/aboutepa/about-office-enforcement-and-compliance-assurance-oeca">Office of Enforcement and Compliance Assurance (OECA)</a>)</em>.]]></description>
<pubDate>Thu, 27 Oct 2016 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>	
</item>

<item> 
<date>October 27, 2016</date>
<title>Updated Version of Pesticide Label Review Manual Chapter 1 Now Available </title>  
<link>https://www.epa.gov/pesticide-registration/label-review-manual</link>	
<description><![CDATA[EPA has updated the Pesticide Label Review Manual (LRM)&rsquo;s Chapter 1. This manual began as a guide for EPA label reviewers, and now it serves as a tool to assist EPA&rsquo;s stakeholders in understanding the pesticide labeling process. The LRM is also useful in understanding approaches for how labels should generally be drafted.   <a href="http://www.epa.gov/pesticides/index.htm">Office of Chemical Safety and Pollution Prevention (OCSPP)</a>]]></description>
<pubDate>Thu, 27 Oct 2016 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>	
</item>	


<item> 
<date>October 11, 2016</date>
<title>EPA Awarding $1.3 Million to Revitalize America's Urban Waters and Surrounding Communities</title>  
<link>https://www.epa.gov/urbanwaters/urban-waters-small-grants</link>	
<description><![CDATA[EPA is awarding $1.3 million to 22 organizations in 18 states to help protect and restore urban waters and to support community revitalization and other local priorities. <em>(<a href="http://www.epa.gov/aboutepa/about-office-water">Office of Water (OW)</a>)</em>.]]></description>
<pubDate>Tue, 11 Oct 2016 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>	
</item>	


<item> 
<date>October 6, 2016</date>
<title>On 10th Anniversary, EPA Honors WaterSense 2016 Partners of the Year </title>  
<link>https://www3.epa.gov/watersense/partners/winners_2016.html</link>	
<description><![CDATA[Since the program began in 2006, WaterSense labeled products have helped Americans save 1.5 trillion gallons of water and $32.6 billion in water and energy bills. In 2015 alone, WaterSense labeled products saved 437 billion gallons of water. By working together, WaterSense partners across the country continue to make a difference every day. WaterSense recognizes four Sustained Excellence Award winners, seven WaterSense Partners of the Year, and nine Excellence Award winners for helping to advance and promote WaterSense and water efficiency throughout 2015.  <em>(<a href="http://www.epa.gov/aboutepa/about-office-water">Office of Water (OW)</a>)</em>.]]></description>
<pubDate>Thu, 06 Oct 2016 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>	
</item>	


<item> 
<date>October 6, 2016</date>
<title>Detroit Diesel Corp. to Pay Penalty and Reduce Exposure to Harmful Diesel Exhaust to Resolve Clean Air Act Violations</title>  
<link>https://www.epa.gov/enforcement/detroit-diesel-corp-clean-air-act</link>	   
<description><![CDATA[A settlement with Detroit Diesel Corp. resolves alleged violations of the Clean Air Act for selling heavy-duty diesel engines that were not certified by EPA and did not meet applicable emission standards. Under the settlement, Detroit Diesel will spend $14.5 million on projects to reduce nitrogen oxide and other pollutants, including replacing high-polluting diesel school buses and locomotive engines with models that meet current emissions standards. Detroit Diesel will also pay a $14 million civil penalty. The government&rsquo;s complaint, filed along with the settlement, alleges that Detroit Diesel violated the Clean Air Act by introducing into commerce 7,786 heavy-duty diesel engines for use in trucks and buses in model year 2010 without a valid EPA-issued certificate of conformity demonstrating conformance with Clean Air Act standards to control nitrogen oxide (NOx) emissions. The complaint also alleges that the engines did not conform to emission standards applicable to model year 2010 engines. The school bus and locomotive replacement projects will reduce ambient air levels of NOx and other pollutants. In addition, the school bus program will improve air quality inside school buses by reducing exposure to diesel exhaust. Diesel exhaust poses a lung cancer hazard for people and can cause respiratory effects such as asthma. Detroit Diesel intends to target areas for the replacement projects that do not meet Clean Air Act standards for certain air pollutants and areas with low-income communities. <em>(<a href="http://www.epa.gov/aboutepa/about-office-enforcement-and-compliance-assurance-oeca">Office of Enforcement and Compliance Assurance (OECA)</a>)</em>.]]></description>
<pubDate>Thu, 06 Oct 2016 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>	
</item>

<item> 
<date>October 6, 2016</date>
<title>New EPA Web Portal Helps Communities Prepare for Climate Change</title>  
<link>https://www.epa.gov/arc-x</link>	   
<description><![CDATA[A new online portal  will provide local leaders in the nation&rsquo;s 40,000 communities with information and tools to increase resilience to climate change. Using a self-guided format, the Adaptation Resource Center (ARC-X) provides users with information tailored specifically to their needs, based on where they live and the particular issues of concern to them. Recent statistics from the Office of Management and Budget show the federal government has incurred more than $357 billion in direct costs due to extreme weather and fire alone over the last 10 years. Climate change is also expected to pose significant financial and infrastructural challenges to communities in coming decades. EPA designed ARC-X to help all local government official address these challenges – from those with extensive experience and expertise dealing with the impacts of climate change, to those working in underserved communities who are just beginning to meet those challenges. <em>(<a href="http://www.epa.gov/aboutepa/about-office-air-and-radiation-oar">Office of Air and Radiation (OAR)</a>)</em>.]]></description>
<pubDate>Thu, 06 Oct 2016 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>	
</item>

<item> 
<date>October 5, 2016</date>
<title>EPA Awards $1.2 Million in Environmental Justice Collaborative Problem-Solving Cooperative Agreements</title>  
<link>https://www.epa.gov/environmentaljustice/environmental-justice-collaborative-problem-solving-cooperative-agreement-2</link>	   
<description><![CDATA[EPA&rsquo;s Environmental Justice Collaborative Problem-Solving Cooperative Agreement program provides funding for non-profit and tribal organizations to partner with stakeholders from across industry, government, and academia to develop and implement solutions that significantly address environmental and/or public health issues in America&rsquo;s low income and minority communities. Each of this year&rsquo;s recipients will receive up to $120,000 to support two-year projects. The projects will address a variety of environmental justice issues through innovative project activities in areas like green infrastructure, stormwater management and recycling. <em>(<a href="http://www.epa.gov/aboutepa/about-office-enforcement-and-compliance-assurance-oeca">Office of Enforcement and Compliance Assurance (OECA)</a>)</em>.]]></description>
<pubDate>Wed, 05 Oct 2016 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>	
</item>

<item> 
<date>Sept 29, 2016</date>
<title>Sears to Improve Public Health Protections from Lead Pollution During Home Renovations</title>  
<link>https://www.epa.gov/enforcement/sears-home-improvement-products-inc-lead-rrp-rule-settlement</link>	   
<description><![CDATA[EPA and the U.S. Department of Justice (DOJ) announced a settlement with Sears Home Improvement Products Inc. that resolves alleged violations of the federal Lead Renovation, Repair and Painting (RRP) Rule for work performed by Sears&rsquo; contractors during home renovation projects across the country. Under the settlement, Sears will implement a comprehensive, corporate-wide program to ensure that the contractors it hires to perform work minimize lead dust from home renovation activities. Sears will also pay a $400,000 civil penalty.  <em>(<a href="http://www.epa.gov/aboutepa/about-office-enforcement-and-compliance-assurance-oeca">Office of Enforcement and Compliance Assurance (OECA)</a>)</em>.]]></description>
<pubDate>Thu, 29 Sep 2016 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>	
</item>


<item> 
<date>Sept 26, 2016</date>
<title>Memorandum of Understanding Regarding Interagency Coordination and Collaboration for the Protection of Tribal Treaty Rights</title>  
<link>https://www.epa.gov/tribal/memorandum-understanding-regarding-interagency-coordination-and-collaboration-protection</link>	
<description><![CDATA[EPA has announced an interagency agreement on tribal treaty rights and other initiatives designed to advance tribal sovereignty and self-determination. EPA Administrator Gina McCarthy announced this and other initiatives to improve human health and the environment on Indian reservations in remarks at the White House Tribal Nations Conference in Washington. <em>(<a href="https://www.epa.gov/aboutepa/about-office-international-and-tribal-affairs-oita">About the Office of International and Tribal Affairs (OITA)</a>)</em>.]]></description>
<pubDate>mon, 26 Sep 2016 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>	
</item>	

<item> 
<date>Sept 22, 2016</date>
<title>EPA Releases National Assessment of Strategies to Reduce Air Pollution at Ports</title>  
<link>https://www.epa.gov/ports-initiative/national-port-strategy-assessment</link>	   
<description><![CDATA[Ports are a vital part of the United States economy, with seaports, Great Lakes ports, and inland river ports serving as gateways for moving freight and passengers across the country and around the world. As our nation adapts to meet economic and infrastructure demands, it is critical to understand the potential impacts on air pollution, greenhouse gases (GHGs), and the people living, working, and recreating near ports. EPA developed this national scale assessment to examine current and future emissions from a variety of diesel sources operating in port areas, and to explore the potential of a range of available strategies to reduce emissions from port-related trucks, locomotives, cargo handling equipment, harbor craft, and ocean-going vessels. Diesel engines are the modern-day workhorse of the American economy, and although they can be reliable and efficient, older diesel engines can emit significant amounts of air pollution, including fine particulate matter (PM2.5), nitrogen oxides (NOx), air toxics, and carbon dioxide (CO2), which impact human health and the planet. State and local governments, ports and port operators, Tribes, communities, and other stakeholders can use this assessment as a tool to inform their priorities and decisions for port areas and achieve more emission reductions across the United States. <em>(<a href="http://www.epa.gov/aboutepa/about-office-air-and-radiation-oar">Office of Air and Radiation (OAR)</a>)</em>.]]></description>
<pubDate>Thu, 22 Sep 2016 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>	
</item>

<item> 
<date>Sept 15, 2016</date>
<title>EPA Draft Malathion Human Health Assessment Available </title>  
<link>https://www.epa.gov/mosquitocontrol/malathion</link>	
<description><![CDATA[EPA is making the draft malathion human health risk assessment available. For this draft risk assessment, EPA considered exposures from all sources, including food, drinking water, and insect sprays.  In addition, EPA considered all populations including infants, children, and women of child-bearing age.  <a href="http://www.epa.gov/pesticides/index.htm">Office of Chemical Safety and Pollution Prevention (OCSPP)</a>]]></description>
<pubDate>Thu, 15 Sep 2016 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>	
</item>	

<item> 
<date>Sept 1, 2016</date>
<title>EPA Kicks Off Fifth Annual Campus RainWorks Challenge</title>  
<link>https://www.epa.gov/green-infrastructure/campus-rainworks-challenge-0</link>	
<description><![CDATA[EPA launched its fifth annual Campus RainWorks Challenge, a competition for college and university students to design innovative solutions for our nation&rsquo;s water infrastructure. Using their campuses as labs, teams develop green infrastructure systems to reduce stormwater pollution and build resilience to climate change. Since 2012, more than 420 student teams have participated in the challenge. <a href="http://www.epa.gov/aboutepa/about-office-policy-op">Office of Policy (OP)</a>]]></description>  
<pubDate>Thu, 1 Sep 2016 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>	
</item>

<item> 
<date>August 24, 2016</date>
<title>Obama Administration to Help Appalachian Communities Revitalize Downtowns through Broadband Service</title>  
<link>https://www.epa.gov/smartgrowth/cool-connected</link>	
<description><![CDATA[EPA, the U.S. Department of Agriculture (USDA) and the Appalachian Regional Commission (ARC) announced the selection of 10 communities in six states that will participate in the Cool &amp; Connected planning assistance program, an innovative initiative to help people use broadband service for downtown revitalization and economic development. <a href="http://www.epa.gov/aboutepa/about-office-policy-op">Office of Policy (OP)</a>]]></description>  
<pubDate>Wed, 24 Aug 2016 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>	
</item>

<item> 
<date>August 18, 2016</date>
<title>Harley-Davidson to Stop Sales of Illegal Devices that Increased Air Pollution from the Company's Motorcycles</title>  
<link>https://www.epa.gov/enforcement/harley-davidson-clean-air-act-settlement</link>	   
<description><![CDATA[EPA and the U.S. Department of Justice (DOJ) today announced a settlement with Harley-Davidson, Inc., Harley-Davidson Motor Company Group, LLC, Harley-Davidson Motorcycle Company, Inc., and Harley-Davidson Motor Company Operations, Inc. (collectively Harley-Davidson), that requires the companies to stop selling and to buy back and destroy illegal tuning devices that increase air pollution from their motorcycles, and to sell only tuning devices that are certified to meet Clean Air Act emissions standards.  Harley-Davidson will also pay a $12 million civil penalty and spend $3 million on a project to mitigate air pollution through a project to replace conventional woodstoves with cleaner-burning stoves in local communities. <em>(<a href="http://www.epa.gov/aboutepa/about-office-enforcement-and-compliance-assurance-oeca">Office of Enforcement and Compliance Assurance (OECA)</a>)</em>.]]></description>
<pubDate>Thu, 18 Aug 2016 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>	
</item>

<item> 
<date>August 16, 2016</date>
<title>White House, EPA Honor Environmental Educators and Student Award Winners</title>  
<link>https://www.epa.gov/education</link>	   
<description><![CDATA[EPA and the White House Council on Environmental Quality, recognized 18 teachers and 63 students from across the country for their outstanding contributions to environmental education and stewardship.  These 2015 winners and honorable mentions for the annual President&rsquo;s Environmental Youth Award (PEYA) and 2015/2016 Presidential Innovation Award for Environmental Educators (PIAEE) were honored for their work at a ceremony today at the White House. The event included remarks from Gina McCarthy, EPA Administrator; Dr. John Holdren, President Obama&rsquo;s Chief Senior Advisor; and John King, Secretary of Education. <em>(<a href="https://www.epa.gov/aboutepa/about-office-administrator">Office of the Administrator (OA)</a>)</em>.]]></description>
<pubDate>Tue, 16 Aug 2016 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>	
</item>

<item> 
<date>August 16, 2016</date>
<title>EPA and DOT Finalize Greenhouse Gas and Fuel Efficiency Standards for Heavy-Duty Trucks</title>  
<link>https://www3.epa.gov/otaq/climate/regs-heavy-duty.htm</link>	   
<description><![CDATA[EPA and the Department of Transportation&rsquo;s National Highway Traffic Safety Administration jointly finalized standards for medium- and heavy-duty vehicles that would improve fuel efficiency and cut carbon pollution to reduce the impacts of climate change, while bolstering energy security and spurring manufacturing innovation. The final phase two program promotes a new generation of cleaner, more fuel efficient trucks by encouraging the development and deployment of new and advanced cost-effective technologies. The product of four years of extensive testing and research, the vehicle and engine performance standards would cover model years 2018-2027 for certain trailers and model years 2021-2027 for semi-trucks, large pickup trucks, vans, and all types and sizes of buses and work trucks. The final standards are expected to lower CO2 emissions by approximately 1.1 billion metric tons, save vehicle owners fuel costs of about $170 billion, and reduce oil consumption by up to two billion barrels over the lifetime of the vehicles sold under the program. <em>(<a href="http://www.epa.gov/aboutepa/about-office-air-and-radiation-oar">Office of Air and Radiation (OAR)</a>)</em>.]]></description>
<pubDate>Tue, 16 Aug 2016 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>	
</item>

<item> 
<date>August 4, 2016</date>
<title>EPA Awards $4.5 Million to Advance Air Monitoring Technology</title>  
<link>https://cfpub.epa.gov/ncer_abstracts/index.cfm/fuseaction/recipients.display/rfa_id/587</link>	   
<description><![CDATA[EPA awarded grants to six research organizations to work with local communities to explore data quality, durability and uses of low-cost air pollution sensor technology. These research projects will explore how scientific data can be effectively gathered and used by communities to learn about local air quality. These grants are funded through the Science to Achieve Results (STAR) program. <em>(<a href="http://www.epa.gov/aboutepa/about-office-air-and-radiation-oar">Office of Air and Radiation (OAR)</a>)</em>.]]></description>
<pubDate>Thu, 4 Aug 2016 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>	
</item>

<item> 
<date>August 2, 2016</date>
<title>EPA Report Tracks Our Changing Climate</title>  
<link>https://www.epa.gov/climate-indicators/downloads-indicators-report</link>	   
<description><![CDATA[EPA recently released a report that shows compelling and clear evidence of long-term changes to our climate, and highlights impacts on human health and the environment in the United States and around the world. The report, Climate Change Indicators in the United States, features observed trend data on 37 climate indicators, including U.S. and global temperatures, ocean acidity, sea level, river flooding, droughts and wildfires. The report shows that average annual carbon dioxide in the atmosphere has exceeded 400 parts per million for the first time in at least 800,000 years and that average surface air temperatures have risen across the U.S. since 1901. Eight of the top 10 warmest years on record have occurred since 1998, and 2012 and 2015 were the two warmest years on record.  <em>(<a href="http://www.epa.gov/aboutepa/about-office-air-and-radiation-oar">Office of Air and Radiation (OAR)</a>)</em>.]]></description>
<pubDate>Tue, 2 Aug 2016 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>	
</item>
	
<item> 
<date>July 27, 2016</date>
<title>Applying TEAM in Regional Sketch Planning: Three Case Studies in Atlanta, Orlando, St. Louis</title>  
<link>https://www3.epa.gov/otaq/stateresources/policy/pag_transp.htm#tcm</link>	   
<description><![CDATA[EPA has released a new report documenting 3 case studies on the use of TEAM (Travel Efficiency Assessment Method) to estimate potential travel activity and emissions reductions that could be achieved if combinations of travel efficiency strategies were to be adopted in Atlanta, Orlando and St. Louis. The case studies provide a useful planning resource for modeling and estimating greenhouse gas and criteria air pollutant emission reductions resulting from travel efficiency strategies.  <em>(<a href="http://www.epa.gov/aboutepa/about-office-air-and-radiation-oar">Office of Air and Radiation (OAR)</a>)</em>.]]></description>
<pubDate>Wed, 27 Jul 2016 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>	
</item>
	
<item> 
<date>July 27, 2016</date>
<title>EPA Issues Final Rule to Protect the Public from Exposure to Formaldehyde</title>  
<link>https://www.epa.gov/formaldehyde/formaldehyde-emission-standards-composite-wood-products-0</link>	
<description><![CDATA[EPA has finalized a rule to reduce exposure to formaldehyde vapors from certain wood products produced domestically or imported into the United States. EPA worked with the California Air Resources Board to help ensure the final national rule is consistent with California&rsquo;s requirements for composite wood products. The Formaldehyde Emission Standards for Composite Wood Products Act of 2010 established emission standards for formaldehyde from composite wood products and directed EPA to finalize a rule on implementing and enforcing a number of provisions covering composite wood products. <a href="http://www.epa.gov/pesticides/index.htm">Office of Chemical Safety and Pollution Prevention (OCSPP)</a>]]></description>
<pubDate>Wed, 27 Jul 2016 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>	
</item>	

<item> 
<date>July 27, 2016</date>
<title>Cement Manufacturer Cemex to Reduce Harmful Air Pollution from Five Plants under Settlement with EPA and Justice Department</title>  
<link>https://www.epa.gov/enforcement/cemex-inc-global-clean-air-act-settlement</link>	
<description><![CDATA[EPA and the U.S. Department of Justice (DOJ) announced a settlement with Cemex, Inc., under which the company will invest approximately $10 million to cut emissions of harmful air pollution at five of its cement manufacturing plants in Alabama, Kentucky, Tennessee and Texas to resolve alleged violations of the Clean Air Act. Under the consent decree lodged in the U.S. District Court for the Eastern District of Tennessee, Cemex will also pay a $1.69 million civil penalty, conduct energy audits at the five plants, and spend $150,000 on energy efficiency projects to mitigate the effects of past excess emissions of nitrogen oxides (NOx) from its facilities.  <em>(<a href="http://www.epa.gov/aboutepa/about-office-land-and-emergency-management-olem">Office of Land and Emergency Management (OLEM)</a>)</em>.]]></description>
<pubDate>Wed, 27 Jul 2016 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>	
</item>	

<item> 
<date>July 25, 2016</date>
<title>EPA Determines that Aircraft Emissions Contribute to Climate Change Endangering Public Health and the Environment</title>  
<link>https://www3.epa.gov/otaq/aviation.htm</link>	   
<description><![CDATA[The EPA finalized findings that greenhouse gas (GHG) emissions from certain classes of engines used in aircraft contribute to the air pollution that causes climate change endangering public health and welfare under section 231(a) of the Clean Air Act. These findings focus on the six well-mixed GHGs that together represent the largest driver of human-caused climate change: carbon dioxide, methane, nitrous oxide, hydrofluorocarbons, perfluorocarbons, and sulfur hexafluoride. The EPA&rsquo;s final endangerment and contribution findings for aircraft GHG emissions are in preparation for a future domestic rulemaking process to adopt future GHG standards. Any future proposed aircraft engine standards would also be open to public comment and review before they could take effect.  <em>(<a href="http://www.epa.gov/aboutepa/about-office-air-and-radiation-oar">Office of Air and Radiation (OAR)</a>)</em>.]]></description>
<pubDate>Mon, 25 Jul 2016 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>	
</item>	

<item> 
<date>July 20, 2016</date>
<title>2016 Clean Air Excellence Awards </title>  
<link>https://www.epa.gov/caaac/clean-air-excellence-awards</link>	   
<description><![CDATA[ EPA recently recognized 7 groups and individuals for their innovative work on clean air and climate projects. Awards are given to state, local, tribal, and private sector programs in 5 categories of activity that improve air quality, including public education, technology development, and transportation. <em>(<a href="http://www.epa.gov/aboutepa/about-office-air-and-radiation-oar">Office of Air and Radiation (OAR)</a>)</em>.]]></description>
<pubDate>Wed, 20 Jul 2016 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>	
</item>	

<item> 
<date>July 20, 2016</date>
<title>Enbridge Reach $177 Million Settlement after 2010 Oil Spills in Michigan and Illinois </title>  
<link>https://www.epa.gov/enforcement/enbridge-clean-water-act-settlement</link>	   
<description><![CDATA[EPA and the Department of Justice  announced a settlement with Enbridge Energy Limited Partnership and several related Enbridge companies to resolve claims stemming from its 2010 oil spills in Marshall, Mich. and Romeoville, Ill. Enbridge has agreed to spend at least $110 million on a series of measures to prevent spills and improve operations across nearly 2,000 miles of its pipeline system in the Great Lakes region. Enbridge will also pay civil penalties totaling $62 million for Clean Water Act violations -- $61 million for discharging at least 20,082 barrels of oil in Marshall and $1 million for discharging at least 6,427 barrels of oil in Romeoville.  <em>(<a href="http://www.epa.gov/aboutepa/about-office-enforcement-and-compliance-assurance-oeca">Office of Enforcement and Compliance Assurance (OECA)</a>)</em>.]]></description>
<pubDate>Wed, 20 Jul 2016 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>	
</item>

<item> 
<date>July 20, 2016</date>
<title>EPA Research Shows Moderate or Severe Corrosion in Majority of Diesel Fuel Underground Storage Tank Systems Studied</title>  
<link>https://www.epa.gov/ust/alternative-fuels-and-underground-storage-tanks-usts#tab-5</link>	
<description><![CDATA[In a report on corrosion inside diesel fuel underground storage tanks (USTs), the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) found moderate or severe corrosion that could affect metal components inside both steel and fiberglass underground tank systems. Corrosion inside USTs can cause equipment failure by preventing proper operation of release detection and prevention equipment.  If left unchecked, corrosion could cause UST system failures and releases, which could lead to groundwater contamination. Underground tank releases have historically been a leading cause of groundwater contamination. Groundwater is a source of drinking water for almost half of the people in the U.S. EPA&rsquo;s report shows that 35 of 42 – or 83 percent – of the USTs studied exhibited moderate or severe corrosion, but less than 25 percent of owners were aware of corrosion prior to the internal inspection. <em>(<a href="http://www.epa.gov/aboutepa/about-office-land-and-emergency-management-olem">Office of Land and Emergency Management (OLEM)</a>)</em>.]]></description>
<pubDate>Wed, 20 Jul 2016 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>	
</item>	

<item> 
<date>July 18, 2016</date>
<title>Tesoro and Par Clean Air Act Settlement </title>  
<link>https://www.epa.gov/enforcement/tesoro-and-par-clean-air-act-settlement</link>	   
<description><![CDATA[EPA and the U.S. Department of Justice announced a $425 million settlement with subsidiaries of Tesoro Corp., and Par Hawaii Refining that will increase public health protections by reducing air pollution at six refineries and resolving alleged Clean Air Act violations at those same refineries. Under the settlement, the companies will spend about $403 million to install and operate pollution control equipment and Tesoro will spend about $12 million to fund projects that will improve public health in local communities previously impacted by pollution. Tesoro will also pay a civil penalty of more than $10 million to resolve its alleged Clean Air Act violations. <em>(<a href="http://www.epa.gov/aboutepa/about-office-enforcement-and-compliance-assurance-oeca">Office of Enforcement and Compliance Assurance (OECA)</a>)</em>.]]></description>
<pubDate>Mon, 18 Jul 2016 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>	
</item>

<item> 
<date>July 18, 2016</date>
<title>Draft Technical Assessment Report (TAR) </title>  
<link>https://www3.epa.gov/otaq/climate/mte.htm#tar</link>	   
<description><![CDATA[ EPA, NHTSA, and CARB have jointly issued a Draft TAR for public comment. The Draft TAR is a technical report, not a decision document, and examines a wide range of issues relevant to the 2022-2025 standards. Public input on the Draft TAR, along with new data and information, will inform EPA&raquo;s Proposed Determination.  <em>(<a href="http://www.epa.gov/aboutepa/about-office-air-and-radiation-oar">Office of Air and Radiation (OAR)</a>)</em>.]]></description>
<pubDate>Mon, 18 Jul 2016 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>	
</item>	

<item> 
<date>June 30, 2016</date>
<title>The Frank R. Lautenberg Chemical Safety for the 21st Century Act </title>  
<link>https://www.epa.gov/assessing-and-managing-chemicals-under-tsca/frank-r-lautenberg-chemical-safety-21st-century-act</link>	
<description><![CDATA[On June 22, 2016, President Obama signed into law the Frank R. Lautenberg Chemical Safety for the 21st Century Act which amends the Toxic Substance Control Act (TSCA), the Nation&rsquo;s primary chemicals management law. The new law, which received bipartisan support in both the U.S. House of Representatives and the Senate, includes much needed improvements such as: Mandatory requirement for EPA to evaluate existing chemicals with clear and enforceable deadlines; New risk-based safety standard; Increased public transparency for chemical information; and Consistent source of funding for EPA to carry out the responsibilities under the new law.  <a href="http://www.epa.gov/pesticides/index.htm">Office of Chemical Safety and Pollution Prevention (OCSPP)</a>]]></description>
<pubDate>Thu, 30 Jun 2016 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>	
</item>	

<item> 
<date>June 28, 2016</date>
<title>Volkswagen Clean Air Act Partial Settlement </title>  
<link>https://www.epa.gov/enforcement/volkswagen-clean-air-act-partial-settlement</link>	   
<description><![CDATA[On June 28, 2016, the United States lodged with the court a settlement with automakers Volkswagen AG, Audi AG, Volkswagen Group of America, Inc., and Volkswagen Group of America Chattanooga Operations, LLC.  The settlement partially resolves allegations that Volkswagen violated the Clean Air Act.  The allegations were set forth in a complaint filed by the United States on January 4, 2016, on behalf of the EPA, alleging that these vehicles are equipped with defeat devices in the form of computer software designed to cheat on federal emissions tests.  The settlement is a partial settlement because it only addresses what Volkswagen must do to address the 2.0 liter cars on the road and the pollution from these vehicles, and does not address other aspects of the United States&rsquo; complaint. The major excess pollutant at issue in this case is oxides of nitrogen (NOx), and is a serious health concern. <em>(<a href="http://www.epa.gov/aboutepa/about-office-enforcement-and-compliance-assurance-oeca">Office of Enforcement and Compliance Assurance (OECA)</a>)</em>.]]></description>
<pubDate>Tue, 28 Jun 2016 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>	
</item>


<item> 
<date>June 23, 2016</date>
<title>Greening America's Communities</title>  
<link>https://www.epa.gov/smartgrowth/greening-americas-communities</link>	
<description><![CDATA[EPA has selected six cities for technical assistance with sustainable design strategies under its Greening America&rsquo;s Communities (GAC) program. The 2016 cities chosen for assistance are: Columbia, SC; Brownsville, TX; Oklahoma City, OK; Muscatine, IA; Honolulu, HI; and Multnomah County, OR. <a href="http://www.epa.gov/aboutepa/about-office-policy-op">Office of Policy (OP)</a>]]></description>  
<pubDate>Thu, 23 Jun 2016 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>	
</item>


<item> 
<date>June 21, 2016</date>
<title>Antimicrobial Data Requirements Training Videos</title>  
<link>https://www.epa.gov/pesticide-registration/antimicrobial-data-requirements-training-videos</link>	
<description><![CDATA[EPA is releasing five training videos providing guidance on EPA&rsquo;s 40 CFR Part 158W data requirements for antimicrobial pesticides. EPA is offering these training videos to help the public and the pesticide industry better understand the pesticide registration process and to make the process more efficient and transparent.   <a href="http://www.epa.gov/pesticides/index.htm">Office of Chemical Safety and Pollution Prevention (OCSPP)</a>]]></description>
<pubDate>Thu, 21 Jun 2016 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>	
</item>	

<item> 
<date>June 13, 2016</date>
<title>EPA Honors Winners of the 2016 Presidential Green Chemistry Challenge Awards </title>  
<link>https://www.epa.gov/greenchemistry/presidential-green-chemistry-challenge-winners</link>	
<description><![CDATA[EPA is recognizing landmark green chemistry technologies developed by industrial pioneers and leading scientists that turn climate risk and other environmental problems into business opportunities, spurring innovation and economic development. <a href="http://www.epa.gov/pesticides/index.htm">Office of Chemical Safety and Pollution Prevention (OCSPP)</a>]]></description>
<pubDate>Mon, 13 Jun 2016 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>	
</item>	

<item> 
<date>June 7, 2016</date>
<title>Slowing and Combating Pest Resistance to Pesticides </title>  
<link>https://www.epa.gov/pesticide-registration/slowing-and-combating-pest-resistance-pesticides</link>	
<description><![CDATA[EPA has made available for a 60-day comment period two draft Pesticide Registration Notices (PR Notices) that are aimed at combating pesticide resistance. Pesticides can be used to control a variety of pests, such as insects, weeds, rodents, bacteria, and fungi. Over time, many pesticides have gradually lost their effectiveness because pests have developed resistance &ndash; a significant decrease in sensitivity to a pesticide, which reduces the field performance of these pesticides. The Agency is concerned about resistance issues and believes that managing the development of pesticide resistance, in conjunction with alternative pest-management strategies and Integrated Pest Management programs, is an important part of sustainable pest management. To address the growing issue of resistance and preserve the useful life of pesticides, the Agency is beginning to embark on a more widespread effort that is aimed at combating and slowing the development of pesticide resistance. The release of these two PR Notices will allow the Agency to communicate (and seek comment) on potential strategies to combat pesticide resistance. <a href="http://www.epa.gov/pesticides/index.htm">Office of Chemical Safety and Pollution Prevention (OCSPP)</a>]]></description>
<pubDate>Tue, 07 Jun 2016 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>	
</item>	


<item> 
<date>June 7, 2016</date>
<title>Incorporating Environmental Justice into Regulatory Efforts </title>  
<link>https://www.epa.gov/environmentaljustice/technical-guidance-assessing-environmental-justice-regulatory-analysis</link>	   
<description><![CDATA[EPA recently issued its first-ever <em>Technical Guidance for Assessing Environmental Justice in Regulatory Analysis</em>. This guidance represents a significant step towards ensuring the impacts of EPA regulations on vulnerable populations are understood and considered in the decision-making process.
The EJ Technical Guidance improves our ability to perform some of the most important work we do. Better integrating environmental justice in EPA&rsquo;s core regulatory function is essential to ensure that all Americans, regardless of their race, ethnicity, or income level, have access to clean water, clean air, and healthy communities. <em>(<a href="http://www.epa.gov/aboutepa/about-office-enforcement-and-compliance-assurance-oeca">Office of Enforcement and Compliance Assurance (OECA)</a>)</em>.]]></description>
<pubDate>Tue, 07 Jun 2016 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>	
</item>

<item> 
<date>June 2, 2016</date>
<title>EPA Releases Draft Triazine Ecological Risk Assessments</title>  
<link>https://www.epa.gov/ingredients-used-pesticide-products/draft-ecological-risk-assessments-triazines</link>	
<description><![CDATA[EPA is releasing the draft ecological risk assessments for atrazine, propazine and simazine, which evaluate risks to animals and plants including, amphibians, birds, mammals, fish, reptiles, aquatic invertebrates, aquatic plant communities, and terrestrial plants. All three pesticides are in the triazine class of pesticides.  <a href="http://www.epa.gov/pesticides/index.htm">Office of Chemical Safety and Pollution Prevention (OCSPP)</a>]]></description>
<pubDate>Thu, 02 Jun 2016 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>	
</item>	

<item> 
<date>May 31, 2015</date>
<title>EPA Awards Environmental Education Grants in 26 States</title>  
<link>https://www.epa.gov/education/environmental-education-ee-grants</link>	   
<description><![CDATA[EPA has announced the completion of grant awards under the 2015 Environmental Education (EE) Grants Program. EPA will award grants under the 2016 EE Grants Program later this year. Projects address a range of topics and audiences, including tribal middle school education in Washington, watershed literacy in Montana, urban agriculture in Oklahoma, teacher training in Louisiana, green infrastructure in Ohio, and EE in community colleges in New England. <em>(<a href="http://www.epa.gov/aboutepa/about-office-public-engagement-and-environmental-education-opeee">Office of Public Engagement and Environmental Education (OPEEE)</a>)</em>.]]></description>
<pubDate>Tue, 31 May 2015 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>	
</item>	

<item> 
<date>May 5, 2016</date>
<title>Cool &amp; Connected planning assistance program</title>  
<link>https://www.epa.gov/smartgrowth/cool-connected</link>	
<description><![CDATA[Five pilot-phase communities were selected to receive assistance from EPA and USDA to use broadband service to revitalize main streets and promote economic development. <a href="http://www.epa.gov/aboutepa/about-office-policy-op">Office of Policy (OP)</a>]]></description>  
<pubDate>Thu, 05 May 2016 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>	
</item>


<item> 
<date>May 13, 2016</date>
<title>New York High School Student Receives Prestigious Award for Developing Clean Drinking Water Project</title>  
<link>https://www.epa.gov/research/intel-international-science-and-engineering-fair</link>	
<description><![CDATA[A Dix Hills, New York, high school senior has won the EPA&rsquo;s Patrick H. Hurd Sustainability Award for a project currently providing clean drinking water affordably to a community in Kenya. <a href="http://www.epa.gov/aboutepa/about-office-research-and-development-ord">Office of Research and Development (ORD)</a>]]></description>  
<pubDate>Fri, 13 May 2016 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>	
</item>	


<item> 
<date>May 5, 2016</date>
<title>New Tool Helps Communities Assess Economic Impacts of Climate Change</title>  
<link>https://www.epa.gov/smartgrowth/planning-framework-climate-resilient-economy</link>	
<description><![CDATA[EPA worked with the Rhode Island Division of Panning to develop a Planning Framework for a Climate-Resilient Economy to help communities assess how climate change might affect their economy and how to improve their economic resilience. <a href="http://www.epa.gov/aboutepa/about-office-policy-op">Office of Policy (OP)</a>]]></description>  
<pubDate>Thu, 05 May 2016 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>	
</item>

<item> 
<date>May 3, 2016</date>
<title>EPA Celebrates Programs, Tools to Prevent Asthma Attacks</title>  
<link>https://www.epa.gov/asthma/national-environmental-leadership-award-asthma-management</link>	   
<description><![CDATA[May is Asthma Awareness Month, when EPA spotlights ways people can take simple steps to help prevent asthma attacks. EPA also honors local asthma management programs for their leadership in improving the lives of people living with asthma, especially those in underserved communities. On May 12, EPA will honor the winners of the agency&rsquo;s National Environmental Leadership Award in Asthma Management. Each winner is an outstanding national model for comprehensive asthma care.  These four winners are: AmeriHealth Caritas of Philadelphia; Urban Health Plan of Bronx, N.Y.; New England Asthma Innovation Collaborative of Boston; and Public Health – Seattle and King County of Seattle.   <em>(<a href="http://www.epa.gov/aboutepa/about-office-air-and-radiation-oar">Office of Air and Radiation (OAR)</a>)</em>.]]></description>
<pubDate>Tue, 03 May 2016 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>	
</item>	

<item> 
<date>May 2, 2016</date>
<title>Pesticide Program Update: Updated Registration Review Schedule Now Available</title>  
<link>https://www.epa.gov/pesticide-reevaluation/registration-review-schedules</link>	
<description><![CDATA[EPA has released an updated schedule for the Pesticide Registration Review program, covering planned draft risk assessments, proposed interim decisions, and interim decisions for antimicrobials, biopesticides and conventional chemicals through the end of the 2016 fiscal year. Through the Pesticide Registration Review program, EPA reviews all registered pesticides at least every 15 years, as mandated by the Federal Insecticide, Fungicide, and Rodenticide Act. EPA bases its decisions on the best available sound science. However, science is constantly evolving, and new scientific information can come to light at any time and change our understanding of potential risks from pesticides. The review of new data could potentially prolong the risk assessment and decision-making process and change this schedule. <a href="http://www.epa.gov/pesticides/index.htm">Office of Chemical Safety and Pollution Prevention (OCSPP)</a>]]></description>
<pubDate>Mon, 02 May 2016 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>	
</item>	

<item> 
<date>April 28, 2016</date>
<title>EPA Administrator McCarthy Announces 2016 Safer Choice Partner of the Year Awards</title>  
<link>https://www.epa.gov/saferchoice/safer-choice-partner-year-awards</link>	
<description><![CDATA[EPA is recognizing 24 Safer Choice Partner of the Year award winners across 12 states, the District of Columbia and Canada for outstanding achievement in the design, manufacture, promotion and use of a range of cleaning and other household products that carry the Safer Choice label.  <a href="http://www.epa.gov/pesticides/index.htm">Office of Chemical Safety and Pollution Prevention (OCSPP)</a>]]></description>
<pubDate>Thu, 28 Apr 2016 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>	
</item>	

<item> 
<date>April 21, 2016</date>
<title>2016 SmartWay Affiliate Challenge</title>  
<link>https://www3.epa.gov/smartway/forsupporters/index.htm#affiliate</link>	   
<description><![CDATA[EPA's annual Affiliate Challenge is a way for EPA to recognize top-performing Affiliates that conduct exceptional educational activities supporting the SmartWay program.   <em>(<a href="http://www.epa.gov/aboutepa/about-office-air-and-radiation-oar">Office of Air and Radiation (OAR)</a>)</em>.]]></description>
<pubDate>Thu, 21 Apr 2016 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>	
</item>	

<item> 
<date>April 19, 2016</date>
<title>Food: Too Good to Waste Implementation Guide and Toolkit</title>  
<link>https://www.epa.gov/sustainable-management-food/food-too-good-waste-implementation-guide-and-toolkit</link>	
<description><![CDATA[Thirty-seven million tons of food waste was generated by Americans in 2013; 95% of that was thrown away in incinerators and landfills. Wasted food in landfills becomes a significant source of methane, a powerful greenhouse gas, as it rots. By donating wholesome, nutritious food and composting inedible food, we can help feed our communities and the earth while reducing greenhouse gas emissions. Earth Day is April 22. Combat food waste by using smart household food management practices. EPA&rsquo;s Food: Too Good to Waste Toolkit offers simple tips about how to reduce your wasted food through awareness, smart shopping, storage, and saving.  <em>(<a href="http://www.epa.gov/aboutepa/about-office-land-and-emergency-management-olem">Office of Land and Emergency Management (OLEM)</a>)</em>.]]></description>
<pubDate>Tue, 19 Apr 2016 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>	
</item>	


<item> 
<date>April 6, 2016</date>
<title>EPA Takes Action to Reduce Exposure to TCE in Art and Crafts Spray Fixatives</title>  
<link>https://www.epa.gov/assessing-and-managing-chemicals-under-tsca/trichloroethylene-significant-new-use-rule-federal</link>	
<description><![CDATA[EPA has finalized a significant new use rule (SNUR) for trichloroethylene (TCE). The significant new use is the manufacture or processing for use in a consumer product, with an exception for use of TCE in cleaners and solvent degreasers, film cleaners, hoof polishes, lubricants, mirror edge sealants, and pepper spray. <a href="http://www.epa.gov/pesticides/index.htm">Office of Chemical Safety and Pollution Prevention (OCSPP)</a>]]></description>
<pubDate>Wed, 06 Apr 2016 10:00:00 EST</pubDate>	
</item>	




</channel></rss>