<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?><rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.epa.gov/feed/50563/rss.xml" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/" xmlns:og="http://ogp.me/ns#" xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#" xmlns:sioc="http://rdfs.org/sioc/ns#" xmlns:sioct="http://rdfs.org/sioc/types#" xmlns:skos="http://www.w3.org/2004/02/skos/core#" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#">
  <channel>
    <title>Criteria Air Pollutants</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/feed/50563/rss.xml</link>
    <description>Updated Criteria Air Pollutants content from the US Environmental Protection Agency</description>
    <language>en</language>
     <atom:link href="https://www.epa.gov/feed/50563/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      <item>
    <title>Fact Sheet: Supplemental Proposal: State Plans to Address Emissions during Startup, Shutdown and Malfunction (SSM)</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/criteria-air-pollutants/fact-sheet-supplemental-proposal-state-plans-address-emissions-during</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;On September 5, 2014, the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) proposed a rule supplementing and revising its February 2013 proposal to ensure states have plans in place that require industrial facilities across the country to follow air pollution rules during times when the facility is starting up or shutting down, or when a malfunction occurs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-270819&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-03/documents/ssm_sip_snpr_fact_sheet.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=34793&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Fact Sheet: State Plans to Address Emissions during Startup, Shutdown and Malfunction: Supplemental Proposal to Address Affirmative Defense Provisions (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(4 pp, 35 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 24 Mar 2016 19:53:18 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>rcopland</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">141293 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Fact Sheet: Proposed Rule: State Plans to Address Emissions During Startup, Shutdown, and Malfunction (SSM)</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/criteria-air-pollutants/fact-sheet-proposed-rule-state-plans-address-emissions-during-startup</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;On February 12, 2013, the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) proposed a rule that would ensure states have plans in place that require industrial facilities across the country to follow air pollution rules during times when the facility is starting up or shutting down, or when a malfunction occurs. Air pollution emitted during these periods may adversely impact the health of people nearby and contribute to smog and other problems in communities that are further downwind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-270807&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-03/documents/ssm_fs_021213.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=33190&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Fact Sheet: State Plans to Address Emissions During Startup, Shutdown, and Malfunction: Proposed Response to Petition for Rulemaking , Findings of Inadequacy, and Call for Plan Revisions (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(4 pp, 33 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 24 Mar 2016 19:43:38 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>rcopland</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">141287 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Fact Sheet: Final Rule: State Plans to Address Emissions During Startup, Shutdown and Malfunction (SSM)</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/criteria-air-pollutants/fact-sheet-final-rule-state-plans-address-emissions-during-startup-shutdown</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;On May 22, 2015, the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) issued a final action to ensure states have plans in place that are fully consistent with the Clean Air Act and recent court decisions concerning startup, shutdown and malfunction (SSM) operations. Air pollution emitted during these periods may adversely affect the health of people in neighboring and downwind communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This final action specifically:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;responds to the Sierra Club Petition&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;clarifies the EPA’s SSM Policy to assure consistency with the Clean Air Act and recent court decisions; and&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;finalizes the Administrator’s findings that the SSM provisions in the SIPs of 36 states (applicable in 45 statewide and local jurisdictions and no tribal areas) do not meet the requirements of the Clean Air Act (CAA) and accordingly issues a “SIP call” for each of those states. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-270795&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-03/documents/20150522fs.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=62541&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Fact Sheet: State Plans to Address Emissions During Startup, Shutdown and Malfunction: Final Action on Response to Petition for Rulemaking, Restatement of Policy, Findings of Inadequacy and Call for Revisions (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(5 pp, 63 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 24 Mar 2016 19:36:33 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>rcopland</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">141283 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Startup, Shutdown, &amp; Malfunction (SSM) Emissions</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/criteria-air-pollutants/startup-shutdown-malfunction-ssm-emissions</link>
    <description>&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;May 22, 2015&lt;/strong&gt; - EPA issued a final action to ensure states have plans in place that are fully consistent with the Clean Air Act and recent court decisions concerning startup, shutdown and malfunction (SSM) operations.

		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gpo.gov/fdsys/pkg/FR-2015-06-12/pdf/2015-12905.pdf#page=2&quot;&gt;Final Rule: State Implementation Plans: Response to Petition for Rulemaking; Restatement and Update of EPA’s SSM Policy Applicable to SIPs; Findings of Substantial Inadequacy; and SIP Calls to Amend Provisions Applying to Excess Emissions During Periods of Startup, Shutdown and Malfunction (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(147 pp, 928 K, &lt;a href=&quot;/home/pdf-files&quot;&gt;About PDF&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/criteria-air-pollutants/fact-sheet-final-rule-state-plans-address-emissions-during-startup-shutdown&quot;&gt;Fact Sheet on the Final Rule&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gpo.gov/fdsys/pkg/FR-2015-06-12/pdf/2015-12905.pdf#page=8&quot;&gt;List of Affected States (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(147 pp, 928 K, &lt;a href=&quot;/home/pdf-files&quot;&gt;About PDF&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Background Information:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;June 2011:  &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.regulations.gov/#!documentDetail;D=EPA-HQ-OAR-2012-0322-0002&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Sierra Club&#039;s Petition&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;February 4, 2013:  &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.regulations.gov/#!documentDetail;D=EPA-HQ-OAR-2012-0322-0029&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Legal Background Memorandum&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;February 22, 2013:  &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gpo.gov/fdsys/pkg/FR-2013-02-22/pdf/2013-03734.pdf#page=2&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Federal Register Proposed Rule (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(82 pp, 675 K, &lt;a href=&quot;/home/pdf-files&quot;&gt;About PDF&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/criteria-air-pollutants/fact-sheet-proposed-rule-state-plans-address-emissions-during-startup&quot;&gt;Fact Sheet on the Proposed Rule&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;September 5, 2014
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gpo.gov/fdsys/pkg/FR-2014-09-17/pdf/2014-21830.pdf#page=2&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Supplemental Proposal (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(38 pp, 464 K, &lt;a href=&quot;/home/pdf-files&quot;&gt;About PDF&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/criteria-air-pollutants/fact-sheet-supplemental-proposal-state-plans-address-emissions-during&quot;&gt;Fact Sheet on the Supplemental Proposal&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 24 Mar 2016 16:05:45 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>rcopland</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">141237 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Menu of Control Measures for NAAQS Implementation</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/criteria-air-pollutants/menu-control-measures-naaqs-implementation</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;The Menu of Control Measures (MCM) provides state, local and tribal air agencies with the existing emission reduction measures as well as relevant information concerning the efficiency and cost effectiveness of the measures. State, local and tribal agencies will be able to use this information in developing emission reduction strategies, plans and programs to assure they attain and maintain the National Ambient Air Quality Standards (NAAQS). The MCM is a living document that can be updated with newly available or more current data as it becomes available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;file-258291&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-vndopenxmlformats-officedocumentspreadsheetmlsheet&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/sites/production/files/2016-02/menuofcontrolmeasures.xlsx&quot; type=&quot;application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.spreadsheetml.sheet; length=491163&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Menu of Control Measures (Excel)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(491 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-253711&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-02/documents/menuofcontrolmeasures.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=560779&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Menu of Control Measures (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(66 pp, 561 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 23 Feb 2016 20:33:08 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>rcopland</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">136491 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>NAAQS Implementation Process</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/criteria-air-pollutants/naaqs-implementation-process</link>
    <description>&lt;div class=&quot;box multi related-info right&quot;&gt;
	&lt;h2 class=&quot;pane-title&quot;&gt;Process of Setting and Implementing NAAQS&lt;/h2&gt;

	&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/criteria-air-pollutants/process-reviewing-national-ambient-air-quality-standards&quot;&gt;Standards&lt;/a&gt; - setting, reviewing, and revising the standards&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/criteria-air-pollutants/naaqs-designations-process&quot;&gt;Designations&lt;/a&gt; - determining whether areas meet the standards&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Implementation&lt;/strong&gt; - attaining and maintaining the standards&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When EPA establishes a new national ambient air quality standard (NAAQS) or revises an existing standard for each &lt;a href=&quot;/criteria-air-pollutants&quot;&gt;criteria air pollutant&lt;/a&gt;, it sets in motion a series of actions aimed at ensuring that air quality throughout the country meets those standards. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA must designate areas as meeting (attainment) or not meeting (nonattainment) the standard. The Clean Air Act requires states to develop a general plan to attain and maintain the standards in all areas of the country and a specific plan to attain the standards for each area designated nonattainment. These plans, known as State Implementation Plans or SIPs, are developed by state and local air quality management agencies and submitted to EPA for approval.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The SIPs serve two main purposes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;Demonstrate that the state has the basic air quality management program components in place to implement a new or revised NAAQS.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Identify the emissions control requirements the state will rely upon to attain and/or maintain the primary and secondary NAAQS.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;h2&gt;SIP Development Process&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Within two years after setting a new NAAQS or revising an exiting standard:&lt;/strong&gt; With input from the states and tribes, EPA must identify or &quot;designate&quot; areas as meeting (attainment areas) or not meeting (nonattainment areas), the standards. Designations are based on the most recent set of air monitoring or modeling data characterizing an area.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Within three years after setting a new NAAQS or revising an exiting standard:&lt;/strong&gt; All states must submit state implementation plans to show they have the basic air quality management program components in place to implement a new or revised NAAQS, as specified in Clean Air Act section 110. These plans are often called &quot;infrastructure SIPs.&quot; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www3.epa.gov/airquality/urbanair/sipstatus/infrastructure.html&quot;&gt;Learn more about Infrastructure SIP requirements&lt;/a&gt;. See &lt;a href=&quot;https://www3.epa.gov/airquality/urbanair/sipstatus/docs/Guidance_on_Infrastructure_SIP_Elements_Multipollutant_FINAL_Sept_2013.pdf&quot;&gt;Guidance on Development and Submission of Infrastructure State Implementation Plans for National Ambient Air Quality Standards (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt; (62pp, 533k)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Within 18-36 months after designations:&lt;/strong&gt; Due dates for nonattainment area SIPs are based on the area designation date and vary by pollutant and area classification. SIPs for areas designated as nonattainment for sulfur dioxide (SO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;), nitrogen dioxide (NO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;), coarse particle pollution (PM&lt;sub&gt;10&lt;/sub&gt;), and lead (Pb) are generally due no later than 18 months from the date of designation. SIPs for Ozone (O&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;), fine particle pollution (PM&lt;sub&gt;2.5&lt;/sub&gt;), and carbon monoxide (CO) nonattainment areas are generally due within 36 months from the date of designation. Each nonattainment area SIP must outline the strategies and emissions control measures that show how the area will improve air quality and meet the NAAQS. In addition, the Clean Air Act mandates that areas adopt certain specified control requirements. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www3.epa.gov/airquality/urbanair/sipstatus/nonattainment.html&quot;&gt;Learn more about SIP requirements for nonattainment areas&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;SIPs must be developed with public input, be formally adopted by the state, and submitted by the Governor&#039;s designee to EPA. After reviewing submitted SIPs, EPA proposes to approve or disapprove all or part of each plan. The public has an opportunity to comment on EPA&#039;s proposed action. EPA considers public input before taking final action on a state&#039;s plan. If EPA approves all or part of a SIP, those control measures are enforceable in federal court. If a state fails to submit an approvable plan or if EPA disapproves a plan, EPA is required to develop a federal implementation plan (FIP).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2014 15:43:34 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>rcopland</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">50847 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>NAAQS Designations Process</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/criteria-air-pollutants/naaqs-designations-process</link>
    <description>&lt;div class=&quot;box multi related-info right&quot;&gt;
	&lt;h2 class=&quot;pane-title&quot;&gt;Process of Setting and Implementing NAAQS&lt;/h2&gt;

	&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/criteria-air-pollutants/process-reviewing-national-ambient-air-quality-standards&quot;&gt;Standards&lt;/a&gt; - setting, reviewing, and revising the standards&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Designations&lt;/strong&gt; - determining whether areas meet the standards&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/criteria-air-pollutants/naaqs-implementation-process&quot;&gt;Implementation&lt;/a&gt; - attaining and maintaining the standards&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After EPA sets a new National Ambient Air Quality Standard or revises an existing standard for each &lt;a href=&quot;/criteria-air-pollutants&quot;&gt;criteria air pollutant&lt;/a&gt;, the Clean Air Act requires EPA to determine if areas the country meet the new standards. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;States and tribes submit recommendations to the EPA as to whether or not an area is attaining the national ambient air quality standards for a criteria pollutant. The states and tribes base these recommendations on air quality data collected from monitors at locations in urban and rural settings as well as other information characterizing air quality such as modeling. After working with the states and tribes and considering the information from air quality monitors, and/or models, EPA will &quot;designate&quot; an area as attainment or nonattainment for the standard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the air quality in a geographic area meets or is cleaner than the national standard, it is called an attainment area (designated “unclassifiable/attainment”); areas that don&#039;t meet the national standard are called nonattainment areas.  In some cases, EPA is not able to determine an area&#039;s status after evaluating the available information.  Those areas are designated &quot;unclassifiable.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once designations take effect, state and local governments must develop implementation plans outlining how areas will attain and maintain the standards by reducing air pollutant emissions. Tribes may elect to develop tribal implementation plans but are not required to do so.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2014 15:42:08 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>rcopland</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">50845 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Process of Reviewing the National Ambient Air Quality Standards</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/criteria-air-pollutants/process-reviewing-national-ambient-air-quality-standards</link>
    <description>&lt;div class=&quot;box multi related-info right&quot;&gt;
	&lt;h2 class=&quot;pane-title&quot;&gt;Process of Setting and Implementing NAAQS&lt;/h2&gt;

	&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Standards&lt;/strong&gt; - setting, reviewing, and revising the standards&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/criteria-air-pollutants/naaqs-designations-process&quot;&gt;Designations&lt;/a&gt; - determining whether areas meet the standards&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/criteria-air-pollutants/naaqs-implementation-process&quot;&gt;Implementation&lt;/a&gt; - attaining and maintaining the standards&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sections 108 and 109 of the &lt;a href=&quot;/clean-air-act-overview&quot;&gt;Clean Air Act (CAA)&lt;/a&gt; govern the establishment, review, and revision, as appropriate, of the National Ambient Air Quality Standards (NAAQS) for each &lt;a href=&quot;/criteria-air-pollutants&quot;&gt;criteria air pollutant&lt;/a&gt; to provide protection for the nation’s public health and the environment.  The CAA requires periodic review of the science upon which the standards are based and the standards themselves.  Reviewing the NAAQS is a lengthy undertaking and includes the following major phases:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Planning&lt;/strong&gt;:  The planning phase of the NAAQS review process begins with a science policy workshop, which is intended to gather input from the scientific community and the public regarding policy-relevant issues and questions that will frame the review.  Drawing from the workshop discussions, EPA prepares an Integrated Review Plan (IRP) that presents the schedule for the entire review, the process for conducting the review, and the key policy-relevant science issues that will guide the review. &lt;/p&gt;

	&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Integrated Science Assessment (ISA)&lt;/strong&gt;:  This assessment is a comprehensive review, synthesis, and evaluation of the most policy-relevant science, including key science judgments that are important to inform the development of the risk and exposure assessments, as well as other aspects of the NAAQS review.  &lt;/p&gt;

	&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Risk/Exposure Assessment (REA)&lt;/strong&gt;:  This assessment draws upon information and conclusions presented in the ISA to develop quantitative characterizations of exposures and associated risks to human health or the environment associated with recent air quality conditions and with air quality estimated to just meet the current or alternative standard(s) under consideration.  This assessment includes a characterization of the uncertainties associated with such estimates. &lt;/p&gt;

	&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Policy Assessment (PA):&lt;/strong&gt;  This assessment provides a transparent staff analysis of the scientific basis for alternative policy options for consideration by senior EPA management prior to rulemaking.  Such an evaluation of policy implications is intended to help ‘‘bridge the gap’’ between the Agency’s scientific assessments, presented in the ISA and REA(s), and the judgments required of the EPA Administrator in determining whether it is appropriate to retain or revise the NAAQS.  In so doing, the PA is also intended to facilitate the &lt;a href=&quot;http://yosemite.epa.gov/sab/sabpeople.nsf/WebCommittees/CASAC&quot;&gt;Clean Air Scientific Advisory Committee’s (CASAC’s&lt;/a&gt;) advice to the Agency and recommendations to the Administrator, as provided for in the CAA, on the adequacy of the existing standards or revisions that may be appropriate to consider.  The PA focuses on the information that is most pertinent to evaluating the basic elements of the NAAQS:  indicator, averaging time, form, and level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scientific review during the development of these documents is thorough and extensive.  Drafts of all documents are reviewed by CASAC and the public has an opportunity to comment on them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rulemaking:  &lt;/strong&gt;Taking into consideration the information in the ISA, REA(s), and PA and the advice of CASAC, EPA develops and publishes a notice of proposed rulemaking that communicates the Administrator’s proposed decisions regarding the review of the NAAQS.  A public comment period, during which public hearings are generally held, follows publication of the notice of proposed rulemaking.  Taking into account comments received on the proposed rule, EPA issues a final rule.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/naaqs/historical-information-naaqs-review-process&quot;&gt;More Information on the NAAQS review process&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Fri, 11 Apr 2014 16:07:20 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>rcopland</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">50751 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>NAAQS Table</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/criteria-air-pollutants/naaqs-table</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;/clean-air-act-overview&quot;&gt;Clean Air Act&lt;/a&gt;, which was last amended in 1990, requires EPA to set National Ambient Air Quality Standards (40 CFR part 50) for pollutants considered harmful to public health and the environment. The Clean Air Act identifies two types of national ambient air quality standards. &lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;Primary standards&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/i&gt; provide public health protection, including protecting the health of &quot;sensitive&quot; populations such as asthmatics, children, and the elderly. &lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;Secondary standards&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/i&gt; provide public welfare protection, including protection against decreased visibility and damage to animals, crops, vegetation, and buildings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The EPA has set National Ambient Air Quality Standards for six principal pollutants, which are called &lt;a href=&quot;/criteria-air-pollutants&quot;&gt;&quot;criteria&quot; air pollutants&lt;/a&gt;. Periodically, the standards are reviewed and may be revised. The current standards are listed below. Units of measure for the standards are parts per million (ppm) by volume, parts per billion (ppb) by volume, and micrograms per cubic meter of air (µg/m&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;Pollutant&lt;br /&gt;
				[links to historical tables of NAAQS reviews]&lt;/th&gt;
			&lt;th&gt;Primary/&lt;br /&gt;
				Secondary&lt;/th&gt;
			&lt;th&gt;Averaging Time&lt;/th&gt;
			&lt;th&gt;Level&lt;/th&gt;
			&lt;th&gt;Form&lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot; rowspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/co-pollution/table-historical-carbon-monoxide-co-national-ambient-air-quality-standards-naaqs&quot;&gt;Carbon Monoxide (CO)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td rowspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;primary&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;8 hours&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;9 ppm&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td rowspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;Not to be exceeded more than once per year&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;1 hour&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;35 ppm&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;blue&quot; colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/lead-air-pollution/table-historical-lead-pb-national-ambient-air-quality-standards-naaqs&quot;&gt;Lead (Pb)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td class=&quot;blue&quot;&gt;primary and&lt;br /&gt;
				secondary&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td class=&quot;blue&quot;&gt;Rolling 3 month average&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td class=&quot;blue&quot;&gt;0.15 μg/m&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#1&quot;&gt;(1)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td class=&quot;blue&quot;&gt;Not to be exceeded&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td colspan=&quot;2&quot; rowspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/no2-pollution/table-historical-nitrogen-dioxide-national-ambient-air-quality-standards-naaqs&quot;&gt;Nitrogen Dioxide (NO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;primary&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;1 hour&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;100 ppb&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;98th percentile of 1-hour daily maximum concentrations, averaged over 3 years&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;primary and&lt;br /&gt;
				secondary&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;1 year&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;53 ppb &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#2&quot;&gt;(2)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Annual Mean&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;blue&quot; colspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/ozone-pollution/table-historical-ozone-national-ambient-air-quality-standards-naaqs&quot;&gt;Ozone (O&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td class=&quot;blue&quot;&gt;primary and&lt;br /&gt;
				secondary&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td class=&quot;blue&quot;&gt;8 hours&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td class=&quot;blue&quot;&gt;0.070 ppm &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#3&quot;&gt;(3)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td class=&quot;blue&quot;&gt;Annual fourth-highest daily maximum 8-hour concentration, averaged over 3 years&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td rowspan=&quot;4&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/pm-pollution/table-historical-particulate-matter-pm-national-ambient-air-quality-standards-naaqs&quot;&gt;Particle Pollution (PM)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td rowspan=&quot;3&quot;&gt;PM&lt;sub&gt;2.5&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;primary&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;1 year&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;12.0 μg/m&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;annual mean, averaged over 3 years&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;secondary&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;1 year&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;15.0 μg/m&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;annual mean, averaged over 3 years&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;primary and&lt;br /&gt;
				secondary&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;24 hours&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;35 μg/m&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;98th percentile, averaged over 3 years&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;PM&lt;sub&gt;10&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;primary and&lt;br /&gt;
				secondary&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;24 hours&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;150 μg/m&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Not to be exceeded more than once per year on average over 3 years&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;blue&quot; colspan=&quot;2&quot; rowspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/so2-pollution/table-historical-sulfur-dioxide-national-ambient-air-quality-standards-naaqs&quot;&gt;Sulfur Dioxide (SO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td class=&quot;blue&quot;&gt;primary&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td class=&quot;blue&quot;&gt;1 hour&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td class=&quot;blue&quot;&gt;75 ppb &lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#4&quot;&gt;(4)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td class=&quot;blue&quot;&gt;99th percentile of 1-hour daily maximum concentrations, averaged over 3 years&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;blue&quot;&gt;secondary&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td class=&quot;blue&quot;&gt;3 hours&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td class=&quot;blue&quot;&gt;0.5 ppm&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td class=&quot;blue&quot;&gt;Not to be exceeded more than once per year&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot; id=&quot;1&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;(1) In areas designated nonattainment for the Pb standards prior to the promulgation of the current (2008) standards, and for which implementation plans to attain or maintain the current (2008) standards have not been submitted and approved, the previous standards (1.5 µg/m3 as a calendar quarter average) also remain in effect.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot; id=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;(2) The level of the annual NO2 standard is 0.053 ppm. It is shown here in terms of ppb for the purposes of clearer comparison to the 1-hour standard level.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot; id=&quot;3&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;(3) Final rule signed October 1, 2015, and effective December 28, 2015. The previous (2008) O3 standards additionally remain in effect in some areas. Revocation of the previous (2008) O3 standards and transitioning to the current (2015) standards will be addressed in the implementation rule for the current standards. &lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;caption&quot; id=&quot;4&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;(4) The previous SO2 standards (0.14 ppm 24-hour and 0.03 ppm annual) will additionally remain in effect in certain areas: (1) any area for which it is not yet 1 year since the effective date of designation under the current (2010) standards, and (2)any area for which an implementation plan providing for attainment of the current (2010) standard has not been submitted and approved and which is designated nonattainment under the previous SO2 standards or is not meeting the requirements of a SIP call under the previous SO2 standards (40 CFR 50.4(3)).  A SIP call is an EPA action requiring a state to resubmit all or part of its State Implementation Plan to demonstrate attainment of the required NAAQS.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p id=&quot;menu&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Menu of Control Measures for NAAQS Implementation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Menu of Control Measures (MCM) provides state, local and tribal air agencies with the existing emission reduction measures as well as relevant information concerning the efficiency and cost effectiveness of the measures. State, local and tribal agencies will be able to use this information in developing emission reduction strategies, plans and programs to assure they attain and maintain the National Ambient Air Quality Standards (NAAQS). The MCM is a living document that can be updated with newly available or more current data as it becomes available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/criteria-air-pollutants/menu-control-measures-naaqs-implementation&quot;&gt;Menu of Control Measures&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 10 Apr 2014 18:02:37 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>pdickers</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">50665 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  </channel>
</rss>

<!-- Page cached by Boost @ 2017-01-25 04:37:09, expires @ 2017-01-25 16:37:09, lifetime 12 hours -->