<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?><rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.epa.gov/feed/139055/rss.xml" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/" xmlns:og="http://ogp.me/ns#" xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#" xmlns:sioc="http://rdfs.org/sioc/ns#" xmlns:sioct="http://rdfs.org/sioc/types#" xmlns:skos="http://www.w3.org/2004/02/skos/core#" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#">
  <channel>
    <title>Ozone Pollution and Your Patients&#039; Health</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/feed/139055/rss.xml</link>
    <description>Updated Ozone Pollution and Your Patients&#039; Health content from the US Environmental Protection Agency</description>
    <language>en</language>
     <atom:link href="https://www.epa.gov/feed/139055/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      <item>
    <title>Ozone and Your Patients&#039; Health: Course Developers</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/ozone-pollution-and-your-patients-health/ozone-and-your-patients-health-course-developers</link>
    <description>&lt;strong&gt;Course Developers:&lt;/strong&gt;



&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;William F. McDonnell, MD, PhD, &lt;/b&gt;is an environmental health consultant whose current research interests include development and evaluation of ozone exposure-response models for use in risk assessment.  He previously served as a United States Public Health Service officer detailed to the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency (EPA). He received his MD from Washington University in St. Louis and his PhD in epidemiology from the University of North Carolina, and he is trained in General Preventive Medicine. Dr. McDonnell developed and implemented the EPA&#039;s ozone epidemiology research strategy and studied the respiratory health effects of experimental ozone exposure in humans for 25 years at EPA&#039;s Human Studies Facility in Chapel Hill, North Carolina. Dr. McDonnell has published widely on the health effects of ozone and has received numerous scientific and honor awards from EPA.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;James A. Raub, MS,&lt;/b&gt; was a Health Scientist and Project Manager in EPA&#039;s National Center for Environmental Assessment in Research Triangle Park, North Carolina. Mr. Raub&#039;s public health career involved the assessment of cardiopulmonary changes caused by the exposure of humans and laboratory animals to environmental pollutants found in the ambient air. Early in his career, Mr. Raub developed research methods for measuring cardiopulmonary function in laboratory animals exposed to pharmaceutical compounds and environmental pollutants. After that, his work focused on the health assessment of ozone and carbon monoxide, for which he received EPA&#039;s Gold and Bronze Medals for Exceptional Service to the Public. In addition to publishing journal articles and book chapters on the use of animal models for pollutant risk assessment, he organized and contributed to the most recent EPA Air Quality Criteria Documents on ozone and carbon monoxide that provide the scientific basis for ambient air quality standards in the United States. He also served as a temporary advisor to the World Health Organization on environmental health criteria for international air quality guidelines. Mr. Raub has a BS in zoology from Pennsylvania State University and an MS in physiology from the University of California, Davis, and did PhD graduate work in toxicology at the University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Donald C. Spencer, MD, MBA, &lt;/b&gt;is board certified in family medicine and has been with the Department of Family Medicine at the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill (UNC) since 1996, where he is a Professor of Family Medicine and the Associate Director of Medical Informatics. Dr. Spencer graduated in 1973 from Stanford University with a degree in biology, received his MD in 1977 from the UCLA School of Medicine, and completed his residency in family medicine in 1980 at the University of Missouri-Columbia. Dr. Spencer also received a Masters of Business Administration in 1993 from the University of Missouri- Columbia. Between 1980 and 1986 he worked in private practice in rural Anson County, North Carolina, and then between 1986 and 1996 he taught and practiced at the University of Missouri-Columbia Department of Family and Community Medicine, where he established office information systems in three rural practice sites and was responsible for informatics curriculum development in the family medicine residency.

		&lt;p&gt;Dr. Spencer&#039;s interests are in the areas of medical practice management and information sciences. His informatics activities include membership on the UNC Health Care Information Technology Advisory Board, chair of the UNC Health Care Medical Information Management Committee, and member of the UNC Health Care HIPAA Policy Committee. Dr. Spencer is a member of the American Academy of Family Physicians (AAFP).&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Susan Lyon Stone, MS&lt;/b&gt;, is a Senior Environmental Health Scientist with EPA’s Office of Air Quality Planning and Standards in the group that reviews the national ambient air quality standards. Ms. Stone is the team leader for the review of the ozone standard and has worked on the reviews of the standards for particulate matter and sulfur dioxide. She is the Air Quality Index (AQI) team leader, has coauthored many of EPA’s public information documents about the AQI, the health effects of criteria pollutants, and she has given presentations across the U.S. and internationally on these subjects, including a course at the United Nations Commission on Sustainable Development. She is the co-lead for the National-Scale Activity Survey (N-SAS) which will evaluate the effectiveness of AQI advisories in changing public behavior. Ms. Stone has an M.S. from the School of Public Health at the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;James Brown, MSPH, PhD,&lt;/b&gt; is a Senior Health Scientist for the U.S. EPA, National Center for Environmental Assessment (NCEA), Environmental Media Assessment Group. He received a masters (1991) and doctorate (2000) from the School of Public Health at the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill (UNC-CH). Prior to joining NCEA in December 2003, he was a Research Associate for the Center for Environmental Medicine, Asthma, and Lung Biology at UNC-CH. His primary research interest is the transport, deposition, and clearance of particles and gases in the healthy and diseased human respiratory tract. In 2006, he served as a Monograph Working Group member evaluating the carcinogenic risk to humans from exposure to carbon black, titanium dioxide, and non-asbestiform talc for the International Agency for Research on Cancer. He has received numerous awards for his research and particulate matter and ozone assessments including three U.S. EPA Gold Medals and a Young Investigator Award from the International Society for Aerosols in Medicine in 2003. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ellen Wildermann, MSPH,&lt;/strong&gt; has worked as an Environmental Engineer with EPA&#039;s Office of Air Quality Planning and Standards (OAQPS) since 1989. Currently, one of her responsibilities is to develop training and outreach materials for a variety of audiences, including health care providers. The outreach topics include promoting understanding and use of the Air Quality Index to reduce exposure to unhealthy air. She has a Master of Science in Public Health (MSPH) degree from the School of Public Health at the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
     <pubDate>Fri, 30 Sep 2016 14:17:48 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>mpayne02</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">161695 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>End of Ozone Pollution and Your Patients&#039; Health Training</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/ozone-pollution-and-your-patients-health/end-ozone-pollution-and-your-patients-health-training</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;You have now reached the end of the online training course, Ozone Pollution and Your Patients&#039; Health.&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg right view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:250px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;patient education&quot; height=&quot;197&quot; width=&quot;250&quot; class=&quot;right media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2016-06/patient-ed.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Return to the &lt;a href=&quot;/ozone-pollution-and-your-patients-health&quot;&gt;main page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jun 2016 15:33:49 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>rcopland</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">153437 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Table 2. Gradation of Individual Responses to  Short-Term Ozone Exposure in People with Lung Disease</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/ozone-pollution-and-your-patients-health/table-2-gradation-individual-responses-short-term-ozone</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;Table 2. Gradation of Individual Responses to &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;Short-Term Ozone Exposure in People with Lung Disease&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-293599&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-06/documents/aqi_table_2_ozone_and_your_patients_health_us_epa.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=139454&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;aqi_table_2_ozone_and_your_patients_health (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(1 pg, 139 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jun 2016 12:54:16 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>mpayne02</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">152221 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Table 1: Gradation of Individual Responses to Short-Term Ozone Exposure in Healthy People</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/ozone-pollution-and-your-patients-health/table-1-gradation-individual-responses-short-term-ozone</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt; Gradation of Individual Responses to Short-Term Ozone Exposure in Healthy People&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-293597&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-06/documents/aqi_table_1_ozone_and_your_patients_health_us_epa.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=133040&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;aqi_table_1 (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(1 pg, 133 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jun 2016 12:47:54 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>mpayne02</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">152217 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Course Evaluation - Ozone and Your Patients&#039; Health</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/ozone-pollution-and-your-patients-health/forms/course-evaluation-ozone-and-your-patients-health</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;Please let us know what you think of this course. Your answers will help us make improvements in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 11 May 2016 15:49:24 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>rcopland</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">149273 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Clinical Scenarios - Ozone</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/ozone-pollution-and-your-patients-health/clinical-scenarios-ozone</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg left view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:142px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;boy w doctor&quot; title=&quot;boy w doctor&quot; height=&quot;128&quot; width=&quot;142&quot; class=&quot;left media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2016-05/andres_dr2.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg right view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:155px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;doc &amp;amp; young man&quot; title=&quot;doc &amp;amp; young man&quot; height=&quot;128&quot; width=&quot;155&quot; class=&quot;right media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2016-05/havier_dr2_0.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg center view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:170px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;nurse &amp;amp; girl&quot; title=&quot;nurse &amp;amp; girl&quot; height=&quot;128&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; class=&quot;center media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2016-05/nurse_girl2.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Clinical Scenario 1&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A 12-year-old girl arrives at your office with her mother for an evaluation of the child&#039;s asthma. The mother reports that yesterday her daughter developed chest tightness and shortness of breath at soccer practice. A couple of puffs on her albuterol inhaler relieved the symptoms and allowed her to finish the practice. Rescue medication was needed again after dinner, and the girl woke up during the night and this morning with wheezing and shortness of breath. A mild expiratory wheeze is still perceptible. The mother says generally her daughter has been doing fine since starting a daily regimen of ICS six months ago. There have been only two episodes of wheezing and both of them have been during the nights following soccer practices on Code Red ozone air quality days. The mother asks you, &quot;Do you think ozone caused her wheezing? Should I make her skip practice if it&#039;s a Code Red air quality day? Is it safe for her to go out at all on those days?&quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;accordion&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#pane-1&quot; title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;Discussion&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

		&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;pane-1&quot;&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;Clinical Scenario 1: A 12-year-old girl arrives at your office with her mother for an evaluation of the child&#039;s asthma. The mother reports that yesterday her daughter developed chest tightness and shortness of breath at soccer practice. A couple of puffs on her albuterol inhaler relieved the symptoms and allowed her to finish the practice. Rescue medication was needed again after dinner, and the girl woke up during the night and this morning with wheezing and shortness of breath. A mild expiratory wheeze is still perceptible. The mother says generally her daughter has been doing fine since starting a daily regimen of inhaled corticosteroids six months ago. There have been only two episodes of wheezing and both of them have been during the nights following soccer practices on Code Red ozone air quality days. The mother asks you, &quot;Do you think ozone caused her wheezing? Should I make her skip practice if it&#039;s a Code Red air quality day? Is it safe for her to go out at all on those days?&quot; &lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;Discussion: &lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;1. Ozone is a known trigger for exacerbating asthma. As with other triggers, some individuals are more likely to be affected by ozone than others. For each individual, the increased likelihood of having an asthma attack is influenced by baseline asthma status, by individual sensitivity to ozone, and by the dose of ozone inhaled (dose = the product of concentration, minute ventilation, and duration of exposure). An individual whose asthma is quiescent, who has historically not had exacerbations on days when ozone levels are high, and who will be exercising only for a short time on a Code Orange day is less likely to have an ozone related asthma attack than is an individual with a recent viral upper respiratory infection, who is known to be sensitive to ozone, and who will be performing intense, prolonged outdoor exercise on a Code Red day. &lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;2. Balanced response. There is no single &quot;correct&quot; course of action for all individuals with asthma on Code Orange or Red days. Rather the potential costs and benefits of any action must be weighed. On the one hand, physical activity has obvious health benefits, and participation in a particular activity may be of importance to an individual. On the other hand, ozone exposure can increase the probability of an asthma attack. Those with poorly controlled asthma or who are known to be particularly sensitive to ozone exposure will probably benefit more by reducing exposure or increasing medication use than those who are less sensitive to ozone. All asthmatics with an Asthma Action Plan should carefully monitor their asthma status and follow the recommendations of their plan for any sign of worsening asthma. &lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;3. Exposure reduction. As with other agents that are known to exacerbate asthma, reduction of exposure to ozone is likely to reduce the probability of an asthma attack. By reducing the dose of ozone inhaled, exposure can be reduced on heavily polluted days. Because indoor levels are usually only 20% to 80% of outdoor levels, reducing time spent outdoors or reducing the level or duration of outdoor activity during the times of day that ozone levels tend to be highest in your area can be effective measures. For organized sports, practices can be held at traditionally less polluted times of day and activities can be reduced or shortened on more polluted days. Anyone known to respond adversely to ozone should include exposure reduction in his or her Asthma Action Plan. &lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;4. Medication. Because no information specific to treatment or prevention of ozone-induced asthma exacerbations is available, one should probably approach the medical management of asthma during high ozone seasons as one would approach exposures to other asthma triggers. One would likely treat the individual with an occasional exposure differently from an individual attending a two-week soccer camp with long, intense workouts every day during the high ozone season. Although there is some evidence that antioxidant (Vitamins C and E) supplementation in individuals with asthma can modestly reduce the neurally-mediated lung function changes due to ozone exposure, such treatment does not appear to reduce the inflammatory response to ozone, and there is no evidence that it would reduce asthma attacks. There is some evidence that regular treatment with inhaled steroids results in a blunted inflammatory response to ozone exposure without an effect on immediate lung function and symptom changes. Whether this reduction in the inflammatory response would result in a decreased probability of a later asthma exacerbation has not been addressed.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h2&gt;Clinical Scenario 2&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the well-child physical exam of a 3-year-old boy, the mother indicates that she is starting back to work and, for four days a week, she will be leaving her son in a local day care. She has a few questions about the day care situation she has found for him. One of the questions concerns outdoor playtime on days with high levels of air pollution. It is the daycare&#039;s policy to let the children go out for an hour in the morning on Code Orange or Red air quality days. The mother asks you, &quot;Shouldn&#039;t they keep him in on days when air pollution levels are high?&quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;accordion&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#pane-2&quot; title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;Discussion&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

		&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;pane-2&quot;&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;Clinical Scenario 2: During the well-child physical exam of a 3-year-old boy, the mother indicates that she is starting back to work and, for four days a week, she will be leaving her son in a local day care. She has a few questions about the day care situation she has found for him. One of the questions concerns outdoor playtime on days with high levels of air pollution. It is the daycare&#039;s policy to let the children go out for an hour in the morning on Code Orange or Red air quality days. The mother asks you, &quot;Shouldn&#039;t they keep him in on days when air pollution levels are high?&quot; &lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;Discussion: &lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;1. Long-term health effects. Although there is no conclusive answer as to whether long-term exposure to ozone can result in serious health effects in people without asthma, there is some evidence suggesting that long-term exposure may predispose one to development of new asthma and may interfere with the postnatal growth and development of the respiratory system. These potential effects may be related to the reversible respiratory epithelial injury and inflammation accompanying short-term exposure. On the other hand, long-term ozone exposure does not appear to account for a large part of the asthma or other respiratory disease in the population living in some cites of the United States with high ozone levels. Research in these areas will hopefully help quantify any health risks of long-term exposure and identify the determinants of exposure most responsible for any such effects. &lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;2. Benefits of exercise. It is well known that active exercise promotes better health for children and adults. The well-documented benefits of exercise should not be given up as one tries to avoid potential health effects of ozone exposure. If one chooses to reduce outdoor activity when ozone levels are high, indoor activity should be increased on those days or outdoor activity should be increased at times of the day or on other days when pollution levels are lower. &lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;3. Balanced response. Given the known health benefits of exercise, the inevitable scheduling of outdoor activities that may be important to one or one&#039;s children during high ozone periods, and the uncertainties of ozone health effects, it is hard to argue that one should never exercise outdoors on high ozone days. On the other hand, it would be prudent to minimize cumulative exposure when possible by reducing exposure on days when outdoor ozone levels are high (Code Orange or Red days) without reducing the overall level of physical activity. The inhaled dose of ozone (the product of concentration, minute ventilation, and duration of exposure) can be reduced on heavily polluted days by reducing the amount of time spent outdoors or reducing the level and duration of outdoor activity during the times of day that ozone levels tend to be highest in your area. In areas where ozone levels are routinely high, one might develop a schedule for outdoor activities that avoids the worst times of day and that allows for either rescheduling activities or reducing activity levels on bad days.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

			
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Clinical Scenario 3&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A 32-year-old man comes in to the office with concerns about the exercise program he recently started. After discussing problems with a sore knee, he describes an episode of coughing and chest discomfort - like a burning sensation in the airways - that occurred recently. Although it was a Code Orange day for ozone, he decided to go for a run. Shortly after leaving his home, the man started coughing, so he slowed to a brisk walk. Even at that pace, he felt a burning sensation in his chest made worse by taking a deep breath. So he went home and rested on the couch. In about an hour the pain subsided. He asks you, &quot;Can air pollution cause burning like that?&quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;accordion&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#pane-3&quot; title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;Discussion&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

		&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;pane-3&quot;&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;Clinical Scenario 3: A 32-year-old man comes in to the office with concerns about the exercise program he recently started. After discussing problems with a sore knee, he describes an episode of coughing and chest discomfort - like a burning sensation in the airways - that occurred recently. Although it was a Code Orange day for ozone, he decided to go for a run. Shortly after leaving his home, the man started coughing, so he slowed to a brisk walk. Even at that pace, he felt a burning sensation in his chest made worse by taking a deep breath. So he went home and rested on the couch. In about an hour the pain subsided. He asks you, &quot;Can air pollution cause burning like that?&quot; &lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;Discussion: &lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;1. Health effects. Short-term ozone exposure can cause cough, pain or discomfort on deep inspiration, and shortness of breath during and immediately following exposure in otherwise healthy people. These symptoms are reversible and usually disappear within several hours of terminating exposure. There is some evidence suggesting that long-term exposure to high ozone levels may have long-term effects, but this is preliminary, and there is no information as to whether an acutely sensitive individual would be at more risk of a long-term effect. The limited data available indicate that the degree of sensitivity as measured by symptoms (e.g., cough) is not related to the degree of sensitivity as measured by the reactions in the respiratory tract (e.g., reversible respiratory epithelial cell injury and inflammation) that also accompany ozone exposure. &lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;2. Inter-individual variability. Individuals vary in their responsiveness to ozone. This individual appears to be a more responsive individual. Although there is variability in responsiveness within an age group, in general, young adults (teens to thirties) appear to be more responsive than older adults (fifties to eighties), though children do not appear to be more sensitive than young adults with regard to respiratory symptoms.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Clinical Scenario 4&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A 68 year old patient comes to your office for a routine visit six months following an uncomplicated myocardial infarction.  He has just completed cardiac rehabilitation and is asking your advice about his proposed ongoing exercise program.  He has experienced no chest pain or shortness of breath since his MI, and his hypertension is controlled.  He would like to exercise for 30 minutes on a cycle ergometer on three days per week at a local gym and take a 60 minute outdoor walk on two other days.  However, he heard on NPR that the National Research Council has found that more people are likely to die on days when ozone pollution is bad and wonders if there is anything he can do to avoid that risk. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;accordion&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#pane-4&quot; title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot;&gt;&lt;small&gt;Discussion&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

		&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;pane-4&quot;&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;Clinical Scenario 4: A 68-year old patient comes to your office for a routine visit six months following an uncomplicated myocardial infarction (MI). He has just completed cardiac rehabilitation and is asking your advice about his proposed ongoing exercise program. He has experienced no chest pain or shortness of breath since his MI, and his hypertension is controlled. He would like to exercise for 30 minutes on a cycle ergometer on three days per week at a local gym and take a 60 minute outdoor walk on two other days. However, he heard on NPR that the National Research Council has found that more people are likely to die on days when ozone pollution is bad and wonders if there is anything he can do to avoid that risk. &lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;Discussion: &lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;1. Mortality risk of ozone exposure. It is true that non-accidental mortality rates are generally higher on days when ozone concentrations are high than when they are low. Daily death rates increase approximately 0.5% for each 20 ppb increase in the 24-hour average ozone concentration, and available data suggest that this effect is present even at very low concentrations of ozone. Although this suggests that ozone is responsible for many deaths in the total population, the absolute increase in risk to the average individual on any given day is quite low. For example, a 0.5% increase in daily death rates for an individual with a 10 year average life expectancy increases the daily probability of death from 0.0001176 to 0.0001182 or approximately 6 additional deaths per day per 10 million people. There appears to be some variability in the effect of ozone across different regions with the risk potentially being somewhat higher in some areas and somewhat lower in others. It is also true that elevated levels of particle pollution, another air pollutant, have been observed to be associated with increased daily mortality and with adverse events in patients with underlying cardiovascular disease. &lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;2. Benefits of exercise. The benefits of regular exercise on many aspects of physical and mental health have been well documented as have the benefits for reducing the probability of a recurrent MI in those with underlying cardiovascular disease. This patient should be strongly encouraged to maintain a program of regular exercise to realize these well established benefits. &lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;3. Balanced response. The optimal solution for this patient is to continue his exercise program as planned while taking several steps that may reduce his risk from air pollution. These steps involve reducing exposure when feasible without creating barriers to exercise, and they require the patient to become familiar with the daily Air Quality Index and with temporal patterns of air pollution in his location. Because outdoor concentrations of ozone are almost always higher than indoor concentrations, the patient could vary his days of indoor and outdoor exercise such that he exercised indoors on days when ozone concentrations were highest and outdoors on lower concentrations days. Ozone concentrations usually fluctuate over the course of the day in a stable pattern for a single location. Outdoor exercise could be scheduled to occur at times of the day such as early mornings when ozone is usually low. A similar approach could be used to jointly reduce exposure to particle pollution. Unfortunately indoor concentrations of particles are not much lower than those encountered outdoors so indoor exercise is not as effective in reducing exposure as it is for ozone. However, avoiding exercise at times of day when and where particle pollution levels are generally high could result in a lower risk. This includes morning and evening rush hour, locations along busy roadways, and times when there is smoke in the air from wood stoves, fireplaces, or forest fires. On the occasional days when ozone and particle pollution levels are extremely high all day, it may be prudent to avoid or reduce the intensity or duration of exercise.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 class=&quot;indented&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/ozone-pollution-and-your-patients-health/patient-exposure-and-air-quality-index&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PREVIOUS&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;    |    &lt;a href=&quot;/ozone-pollution-and-your-patients-health/frequent-questions-ozone-and-your-patients-health&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NEXT&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Mon, 02 May 2016 14:44:46 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>rcopland</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">148265 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Review Questions - Ozone</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/ozone-pollution-and-your-patients-health/review-questions-ozone</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;q01&quot; name=&quot;q01&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol start=&quot;1&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Harmful ambient ozone levels typically occur in the summertime, but they can occur throughout the year in some southern and mountain locations.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;indented&quot;&gt;&lt;input name=&quot;question1&quot; type=&quot;radio&quot; value=&quot;&quot; /&gt; A. True &lt;br /&gt;&lt;input name=&quot;question1&quot; type=&quot;radio&quot; value=&quot;&quot; /&gt; B. False &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;accordion&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#pane-1&quot; title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot;&gt;Answer&lt;/a&gt;

		&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;pane-1&quot;&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;True: Within the last decade, high ozone concentrations have been observed under specific circumstances in cold months, where a few high elevation areas in the Western U.S. with high levels of local VOC and NOx emissions have formed ozone when snow is on the ground and temperatures are near or below freezing. Ozone contributes to what we typically experience as &quot;smog&quot; or haze, which still occurs most frequently in the summertime, but can occur throughout the year in some southern and mountain regions.&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ol start=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Only individuals who exercise heavily outdoors are affected by ozone.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;indented&quot;&gt;&lt;input name=&quot;question2&quot; type=&quot;radio&quot; value=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt; A. True&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;input name=&quot;question2&quot; type=&quot;radio&quot; value=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt; B. False &lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;accordion&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#pane-2&quot; title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot;&gt;Answer&lt;/a&gt;

		&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;pane-2&quot;&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;False: Anyone who spends time outdoors when ozone levels are high may be affected, but people who exercise heavily, such as children, joggers and outdoor workers, may be at particular risk for experiencing ozone health effects. This is because the effects of ozone exposure relate directly to the inhaled dose, which depends, in part, on how hard an individual is breathing (minute ventilation). Ozone exposure also depends on the ambient ozone concentration and the duration of exposure.&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ol start=&quot;3&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Only individuals living near urban areas are at risk of significant ozone exposure.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;indented&quot;&gt;&lt;input name=&quot;question3&quot; type=&quot;radio&quot; value=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt; A. True&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;input name=&quot;question3&quot; type=&quot;radio&quot; value=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt; B. False &lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;accordion&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#pane-3&quot; title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot;&gt;Answer&lt;/a&gt;

		&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;pane-3&quot;&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;False. As a result of long-range transport of ozone or ozone precursors, ground-level ozone can occur many miles from emission sources and, therefore, can be higher in rural areas than in urban areas.&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ol start=&quot;4&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;In the general population, short-term ozone exposure is associated with&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;indented&quot;&gt;&lt;input name=&quot;question4&quot; type=&quot;radio&quot; value=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt; A. An increase in daily mortality&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;input name=&quot;question4&quot; type=&quot;radio&quot; value=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt; B. Lung function changes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;input name=&quot;question4&quot; type=&quot;radio&quot; value=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt; C. Respiratory inflammation&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;input name=&quot;question4&quot; type=&quot;radio&quot; value=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt; D. Respiratory symptoms&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;input name=&quot;question4&quot; type=&quot;radio&quot; value=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt; E. B, C, and D&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;input name=&quot;question4&quot; type=&quot;radio&quot; value=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt; F. All of the above &lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;accordion&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#pane-4&quot; title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot;&gt;Answer&lt;/a&gt;

		&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;pane-4&quot;&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;F. All of the above. Ozone exposure has been experimentally determined to cause lung function changes, respiratory inflammation, and respiratory symptoms in all populations. Multiple epidemiological studies have observed an association between short-term ozone concentration and daily mortality rates. Although it may ultimately turn out that the individuals most at risk of dying have underlying disease, this has not been established at this time.&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ol start=&quot;5&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Individuals with which of the following conditions are more susceptible to the effects of ozone?&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;indented&quot;&gt;&lt;input name=&quot;question5&quot; type=&quot;radio&quot; value=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt; A. Allergic rhinitis&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;input name=&quot;question5&quot; type=&quot;radio&quot; value=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt; B. Asthma &lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;input name=&quot;question5&quot; type=&quot;radio&quot; value=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt; C. Angina&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;input name=&quot;question5&quot; type=&quot;radio&quot; value=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt; D. Congestive heart failure &lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;accordion&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#pane-5&quot; title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot;&gt;Answer&lt;/a&gt;

		&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;pane-5&quot;&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;B. Asthma. Numerous studies have reported that elevated ozone levels are associated with aggravation of asthma, but ozone has not been shown to be associated with allergic rhinitis, angina, or congestive heart failure. Sensitive groups also include children; people with other lung diseases, such chronic bronchitis, and emphysema; older adults; and active people who work or exercise outdoors.&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;q06&quot; name=&quot;q06&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol start=&quot;6&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;The mechanisms that might contribute to ozone&#039;s ability to worsen existing asthma include:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;indented&quot;&gt;&lt;input name=&quot;question6&quot; type=&quot;radio&quot; value=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt; A. Increased nonspecific airway reactivity&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;input name=&quot;question6&quot; type=&quot;radio&quot; value=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt; B. Increased respiratory inflammation&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;input name=&quot;question6&quot; type=&quot;radio&quot; value=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt; C. Increased responsiveness to inhaled allergen&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;input name=&quot;question6&quot; type=&quot;radio&quot; value=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt; D. A and C only&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;input name=&quot;question6&quot; type=&quot;radio&quot; value=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt; E. A, B, and C &lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;accordion&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#pane-6&quot; title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot;&gt;Answer&lt;/a&gt;

		&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;pane-6&quot;&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;E. A, B, and C. Exposure to ozone has been shown to cause each of these health endpoints, and each health endpoint contributes to aggravation of existing asthma.&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;q07&quot; name=&quot;q07&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol start=&quot;7&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Ozone health effects can be reduced by:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;indented&quot;&gt;&lt;input name=&quot;question7&quot; type=&quot;radio&quot; value=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt; A. Reducing activity level during high ozone periods&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;input name=&quot;question7&quot; type=&quot;radio&quot; value=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt; B. Drinking plenty of fluids&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;input name=&quot;question7&quot; type=&quot;radio&quot; value=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt; C. Spending more time indoors during high ozone periods&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;input name=&quot;question7&quot; type=&quot;radio&quot; value=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt; D. A and C only &lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;input name=&quot;question7&quot; type=&quot;radio&quot; value=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt; E. A, B, and C &lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;accordion&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#pane-7&quot; title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot;&gt;Answer&lt;/a&gt;

		&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;pane-7&quot;&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;D. A and C only. Reducing outdoor activity level and staying indoors when ozone levels are high will reduce ozone exposure and reduce the amount of ozone penetrating deeply into the lungs. Drinking plenty of fluids has no effect on ozone exposure or ozone-related health effects.&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;q08&quot; name=&quot;q08&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol start=&quot;8&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Ozone is primarily scrubbed from inhaled air in the nose.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;indented&quot;&gt;&lt;input name=&quot;question8&quot; type=&quot;radio&quot; value=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt; A. True&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;input name=&quot;question8&quot; type=&quot;radio&quot; value=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt; B. False &lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;accordion&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#pane-8&quot; title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot;&gt;Answer&lt;/a&gt;

		&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;pane-8&quot;&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;B. False. Most ozone breathed penetrates into the lungs. Because ozone has limited solubility in water, the upper respiratory tract is not as effective in scrubbing ozone from inhaled air as it is for more water soluble pollutants such as sulfur dioxide (SO2) or chlorine gas (Cl2). Consequently, the majority of inhaled ozone reaches the lower respiratory tract and dissolves in the thin layer of epithelial lining fluid (ELF) throughout the conducting airways of the lung.&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;q09&quot; name=&quot;q09&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol start=&quot;9&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Common symptoms due to short-term ozone exposure include:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;indented&quot;&gt;&lt;input name=&quot;question9&quot; type=&quot;radio&quot; value=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt; A. Cough&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;input name=&quot;question9&quot; type=&quot;radio&quot; value=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt; B. Pain on deep inspiration&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;input name=&quot;question9&quot; type=&quot;radio&quot; value=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt; C. Eye irritation&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;input name=&quot;question9&quot; type=&quot;radio&quot; value=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt; D. Shortness of breath&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;input name=&quot;question9&quot; type=&quot;radio&quot; value=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt; E. A, B, and D &lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;input name=&quot;question9&quot; type=&quot;radio&quot; value=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt; F. A, C, and D &lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;accordion&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#pane-9&quot; title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot;&gt;Answer&lt;/a&gt;

		&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;pane-9&quot;&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;E. A, B, and D. Exposure to elevated ozone levels has been shown to cause cough, chest pain, and shortness of breath. The mechanisms that cause this are explained in the section &quot;What are ozone&#039;s acute physiological and symptom effects?&quot; Eye irritation is not caused by ozone but by peroxyacetyl nitrate (PAN), which is a different oxidant that often is formed in the ambient air when ozone levels are high.&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;q10&quot; name=&quot;q10&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol start=&quot;10&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Hospital admissions for respiratory disease tend to be higher than normal following days on which ozone concentrations are high.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;indented&quot;&gt;&lt;input name=&quot;question10&quot; type=&quot;radio&quot; value=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt; A. True &lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;input name=&quot;question10&quot; type=&quot;radio&quot; value=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt; B. False &lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;accordion&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#pane-10&quot; title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot;&gt;Answer&lt;/a&gt;

		&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;pane-10&quot;&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;True. Epidemiological studies have found associations between elevated ambient ozone levels and increased hospital admissions for respiratory disease about 24 hours later. This lag may be related to the delayed inflammatory response caused by exposure to ozone.&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;q11&quot; name=&quot;q11&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol start=&quot;11&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Recent ozone exposure can be assessed by measuring ozone levels in the blood.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;indented&quot;&gt;&lt;input name=&quot;question11&quot; type=&quot;radio&quot; value=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt; A. True&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;input name=&quot;question11&quot; type=&quot;radio&quot; value=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt; B. False &lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;accordion&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#pane-11&quot; title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot;&gt;Answer&lt;/a&gt;

		&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;pane-11&quot;&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;False. Ozone is a reactive gas that reacts with molecules in the epithelial lining fluid or the airway epithelium itself and, therefore, it does not enter the bloodstream through the lungs. Ozone has been measured in the blood but is present as a result of endogenous production.&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;q12&quot; name=&quot;q12&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol start=&quot;12&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Long-term exposure to ozone is known to be relatively harmless.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;indented&quot;&gt;&lt;input name=&quot;question12&quot; type=&quot;radio&quot; value=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt; A. True &lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;input name=&quot;question12&quot; type=&quot;radio&quot; value=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt; B. False &lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;accordion&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#pane-12&quot; title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot;&gt;Answer&lt;/a&gt;

		&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;pane-12&quot;&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;False. Experimental animal studies have shown that long-term exposure to ozone can cause permanent changes in lung structure, described as scarring of lung tissue. There is concern that repeated episodes of inflammation may permanently alter lung structure and may lead to reduced quality of life in older individuals.&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;q13&quot; name=&quot;q13&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol start=&quot;13&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Short-term ozone exposure has been associated with increased medication usage among people with asthma.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;indented&quot;&gt;&lt;input name=&quot;question13&quot; type=&quot;radio&quot; value=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt; A. True &lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;input name=&quot;question13&quot; type=&quot;radio&quot; value=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt; B. False&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;accordion&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#pane-13&quot; title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot;&gt;Answer&lt;/a&gt;

		&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;pane-13&quot;&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;True. In epidemiological studies, ozone exposure has been associated with aggravation and worsening of asthma, as evidenced by increased medication usage among individuals with asthma. &lt;a href=&quot;/ozone-pollution-and-your-patients-health/health-effects-ozone-patients-asthma-and-other-chronic&quot;&gt;Figure 11&lt;/a&gt; summarizes some of these findings.&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;q14&quot; name=&quot;q14&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol start=&quot;14&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Indoor concentrations of ozone are usually lower than outdoor concentrations.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;indented&quot;&gt;&lt;input name=&quot;question14&quot; type=&quot;radio&quot; value=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt; A. True &lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;input name=&quot;question14&quot; type=&quot;radio&quot; value=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt; B. False &lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;accordion&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#pane-14&quot; title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot;&gt;Answer&lt;/a&gt;

		&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;pane-14&quot;&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;True. Without sunlight, ozone does not form indoors, and ambient ozone that makes its way indoors tends to be destroyed by reacting with anything it comes in contact with (e.g., walls, furnishings). If windows are closed and air conditioning is used in the summer, indoor ozone levels can be as low as 10% of outdoor levels.&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;q15&quot; name=&quot;q15&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol start=&quot;15&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;There is a wide range in the sensitivity of otherwise healthy individuals to ozone.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;indented&quot;&gt;&lt;input name=&quot;question15&quot; type=&quot;radio&quot; value=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt; A. True &lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;input name=&quot;question15&quot; type=&quot;radio&quot; value=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt; B. False &lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;accordion&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#pane-15&quot; title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot;&gt;Answer&lt;/a&gt;

		&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;pane-15&quot;&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;True. Some healthy individuals, possibly as many as 5-20% of the population, have been shown to be very sensitive to low-level exposure to ozone, while others show little or no response to low-level ozone exposure.&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;q16&quot; name=&quot;q16&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol start=&quot;16&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Older adults have larger lung function and symptom responses to ozone exposure than do younger adults.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;indented&quot;&gt;&lt;input name=&quot;question16&quot; type=&quot;radio&quot; value=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt; A. True&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;input name=&quot;question16&quot; type=&quot;radio&quot; value=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt; B. False &lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;accordion&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#pane-16&quot; title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot;&gt;Answer&lt;/a&gt;

		&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;pane-16&quot;&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;False. Older adults (fifties to eighties) have been shown in clinical studies to be less responsive to ozone than younger adults (teens to thirties).&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;q17&quot; name=&quot;q17&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol start=&quot;17&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Ozone-induced respiratory symptoms are the result of stimulation of airway neural receptors by ozone or other reactive intermediates.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;indented&quot;&gt;&lt;input name=&quot;question17&quot; type=&quot;radio&quot; value=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt; A. True &lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;input name=&quot;question17&quot; type=&quot;radio&quot; value=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt; B. False &lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;accordion&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#pane-17&quot; title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot;&gt;Answer&lt;/a&gt;

		&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;pane-17&quot;&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;True. Human and animal studies suggest that stimulation of airway neural receptors is the primary mechanism causing ozone-induced respiratory symptoms.&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;q18&quot; name=&quot;q18&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol start=&quot;18&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Ozone-induced respiratory symptoms in individuals without asthma may take 1 week to completely resolve.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;indented&quot;&gt;&lt;input name=&quot;question18&quot; type=&quot;radio&quot; value=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt; A. True &lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;input name=&quot;question18&quot; type=&quot;radio&quot; value=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt; B. False &lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;accordion&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#pane-18&quot; title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot;&gt;Answer&lt;/a&gt;

		&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;pane-18&quot;&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;False. Typically ozone-induced respiratory symptoms in individuals without asthma will return to normal within 24 to 48 hours after ozone exposure ceases.&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;q19&quot; name=&quot;q19&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol start=&quot;19&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;The Air Quality Index (AQI) health and cautionary statements are pollutant-specific, and they suggest relatively simple measures people can take to reduce their risk from exposure to air pollution.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;indented&quot;&gt;&lt;input name=&quot;question19&quot; type=&quot;radio&quot; value=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt; A. True &lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;input name=&quot;question19&quot; type=&quot;radio&quot; value=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt; B. False &lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;accordion&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#pane-19&quot; title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot;&gt;Answer&lt;/a&gt;

		&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;pane-19&quot;&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;True. These cautionary statements and measures to reduce risk from air pollution exposure can be found in EPA&#039;s Air Quality Index brochure. For example, when the AQI value for ozone is between 101 and 150, or Code Orange, air quality is considered &quot;unhealthy for sensitive groups,&quot; and children, older adults, people who are active outside, and people with lung disease, such as asthma, are advised to reduce prolonged or heavy exertion outdoors.&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;q20&quot; name=&quot;q20&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol start=&quot;20&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;The AQI has sub-indices for the following pollutants:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;indented&quot;&gt;&lt;input name=&quot;question20&quot; type=&quot;radio&quot; value=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt; A. Ozone&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;input name=&quot;question20&quot; type=&quot;radio&quot; value=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt; B. Particulate matter (PM&lt;/span&gt;&lt;sub&gt;2.5&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;span&gt; and PM&lt;/span&gt;&lt;sub&gt;10&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;span&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;input name=&quot;question20&quot; type=&quot;radio&quot; value=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt; C. Carbon monoxide&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;input name=&quot;question20&quot; type=&quot;radio&quot; value=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt; D. Sulfur dioxide&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;input name=&quot;question20&quot; type=&quot;radio&quot; value=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt; E. Nitrogen dioxide&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;input name=&quot;question20&quot; type=&quot;radio&quot; value=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;span&gt; F. All of the above &lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;accordion&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#pane-20&quot; title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot;&gt;Answer&lt;/a&gt;

		&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;pane-20&quot;&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;F. All of the above. The only &quot;criteria pollutant&quot; for which there is no AQI sub-index is lead.&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 class=&quot;indented&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/ozone-pollution-and-your-patients-health/course-outline-and-key-points-ozone&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PREVIOUS&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;    |    &lt;a href=&quot;/ozone-pollution-and-your-patients-health/patient-education-tools-ozone-pollution-and-your-patients&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NEXT&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;</description>
     <pubDate>Mon, 02 May 2016 14:22:04 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>rcopland</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">148245 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>References - Ozone and Your Patients&#039; Health</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/ozone-pollution-and-your-patients-health/references-ozone-and-your-patients-health</link>
    <description>&lt;h2 class=&quot;highlighted&quot;&gt;References:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adams, W. C. (2006) Comparison of chamber 6.6-h exposures to 0.04–0.08 PPM ozone via square-wave and triangular profiles on pulmonary responses. Inhal. Toxicol. 18: 127-136&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anderson, H. R.; Spix, C.; Medina, S.; Schouten, J. P.; Castellsague, J.; Rossi, G.; Zmirou, D.; Touloumi, G.; Wojtyniak, B.; Ponka, A.; Bacharova, L.; Schwartz, J.; Katsouyanni, K. (1997) Air pollution and daily admissions for chronic obstructive pulmonary disease in 6 European cities: results from the APHEA project. Eur. Respir. J. 10: 1064-1071.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apte MG, Buchanan IS, Mendell MJ. (2008) Outdoor ozone and building-related symptoms in the BASE Study. Indoor Air ;18:156-70.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bell, M. L.; McDermott, A.; Zeger, S. L.; Samet, J. M.; Dominici, F. (2004) Ozone and short-term mortality in 95 US urban communities, 1987-2000. JAMA J. Am. Med. Assoc. 292: 2372-2378.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bell, M. L.; Dominici, F.; Samet, J. M. (2005) A meta-analysis of time-series studies of ozone and mortality with comparison to the national morbidity, mortality, and air pollution study. Epidemiology 16: 436-445.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brown JS, Bateson TF, McDonnell WF. (2008) Effects of Exposure to 0.06 ppm Ozone on FEV1 in Humans:  A Secondary Analysis of Existing Data. Environ Heath Perspect. 116:1023-1026.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brauer, M.; Blair, J.; Vedal, S. (1996) Effect of ambient ozone exposure on lung function in farm workers. Am. J. Respir. Crit. Care Med. 154: 981-987.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Burnett, R. T.; Dales, R. E.; Raizenne, M. E.; Krewski, D.; Summers, P. W.; Roberts, G. R.; Raad-Young, M.; Dann, T.; Brook, J. (1994) Effects of low ambient levels of ozone and sulfates on the frequency of respiratory admissions to Ontario hospitals. Environ. Res. 65: 172-194. [44876]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Burnett, R. T.; Brook, J. R.; Yung, W. T.; Dales, R. E.; Krewski, D. (1997) Association between ozone and hospitalization for respiratory diseases in 16 Canadian cities. Environ. Res. 72: 24-31.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. (1998) Forecasted state-specific estimates of self-reported asthma prevalence--United States, 1998. Morb. Mortal. Wkly. Rep. 47: 1022-1025. [17134]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. (2003) Asthma Prevalence, Health Care Use and Mortality, 2000-2001.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Devlin, R. B.; Raub, J. A.; Folinsbee, L. J. (1997) Health effects of ozone. Sci. Med. (May/June): 8-17.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Folinsbee et al. (1988) Pulmonary function and symptom response after 6.6-hour exposure to 0.12 ppm ozone with moderate exercise. JAPCA 38: 28-35.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Friedman, M.S.; Powell, K.E.; Hutwagner, L.; Graham, L.M.; Teague, W.G. (2001) Impact of changes in transportation and commuting behaviors during the 1996 Olympic games in Atlanta on air quality and childhood asthma. JAMA. 285(7): 897-905&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Homa, D. M.; Mannino, D. M.; Redd, S. C. (2002) Regional differences in hospitalizations for asthma in the United States, 1988-1996. J. Asthma 39: 449-455. [35205]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Horstman et al. (1990) Ozone concentration and pulmonary response relationships for 6.6-hour exposures with five hours of moderate exercise to 0.08, 0.10, and 0.12 ppm. Am. Rev. Respir. Dis. 142: 1158-1163.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kehrl, H. R.; Peden, D. B.; Ball, B. A.; Folinsbee, L. J.; Horstman, D. H. (1999) Increased specific airway reactivity of persons with mild allergic asthma after 7.6 hours of exposure to 0.16 ppm ozone. J. Allergy. Clin. Immunol. 104: 1198-1204. [22101]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Korrick, S. A.; Neas, L. M.; Dockery, D. W.; Gold, D. R.; Allen, G. A.; Hill, L. B.; Kimball, K. D.; Rosner, B. A.; Speizer, F. E. (1998) Effects of ozone and other pollutants on the pulmonary function of adult hikers. Environ. Health Perspect. 106: 93-99.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mannino, D. M.; Homa, D. M.; Pertowski, C. A.; Ashizawa, A.; Nixon, L. L.; Johnson, C. A.; Ball, L. B.; Jack, E.; Kang, D. S. (1998) Surveillance for asthma--United States, 1960-1995. Morb. Mortal. Wkly. Rep. 47(SS-1): 1-28.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mannino, D. M.; Homa, D. M.; Akinbami, L. J.; Moorman, J. E.; Gwynn, C.; Redd, S. C. (2002) Surveillance for asthma--United States, 1980-1999. Morb. Mortal. Wkly. Rep. 51(SS-1): 1-13.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;McDonnell, W. F.; Kehrl, H. R.; Abdul-Salaam, S.; Ives, P. J.; Folinsbee, L. J.; Devlin, R. B.; O&#039;Neil, J. J.; Horstman, D. H. (1991) Respiratory response of humans exposed to low levels of ozone for 6.6 hours. Arch. Environ. Health 46: 145-150.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;McDonnell, W.F.; Stewart, P.W.; Smith, M.V. (2007) The temporal dynamics of ozone-induced FEV1 changes in humans: an exposure-response model. Inhal.Toxicol. 19:483-494.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mortimer, K. M.; Neas, L. M.; Dockery, D. W.; Redline, S.; Tager, I. B. (2002) The effect of air pollution on inner-city children with asthma. Eur. Respir. J. 19: 699-705.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;National Research Council (NRC), Committee on Estimating Mortality Risk Reduction Benefits from Decreasing Troposhpheic Ozone Exposure.  Estimating mortality risk reduction and economic benefits from controlling ozone air pollution.  ISBN: 0-309-11995-2. 2008.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neidell, M. Essays on the impact of Environmental Factors on Children&#039;s Health and Human Capital, Ph.D. Dissertation, University of California, Los Angeles, 2002&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Peel, J. L.; Tolbert, P. E.; Klein, M.; Metzger, K. B.; Flanders, W. D.; Knox, T.; Mulholland, J. A.; Ryan, P. B.; Frumkin, H. (2005) Ambient air pollution and respiratory emergency department visits. Epidemiology 16: 164-174.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Schelegle, E.S.; Morales, C.A.; Walby, W.F.; Marion, S.; Allen, R.P. (2009) 6.6 hour inhalation of ozone concentrations from 60 to 87 ppb in healthy humans. Am. J. Respir. Crit. Care Med. 180:265-272.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stieb, D. M.; Burnett, R. T.; Beveridge, R. C.; Brook, J. R. (1996) Association between ozone and asthma emergency department visits in Saint John, New Brunswick, Canada. Environ. Health Perspect. 104: 1354-1360.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thurston, G.D.; Bates, D.V. (2003) Air Pollution as an Underappreciated Cause of Asthma Symptoms. JAMA. 290: 1915-1917.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thurston, G. D.; Lippmann, M.; Scott, M. B.; Fine, J. M. (1997) Summertime haze air pollution and children with asthma. Am. J. Respir. Crit. Care Med. 155: 654-660. [77645]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;U.S. Environmental Protection Agency. (1996) Air quality criteria for ozone and related photochemical oxidants, v. I-III. Research Triangle Park, NC: Office of Research and Development; report no. EPA/600/P-93/004aF-cF. Available from: NTIS, Springfield, VA; PB96-185582. PB96-185590, and PB96-185608.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;U.S. EPA (1996) Review of National Ambient Air Quality Standards for Ozone: Assessment of Scientific and Technical Information, OAQPS Staff Paper. EPA-452/R-96-007. Office of Air Quality Planning and Standards, Research Triangle Park, NC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vagaggini, B.; Taccola, M.; Conti, I.; Carnevali, S.; Cianchetti, S.; Bartoli, M. L.; Bacci, E.; Dente, F. L.; Di Franco, A.; Giannini, D.; Paggiaro, P. L. (2001) Budesonide reduces neutrophilic but not functional airway response to ozone in mild asthmatics. Am. J. Respir. Crit. Care Med. 164: 2172-2176.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Weisel, C. P.; Cody, R. P.; Lioy, P. J. (1995) Relationship between summertime ambient ozone levels and emergency department visits for asthma in central New Jersey. Environ. Health Perspect. 103(suppl. 2): 97-102. [42438]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;White, M. C.; Etzel, R. A.; Wilcox, W. D.; Lloyd, C. (1994) Exacerbations of childhood asthma and ozone pollution in Atlanta. Environ. Res. 65: 56-68. [39302]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whitfield, R.G.; Biller, W.F.; Jusko, M.J.; Keisler, J.M. (1996) A Probabilistic Assessment of Health Risks Associated with Short-term Exposure to Tropospheric Ozone. Report prepared for U.S. EPA, OAQPS. Argonne National Laboratory; Argonne, IL.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 class=&quot;indented&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/ozone-pollution-and-your-patients-health/patient-education-tools-ozone-pollution-and-your-patients&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PREVIOUS&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;    |    &lt;a href=&quot;/ozone-pollution-and-your-patients-health/end-ozone-pollution-and-your-patients-health-training&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NEXT&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 28 Apr 2016 16:01:21 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>rcopland</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">147933 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Patient Education Tools - Ozone Pollution and Your Patients&#039; Health</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/ozone-pollution-and-your-patients-health/patient-education-tools-ozone-pollution-and-your-patients</link>
    <description>&lt;p style=&quot;width:auto&quot;&gt;You will need Adobe Acrobat Reader to view the Adobe PDF files on this page. See &lt;a href=&quot;/epahome/pdf.html&quot;&gt;EPA&#039;s PDF page&lt;/a&gt; for more information about getting and using the free Acrobat Reader.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;box multi related-info right&quot;&gt;
	&lt;h2 class=&quot;pane-title&quot;&gt;A Patient Learning about the Air Quality Index&lt;/h2&gt;

	&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg center view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:250px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;patient&quot; height=&quot;197&quot; width=&quot;250&quot; class=&quot;center media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2016-05/patient-ed_0.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ozone and Your Health:&lt;/strong&gt; This pamphlet covers who is at risk from exposure to ozone, what health effects are caused by ozone, and provides simple measures to reduce health risk. &lt;a href=&quot;https://airnow.gov/index.cfm?action=ozone_health.index&quot;&gt;HTML&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www3.epa.gov/airnow/ozone-c.pdf&quot;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt; (2pp, 2.5 MB)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Smog - Who Does it Hurt?:&lt;/strong&gt; This booklet provides more detailed information than &quot;Ozone and Your Health&quot; about ozone health effects and how to avoid them.  &lt;a href=&quot;https://airnow.gov/index.cfm?action=smog.index&quot;&gt;HTML&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www3.epa.gov/airnow/health/smog.pdf&quot;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(10pp, 274KB)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;caption&quot;&gt; &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Air Quality Index - A Guide to Air Quality and Your Health:&lt;/strong&gt; This booklet explains EPA&#039;s Air Quality Index and the health effects of major air pollutants. &lt;a href=&quot;https://airnow.gov/index.cfm?action=aqi_brochure.index&quot;&gt;HTML&lt;/a&gt; or  &lt;a href=&quot;https://www3.epa.gov/airnow/aqi_brochure_02_14.pdf&quot;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt; (12pp, 629KB)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AQI Forecasts: Your Advance Notification About Unhealthy Air:&lt;/strong&gt; This brochure explains how to use the Air Quality Index, and how high levels of ozone and particle matter can affect your health. Learn where this pollution comes from and what you can do to protect yourself when air quality is poor. &lt;a href=&quot;https://airnow.gov/index.cfm?action=pubs.aqiforecast&quot;&gt;HTML&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www3.epa.gov/airnow/aqi-forecasts.pdf&quot;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(2pp, 3MB)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Effects of Common Air Pollutants Medical Poster:&lt;/strong&gt; This colorful poster is designed for use in patient waiting areas or exam rooms to educate your patients about the health effects of air pollution on the respiratory and cardiovascular systems. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www3.epa.gov/airnow/health-prof/common-air-pollutants-2011-high.pdf&quot;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(1pp. 888KB) &lt;/span&gt;| &lt;a href=&quot;https://www3.epa.gov/airnow/health-prof/common-air-pollutants-2011-lo.pdf&quot;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt; &quot;18x24&quot; Printable Version &lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(1p, 7.9MB)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Heart Disease, Stroke, and Outdoor Air Pollution:&lt;/strong&gt; A fact sheet to increase awareness that air pollution can trigger heart attacks, stroke, and other health effects. It includes information about risk factors and warning signs for heart disease and stroke.  &lt;a href=&quot;https://airnow.gov/index.cfm?action=pubs.heartdisease&quot;&gt;HTML&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www3.epa.gov/airnow/heartflyer.pdf&quot;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt; (2pp. 325KB) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Asthma and Outdoor Air Pollution:&lt;/strong&gt; A fact sheet to increase awareness that air pollution can make asthma symptoms worse and can trigger attacks in people with asthma. It also includes steps to take to protect health and reduce exposure.  &lt;a href=&quot;https://www3.epa.gov/airnow/asthma-flyer.pdf&quot;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt; (2pp. 502KB)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-gif center view-mode-medium&quot; style=&quot;width:150px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;enviroflash&quot; title=&quot;enviroflash&quot; height=&quot;130&quot; width=&quot;150&quot; class=&quot;center media-element file-medium center&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/medium/public/2016-05/enviroflash_2.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;EnviroFlash:&lt;/strong&gt; An email and cell phone notification service that gives you up-to-date, local air quality information. Sign up at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.enviroflash.info/&quot;&gt;www.enviroflash.info&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why is Coco Orange?:&lt;/strong&gt; A picture book to educate children about the Air Quality Index and how to stay healthy when the air quality is bad. Ages 4-8. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.airnow.gov/index.cfm?action=picture_book.index&quot;&gt;HTML&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;https://www3.epa.gov/airnow/picturebook/cocos-orange-day.pdf&quot;&gt;PDF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt; (19 pp., 1.7MB)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Some of these publications are available &lt;/b&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.airnow.gov/index.cfm?action=pubs_spanish.index&quot;&gt;En español&lt;/a&gt; and as &lt;a href=&quot;https://airnow.gov/index.cfm?action=pubs.index&quot;&gt;web pages&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Additional US EPA Links:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/asthma&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Asthma and Indoor Environments&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; provides resources and educational tools to help parents and children learn about asthma triggers and manage their health. Most materials are offered in English and Spanish.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.airnow.gov/index.cfm?action=pubs.index&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;More publications&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; are available on the AIRNow website.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;h2 class=&quot;indented&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/ozone-pollution-and-your-patients-health/review-questions-ozone&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PREVIOUS&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;    |    &lt;a href=&quot;/ozone-pollution-and-your-patients-health/references-ozone-and-your-patients-health&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NEXT&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;


</description>
     <pubDate>Mon, 25 Apr 2016 18:12:45 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>rcopland</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">147547 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  </channel>
</rss>

<!-- Page cached by Boost @ 2017-01-25 17:50:44, expires @ 2017-01-26 05:50:44, lifetime 12 hours -->