<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?><rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.epa.gov/feed/32663/rss.xml" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/" xmlns:og="http://ogp.me/ns#" xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#" xmlns:sioc="http://rdfs.org/sioc/ns#" xmlns:sioct="http://rdfs.org/sioc/types#" xmlns:skos="http://www.w3.org/2004/02/skos/core#" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#">
  <channel>
    <title>Careers</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/feed/32663/rss.xml</link>
    <description>Updated Careers content from the US Environmental Protection Agency</description>
    <language>en</language>
     <atom:link href="https://www.epa.gov/feed/32663/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      <item>
    <title>Instructions for Sending Paper Documents to the EPA Personnel Security Branch</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/careers/instructions-sending-paper-documents-epa-personnel-security-branch</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;The instructions below contain information to help you securely send paper documents to the EPA Personnel Security Branch. Please use a delivery method that safeguards your information and is trackable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-341195&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-12/documents/instructions_for_sending_paper_documents_to_the_epa_personnel_security_branch.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=31278&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Instructions for Sending Paper Documents to the EPA Personnel Security Branch (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(1 pg, 31 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 22 Dec 2016 19:38:46 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>sarah_riggs</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">167763 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Profiles of Americans with Disabilities at EPA: Elizabeth “Jo” Klein</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/careers/profiles-americans-disabilities-epa-elizabeth-jo-klein</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/careers/national-disability-employment-awareness-month&quot;&gt;Profiles of Members of Americans with Disabilities at EPA&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-gif right view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:125px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Picture of a smiling women.&quot; height=&quot;175&quot; width=&quot;125&quot; class=&quot;right media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2016-11/ek_proof.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;Elizabeth “Jo” Klein&lt;br /&gt;
	Oak Ridge Associated Universities Student Service Contractor&lt;br /&gt;
	U.S. EPA, NHEERL,&lt;br /&gt;
	Environmental Public Health Division, Epidemiology Branch &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Where were you born?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was born in Tucson, AZ but grew up in Sanford, NC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is your highest level of education? What was your major? &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I went to college at the University of Maryland Baltimore County (UMBC) for a BS in Biology. I’m working on a Master’s degree in Library and Information Studies at UNCG now, and plan to get another Master’s in Wildlife Ecology in the near future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What brought you to EPA?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wanted to be involved in ecology and environmental research; living in Maryland in the Chesapeake Bay area and seeing the differences between polluted and non-polluted areas of the Susquehanna River every day, as well as experiencing the effects of climate change on high-elevation alpine meadow ecosystems as an undergraduate researcher at the Rocky Mountain Biological Laboratory in Colorado really cemented my desire to work to improve environmental health.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What kind of work do you do at EPA? &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m a student services contractor with the Epidemiology Branch and I help with lab cleanup and organization to make sure our research runs smoothly, as well as run immunoassays and help analyze data using statistical computing and graphics software.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What message would you like to send to young Americans with disabilities considering going to college or a career in environmental protection? &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t be afraid to ask for help or to let others around you know about your disability. Accommodations – especially in college – and your network of peers and coworkers are there to help you succeed, and there is no shame in asking for and accepting help. Environmental protection is also a very connected field, with the nearest source of support usually right next door.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Mon, 14 Nov 2016 17:31:18 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>rwashing</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">165053 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Profiles of Members of EPA&#039;s Asian-American and Pacific Islander Community: Piyachat Terrell</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/careers/profiles-members-epas-asian-american-and-pacific-islander-community-piyachat-terrell</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/careers/profiles-members-epas-asian-american-and-pacific-islander-community&quot;&gt;Profiles of Members of EPA&#039;s Asian-American and Pacific Islander Community&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-gif right view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:125px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Picture of a pretty smiling women.&quot; height=&quot;175&quot; width=&quot;125&quot; class=&quot;right media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2016-11/piyachat_terrell.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;Piyachat Terrell, Program Analyst&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Office of Human Resources&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Washington, DC&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Where were you born?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was born in Thailand and grew up in the U.S. and Germany.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What brought you to EPA?&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started my federal career at NASA but have always believed in EPA’s mission to protect human health and the environment. When an opportunity for career advancement in the budget field became available, I moved to EPA and have been here since.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What type of work do you do at EPA? &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At EPA, I have been fortunate to work in various fields including budget, grant, community engagement, translation, recruitment and outreach. I work with amazing people who are committed to protecting our environment. In my current position, I work with students to expose them to environmental careers. In 2010, a group of interns developed an interactive garden project for students with disabilities. Since then, disabled students at Longview Elementary school are able to participate in environmental activities. My work with students is meaningful and makes EPA a wonderful place to work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is your highest level of education? What was your major?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a Bachelor of Arts in Art and Health.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What message would you like to send other Asian Americans who are considering college or a career in environmental protection?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&#039;s important to consider what kind of environmental career you would like to pursue (like research, policy, law, science, community engagement, management, or other). Look at the requirements in the area that most interest you. Expand your knowledge and build required skills through internship and volunteer opportunities, environmental conferences, on-campus environmental activities, and reach out to environmental experts who are in the field you are interested in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Mon, 14 Nov 2016 16:46:02 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>rwashing</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">165043 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Profiles of Members of EPA&#039;s Asian-American and Pacific Islander Community: Lisa Pham</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/careers/profiles-members-epas-asian-american-and-pacific-islander-community-lisa-pham</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/careers/profiles-members-epas-asian-american-and-pacific-islander-community&quot;&gt;Profiles of Members of EPA&#039;s Asian-American and Pacific Islander Community&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-gif right view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:125px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Picture of a smiling woman.&quot; height=&quot;175&quot; width=&quot;125&quot; class=&quot;right media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2016-11/pham_lisa.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;Lisa Pham, Environmental Engineer&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Water Quality Protection Division&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dallas, TX (Region 6)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Where were you born?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saigon, Vietnam&lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What brought you to EPA?&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA was “born” 5 years before the end of the Vietnam War. I remember that because it was the time that many Vietnamese came to this country without anything. My family was among those.  The U.S. government and the Americans have opened their arms to let us in this country.  Their generosity and compassion inspire me to public service.   Working with EPA is not only a privilege but also a meaningful way to pay back the huge debt that my family and several hundred thousands of Vietnamese refugees owe this great country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What type of work do you do at EPA? &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been working with EPA Region 6 for more than 22 years.  Currently, I am coordinating aquifer exemption projects of Region 6’s Office of Water and managing the Underground Injection Control (UIC) programs in New Mexico.  As Region 6’s liaison to the Vietnamese-American community, I have initiated many of EPA’s Environmental Justice outreach efforts to address environmental and health issues that they are facing daily, notably, the Nail Salon Project.  During the EPA response to the devastation of hurricanes Katrina, Rita, Gustav, and the BP Oil Spill Response, I was deployed to assist the Vietnamese community living along the Gulf Coast. I also have translated numerous EPA documents into Vietnamese and actively developed the EPA’s Vietnamese web page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is your highest level of education? What was your major?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I received my Master of Science and Bachelor of Science in Chemical Engineering from Louisiana State University.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What message would you like to send other Asian Americans who are considering college or a career in environmental protection?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA is a great place to be considered for a career in the environmental field.  Your knowledge and skills will be fully utilized in order to address the many environmental issues that Americans are facing. With a diverse workforce, EPA has been effectively helping various impacted communities throughout the United States. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Mon, 14 Nov 2016 16:01:29 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>rwashing</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">165035 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>United States Environmental Protection Agency Region 2 Job Announcement</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/careers/united-states-environmental-protection-agency-region-2-job-announcement</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;The United States Environmental Protection Agency (“EPA”), Region 2, Office of Regional Counsel (“ORC”), is accepting applications for a staff attorney position in EPA’s office in Manhattan. The position is in one of ORC’s branches that handles legal matters arising under the Comprehensive Environmental Response, Compensation, and Liability Act (“CERCLA,” also known as the “Superfund” law).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ABOUT REGION 2 AND ORC:&lt;/strong&gt; With close to 800 employees, Region 2 is one of ten EPA regional offices and covers the geographic area of New Jersey, New York, Puerto Rico, the U.S. Virgin Islands and eight tribal nations. The Office of Regional Counsel includes about 80 lawyers and provides legal support to the Region on both enforcement and counseling matters under the broad range of federal environmental laws, including the Clean Air Act, Clean Water Act, Safe Drinking Water Act, Resource Conservation and Recovery Act, Toxic Substances Control Act, Federal Insecticide, Fungicide, and Rodenticide Act, and CERCLA. We also work collaboratively with state, tribal, and local governments to implement these environmental laws. Our attorneys represent the Agency in administrative proceedings and work with the Department of Justice on cases brought in federal court. Region 2 offers a diverse and supportive work environment. Further information about Region 2 can be found at &lt;a href=&quot;/aboutepa/epa-region-2&quot;&gt;https://www.epa.gov/aboutepa/epa-region-2&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DUTIES OF POSITION:&lt;/strong&gt; The staff attorneys in ORC’s Superfund branches conduct negotiations, prepare administrative orders and settlement documents, provide legal counseling to the EPA Region 2 Superfund program office, prepare judicial litigation referral memoranda, work closely with the Department of Justice on specific matters that have been referred to the Department for litigation, and perform other functions to implement and enforce CERCLA. From time to time, the staff attorneys may also represent EPA in enforcement matters arising under the Emergency Planning and Community Right-to-Know Act or Section 112(r) of the Clean Air Act; such work may involve representing the Agency in adjudicative hearings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SALARY:&lt;/strong&gt; For this position, EPA is seeking recent law school graduates (2015 or 2016) and therefore, hiring will be at either the GS-11 or GS-12 level. At present, in the New York City area, the starting salaries for these grade levels are $66,940 and $80,234, respectively. The career ladder of this position extends to GS-14. The current salary table may be found at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.opm.gov/policy-data-oversight/pay-leave/salaries-wages/salary-tables/pdf/2016/NY.pdf&quot;&gt;https://www.opm.gov/policy-data-oversight/pay-leave/salaries-wages/salary-tables/pdf/2016/NY.pdf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Federal employment benefits are among the most comprehensive programs available anywhere. See &lt;a href=&quot;/careers/salaries-and-benefits&quot;&gt;https://www.epa.gov/careers/salaries-and-benefits&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;QUALIFICATIONS:&lt;/strong&gt; This vacancy is open to all qualified applicants. To qualify, an applicant must: (a) be a U.S. citizen; (b) have a law degree (LL.B. or J.D.) from an accredited law school; and (c) through academic courses, internships, work or other activities, have a demonstrated interest in environmental law and/or environmental protection. Applicants should have excellent written and oral communication skills and a strong interest in public service, especially in the mission of EPA.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be considered at the GS-12 level, candidates must already be admitted to practice before the highest court of a state, the District of Columbia or the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico, and have one year of experience as a practicing attorney. Individuals who begin at the GS-11 level must either have been admitted to practice before the highest court of a state, the District of Columbia or the Commonwealth of Puerto Rico, or be admitted within 14 months of starting work with EPA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A background security investigation will be required for all new hires. Appointment and continued employment will be subject to the applicant’s completion of the security investigation and favorable adjudication. Failure to successfully meet these requirements will be grounds for termination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA will not pay relocation expenses.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;HOW TO APPLY:&lt;/strong&gt; Applications must be submitted electronically by no later than &lt;strong&gt;November 30, 2016 &lt;/strong&gt;to &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:simon.paul@epa.gov&quot;&gt;simon.paul@epa.gov&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;strong&gt;The words “EPA Region 2 attorney position” should be included in the subject line of the email message&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Applications should include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;A resume, including significant accomplishments, work experience, class rank or G.P.A., contact telephone numbers, and e-mail address.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;An unofficial transcript of law school grades.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;A cover letter explaining your interest in the position and highlighting any environmental experience or environmental law training.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;The name, address and telephone numbers of at least three professional or academic references.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;A short writing sample not to exceed ten pages.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Proof of current state bar membership (or a statement that you are a 2016 J.D. graduate with bar membership pending).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Questions regarding this job announcement may be directed to Paul Simon at (212) 637-3152 or &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:simon.paul@epa.gov&quot;&gt;simon.paul@epa.gov&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no formal rating system for applying veterans&#039; preference to attorney appointments in the excepted service. (Attorney appointments within the Office of Regional Counsel are positions in the excepted service, not the competitive civil service.) Nevertheless, EPA considers veterans&#039; preference eligibility as a positive factor in attorney hiring. Thus, applicants eligible for veterans&#039; preference should include that information in their cover letter or resume and attach supporting documentation (e.g., the DD 214, Certificate of Release or Discharge from Active Duty and other supporting documentation) to their submissions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA is an equal opportunity employer; selection for this position will be based solely on merit without regard to race, color, religion, age, gender, national origin, political affiliation, disability, sexual orientation, marital or family status, or other differences. Women, minorities, and attorneys with disabilities are strongly encouraged to apply. EPA provides reasonable accommodation to applicants with disabilities. If you need a reasonable accommodation for any part of the application and hiring process, please notify Mr. Simon at the above-referenced phone number or e-mail address. The decision on granting reasonable accommodation will be made on a case-by-case basis.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Mon, 07 Nov 2016 17:21:34 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cglazer</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">164731 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Profiles of Americans with Disabilities at EPA: Christopher Emanuel</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/careers/profiles-americans-disabilities-epa-christopher-emanuel</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/careers/national-disability-employment-awareness-month&quot;&gt;Profiles of Members of Americans with Disabilities at EPA&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-gif right view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:125px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Picture of a man smiling.&quot; height=&quot;175&quot; width=&quot;125&quot; class=&quot;right media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2016-10/chris_emmanuel.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;Christopher Emanuel,&lt;br /&gt;
	EEO Manager/Disability Employment Program&lt;br /&gt;
	U.S. EPA, Office of Civil Rights&lt;br /&gt;
	Office of the Administrator&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Where were you born?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Harlem, New York&lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is your highest level of education? What was your major? &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I received dual degrees from the University of Southern California in International Relations and Public Policy and Business Management.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What brought you to EPA?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am the current National Program Manager for Persons with Disabilities. I have served 15 years at the Environmental Protection Agency, 8 of those year as the National Program Manager for Persons with Disabilities. I served as a Pass Board of Trustee Member for two colleges – Crafton Hills College, and San Bernardino Valley College in California, where I have worked closely on disability policies and issues for those institutions. I had the opportunity to appear on the Oprah Winfrey Show as a guest to discuss an “Affirmative Action and Reverse Discrimination” Case in 1995. In that same year, I had the pleasure of being a participant on an education roundtable with President Bill Clinton in 1995 to discuss education policy for Community Colleges. I have worked periodically on an inter-agency collaboration with the Department of Justice as an accessibility and accommodations tester. In this capacity, I was sent to hotels and restaurants throughout New York, Philadelphia and Washington to ensure that public accommodations are accessible to patrons with disabilities. I’m a CSPAN junkie, so I really like national and international politics and economics, as well as good books and interesting lectures. I love history, really enjoy reading about the accomplishment of individuals, and events that happened in the past eras. I believe that there’s a lot that can be learned from the experiences of others in history. On the lighter side, I also enjoy model trains, different cultures/languages and a good physical workout to keep the mind and body in shape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What are your words of wisdom for other disabled individuals who might be interested in pursuing a career in environmental science?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Always continue to pursue your goals and your dreams no matter how many times you fall or life shuts the door on you. Always know that there is a great power working than yourself, you just need to believe and tap into it. Never give up!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 19 Oct 2016 17:48:20 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>rwashing</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">163027 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Profiles of Americans with Disabilities at EPA: Anthony Napoli</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/careers/profiles-americans-disabilities-epa-anthony-napoli</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/careers/national-disability-employment-awareness-month&quot;&gt;Profiles of Members of Americans with Disabilities at EPA&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-gif right view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:125px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Picture of a man smiling.&quot; height=&quot;175&quot; width=&quot;125&quot; class=&quot;right media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2016-10/napoli.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;Anthony Napoli, MPA&lt;br /&gt;
	Diversity &amp;amp; Inclusion Coordinator&lt;br /&gt;
	Diversity, Recruitment, and Employee Services Division&lt;br /&gt;
	Office of Administration and Resources Management&lt;br /&gt;
	U.S. Environmental Protection Agency&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Where were you born?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rochester, New York&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is your highest level of education? What was your major? &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hold a Master of Public Administration from American University.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What brought you to EPA?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I joined EPA through the agency’s intern program. I have always had the aspiration and inspiration to protect the environment and serve my country, and to make changes that impact not just in the federal workforce and the nation but also the world and beyond.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What kind of work do you do at EPA? &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I assist the agency as one of the National Diversity &amp;amp; Inclusion coordinators to strengthen diversity, inclusion and equal employment opportunity activities and programs. In my capacity as the agency’s Diversity &amp;amp; Inclusion Liaison for the Disability Employment, Federal Women’s and American Indian/Alaska Native Employment Programs, I draft agency-wide policy changes and agency actions to senior officials. I also coordinate outreach programs or activities and help lead working groups, or subcommittees. As a Liaison for my office, one of my previous outreach activities was to conduct a career mock interview for deaf/hard of hearing students at Gallaudet University and the National Institute for the Deaf to strengthen their chances of employment opportunities. I currently co-chair the Transgender Workgroup and work with a team of champions. We just made history and finalized a milestone EPA Order and was issued in June of 2016 protecting Transgender and Gender Non-Conforming Employees. I love what I do, making a difference and I have a great team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What message would you like to send to young Americans with disabilities considering going to college or a career in environmental protection? &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please join me and positively change the world and make it a better place to live in!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 19 Oct 2016 17:32:46 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>rwashing</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">163023 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>National Disability Employment Awareness Month</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/careers/national-disability-employment-awareness-month</link>
    <description>&lt;h2&gt;Americans with Disabilities at EPA&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the United States, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.census.gov/eeo/special_emphasis_programs/disability_month.html&quot;&gt;National Disability Employment Awareness Month&lt;/a&gt; is observed during the month of October to honor the contributions of Americans with disabilities to our nation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At EPA, we are highlighting some of our employees with disabilities who contribute daily to our mission of protecting human health and the environment. We appreciate their efforts in responding to the many environmental challenges we face.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We hope that these profiles will serve as an inspiration to others who are interested in protecting our planet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Together, we can work to make a difference in our communities to achieve a healthier and more sustainable environment for all today and for future generations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.whitehouse.gov/the-press-office/2016/09/30/presidential-proclamation-national-disability-employment-awareness-month&quot;&gt;Presidential Proclamation—National Disability Employment Awareness Month, 2016&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Profiles of featured EPA employees with disabilities: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=&quot;vertical-align:top&quot;&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Westley Foster, EPA Tribal Coordinator&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
					Indian General Assistance Program&lt;br /&gt;
					EPA Region 10&lt;/p&gt;

				&lt;p&gt;I am a Tribal Coordinator in EPA’s Region 10. &lt;a href=&quot;/careers/profiles-americans-disabilities-epa-westley-foster&quot;&gt;Read more about Westley Foster&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td style=&quot;vertical-align:top&quot;&gt;
				&lt;div class=&quot;figure image mode-full center&quot; style=&quot;width:125px&quot;&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg center view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:125px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Picture of westley standing on the top of a mountain.&quot; height=&quot;175&quot; width=&quot;125&quot; class=&quot;center media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2016-10/fosterwestley-cc.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=&quot;vertical-align:top&quot;&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Amanda Sweda, National Reasonable Accommodation Coordinator&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

				&lt;p&gt;I serve as the Agency’s National Reasonable Accommodation Coordinator (NRAC). &lt;a href=&quot;/careers/profiles-americans-disabilities-epa-amanda-sweda&quot;&gt;Read more about Amanda Sweda&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td style=&quot;vertical-align:top&quot;&gt;
				&lt;div class=&quot;figure image mode-full center&quot; style=&quot;width:125px&quot;&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg center view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:125px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Picture of a amanda smiling.&quot; height=&quot;175&quot; width=&quot;125&quot; class=&quot;center media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2016-10/swedaamanda-cc.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=&quot;vertical-align:top&quot;&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Anthony Napoli, MPA&lt;br /&gt;
					Diversity &amp;amp; Inclusion Coordinator&lt;br /&gt;
					Diversity, Recruitment, and Employee Services Division &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

				&lt;p&gt;I assist the agency as one of the National Diversity &amp;amp; Inclusion coordinators to strengthen diversity, inclusion and equal employment opportunity activities and programs. &lt;a href=&quot;/careers/profiles-americans-disabilities-epa-anthony-napoli&quot;&gt;Read more about Anthony Napoli&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td style=&quot;vertical-align:top&quot;&gt;
				&lt;div class=&quot;figure image mode-full center&quot; style=&quot;width:125px&quot;&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-gif center view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:125px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Picture of a man smiling.&quot; height=&quot;175&quot; width=&quot;125&quot; class=&quot;center media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2016-10/napoli.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=&quot;vertical-align:top&quot;&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Christopher Emanuel, EEO Manager/Disability Employment Program&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

				&lt;p&gt;I am the current National Program Manager for Persons with Disabilities. &lt;a href=&quot;/careers/profiles-americans-disabilities-epa-christopher-emanuel&quot;&gt;Read more about Christopher Emanuel&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td style=&quot;vertical-align:top&quot;&gt;
				&lt;div class=&quot;figure image mode-full center&quot; style=&quot;width:125px&quot;&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-gif center view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:125px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Picture of a man smiling.&quot; height=&quot;175&quot; width=&quot;125&quot; class=&quot;center media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2016-10/chris_emmanuel.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=&quot;vertical-align:top&quot;&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Elizabeth “Jo” Klein, Oak Ridge Associated Universities Student Service Contractor &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

				&lt;p&gt;I’m a student services contractor with the Epidemiology Branch. &lt;a href=&quot;/careers/profiles-americans-disabilities-epa-elizabeth-jo-klein&quot;&gt;Read more about Elizabeth “Jo” Klein&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td style=&quot;vertical-align:top&quot;&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-gif center view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:125px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Picture of a smiling women.&quot; height=&quot;175&quot; width=&quot;125&quot; class=&quot;center media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2016-11/ek_proof.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 18 Oct 2016 14:23:45 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>rwashing</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">162881 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Profiles of Americans with Disabilities at EPA: Amanda Sweda</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/careers/profiles-americans-disabilities-epa-amanda-sweda</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/careers/national-disability-employment-awareness-month&quot;&gt;Profiles of Members of Americans with Disabilities at EPA&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg right view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:125px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Picture of a amanda smiling.&quot; height=&quot;175&quot; width=&quot;125&quot; class=&quot;right media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2016-10/swedaamanda-cc.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;Amanda Sweda&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Where were you born?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was born in Chicago, Illinois and raised in Dallas, Texas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is your highest level of education? What was your major? &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I earned my Master of Arts in Communications Sciences and Disorders (Deaf Education) and a Bachelor of Arts in History and Psychology from the University of Texas-Austin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What brought you to EPA?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I participated in a wonderful program with the Department of Labor and Department of Defense called the Workforce Recruitment Program (WRP) while in college. I had a couple of summer internships with various federal agencies in Washington, DC and in Dallas through this program while I was finishing my masters. Right when I was graduating, I received a letter from EPA asking me to apply to a career development program they had. I was intrigued by EPA’s mission and by the opportunities in the program and figured “why not?” I applied and interviewed and EPA offered me a position and the rest is history!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What kind of work do you do at EPA? &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I serve as the Agency’s National Reasonable Accommodation Coordinator (NRAC). Reasonable accommodations are what we do differently at EPA to remove workplace barriers for employees with disabilities. I help employees and managers navigate the reasonable accommodation process for the entire Agency. The reasonable accommodation process is a step by step process for each person who needs it. Each person is unique and has different needs or limitations that needs to be addressed during the process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What message would you like to send to young Americans with disabilities considering going to college or a career in environmental protection? &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You are your own best advocate! Don’t let anyone tell you that you cannot do what you love. You may need to do it differently from everyone else and that is okay. Remember that hidden in the word “impossible” is “I’m possible.” I majored in liberal arts subjects and did not take a traditional path into EPA and that is ok too because we can’t all be scientists. I bring a different perspective because of my educational background and because of my life experiences of having a disability. Sometimes the solutions to issues EPA is trying to solve requires us to look at the problem differently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 18 Oct 2016 14:07:02 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>rwashing</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">162877 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  </channel>
</rss>

<!-- Page cached by Boost @ 2017-01-26 11:05:44, expires @ 2017-01-27 11:05:44, lifetime 1 day -->