<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?><rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.epa.gov/feed/61811/rss.xml" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/" xmlns:og="http://ogp.me/ns#" xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#" xmlns:sioc="http://rdfs.org/sioc/ns#" xmlns:sioct="http://rdfs.org/sioc/types#" xmlns:skos="http://www.w3.org/2004/02/skos/core#" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#">
  <channel>
    <title>EPA in Virginia</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/feed/61811/rss.xml</link>
    <description>Updated EPA in Virginia content from the US Environmental Protection Agency</description>
    <language>en</language>
     <atom:link href="https://www.epa.gov/feed/61811/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      <item>
    <title>Griffin Pipe Products Company – Madison Heights, VA  VAD000800532</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/va/griffin-pipe-products-company-madison-heights-va-vad000800532</link>
    <description></description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2017 11:51:01 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>tscipion</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">169347 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Additional Documents for Griffin Pipe Products Company - Madison Heights, VA</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/va/additional-documents-griffin-pipe-products-company-madison-heights-va</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;Formal Public Notice and Statement of Basis&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-346773&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2017-01/documents/griffenpipe_pn.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=91871&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Formal Public Notice for Griffin Pipe Products Company (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(1 pg, 92 K, 
  January 18, 2017)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-346775&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2017-01/documents/griffinpipe_sb.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=1771740&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Griffin Pipe Products Company Statement of Basis (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(16 pp, 2 MB, 
  January 18, 2017)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;field field-name-field-document-description field-type-text field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    This SB highlights key information relied upon by EPA in making its proposed remedy.  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2017 11:38:30 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>tscipion</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">169345 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Designing Green School Grounds</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/va/designing-green-school-grounds</link>
    <description>&lt;h2&gt;Stories of Progress in Achieving Healthy Waters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;U.S. EPA Region 3 Water Protection Division&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Newport News, Virginia • January 5, 2017&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA is helping Newport News, Virginia take steps to prevent flooding and control stormwater on school grounds – part of an overall effort by government agencies and other partners to address the city’s revitalization needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Newport News is one of five communities in EPA’s Mid-Atlantic Region receiving assistance under the Agency’s &lt;a href=&quot;/smartgrowth/making-visible-difference-communities&quot;&gt;“Making a Visible Difference in Communities”&lt;/a&gt; (MVD) effort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The EPA Mid-Atlantic Region’s Office of State and Watershed Partnerships engaged the Newport News Public Schools and the city in a Green School Grounds Initiative that focuses on using green infrastructure techniques to manage stormwater on school property. The effort is aimed at helping the city comply with stormwater requirements, protect water quality and promote environmental literacy and stewardship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The school system selected Sedgefield Elementary School in the city’s Southeast community as a starting point for the initiative. The school is affected by localized flooding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A special forum generated green design ideas from the city’s engineering and public works staffs, school facilities personnel, experts from Virginia Tech, landscape architects and community representatives. There were also presentations from the school’s 3rd, 4th and 5th grade students themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ideas are being used to develop concept designs for the grounds – a necessary step in order to seek project funding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of the initiative, the green approach taken by the city and the school system is being developed into a step-by-step “Storm Smart Schools Guidebook” that will be transferrable to other communities. The guidebook is expected to be released in early 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Green School Grounds Initiative was among the topics discussed at a Newport News revitalization forum sponsored by EPA, the Southeast CARE Coalition and the city.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the forum, more than 80 people engaged in finding solutions to the most pressing problems facing the city’s most overburdened neighborhoods – from air and toxics pollution to equitable development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg left view-mode-medium&quot; style=&quot;width:448px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;A map of Virginia highlighting the location of Newport News&quot; height=&quot;346&quot; width=&quot;448&quot; class=&quot;left media-element file-medium left&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/medium/public/2017-01/va_newport_news.jpg&quot; title=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-342819&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2017-01/documents/va_progress_-_making_a_difference_in_newport_news.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=657495&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Designing Green School Grounds (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(1 pg, 657 K, 
  01/05/2017)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jan 2017 14:29:12 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>nholomuz</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">168151 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Mining Upgrades to Reduce Pollution</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/va/mining-upgrades-reduce-pollution</link>
    <description>&lt;h2&gt;Stories of Progress in Achieving Healthy Waters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;U.S. EPA Region 3 Water Protection Division&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Appalachia • December 22, 2016&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href=&quot;/newsreleases/southern-coal-corporation-agrees-make-system-wide-upgrades-reduce-water-pollution&quot;&gt;settlement with Southern Coal Corporation &lt;/a&gt;and 26 affiliates requires the companies to comprehensively upgrade their coal mining and processing operations to prevent polluted wastewater from threatening rivers and streams and overburdened communities across Appalachia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The estimated cost of the upgrades is $5 million. The companies will also pay a $900,000 civil penalty for past violations. The consent decree, approved by a federal judge December 2016, will help reduce the exposure of Appalachian communities to a number of pollutants, including selenium and sulfates, as well as solids, which can impair watersheds. An annual cut in pollution of approximately five million pounds is expected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The action was listed in a &lt;a href=&quot;/enforcement/enforcement-annual-results-fiscal-year-2016&quot;&gt;roundup of enforcement and compliance results &lt;/a&gt;for the 2016 fiscal year as one of EPA’s high impact cases delivering environmental and public health benefits across the U.S.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The settlement resolves alleged violations of state-issued Clean Water Act National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System (NPDES) permits at the companies’ operations in Alabama, Kentucky, Tennessee, Virginia and West Virginia. In addition, there were numerous violations of the companies’ legal responsibilities to sample their discharges to rivers and streams required by their NPDES permits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under the settlement approved by the U.S. District Court for the Western District of Virginia, the Roanoke-based Southern Coal Corporation must implement a series of measures to ensure compliance and prevent future Clean Water Act violations, including.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Implementing a company-wide, EPA-approved environmental management system.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Maintaining a centralized data management system to track audit results, violations, water sampling data and compliance efforts.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Constructing a publicly accessible website for posting of key documents, such as discharge monitoring reports, water sampling data, notices of violations and compliance orders.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Paying escalated stipulated penalties if Clean Water Act permit violations continue to occur.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Taking steps to ensure sufficient funds and a mechanism to achieve compliance if Southern Coal fails to perform.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The government complaint filed concurrently with the consent decree alleged that over a five-year period, Southern Coal violated NPDES discharge permits for pollutants including iron, total suspended solids, aluminum, pH and manganese in their permits. The complaint also alleged that Southern Coal failed to submit complete and timely discharge monitoring reports, made unauthorized discharges and failed to respond to EPA requests for information. The settlement follows two others with coal companies this fiscal year, including &lt;a href=&quot;/newsreleases/settlement-us-and-pennsylvania-requires-consol-energy-implement-water-management&quot;&gt;Consol&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://triblive.com/business/headlines/11071719-74/corsa-environmental-federal&quot;&gt;Corsa Coal&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot; class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;, all of which resulted in a collective $10.4 million in penalties and $7 million in investments for pollution control projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg left view-mode-medium&quot; style=&quot;width:448px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Map highlighting the location of Roanoke, Virginia.&quot; height=&quot;346&quot; width=&quot;448&quot; class=&quot;left media-element file-medium left&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/medium/public/2016-12/va_roanoke.jpg&quot; title=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-340963&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-12/documents/multi_state_progress_-_mining_upgrades_to_reduce_pollution.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=601854&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Mining Upgrades to Reduce Pollution (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(1 pg, 602 K, 
  2016-12-22)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 21 Dec 2016 22:12:02 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>apruzins</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">167703 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Virginia Agency Agrees to Stormwater Controls</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/va/virginia-agency-agrees-stormwater-controls</link>
    <description>&lt;h2&gt;Stories of Progress in Achieving Healthy Waters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;U.S. EPA Region 3 Water Protection Division&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Richmond, VA • June 11, 2015&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In agreements with EPA, the Virginia Department of Transportation (VDOT) has made a state- and agency-wide commitment to improve stormwater pollution controls and practices for roads, facilities and construction sites it manages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under two related agreements, the VDOT will address widespread Clean Water Act violations of municipal and construction stormwater general permits observed during an October 2012 statewide inspection. The VDOT will implement $600,000 in environmentally beneficial projects, including the repaving of a park-and-ride lot with permeable material, and land conservation. The state agency will also pay a civil penalty of $36,000.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2012 inspection was led by the EPA Mid-Atlantic Water Protection Division’s National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System (NPDES) Enforcement Branch. It covered extensive document review, inspection of 11 construction sites and nine maintenance yards, and coordination with state inspectors using four teams operating in seven counties – all within one week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The team found violations of Virginia’s NPDES General Permit for Discharges of Stormwater from Construction Activities and Virginia’s General Permit for Discharges of Stormwater from Small Municipal Separate Storm Sewer Systems (MS4). EPA determined the VDOT did not provide annual inspection reports of all of its post-construction stormwater management facilities nor fully implement programs to detect and eliminate illicit discharges or prevent pollution from its maintenance facilities. EPA also found that the VDOT did not consistently maintain required erosion and sediment controls at its construction sites or record all required inspections of the sites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under an administrative order on consent, the VDOT has agreed to implement the pollution reduction and prevention projects within the next two years, and develop and execute a statewide plan to prevent future violations of Virginia’s construction general permit and MS4 permits. The projects will include the park-and-ride, salt water runoff recycling, the purchase of trading credits for land conservation, and a pilot program at maintenance yards to study the effectiveness of stormwater drains. In a related administrative consent agreement, the VDOT will pay a $36,000 cash penalty for the violations. Chuck Schadel of the NPDES Enforcement Branch said that since the 2012 inspection, the VDOT has been proactive in upgrading its stormwater management program. The region’s Office of Regional Counsel worked with the NPDES team to negotiate and secure the agreements with VDOT.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg left view-mode-medium&quot; style=&quot;width:448px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;A map of Virginia highlighting the location of Richmond&quot; height=&quot;346&quot; width=&quot;448&quot; class=&quot;left media-element file-medium left&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/medium/public/2016-11/va_richmond_20160226_0.jpg&quot; title=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-330341&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-11/documents/va_progress_-_vadot_commits_to_stormwater_improvement_20150611.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=617447&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;VA Agency Agrees to Stormwater Controls (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(1 pg, 617 K, 
  06/11/2015)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;field field-name-field-document-description field-type-text field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    In agreements with EPA, the Virginia Department of Transportation (VDOT) has made a state- and agency-wide commitment to improve stormwater pollution controls and practices for roads, facilities and construction sites it manages.  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 09 Nov 2016 17:32:39 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>apruzins</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">164897 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Water Reuse Project in Virginia Providing Multiple Benefits</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/va/water-reuse-project-virginia-providing-multiple-benefits</link>
    <description>&lt;h2&gt;Stories of Progress in Achieving Healthy Waters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;U.S. EPA Region 3 Water Protection Division&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Fairfax County, Virginia • September 17, 2015&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More than 500 million gallons a year of treated wastewater that would otherwise be discharged into a tributary of the Chesapeake Bay are instead being put to beneficial reuse to cool a waste-to-energy plant and irrigate a golf course and ball fields in Fairfax County, Virginia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fairfax County used nearly $7 million in EPA Clean Water Act funding to help construct a system to pump the non-potable water to the facilities – providing a source of income for the county, keeping additional nutrients out of Pohick Creek, conserving drinking water, and offering a bargain to reuse customers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A five-mile network of purple pipes – a color reserved for pipes carrying water that is not for drinking purposes – runs from the county’s Noman M. Cole Jr. Pollution Control Plant in Lorton, VA, to the Covanta Fairfax Inc. Resource Recovery Facility, the Laurel Hill Golf Club and a series of ball fields in Lower Potomac Park.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The water reclamation and reuse project is one of a number in operation in counties and communities in Virginia, including Loudon County, where two projects, partially funded by EPA, are delivering reclaimed water to commercial facilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Virginia is home to the nation’s first program to augment a reservoir with recycled water. Since 1978, the upper Occoquan Sewage Authority has been discharging recycled water into a stream above Occoquan Reservoir, a potable water supply source for Fairfax County. Virginia adopted state regulations for water reclamation and reuse projects in October 2008.Fairfax County receives about $1 million a year from the sale of its reclaimed water, according to Michael McGrath, director of the Wastewater Treatment Division of the county’s Department of Public Works and Environmental Services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By preventing volumes of treated wastewater from entering Pohick Creek and eventually the Potomac River and Chesapeake Bay, the project has helped the plant stay under its cap on nitrogen and phosphorus pollution. The water reclamation project is conserving potable water that the energy facility, golf course and fields would ordinarily use, and rewarding those customers with a 25 percent discount on their water bills. Recycled water is most commonly used for agriculture, landscape, public parks, and golf course irrigation, as well as cooling water for power plants and oil refineries, industrial process water, toilet flushing, dust control, construction activities, concrete mixing, and artificial lakes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg left view-mode-medium&quot; style=&quot;width:448px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;A map of Virginia highlighting the location of Fairfax County.&quot; height=&quot;346&quot; width=&quot;448&quot; class=&quot;left media-element file-medium left&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/medium/public/2016-10/va_fairfaxcounty_20160226.jpg&quot; title=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-322947&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-10/documents/va_progress_-_recycled_water_providing_multiple_benefits_-_20150917_0.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=671583&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Water Reuse Project in VA Providing Multiple Benefits (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(1 pg, 672 K, 
  09/17/2015)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;field field-name-field-document-description field-type-text field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    More than 500 million gallons a year of treated wastewater that would otherwise be discharged into a tributary of the Chesapeake Bay are instead being put to beneficial reuse to cool a waste-to-energy plant and irrigate a golf course and ball fields in Fairfax County, Virginia.  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 12 Oct 2016 15:41:34 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>apruzins</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">162471 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Preventing Pollution to Local Waters, Bay; Preserving Historic Natural Bridge in Virginia</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/va/preventing-pollution-local-waters-bay-preserving-historic-natural-bridge-virginia</link>
    <description>&lt;h2&gt;Stories of Progress in Achieving Healthy Waters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;U.S. EPA Region 3 Water Protection Division&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Rockbridge County, Virginia • April 30, 2015&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In helping to preserve one of the oldest tourist destinations in the country – a spectacular natural land bridge in Virginia – EPA funding is protecting the surrounding land from development that would have impacted local waters and the Chesapeake Bay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using a $9.1 million EPA Clean Water State Revolving Fund (CWSRF) loan, the historic Natural Bridge in Rockbridge County, Virginia (just north of Roanoke) has been preserved as part of a larger land conservation project involving 1,500 mostly forested acres.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without the CWSRF loan to close the funding gap for the conservation easement, the private property could have been sold, making the forest available for residential and commercial development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The property, valued at $21 million and once owned by Thomas Jefferson, features a 215-foot limestone arch, a Native American village and a waterfall, among other popular attractions. It will be preserved as part of the Commonwealth of Virginia’s state park system by June of next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Natural Bridge and the surrounding property are located in the James River watershed, which feeds into the Chesapeake Bay. The conservation effort will prevent would-be nutrient pollution from affecting the Bay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Natural Bridge was declared a National Historic Landmark in 1998. According to its &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.naturalbridgeva.com/recreation/the-natural-bridge/&quot;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot; class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;, just before the American Revolution and writing of the Declaration of Independence, Jefferson purchased 157 acres of land including the Natural Bridge from King George III of England for 20 shillings. Legend has it, the website states, that a young George Washington surveyed the site for Lord Fairfax. The land bridge had been included in several “Seven Natural Wonders of the World” lists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using the EPA funds, the $9.1 million land conservation loan was made through the Virginia Department of Environmental Quality’s Clean Water Revolving Loan Fund (CWRLF). It was part of a complex purchase by a newly-formed conservation non-profit, the Virginia Conservation Legacy Fund, Inc. The non-profit was recognized for its Natural Bridge efforts with a 2015 Governor’s Environmental Excellence Award.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Virginia CWRLF has been financing land conservation projects since 2005. The Natural Bridge is the eighth such project, bringing the total to over $33.5 million. Virginia has plans for eight more land conservation projects next year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg left view-mode-medium&quot; style=&quot;width:448px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;A map of Virginia highlighting the location of Rock Bridge County&quot; height=&quot;346&quot; width=&quot;448&quot; class=&quot;left media-element file-medium left&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/medium/public/2016-10/va_rockbridgecounty_20160226.jpg&quot; title=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-322925&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-10/documents/va_progress_-_preventing_pollution_to_local_waters_bay-preserving_historic_natural_bridge_-_20150430.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=677992&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Preventing Pollution to Local Waters, Bay; Preserving Historic Natural Bridge in Virginia (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(1 pg, 678 K, 
  04/30/2015)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;field field-name-field-document-description field-type-text field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    In helping to preserve one of the oldest tourist destinations in the country – a spectacular natural land bridge in Virginia – EPA funding is protecting the surrounding land from development that would have impacted local waters and the Chesapeake Bay.  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 12 Oct 2016 15:14:43 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>apruzins</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">162467 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Plan Sets Stage for Green Features In City Subject to Sea Level Rise</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/va/plan-sets-stage-green-features-city-subject-sea-level-rise</link>
    <description>&lt;h2&gt;Stories of Progress in Achieving Healthy Waters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;U.S. EPA Region 3 Water Protection Division&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Norfolk, Virginia • October 8, 2015&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An EPA-financed plan will help the Knitting Mill Creek watershed in Norfolk, VA, move ahead in using &lt;a href=&quot;http://water.epa.gov/infrastructure/greeninfrastructure/index.cfm&quot;&gt;green infrastructure&lt;/a&gt; to control stormwater pollution in a community vulnerable to sea level rise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In May 2014, EPA provided more than $60,000 in technical assistance to Lafayette Wetlands Partnership, Friends of Norfolk’s Environment, and the City of Norfolk to explore green options for improving water quality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mixture of land uses within the 340-acre Knitting Mill watershed creates a patchwork of impervious surfaces that limits natural infiltration of stormwater. Much of the stormwater runoff from the watershed is collected in a storm drainage system and discharged into the creek without treatment, creating algal blooms that eventually spread downstream to the Lafayette River, and spawning high levels of E.coli bacteria.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The recently-released plan proposes green infrastructure practices in two locations: a green street retrofit of three blocks at the intersection of a residential and commercial corridor with roadside bioretention planter boxes and permeable concrete paver parking areas, and &lt;a href=&quot;/water-research/epa-science-matters-newsletter-what-green-infrastructure&quot;&gt;bioswales&lt;/a&gt; and a permeable pavement walkway along Mayflower Road, bordering Knitting Mill Creek.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The report’s findings are expected to serve as a template for how the practices can be implemented throughout urban areas of the Chesapeake Bay shoreline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;John D. Stewart of the Lafayette Wetlands Partnership said the groups are proceeding on several fronts to keep momentum behind the report. The team has obtained $10,000 toward a demonstration buffer and walkway along Knitting Mill Creek to test materials, plants and aesthetics before committing to a full installation, and has engaged a graduate student in civil engineering to study in more depth the influence of sea level rise on green infrastructure along the creek. “Adaptation to sea level rise is in the foreground here in Norfolk, and we want to understand the life cycle of costly installations along the riverfront,” Stewart said in an e-mail. The partners are also working with the city to link up the plan’s recommendations with a living shorelines project already underway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Norfolk was among 14 communities nationwide that received EPA support to expand the use of green infrastructure to reduce water pollution and boost resilience to climate change impacts. Norfolk, where scientists predict relative sea levels (rising water and sinking land) could rise 1.5 feet in the next 20-30 years, is also a focus of EPA’s “&lt;a href=&quot;/smartgrowth/making-visible-difference-communities&quot;&gt;Making a Visible Difference&lt;/a&gt;” effort. The city last year received a $4.64 million &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.doi.gov/sites/doi.gov/files/migrated/news/upload/2014-grants-list-v2.pdf&quot;&gt;U.S. Department of Interior Hurricane Sandy Coastal Resiliency&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot; class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt; grant to implement eight shoreline restoration projects and develop a green infrastructure plan and network for the Lafayette River watershed improvements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-png left view-mode-medium&quot; style=&quot;width:448px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;A map of Virginia highlighting the location of Norfolk.&quot; height=&quot;194&quot; width=&quot;448&quot; class=&quot;left media-element file-medium left&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/medium/public/2016-10/va_norfolk_20160329.png&quot; title=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-322909&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-10/documents/va_progress_-_plan_sets_stage_for_green_features_in_city_subject_to_sea_level_rise_-_20151008.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=676476&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Plan Sets Stage for Green Features in City Subject to Sea Level Rise (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(1 pg, 676 K, 
  10/08/2015)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;field field-name-field-document-description field-type-text field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    An EPA-financed plan will help the Knitting Mill Creek watershed in Norfolk, VA, move ahead in using green infrastructure to control stormwater pollution in a community vulnerable to sea level rise.  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 12 Oct 2016 14:54:07 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>apruzins</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">162463 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Innovative Settlement Brings Water System Compliance</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/va/innovative-settlement-brings-water-system-compliance</link>
    <description>&lt;h2&gt;Stories of Progress in Achieving Healthy Waters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;U.S. EPA Region 3 Water Protection Division&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luray, Virginia • December 24, 2015&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Residents of a small community water system have higher confidence in their water quality with up-to-date monitoring and a licensed operator as a result of EPA enforcement action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Shenandoah Utility Services water system serves a community population of approximately 55 people in a rural area near Luray, Virginia. Since at least 2009, the system missed required sampling events and was operating without a licensed waterworks operator. EPA issued two Administrative Orders and a Complaint for Penalty to address the violations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA settled the actions using Alternative Dispute Resolution (ADR). The settlement includes a Consent Agreement and Final Order, which contains a penalty, and an Administrative Order on Consent to ensure future compliance through a dedicated escrow account to pay for sampling and analysis through 2017. All monitoring is up-to-date, and the owner has become a licensed operator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Commonwealth of Virginia referred the case to EPA after citing the system for more than 100 violations and attempts to work with the owner failed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The water system was delinquent in collecting water samples for nitrates, metals, VOCs, and radiological and inorganic chemical contaminants, and was inconsistently collecting samples for bacteria. In addition, the system had not hired a licensed operator to oversee water system operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Residents served by the water system have no alternative water supply, as there is no nearby water system to extend lines for connections. While there was no known contamination of the drinking water, regular monitoring assures consumers that drinking water meets EPA and Virginia standards. The owner was reluctant to hire an operator because of the added expense. Concurrent with negotiations to settle the Complaint for Penalty, the owner completed numerous steps to become a licensed operator, including attending operator training classes, getting approval to take the license exam, and passing the exam.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The settlement included a first-time use by Region 3 &lt;a href=&quot;/laws-regulations/summary-safe-drinking-water-act&quot;&gt;Safe Drinking Water Act&lt;/a&gt; enforcement of an escrow account to ensure funding, and a forward-focused commitment by the owner to maintain his license. Negotiating with small system owners and returning them to compliance is a particular challenge. The systems typically have financial and managerial issues. When an owner agrees to make changes, in this case with the help of an ADR judge, families are more assured of a safe and reliable drinking water supply.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg left view-mode-medium&quot; style=&quot;width:448px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;A map of Virginia highlighting the location of Luray&quot; height=&quot;346&quot; width=&quot;448&quot; class=&quot;left media-element file-medium left&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/medium/public/2016-10/va_luray_20160226.jpg&quot; title=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-322883&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-10/documents/va_progress_-_innovative_settlement_-_20151224.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=530656&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Innovative Settlement Brings Water System Compliance (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(1 pg, 531 K, 
  12/24/2015)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;field field-name-field-document-description field-type-text field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    Residents of a small community water system have higher confidence in their water quality with up-to-date monitoring and a licensed operator as a result of EPA enforcement action.  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 12 Oct 2016 14:23:10 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>apruzins</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">162461 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  </channel>
</rss>

<!-- Page cached by Boost @ 2017-01-26 04:02:27, expires @ 2017-01-26 16:02:27, lifetime 12 hours -->