<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?><rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.epa.gov/feed/146987/rss.xml" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/" xmlns:og="http://ogp.me/ns#" xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#" xmlns:sioc="http://rdfs.org/sioc/ns#" xmlns:sioct="http://rdfs.org/sioc/types#" xmlns:skos="http://www.w3.org/2004/02/skos/core#" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#">
  <channel>
    <title>Speeches by EPA&#039;s Administrator</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/feed/146987/rss.xml</link>
    <description>Updated Speeches by EPA&#039;s Administrator content from the US Environmental Protection Agency</description>
    <language>en</language>
     <atom:link href="https://www.epa.gov/feed/146987/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      <item>
    <title>Administrator Gina McCarthy, Remarks at the American Water Summit, Miami, Fl, As Prepared</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/speeches/administrator-gina-mccarthy-remarks-american-water-summit-miami-fl-prepared</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;December 7, 2016&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(Introduction)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you, Ian, for that introduction.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	And thank you to everyone at the American Water Summit for the warm welcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&#039;m here to talk about the future of water, which I believe is one of the top public health and economic challenges now facing our country. This is a moment of opportunity – to drive smart, equitable, resilient investments to modernize our aging water infrastructure; to invent and build the technologies of the future; and to protect our precious water resources.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	To seize this opportunity, we need urgent and sustained action at &lt;i&gt;all&lt;/i&gt; levels of government and from &lt;i&gt;all&lt;/i&gt; sectors of the economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(Protecting Source Water)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&#039;re seeing this play out right here in Florida. The state made national news last summer when toxic algae infested waterways and coastlines, threatening public health, hampering recreation, cutting tourism, and imposing huge costs on the local economy. Florida was under a state of emergency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The nutrient pollution that fuels these toxic algal blooms isn&#039;t limited to Florida – it is one of our country&#039;s most widespread and costly environmental problems. Some 16,000 waterways are impaired by nitrogen and phosphorus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, there was an unprecedented 650-mile long algal bloom on the Ohio River. And in 2014, Toledo had to shut down its drinking water system for days because of a bloom on Lake Erie. Elsewhere across the country we are seeing ground and surface sources of drinking water threatened by unregulated legacy contaminants like PFCs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a wake-up call. We have a serious problem – and we must do more to protect our vital source waters.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	Source water protection is one of the key reasons why the Clean Water Rule, which I signed in 2015, is so critical. It clarifies protection for 60 percent of the nation&#039;s streams and millions of acres of wetlands – those upstream waters that feed into drinking water supplies for one in three Americans – 117 million people. The rule is grounded in law and the latest science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But EPA can&#039;t solve threats to source water through federal action alone. Nutrient pollution comes from many sources including agricultural and other non-point sources that are not regulated under federal law. For example, stormwater pollution is a major problem in hundreds of communities across the country that requires smart land use and investment decisions at the local level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Proactive action to protect drinking water sources and prevent contamination before it happens needs to be a top priority in every community. States and local governments are central and must play a leadership role in this effort. All industries, agriculture utilities and the public need to get involved and do their share to protect this critical resource. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(Investing in Infrastructure)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Florida also reflects another key challenge facing the water sector – that of aging and inadequate infrastructure. In Florida alone, $34 billion is needed to repair and expand the systems that move and treat wastewater, stormwater, and drinking water.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	Our nation collectively needs about $685 billion in investment over the next 20 years. This need is particularly acute in low-income and economically distressed communities – both urban and rural – many of which are struggling to provide safe and reliable basic water services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&#039;ve known for years that our nation&#039;s investments in water infrastructure aren&#039;t keeping up. We need to invest more. We need to make the infrastructure dollars we have work smarter and harder. And we need to make sure these investments are equitable and prioritize the needs of distressed communities like Flint that are falling behind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&#039;s why EPA created the Water Infrastructure Resilience and Finance Center – a &quot;think-and-do-tank&quot; that&#039;s dedicated to driving innovation in water infrastructure finance and helping communities in need.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	We&#039;ve also laid the foundation for implementing the Water Infrastructure Finance and Innovation Act, or WIFIA – a new program that has the potential to provide billions of dollars in low-interest loans to support large infrastructure projects. Just yesterday we finalized the administrative structure for the program and will await appropriations from Congress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Going forward, there&#039;s broad agreement that infrastructure investment is a top national priority. We need to make sure water infrastructure is at the center of that effort. And we need to make sure that this investment is made in a way that benefits the communities that need it most – including by building the capacity of low-income and small communities to get access to funding and to safely and sustainably manage their infrastructure. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(Drinking Water Safety is a Priority)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&#039;s not just physical infrastructure that needs to be upgraded. The country needs to modernize our collective work to provide safe drinking water on which public health and our economy depend. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	EPA has set drinking water standards for more than 90 contaminants, and compliance data show that more than 90 percent of the nation&#039;s water systems consistently meet those standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what about the other 10 percent of the nation&#039;s water systems that don&#039;t meet all the standards all the time? And we still have thousands of people in this country – primarily in disadvantaged communities – that face serious challenges with access to safe and reliable drinking water.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&#039;s why last week we released a Drinking Water Action Plan that serves as a national call to action, urging all levels of government, utilities, community organizations, and other stakeholders to work together to increase the safety and reliability of drinking water.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This plan was developed through extensive engagement with states, tribes, local governments, utilities and other stakeholders and it enjoys broad support. It maps out a set of concrete, practical actions that together have the potential to dramatically strengthen drinking water safety:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Like establishing a 21&lt;sup&gt;st&lt;/sup&gt; century electronic reporting system that gives regulators and the public prompt accurate information on drinking water quality.&lt;br /&gt;
		 &lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Like supporting regional partnerships so utilities can band together to more efficiently and safely manage water infrastructure.&lt;br /&gt;
		 &lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Like promoting watershed partnerships to protect our source waters and driving new monitoring and treatment technologies to address unregulated contaminants.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(Climate Change Makes the Work Tougher)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we chart a course forward, we have to recognize that the greatest environmental challenge of our time – climate change – is hitting the water sector hardest.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	We&#039;re seeing this in more frequent and more intense droughts, stronger storms, flooding, sea level rise, and ocean acidification. This makes all of our efforts more difficult and more critical.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	This conference is being held at an epicenter for these impacts.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	The rate of sea-level rise in South Florida has tripled over the last decade, according to a study from the University of Miami.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	Local officials are responding by making areas like Miami Beach more resilient, with new sewers and pumps and modifications to major roads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile across the country…drought has led to wells running dry in California&#039;s Central Valley, Superstorm Sandy decimated the New Jersey coast, and we&#039;ve seen historic floods hit numerous states. These impacts are costing us billions of dollars and threaten public health, our water infrastructure, our drinking water supplies, and our treasured water bodies.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	Climate change has become a national security challenge – the Pentagon has been vocal about their concerns and in September, the President directed federal agencies to ensure that climate change is addressed as part of national security policy and plans.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	As climate impacts increase, it is not just likely that water shortages will drive international conflicts, but it could well lead to difficult debates among regions, states, and communities here in the U.S. Resilience to its impacts is fundamental to the well-being of our nation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(A New Way Forward)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It feels like in some respects we&#039;re just treading water against these challenges. How are we going to swim instead of sink? We need a paradigm shift in how we view and use water.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	We need to move away from the narrow 20&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; century view of water: as a place to dump waste; as something to just treat and send downstream in pipes; as only an expense for cities and a planning burden for communities.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	We need to accelerate the move to a 21&lt;sup&gt;st&lt;/sup&gt; century view – where we see water as a finite and valuable asset, as a major economic driver, as essential to urban revitalization, as a centerpiece for innovative technology, and as a key focus of our efforts to build resilience.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	This shift presents tremendous opportunities – to revitalize communities, to grow businesses and jobs, to improve public health. But to achieve it, we must make water a top national priority – and we need to be bold and revolutionary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to drive innovation across all dimensions of the water sector: in technology, finance, management, and regulation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We all see how science, technology, and innovation are opening new frontiers, fueling the economy, and changing our world. We must incubate this change in the water sector as well because both the challenges and the opportunities are vast.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	Consider that the nation&#039;s wastewater facilities discharge approximately 9.5 trillion gallons of wastewater per year. Utilities are increasingly turning to technologies and approaches that foster greater reuse of water and recovery of resources that were previously discarded as waste.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Look at Orange County, California, where they are generating over 100 million gallons per day of recycled water. Instead of just discharging that water into the Pacific Ocean, that ultrapure water is used to replenish groundwater in Anaheim, injected to ward off saltwater intrusion in Fountain Valley, and as an indirect source of tap water to 2.5 million people in the county.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	Look at the opportunities for energy efficiency and recovery, key areas for our planet&#039;s long-term sustainability. The water facilities nationwide account for as much as 4 percent of national electricity consumption, costing about $4 billion a year. Now we see utilities producing energy instead – while slashing costs and carbon emissions at the same time!&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	Look at Gresham, Oregon, where the wastewater plant has become a net zero facility – using biogas generators and solar panels to produce more energy than it needs. Not only is that saving city taxpayers half a million dollars per year, but last year the city also earned $250,000 from fees local restaurants are paying to drop off fats, oils and grease.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	These opportunities to harness innovative technology aren&#039;t just good for public health and the environment – they can be enormous economic drivers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2015, the global market for environmental technologies goods and services was more than $1 trillion. The United States environmental technologies industry exported $51.2 billion in goods and services. This same industry supports an estimated 1.6 million jobs here in the U.S.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	So the soundbite that protecting the environment is bad for the economy is just patently false. It&#039;s actually the opposite.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(Closing)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As our nation heads into a time of transition, we need to remember that water is a nonpartisan issue. We all depend on clean and reliable water – our families, our communities, our businesses, our society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, it should come as no surprise that in a Gallup poll last spring, people were asked about their environmental concerns – pollution of drinking water and pollution of rivers and lakes were the top two concerns … people care about water.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right now, this is an all-hands-on-deck issue. To confront the challenges we face and to seize this moment of opportunity, we have to work together – all levels of government, all sectors of the economy, every community. EPA stands ready to partner and to lead in this effort – so let&#039;s do it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 07 Dec 2016 12:27:29 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>jmorin</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">166555 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Administrator Gina McCarthy, Keynote Address at the National Press Club, Washington, DC, As Prepared</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/speeches/administrator-gina-mccarthy-keynote-address-national-press-club-washington-dc-prepared</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;November 21, 2016&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(INTRODUCTION)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PRESIDENT BURR, THANK YOU FOR THE KIND INTRODUCTION. AND THANK YOU TO EVERYONE AT THE NATIONAL PRESS CLUB FOR THE WARM WELCOME.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A FEW OF YOU IN THIS ROOM MIGHT BE OLD ENOUGH TO REMEMBER…I’M CERTAINLY NOT—BUT THERE WAS A TIME WHEN CONGRESS PASSED A LAW WITH A UNANIMOUS VOTE IN THE SENATE—AND ONLY ONE NAY VOTE IN THE HOUSE.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NOPE—NOT THE NAMING OF A POST OFFICE…ANYONE? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;IT WAS THE CLEAN AIR ACT OF 1970. A HISTORIC LAW, SIGNED BY A REPUBLICAN PRESIDENT. IT WAS A GLOBAL TURNING POINT…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;THE CLEAN AIR ACT WAS PASSED IN RESPONSE TO A CHANGING WORLD…IT SOUGHT TO BUILD THIS COUNTRY UP, TO LOOK FORWARD, AND TO CONSIDER HOW OUR ACTIONS WOULD IMPACT PEOPLE WE’D NEVER KNOW…AND A FUTURE WE’D NEVER SEE OURSELVES. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TODAY, TIMES ARE DIFFERENT…BUT THE NATURE OF CHANGE, WELL, HAS NOT CHANGED. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;THE WORLD CONTINUES TO BE IN MOTION…AND IT WILL KEEP CHANGING, REGARDLESS OF THE FEW WHO CHOOSE NOT TO ACKNOWLEDGE IT. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(MISSION OF THE AGENCY IS TIMELESS)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AND WHILE THE WORLD CONTINUES TO CHANGE, EPA’S MISSION CONTINUES TO ENDURE. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OUR MISSION IS TO PROTECT PUBLIC HEALTH – TO SAFEGUARD THE PRECIOUS NATURAL RESOURCES WE NEED TO SURVIVE AND THRIVE.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OUR TASK IS TIMELESS. IT IS NON-PARTISAN. IT IS ESSENTIAL TO EVERY SINGLE LIFE. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;WE CANNOT PURSUE LIBERTY OR HAPPINESS WITHOUT CLEAN AIR TO BREATHE OR CLEAN WATER TO DRINK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HARD WORKING AMERICANS GET UP EVERY MORNING, GET THEIR KIDS TO SCHOOL, AND TAKE THAT EXTRA CLASS OR PICK UP THAT EXTRA SHIFT…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;…THE LAST THING THEY WANT IS TO DEAL WITH IS THE RANCOR THAT TOO OFTEN CHARACTERIZES OUR POLITICS…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;YOU KNOW, PEOPLE MAY BE FED UP WITH WHAT THEY HEAR IN WASHINGTON…BUT THAT DOESN’T MEAN THEY DON’T CARE ABOUT WHAT WE DO AND WHAT WE DON’T DO. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;THEY CARE ABOUT CLEAN AIR…THEY CARE ABOUT SAFE DRINKING WATER AND FISHABLE, SWIMMABLE RIVERS AND STREAMS…THEY CARE ABOUT SAFE PLACES TO LIVE, WORK, AND PLAY…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EVERY ONE OF THOSE HARD-WORKING AMERICANS, THEY CARE ABOUT FOOD THAT’S FREE OF HARMFUL PESTICIDES, PRODUCTS FREE OF HARMFUL TOXICS, AND THEIR NEIGHBORHOODS AND KIDS’ FUTURE’S FREE FROM THE DANGERS OF CLIMATE CHANGE…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;WE’RE HERE, BECAUSE THE AMERICAN PEOPLE DEMANDED WE BE HERE…WE’RE HERE, BECAUSE WE STAND BETWEEN POLLUTION AND OUR PEOPLE…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LOOK, WE’VE MADE TREMENDOUS PROGRESS IN THE PAST 5 DECADES…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;POLLUTION TODAY IS LESS VISIBLE THAN THE “GOOD OLD DAYS” WHEN SMOKESTACKS SPEWED BLACK CLOUDS AND RIVERS CAUGHT FIRE…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;… BUT PEOPLE EXPECT US TO DEAL WITH POLLUTION THEY CAN’T SEE – LIKE AIR POLLUTION THAT TRAVELS INTO OUR COUNTRY AND ACROSS OUR STATES…OR CHEMICALS IN OUR DRINKING WATER. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;…PEOPLE EXPECT US TO DO OUR JOBS USING THE BEST SCIENCE AND RESEARCH TO DEFINE CHALLENGES AND CRAFT SOLUTIONS…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;…PEOPLE EXPECT US TO UNDERSTAND AND USE CHANGE AS A CATALYST FOR GROWTH AND PROSPERITY…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;IF WE DO NOT—IF WE PLACE RANCOR OVER ACTION…IF WE BETRAY THE PEOPLE WHO PUT US HERE…IF WE STUBBORNLY DENY THE SCIENCE AND CHANGE AROUND US—WE WILL FALL VICTIM TO OUR OWN PARALYSIS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(INEVITABILITY / CLEAN ENERGY FUTURE / CLIMATE ACTION)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SCIENCE TELLS US THAT THERE IS NO BIGGER THREAT TO AMERICAN PROGRESS AND PROSPERITY THAN THE THREAT OF GLOBAL CLIMATE CHANGE. AND IF YOU TAKE NOTHING ELSE FROM MY SPEECH TODAY, TAKE THIS: THE TRAIN TO A GLOBAL, CLEAN ENERGY FUTURE HAS ALREADY LEFT THE STATION.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;WE HAVE A CHOICE…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;WE CAN CHOOSE TO GET ON BOARD, TO LEAD…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OR WE CAN CHOOSE TO BE LEFT BEHIND, TO STAND STUBBORNLY STILL…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;WHEN PRESENTED WITH THAT CHOICE, PRESIDENT OBAMA CHOSE LEADERSHIP. HE CHOSE ACTION. HE CHOSE A CALCULATED INVESTMENT IN OUR COLLECTIVE FUTURE.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PRESIDENT OBAMA RECOGNIZES THAT THE INEVITABILITY OF OUR CLEAN ENERGY FUTURE IS BIGGER THAN ANY ONE PERSON OR NATION.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;THE FACTS TODAY PAINT A CLEAR PICTURE—CLIMATE CHANGE IS AMONG THE MOST SIGNIFICANT PUBLIC HEALTH, ECONOMIC, AND SECURITY CHALLENGES WE’VE EVER FACED.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AND UNDER HIS ADMINISTRATION, WITH AN ECONOMIC RECESSION THE LIKES OF WHICH WE HAVE NOT SEEN SINCE THE 1930S, HE HAD THE FORESIGHT TO INVEST IN SOLAR AND WIND AND CLEAN AUTO MANUFACTURING…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;…TO SET A COURSE FOR STRONG DOMESTIC CLIMATE ACTION—POSITIONING THE U.S. TO LEAD THE WAY IN SECURING A HISTORIC INTERNATIONAL AGREEMENT…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AND HE WAS RIGHT—THE PARIS AGREEMENT WAS NEGOTIATED AND IS NOW IN FULL FORCE.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;…AND EPA WILL CONTINUE TO BE ESSENTIAL TO CUTTING CARBON POLLUTION IN THE UNITED STATES, AND MAKING GOOD ON OUR GLOBAL LEADERSHIP…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;WE’VE SET GHG STANDARDS FOR CARS AND TRUCKS THAT SLASH CARBON POLLUTION AND SAVE PEOPLE MONEY AT THE PUMP…WHILE BOOSTING THE AUTO INDUSTRY FROM NEAR BANKRUPTCY TO RECORD INCREASES IN SALES AND JOBS&lt;br /&gt;
		 &lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;…WE’VE SET METHANE STANDARDS FOR LANDFILLS AND NEW OIL AND GAS PRODUCTION UNITS—AND ARE GATHERING DATA TO SET STANDARDS ON EXISTING ONES…&lt;br /&gt;
		 &lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;WE HELPED BROKER TWO HISTORIC INTERNATIONAL AGREEMENTS TO LOWER CARBON EMISSIONS FROM AIRCRAFT…&lt;br /&gt;
		 &lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;…AND SOMETHING ELSE I’M VERY PROUD OF, WE LED THE U.S. DELEGATION THAT SUCCESSFULLY AMENDED AN INTERNATIONAL AGREEMENT TO REDUCE HYDROFLUOROCARBONS…A HIGHLY POTENT GREENHOUSE GAS. THIS ONE AGREEMENT ALONE AVOIDS UP TO 8O BILLION METRIC TONS OF GHG EMISSIONS—WHICH IS THE EQUIVALENT OF 10 YEARS OF U.S. GHG EMISSIONS. &lt;br /&gt;
		 &lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;AND, OF COURSE, WE TOOK HISTORIC ACTION TO SET SENSIBLE CARBON POLLUTION LIMITS AT OUR LARGEST STATIONARY SOURCES—OUR POWER PLANTS…THROUGH THE CLEAN POWER PLAN.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;NOW, I’VE HEARD SOME PEOPLE TALK ABOUT EPA’S CLEAN POWER PLAN LIKE IT’S THE DRIVING FORCE BEHIND THIS COUNTRY’S TRANSITION TO CLEAN ENERGY …&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;THE REALITY IS, THOSE FOLKS GIVE US TOO MUCH CREDIT. THE CPP WAS DESIGNED TO FOLLOW THE CLEAN ENERGY TRANSITION ALREADY UNDERWAY…THE ONE THAT THE ENERGY MARKET NOW DEPENDS ON—AND CONTINUES TO DEMAND.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;JUST LOOK AT WHERE THE US ENERGY SECTOR IS NOW.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;IN 2014 ALONE CLEAN ENERGY INVESTMENT INCREASED BY 14 PERCENT…MORE THAN 5 TIMES GREATER GROWTH THAN THE REST OF THE U.S. ECONOMY. &lt;br /&gt;
		 &lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;U.S. POWER PLANT CO2 EMISSIONS IN 2015 WERE ABOUT 24 PERCENT BELOW 2005 LEVELS, ALREADY WELL ON THE WAY TO THE CPP’S 2030 TARGETS.&lt;br /&gt;
		 &lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;2015 EMISSIONS WERE ABOUT THE SAME AS THE CPP FIRST YEAR GOAL IN 2022, A FULL 7 YEARS AHEAD OF SCHEDULE.&lt;br /&gt;
		 &lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;24 STATES HAD LOWER EMISSIONS IN 2015 THAN THEIR 2022 ANNUAL GOAL…INCLUDING STATES LIKE OHIO, NORTH CAROLINA, PENNSYLVANIA, AND SOUTH DAKOTA.&lt;br /&gt;
		 &lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;AND THE ENERGY INFORMATION AGENCY ESTIMATES THAT ALMOST 70% OF NEW UTILITY-SCALE GENERATING CAPACITY EXPECTED TO COME ONLINE IN 2016 WILL BE ZERO-EMITTING, MOSTLY SOLAR AND WIND.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;CLEARLY THERE IS MORE GOING ON THAN THE CPP. LOOK, I’M NOT TRYING TO SAY THE CPP ISN’T IMPORTANT. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;THE TRUTH IS, TO EXPLAIN THE SIGNIFICANCE AND VIRTUES OF THE CLEAN POWER PLAN WILL NOT FIT INTO THIS SPEECH….IT WILL NOT FIT INTO A SOUNDBITE…AND IT WILL CERTAINLY NOT FIT INTO A TWEET—BELIEVE ME, WE’VE TRIED. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;BUT I TRULY BELIEVE, GUIDED BY PRESIDENT OBAMA’S DELIBERATE VISION, HISTORY WILL SHOW THAT THE CLEAN POWER PLAN MARKED A TURNING POINT IN AMERICAN CLIMATE LEADERSHIP. A POINT WHERE OUR COUNTRY STEPPED UP TO THE PLATE AND DELIVERED…AND THE WORLD FOLLOWED…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;IT’S A SIGN OF U.S. COMMITMENT…IT’S A MARKET SIGNAL TO INVESTORS AND INNOVATORS…AND IT BRINGS STABILITY AND CERTAINTY TO THE ENERGY SECTOR, AND THE WORLD. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;BUT THE GLOBAL TRANSITION TO A LOW CARBON ECONOMY IS MUCH MORE THAN ONE REGULATION…THE ENERGY MARKET AND THE COMMITMENT OF THE PRIVATE SECTOR ARE NOW DRIVING OUR INEVITABLE JOURNEY…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;…A JOURNEY THAT’S CONSISTENT WITH VIRTUALLY EVERY NATION’S UNDERSTANDING OF CLIMATE SCIENCE—AND OUR OBLIGATION TO ACT TO PROTECT OUR CHILDREN’S FUTURES. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;WE’RE IN A SPECTACULARLY DIFFERENT PLACE TODAY THAN WE WERE WHEN PRESIDENT OBAMA TOOK OFFICE. BEFORE, DEVELOPING COUNTRIES POINTED A FINGER AT US…NOW, THEY ARE WONDERING IF THE U.S. WILL TURN ITS BACK ON SCIENCE AND BE LEFT BEHIND. THE CHOICE IS OURS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AS THE PRESIDENT SAID, THE INEVITABILITY OF OUR CLEAN ENERGY FUTURE IS BIGGER THAN ANY ONE PERSON OR NATION.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AND IT MUST BE GUIDED BY A SIMPLE, PROFOUND TRUTH: WE DON’T HAVE TO CHOSE ECONOMY OR ENVIRONMENT…WE CAN, AND MUST, CHOOSE BOTH.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;THIS TRUTH HAS BEEN THE FOUNDATION OF ALL THE PROGRESS WE’VE MADE AT EPA, AND WE HAVE A TRACK RECORD TO SHOW FOR IT…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(PROGRESS)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OVER THE PAST 8 YEARS UNDER PRESIDENT OBAMA’S LEADERSHIP, WE HAVE TAKEN TREMENDOUS STRIDES FORWARD IN ECONOMIC GROWTH: 8 YEARS OF ECONOMIC EXPANSION AND A RECORD INCREASE IN MEDIAN INCOMES…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;…AND AT THE SAME TIME, WE’VE MADE INCREDIBLE PROGRESS IN CUTTING POLLUTION AND PROTECTING PUBLIC HEALTH.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PRESIDENT OBAMA UNDERSTANDS SO CLEARLY THAT A CLEAN, HEALTHY ENVIRONMENT IS NOT A LUXURY. IT’S NOT WINDOW DRESSING. IT’S A RIGHT. IT’S THE FOUNDATION OF OUR ECONOMY AND OUR LIVES...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OUR WORK TO CURB POLLUTION MUST ALWAYS FOCUS NOT ONLY WHAT OUR NATION NEEDS AS A WHOLE—BUT ON THOSE WHO HAVE BEEN DISPROPORTIONALLY HURT…ON DISADVANTAGED COMMUNITIES THAT BEAR THE BURDEN OF ENVIRONMENTAL INJUSTICE…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AND IN THE PAST 8 YEARS, WE’VE PAID ATTENTION TO NATIONAL CHALLENGES—AS WELL AS THE NEED TO PARTNER WITH OUR STATES, LOCAL COMMUNITIES AND TRIBES—AS WE SET MEASURABLE, COMMON SENSE STANDARDS. HERE’S JUST A SAMPLING OF WHAT WE’VE DONE:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;WE’VE REDUCED MERCURY EMISSIONS FROM POWER PLANTS AND PROTECTED MORE PEOPLE FROM HARMFUL LEVELS OF OZONE AND PARTICULATE MATTER IN OUR AIR;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;WE’VE LOWERED SULFUR CONTENT IN FUELS AND POLLUTION FROM CARS…MADE STATES ACCOUNTABLE FOR HARMFUL LEVELS OF AIR POLLUTION THEY SEND DOWNWIND…REQUIRED FENCE LINE MONITORS AROUND REFINERIES…AND MADE PROGRESS IN CLEANING UP OUR PORTS…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;WE’VE CLARIFIED THE JURISDICTIONAL BOUNDARIES OF THE CLEAN WATER ACT…REDUCED TOXIC EFFLUENT FROM POWER PLANTS…AND SET NEW STANDARDS FOR THE MANAGEMENT OF COAL ASH…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;WE’VE PROVIDED FARMWORKERS THE SAME LEVEL OF PROTECTIONS OTHER WORKERS ENJOY AND MADE PROGRESS IN RESTORING ICONIC WATERBODIES LIKE THE CHESAPEAKE BAY AND GREAT LAKES...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AND WE’VE MADE SURE THAT THESE STANDARDS ARE MET WITH ENFORCEMENT THAT PUTS PEOPLE FIRST…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;…LIKE THE DEEPWATER HORIZON SPILL SETTLEMENTS THAT PROVIDED $20 BILLION TO RESTORE AND PROTECT THE GULF…OR THE VOLKSWAGEN SETTLEMENT THAT ENSURES $14 BILLION DOLLARS TO COMPENSATE CONSUMERS, REDUCE POLLUTION, AND BUILD INFRASTRUCTURE FOR ZERO-EMITTING VEHICLES. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;WE’VE LEVERAGED THE POWER OF INFORMATION TO BROADEN AND EMPOWER OUR ENVIRONMENTAL ENTERPRISE…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;… THROUGH PROGRAMS LIKE ENERGY STAR, WATER SENSE, AND SAFER CHOICE WHICH EMPOWER CONSUMERS TO GROW DEMAND AND MARKETS FOR GREENER PRODUCT THROUGH THEIR PURCHASES.&lt;br /&gt;
		 &lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;… EPA APPS LIKE “HOW’S MY WATERWAY,” “AIR NOW,” AND “SCHOOL IQ ASSESSMENT” AND TOOLS LIKE THE ADAPATION RESOURCE CENTER AND THE GREEN INFRASTURE WIZARD THAT UNLOCK THE POWER OF CITIZEN SCIENCE TO HELP US PROTECT MORE PEOPLE, USING PEOPLE POWER NOT MONEY.&lt;br /&gt;
		 &lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;… TRANSPARENT, READILY ACCESSIBLE INFORMATION AND NEW MONITORING TECHNOLOGIES LIKE THE VILLAGE GREEN BENCH THAT DOUBLES AS AN AIR MONITOR OR CAMERAS THAT CAN LITERALLY SEE LEAKS FROM STORAGE TANKS THAT ARE OTHERWISE INVISIBLE.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;WE’VE DEEPENED OUR FOCUS ON THE VULNERABLE COMMUNITIES THAT HAVE BEEN LEFT BEHIND …&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;…THROUGH OUR WORK WITH TRIBES TO RECOGNIZE TRIBAL TREATY RIGHTS…OR OUR WORK TO “MAKE A VISIBLE DIFFERENCE” THAT HAS ALREADY REACHED EVERY REGION OF THE COUNTRY…OR OUR WORK LOOKING AHEAD—SUCH AS OUR E.J. 2020 PLAN OR PLACE-BASED EFFORTS WHERE WE COLLABORATE WITH FEDERAL PARTNERS TO SUPPORT COMMUNITIES IN THEIR EFFORT TO BECOME MORE SUSTAINABLE LIKE LOCAL FOOD, LOCAL PLACES. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;AND OF COURSE, WE’VE INCREASED OUR ATTENTION ON DRINKING WATER. LESSONS LEARNED IN FLINT ARE BEING SHARED ACROSS THE NATION SO WE CAN BETTER PREPARE TO FINISH THE JOB OF ADDRESSING LEGACY CONTAMINANTS, FACE NEW ONES AND FIX OUR AGING INFRASTRUCTURE... &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(EPA IS DEMOCRACY IN ACTION / CLOSING)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;…DOING MORE, DOING BETTER…THAT’S OUR CONSTANT ASPIRATION. IT’S THE NATURE OF OUR DEMOCRACY…WE MAKE PROGRESS USING SCIENCE AND THE LAW, AND WE CONTINUE TO BE RESPONSIVE TO CHANGE…NOT OPPOSE IT.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;THAT’S HOW EPA WAS BORN, AND THAT’S HOW OUR MISSION WILL EXIST, FAR BEYOND THE BOUNDS OF ELECTORAL CYCLES…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;BECAUSE, AT ITS CORE, EPA EMBRACES THE AMERICAN IDEAL E PLURIBUS UNUM – OF MANY, COME ONE – BECAUSE POLLUTION AND HEALTH RISKS DO NOT DISCRIMINATE…AND WE, LIKE THIS NATION, WILL ALWAYS BE A PLACE WHERE WE DRAW STRENGTH FROM OUR DIFFERENCES. AND UNDER THIS PRESIDENT’S WATCH WE HAVE ENGAGED MORE AMERICANS THAN EVER IN THE WORK WE DO.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MILLIONS HAVE INFORMED OUR CLIMATE RULES, WITH THE VAST MAJORITY SIMPLY WANTING US TO PROTECT THEM AND THEIR CHILDREN’S FUTURE BY FOLLOWING THE SCIENCE AND THE LAW. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;MOTHERS OF EVERY COLOR HAVE BANDED TOGETHER TO ENSURE THEIR VOICES ARE HEARD AND LEADERS OF ALL FAITHS HAVE SPOKEN UP ON OUR MORAL OBLIGATION TO TAKE CLIMATE ACTION.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HISPANIC AND AFRICAN AMERICAN VOICES HAVE BEEN SPEAKING UP TO REMIND US THAT THEY ARE OFTEN THE ONES MOST AT RISK IF WE FAIL TO ACT. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;BUSINESSES - BIG AND SMALL - ARE MAKING THE RISKS OF INACTION CLEAR—AND CALLING ATTENTION TO THE OPPORTUNITIES IN FRONT OF US TO BOOST OUR ECONOMY AND CREATE ENTIRE NEW SECTORS OF JOBS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;…AND EPA HAS LISTENED. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’M SO PROUD OF THE WORK WE’VE DONE TO REACH A MORE DIVERSE CONSTITUENCY…TO MAKE EPA MORE ACCESSIBLE…A PLACE WHERE MORE VOICES CAN HAVE A SAY…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;…WHERE COMMUNITIES CONCERNED ABOUT THEIR HEALTH – AND YES, BUSINESSES CONCERNED ABOUT THEIR OPERATIONS – ARE WELCOMED INTO THE DISCUSSION TO WORK WITH US HAND IN HAND...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I KNOW THERE IS A LOT OF ANXIETY THESE DAYS, BUT I AM VERY HOPEFUL FOR A FEW REASONS. WE HAVE DONE OUR JOB AND THE ENVIRONMENTAL ENTERPRISE IS MORE INCLUSIVE AND MORE EFFECTIVE THAN EVER. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;WE’VE ENERGIZED THE AMERICAN PEOPLE WHO WILL DEMAND NOT ONLY CLEAN AIR AND CLEAN WATER FOR THEIR CHILDREN, THEY WILL DEMAND A STABLE PLANET. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;WE’VE CREATED THE KIND OF RESONANCE THAT HAS MOTIVATED A GENERATION OF YOUNG PEOPLE…A FAMILIAR MOVEMENT THAT RESEMBLES TIMES PAST, WHEN MILLIONS OF VOICES—STANDING UP AND SPEAKING OUT—CHANGED OUR COUNTRY’S TRAJECTORY…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AND I AM HOPEFUL BECAUSE IN 2016 A BILL PASSED ON A VOICE VOTE IN THE SENATE AND IN THE HOUSE WITH ONLY 12 NAY VOTES…AGAIN, NO…IT WASN’T NAMING OF A POST OFFICE…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;IT WAS THE LAUTENBERG CHEMICAL SAFETY ACT—THE FIRST UPDATE TO AN ENVIRONMENTAL STATUTE IN 20 YEARS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CONGRESS OVERWHELMINGLY CAME TOGETHER—THIS CONGRESS—TO GIVE THE EPA MORE AUTHORITY TO PROTECT THE AMERICAN PEOPLE FROM DANGEROUS CHEMICALS. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;WHEN HE SIGNED THE BILL INTO LAW, PRESIDENT OBAMA SAID—QUOTE—“THIS IS PROOF THAT…HERE IN WASHINGTON, THINGS CAN WORK. IT’S POSSIBLE. WE CAN KEEP FAMILIES SAFE AND UNLEASH THE ENGINE OF AMERICAN INNOVATION. WE CAN PROTECT THE PLANET AND KEEP CREATING JOBS. IF WE CAN GET THIS BILL DONE, IT MEANS THAT SOMEWHERE OUT THERE ON THE HORIZON, WE CAN MAKE OUR POLITICS LESS TOXIC AS WELL.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I THINK PRESIDENT OBAMA WAS RIGHT-- ALTHOUGH WE MAY NOT BE QUITE THERE YET ON THE LAST POINT. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;WE CAN MAKE THINGS WORK IN WASHINGTON IF WE CHOOSE TO FOCUS ON THE JOB AT HAND…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FOR EPA, THAT’S, PROTECTING THE HEALTH OF THE PEOPLE WE’VE PLEDGED TO SERVE. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I WANT TO END WITH THIS…TO THE UNSUNG HEROES I’VE HAD THE PRIVILEGE OF WORKING WITH AT EPA – THE SCIENTISTS, THE ECONOMISTS, THE LAWYERS AND REGULATORS WHO’VE DEVOTED THEIR LIVES TO PUBLIC SERVICE…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;…AND TO THE OUTSIDE ADVOCATES, BUSINESSES, INNOVATORS AND INDUSTRY VISIONARIES – WE NEED YOU. WE WILL ALWAYS NEED YOU.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I KNOW WHO YOU ARE, I KNOW YOU PLACE SCIENCE AND SERVICE ABOVE PARTISANSHIP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’VE SEEN WHAT YOU’RE CAPABLE OF – AND THAT’S WHY I’M SO CERTAIN THAT OUR FUTURE WILL CONTINUE TO BE BRIGHTER, HEALTHIER, AND MORE JUST FOR ALL.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Mon, 21 Nov 2016 19:31:51 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>jmorin</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">165511 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Administradora Gina McCarthy, discurso ante la conferencia de verano de LULAC en Washington, DC, previamente redactado</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/speeches/administradora-gina-mccarthy-discurso-ante-la-conferencia-de-verano-de-lulac-en-washington</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/speeches/administradora-gina-mccarthy-discurso-ante-la-conferencia-de-verano-de-lulac-en-washington&quot;&gt;English version&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;El 14 de julio de 2016&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quiero dar las gracias y reconocer a Roger Rocha, presidente nacional de LULAC, así como a Green Latinos y muchas otras organizaciones que se aseguran de que las voces de la comunidad latina sean escuchadas dentro del área metropolitana de Washington, DC, así como alrededor de los Estados Unidos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;La EPA continuará dependiendo de su insumo y apoyo como lo hemos hecho para tomar acción sobre el cambio climático, el aire limpio, para tomar acción sobre el agua potable segura y los ríos y arroyos sanos, y hogares y escuelas saludables, sobre los centros de cuidado infantil y áreas de recreo infantiles saludables; sobre sustancias tóxicas y pesticidas en productos y nuestros lugares de trabajo; y para desarrollar la resiliencia comunitaria y fortalecer la gestión de crisis a medida que nos enfrentamos a tormentas más fuertes, incendios forestales más fuertes y enfermedades con el Zika, la Chikungunya, y otras que amenazan la salud y el bienestar de nuestras familias y así como de nuestras generaciones venideras.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hoy, más que nunca, valoramos nuestra creciente alianza y necesitamos su vigilancia y apoyo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Como saben, en nuestra esencia, la EPA es una agencia de salud pública. Protegemos a la gente de los impactos a la salud de la contaminación—eso es lo que hacemos. Hemos logrado grandes avances en los últimos 45 años de los cuales nos sentimos orgullosos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sin embargo, no podemos hacernos de la vista gorda, y no lo hemos hecho ante las realidades de la justicia ambiental.  Es por esa razón que fortalecemos las protecciones para nuestros trabajadores agrícolas con las nuevas normas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No vamos a ignorar a las colonias a lo largo de la frontera entre Estados Unidos y México donde estuve este pasado martes reunida con líderes comunitarios locales que simplemente quieren tener acceso a los sistemas de agua y aguas residuales que funcionan, tener acceso a carreteras donde las ambulancias puedan transitar, y tener alguien que les escuchará y proveerá el apoyo que necesitan. O en Puerto Rico, donde la gente entienda las mejores maneras para proteger a sus hijos del virus del Zika para que ellos, el pueblo de Puerto Rico, pueda tomar sus decisiones y saber que el Gobierno de Estados Unidos se encuentra allí para proveer al apoyo técnico y recursos de los cuales ellos dependen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Demasiadas comunidades de bajos ingresos y minoritarias, incluyendo comunidades latinas, están sobrecargadas por los efectos de la contaminación.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mientras el 8 por ciento de los niños en Estados Unidos padecen de asma, los niños hispanos tienen el doble de probabilidades de ser hospitalizados que los niños blancos. Y los niños puertorriqueños tienen tasas de incidencia de asma del 20 por ciento en comparación con todos los grupos étnicos. Eso es alarmante.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Es por eso que la EPA está apoyando las unidades especializadas en salud ambiental pediátrica—profesionales dedicados—a trabajar en lugares como El Paso y a través de California y Arizona, para entrenar a promotores que ayuden a los padres a eliminar los factores desencadenantes que conducen a los ataques de asma, mientras les ayudan a tener acceso a cuidado médico temprano, o informan a los agricultores acerca de sus derechos bajo los nuevos estándares para la protección del trabajador agrícola.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Y es por eso que en Puerto Rico tenemos una oficina permanente de la EPA para responder a los retos únicos a los cuales se enfrenta el pueblo de Puerto Rico para destacar sus necesidades ante aquellos en Washington quienes escucharán no tan solo con los oídos, sino con sus corazones, así como sus bolsillos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;En Estados Unidos, hay 15 millones de personas que viven a una distancia de media milla de un sitio Brownfield, y desproporcionadamente, la mayoría de estas personas pertenecen a grupos minoritarios, están más lingüísticamente aislados, son de bajos ingresos, y tienen menos probabilidades de haber finalizado sus estudios de secundaria que el resto de la población en Estados Unidos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Podemos y debemos hacer mucho mejor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cuando visito los vecindarios en un lugar contaminado, vea comunidades que han sido marginadas que no se han podido integrar en una economía creciente. Porque la contaminación lo impide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;La contaminación es una barrera para los empleos, los negocios y la calidad de vida que todas las comunidades merecen disfrutar. Fíjense en el caso de Flint, Michigan. El plomo en el agua no tan solo amenazó el futuro de sus hijos, es un síntoma de décadas de desinversiones. Tenemos que conseguirles el agua limpia que merecen y encaminarlos rumbo a la inversión económica.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;¿Por qué tantas comunidades se tienen que enfrentar a esos enormes escollos para alcanzar estas oportunidades cuando somos el patrón oro a nivel mundial cuando se trata de la protección ambiental? Debemos hacerlo mejor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cada comunidad debería tener iguales oportunidades para una economía vibrante. Y comienza con la protección de la salud pública y el medio ambiente. Cuando hacemos eso—la gente regresa, los negocios y empleos repuntan y las economías locales pueden empezar a prosperar nuevamente.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Por lo tanto, la EPA ha redoblado nuestro compromiso hacia nuestra misión de salud pública y la lucha por la justicia ambiental. Y continuaremos trabajando con ustedes, mano a mano, para tomar las acciones necesarias para convertir ese compromiso en una realidad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Es por eso que publicamos un informe sobre los riesgos del cambio climático en la salud. Porque sabemos que el cambio climático afecta las poblaciones vulnerables, incluyendo las comunidades de color y los grupos laborales vulnerables, como los obreros que trabajan al aire libre, quienes son los más afectados.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Es por eso que en la EPA seguimos hacia adelante para abordar la contaminación de carbono, las emisiones de metano y las emisiones tóxicas en los sectores de petróleo, gas y el sector de transportación, en las centrales eléctricas, en los rellenos sanitarios, y hasta en las refinerías, donde las comunidades colindantes tienen que saber los riesgos a los cuales se enfrentan y que la EPA le cubre las espaldas. Y lo hacemos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Estoy tan agradecida por su alianza, y la franqueza que me han demostrado a mí personalmente, y por su continuo compromiso hacia nuestro memorándum de entendimiento con LULAC. Y en los poco menos de 200 días que quedan de esta administración, planeo unirme al Presidente en la carrera para cruzar la meta final el próximo enero. Tenemos tanto más por hacer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Y la EPA está lista para seguir trabajando juntos, con todos ustedes mano a mano, para ayudar a las familias a entender y reducir los riesgos de salud ambiental en los niños. Podemos hacer tanto más juntos, pero no lo podemos lograr solos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Por ejemplo, recientemente seleccionamos a la Red Hispana para realizar un esfuerzo robusto de alcance público sobre nuestro Estándar de Protección del Trabajador Agrícola. Esa es la mejor manera que conocemos para alcanzar a los trabajadores agrícolas que necesitan saber que ellos ahora disfrutan de los mismos niveles de protección otorgados a los trabajadores en otros sectores. Y, de no ser ese el caso, tienen que saber a quién llamar: a la EPA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Y pueden estar seguros que trabajaremos con ahínco para aumentar la diversidad al interior de la EPA al traer a más expertos de salud a la agencia a todos los niveles; ampliando nuestras alianzas con las comunidades médicas y de salud pública; fortaleciendo las colaboraciones interagenciales con la CCA, el ATSDR, y otros socios federales en epidemiología y salud ambiental; y abriendo más oportunidades para estudiantes de orígenes diversos para entrar en la agencia mediante 19 acuerdos de colaboración con instituciones que sirven estudiantes minoritarios a través de la nación.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Necesitamos que los estudiantes de diversos orígenes sepan que hay un lugar para ellos en la EPA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No podemos conformarnos con hablar del tema, tenemos que demostrar nuestro compromiso con nuestras acciones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hemos recorrido un largo camino bajo el liderazgo del presidente Obama y con su ayuda continuaremos logrando avances en los asuntos que nos importan a todos nosotros.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Muchas gracias.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;###&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 19 Jul 2016 15:37:57 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>jmorin</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">155237 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Administrator Gina McCarthy, Remarks at the LULAC Summer Conference  in Washington, DC, As Prepared</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/speeches/administrator-gina-mccarthy-remarks-lulac-summer-conference-washington-dc-prepared</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/speeches/administradora-gina-mccarthy-discurso-ante-la-conferencia-de-verano-de-lulac-en-washington&quot;&gt;En español&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;July 14, 2016&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to thank and recognize Roger Rocha, LULAC National President, as well as Green Latinos and the many other organizations that are making sure the voices of the Latino community are heard – inside the beltway and across America.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA has continued to rely on your input and support as we have taken action on climate change; clean air, safe drinking water and healthy rivers and streams; on healthy homes, schools, daycare centers and playgrounds; on toxics and pesticides in products and at our places of work; and to build community resilience and strengthen crisis management as we face  stronger storms, more wildfires and diseases like Zika, Chikungunya, and others that threaten the health and wellbeing of our families and even our next generation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today more than ever, we value our growing partnership and need your vigilance and support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you know, at our core, EPA is a public health agency. We protect people from the health impacts of pollution – that’s what we do. And we’ve made major progress in the last 45 years that we should be proud of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we cannot, have not, and we will not turn a blind eye to the realities of environmental justice.  That’s why we strengthened protections for our farmworkers with new rules. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will not turn a blind eye to the &lt;em&gt;colonias&lt;/em&gt; along the U.S.-Mexico border where I spent this past Tuesday meeting with local community members who simply wanted access to water and wastewater systems that work, roads where ambulances can travel, and someone who will listen and provide them the support they need. Or to Puerto RicO, where people want to understand the best ways to protect their children from the Zika virus so that they – the people of Puerto Rico – can make their own decisions and know that the U.S. Government is there to provide the technical support and resources they need to rely on.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Too many low-income and minority communities, including Latino communities, are overburdened by the effects of pollution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While 8 percent of Hispanic children in America suffer from asthma, twice as many Hispanic children are likely to be hospitalized for asthma as white children. And Puerto Rican children have the highest asthma rates among all ethnicities at 20 percent. That is staggering. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why EPA is supporting pediatric environmental health specialty units – dedicated medical professionals – to work in places like El Paso and across California and Arizona, to train &lt;em&gt;promotores &lt;/em&gt;who can help parents eliminate the triggers that lead to asthma attacks, or help them access early care, or let farmworkers know about their rights under EPA’s new worker protection standards.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s why in Puerto Rico we have a permanent EPA office to respond to the unique challenges the people of Puerto Rico are facing and to highlight their needs to those in Washington who will listen not just with their ears but with their hearts as well as their wallets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the U.S., there are 15 million people who live within a half mile of a Brownfield site – and they are disproportionately more minority, more linguistically isolated, lower income, and less likely to have a high school education than the U.S. population as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can and must do better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I go out into neighborhoods that have a contaminated site, I see communities held back from becoming a functioning part of a growing economy. Because pollution matters. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pollution is a barrier to the jobs, businesses, and quality of life that every community deserves to enjoy. Just look at Flint, Michigan. The lead in that water didn’t just threaten their children’s future, it is a symptom of decades of disinvestment.  We need to get them the clean water they deserve and to get them on the road to economic investment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why should so many communities have to face such a steep climb to these opportunities when we are the gold standard in the world when it comes to environmental protection?  We have to do better. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every community should have a fair shot at economic vibrancy.  And that starts with protecting public health and the environment.  When you do that – people come back, business and jobs rebound and local economies can start to thrive again. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So EPA has redoubled our commitment to our public health mission and to the pursuit of environmental justice. And we will keep working with you – hand in hand – to take the actions necessary to turn commitment into reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why we issued a report on the health risks of climate change. Because we now know that climate change hits vulnerable populations – including communities of color and vulnerable occupational groups such as outdoor laborers – the very hardest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why EPA moved forward to tackle carbon pollution, methane and toxic emissions in the oil and gas and the transportation sectors, at power plants, landfills, and even refineries – where fence-line communities need to know the risks they may be facing and that EPA has their backs.   And we do. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am so grateful for our partnership, the openness you have shown to me personally, and for our continued commitment to our memorandum of understanding with LULAC.  I have a little less than 200 days left in this administration but I plan to join the President in the race to run across the tape next January.  We have so much more work to do. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And EPA is ready to keep working together, hand in hand with all of you, to help families understand and reduce environmental health risks to children. We can do so much together that we cannot achieve alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, we recently selected the Hispanic Communications Network to conduct robust outreach to Hispanic labor communities about our Worker Protection Standard – that’s the best way we know how to reach farmworkers who need to know that they now enjoy the same levels of protection afforded to workers in other sectors. And, if that is not the case, they need to know who to call: EPA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And rest assured we are working hard to increase diversity within EPA by bringing more health experts into the agency from top to bottom; expanding our partnerships with the medical and public health communities; strengthening interagency collaborations with CEC, ATSDR, and other federal partners on epidemiology and environmental health; and opening up more opportunities for diverse students to enter the agency through 19 collaborative agreements with minority serving institutions across the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need students from all walks of life to know there is a place for them at EPA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We cannot just talk that talk, we must walk the walk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have come a long way under President Obama’s leadership and with your help we will continue to make progress on issues that matter to all of us. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;###&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 14 Jul 2016 20:12:32 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>jmorin</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">154905 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>EPA Administrator McCarthy, Remarks at the VW Press Conference, Washington DC, As Prepared</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/speeches/epa-administrator-mccarthy-remarks-vw-press-conference-washington-dc-prepared</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;06/28/2016&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you Deputy Attorney General Yates for your leadership and Assistant Attorney General John Cruden and the tremendous partnership between DOJ and EPA on this and so many joint efforts to protect public health and the environment.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;I also want to thank FTC Chairwoman Ramirez, as well as recognize the great work of Mary Nichols, chair of the California Air Resources Board, and other states and tribal leaders who have been engaged in these discussions.  They have been crucial players in the delivery of the settlement we are announcing today.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;And it goes without saying how proud I am of the world-class team at EPA – Cynthia Giles, Janet Mccabe, Phil Brooks, Chris Grundler, Byron Bunker, Lee Cook, and Evan Belser, among many others, who spent countless hours bringing the varied interests together to get the job done and done extraordinarily well.  &lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;I say this on a daily basis but it’s worth repeating - every action EPA takes is about protecting public health and the environment. That’s our mission and it includes limiting the pollution vehicles emit into the air we breathe.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;We know that EPA’s vehicle emissions standards work. They take millions of tons of pollution out of our air we breathe.  And they protect people all across the US and beyond from health effects like aggravated asthma, respiratory problems, and even premature death. &lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;A critical part of EPA’s job is to secure and defend these clean air protections using the powers that congress gave us to get the job done.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;By using our Clean Air Act authorities, EPA Has achieved what has to be called a groundbreaking settlement, a settlement to repair the damage VW caused when they sent half a million cars onto our roads emitting amounts of harmful pollution far in excess of reasonably achievable, cost-effective federal standards. &lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Today, using the power of the Clean Air Act, we are getting VW’s polluting vehicles off the road, and reducing harmful pollution in our air – pollution that should never have been emitted in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;The scope of our agreement is unprecedented.  It not only addresses the damage done, it provides funding for states and tribes to make their air even cleaner, and it secures major investments that will support the transformation towards cleaner vehicles that is taking place across the auto industry.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;I want this agreement to remind every American that EPA is on the job and has your back.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;When companies break the rules designed to protect your health…&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;When cheaters stack the deck against businesses that follow the law…&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;When violators try to pull the wool over your eyes …&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;…EPA stands up for you and we reclaim the protections that are rightfully yours under the law.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Today we’re addressing VW’s violations on all 2-liter diesel engines beginning with model year 2009. That includes nearly half a million cars emitting nitrogen oxide – or NOx – pollution up to 40 times the legal limit.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;We’re holding VW accountable for this illegal pollution, and for distorting the market for cleaner cars.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;There are 3 key elements in today’s agreement.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;First, VW will get its polluting cars off the road. Using the Clean Air Act, EPA Has secured every consumer the choice of having VW buy back their car or lease, or modifying their car at no cost – if and when a modification to reduce emissions is approved. To resource this major logistical endeavor, VW will spend up to $10 billion to get at least 85 percent of these polluting cars off the road, and to ensure that consumers are adequately compensated and motivated to take advantage of their choices. You’ll hear more about this from FTC Chairwoman Ramirez.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Second, VW will make up for the pollution it caused. They will put $2.7 billion into a trust fund for pollution-reduction (or mitigation) projects across all 50 states and in tribal communities. This is the largest monetary obligation for pollution reduction in Clean Air Act enforcement history.  And it’s real money. States and tribes will be able to apply for funding to implement clean air projects that make sense for them. And they’ll be able to cut NOx pollution in ways that current budgets could never have realized.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Third, VW will invest in America’s clean transportation future. VW will invest $2 billion in innovation and infrastructure for zero-emission vehicles in the United States. This includes the construction of charging stations, public education projects, and improving access to zero-emission vehicles. It’s $2 billion devoted entirely to supporting the advancement of a thriving auto industry that’s cleaner, greener, and full of consumer choice.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;It’s an historic settlement but there’s still more to come. Today’s settlement does not address VW’s violations for 3-liter vehicles, and we have not yet addressed the criminal charges or civil penalties that are being pursued separately.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;But EPA’s number one priority is done – we have found a path forward to reduce the pollution in our air that threatens our public health.  And using the power of the Clean Air Act, we are capturing investments in infrastructure and innovation that will drive public health improvements over the long term.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;These investments will help catalyze the deployment of cleaner vehicles of all kinds – today and in the future.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;So this agreement is a powerful example of what a strong EPA can do, and is doing, for the American people.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;And it should send a very clear message that when you break the laws designed to protect public health in this country, there are serious consequences.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;EPA will continue to do what is necessary to stand up for public health, our common environment, and the air we all breathe.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Thank you. Now I’ll turn it over to FTC Chairwoman Ramirez.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;###&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jun 2016 13:43:33 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>jmorin</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">153393 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title> Administrator Gina McCarthy, Remarks by EPA at the Energy Efficiency Forum 2016 in Washington, DC, As Prepared</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/speeches/administrator-gina-mccarthy-remarks-epa-energy-efficiency-forum-2016-washington-dc-prepared</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;June 23, 2016&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thank Johnson Controls for hosting this event, and for having me. It’s great to be here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love energy efficiency! I run around talking about it all the time, but you’re the ones actually making it happen in the real world. And you’re doing it in such creative, innovative ways. So I want lead off by saying thank you to everyone here for the work you’re doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Energy efficiency is a proven strategy to protect the environment, grow the economy, and create jobs – all at once. I know I’m preaching to the choir, but it just doesn’t get any better than that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, an additional 1.9 million Americans are employed, in whole or in part, in the energy efficiency sector. And the Department of Energy projects more than a quarter-million new hires in 2016 alone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, the market for energy efficiency in buildings is growing fast – drawing $63.6 billion in revenue just in 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since EPA’s Energy Star program launched in 1992, we’ve been able to leverage energy efficiency to prevent 2.7 billion metric tons of greenhouse gas emissions and save families and businesses $430 billion on their utility bills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Energy Star now has 16,000 retail, utility, public sector, and business leaders on our partners’ roster. And, by the way, more than half of the Fortune 100 companies are on that list.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The point is, energy efficiency is a smart bet, every-time. Families know it, businesses know it, and states know it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nationwide, state energy efficiency programs reduced CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; emissions by 75 million metric tons in 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, every state has some form of demand-side energy efficiency policy, and many are already achieving significant reductions in electricity demand. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;23 states have mandatory energy efficiency requirements, and a handful of others have voluntary targets or allow energy efficiency to be used in meeting their mandatory clean energy goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Massachusetts and Vermont are achieving energy savings of 1.5% or more every year. And those are cumulative savings. Over a five- or ten-year time-horizon – those resources really add up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we’re seeing that innovative local projects can make a big difference, especially in low-income communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As of last year, Energy Outreach Colorado saved low-income utility customers enough natural gas and electricity to avoid 28,000 metric tons of greenhouse gas emissions – that’s equal to the annual energy-related emissions of 2,500 American homes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;California’s Chumash Community Energy Program is providing training and apprenticeships to tribal leaders and members, so they can seize the amazing job opportunities that are opening up in the energy efficiency and renewables. Because they know that’s where the jobs of the future are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;States aren’t taking these steps because they have to, they’re doing it because it’s smart. And EPA agrees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why energy efficiency is a crucial part of our Clean Power Plan to cut carbon pollution from the U.S. power sector – our nation’s biggest contributor to climate change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last week, we proposed additional details about the optional Clean Energy Inventive Program – or C.E.I.P. – which was included in the final Clean Power Plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The C.E.I.P. is designed to help states, tribes, and power plants meet their goals under the Clean Power Plan by encouraging early investment in zero-emitting renewable energy generation, and removing barriers to investment in solar and energy efficiency measures in low-income communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s all about empowering states and facilities to use clean energy and energy efficiency to meet their emission reduction targets – where and how it makes sense for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, even though the Supreme Court has stayed the Clean Power Plan for now, it did not tell EPA to stop all work related to planning for a low carbon future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many states have indicated they will be moving forward voluntarily to cut carbon pollution from power plants. And they’ve asked EPA to continue providing resources and tools to support those efforts – the C.E.I.P. is one of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we’re continuing to provide that assistance to anyone who wants to be prepared to make timely decisions when the stay is ultimately lifted and the Clean Power Plan is upheld – which I am confident it will be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA is focused more than ever on continuing to lift America’s energy efficiency game. It’s a central component of our fight against climate change, and our transition to a low carbon future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And for anyone who’s been living under a rock, I want to make clear that that transition is already underway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Global investments in renewable energy hit a world record in 2015 at $286 billion… that’s more than double what was invested in fossil fuels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And every year, we’re seeing utilities and states spend more than $7 billion to make energy efficiency more accessible to American consumers and businesses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The train has left the station. But we’re going to need all hands on deck – including energy efficiency leaders like you – to make sure that our transition continues to move ahead at full speed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So now, we keep going.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We step up our investments in innovation and finding new ways to achieve greater efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We go out into our communities and make sure families, businesses, and decision makers know that energy efficiency is a viable option to help protect the planet and lower utility bills.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We work with low-income communities to squeeze every possible benefit out of local energy efficiency programs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we continue providing the information and tools that states, tribes, and utilities need to leverage efficiencies, where it makes sense, to meet their greenhouse gas reduction goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s really so much more we can do together. Keep up the amazing work. Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;###&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jun 2016 12:46:25 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cedstrom</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">153219 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Administrator Gina McCarthy, Remarks at the 2016 Vermont Law School Commencement, As Delivered</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/speeches/administrator-gina-mccarthy-remarks-2016-vermont-law-school-commencement-delivered</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;05/21/2016&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you, students, you rock. Hello, Vermont Law School lawyers. I have to start by saying two things. One is congratulations to all the masters, you don&#039;t intimidate me at all. I have one of those. [laughter]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to also admit right up front, I&#039;m not a lawyer and really never liked lawyers until very recently. Actually, sometimes I do. But if I were to describe my anxiety dream, it would be filled with lawyers. [laughter] And I am in Washington, living that dream every day. [applause]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it&#039;s really fun, and really it is an incredible honor to be here, and hopefully I can share of few words of wisdom. But the most important one is to ask you if you&#039;re working in government or outside to keep the mission that drove you to this school. Embrace it, never let it go, because it is a mission that this world needs more people, especially young people to embrace—because the future is yours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I screwed it up, you have to fix it. That&#039;s the way it is. Embrace the challenge. For you today it&#039;s the culmination of years of study. You have learned to trudge through torts, to plow under property law, to conquer corporate law, and to trounce your taxes. You learn firsthand what it means to be arbitrary and capricious as you watched Professor Firestone throw chalk at the wall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before you start cramming for the bar or heading to the bar, do me a little bit of a favor and just take a few seconds to feel proud of yourself. Really, you are graduating (applause) you are not just graduating from any school, you are graduating from Vermont Law School, and Vermont Law School&#039;s Energy Law Program has been ranked number one 17 of the last 24 years. It has never ranked lower than 2 . You are amazing. [applause]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I know when I want to pick a lawyer that will make me most anxious, I go to you guys. Because you are going to do one of two things. You are either going to do exactly what I say, or you are going to tell me how I can get done what I want to do. Either one is fine with me, just don&#039;t be the boring type of lawyer that tells me everything I can&#039;t do, because then I turn into Charlie Brown and it is wha-wah-wah. So we are going to have great fun together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know all of you are especially proud, your family, friends, they have supported you as you turned into whiny faces, wondering if you would get through your first year being absolutely miserable. Do yourselves a favor and clap for everyone who’s been with you along the way. The good news is, they didn&#039;t disown you or disavow you, so it is time at this point to welcome you back to the human race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have to leave this lovely little community and go face the big bad world again, but it is really the start of the next chapter in your life. What I really want you to do most is embrace that. Just embrace it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The uncertainty is great. Stop dwelling on it, don&#039;t get anxious. I would like you to live in that uncertainty for the rest of your life because it constantly challenges you to do something different and better, to learn, to keep conquering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&#039;s what you really need to do if you want to have a continuously rich life, is to live on that edge. I live on it every single day, and I fall off on numerous occasions, but really, for the past three years you&#039;ve been learning the rules of the road. You’ve been learning the legal boundaries that you need to know, but right now it&#039;s all about getting into the real world and starting to test those boundaries, and starting to test yourselves, to see where life leads you. It&#039;s time to get creative, is time to think about what you can do to make sure that business as usual doesn&#039;t remain business as usual. Your job is to always challenge that. [applause]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will tell you that life gets most interesting when you decide not to settle for business as usual. That&#039;s where you definitely won&#039;t be boring. This school has given you all you need to actually get in the game now. It has opened doors for you. Unless you think business as usual is just fine, then start embracing the opportunities that are open to you, that this school has provided to you, and you must go out and make the world more just.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You must go out and make our children healthier. You have to give us more sustainable options moving forward and you have to work hard to make the world a safer place. You came here to do that, you have to exit the same way. You want to exit the world the same way. Continue to drive that forward. And I&#039;m so confident that you can do this. We have seen it in graduating classes from this college time and again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I cannot tell you how many lawyers at EPA came from this school. Actually, I lied. I can. Sixty-nine are now currently working at EPA. [applause] And you are indistinguishable from the other mission-driven 15,000 human beings that work at EPA. So really think big. Now is the time to get excited about what life has to offer, not to get anxious about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just look at my boss, President Obama. He was a constitutional law professor. How boring is that? [laughter] But he has not been boring. He&#039;s done pretty damn well for himself and for us. [applause]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today for the first time in this country, more than 9 in 10 Americans have health insurance. Today anyone in America can marry whomever they want to marry. [applause] Students in the U.S. are now graduating high school at a higher rate than ever. Our economy is in the midst of the longest streak of private sector job growth on record with 14.4 million jobs added over 73 straight months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like this one: we are less reliant on foreign oil than we have been in nearly three decades, and guess what? Last December in Paris, nations all across the world joined together and made a commitment to act on climate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, what made all of this incredible progress possible? A couple of things. One is, I’ve got a president who is as mission driven his you are. He is unwilling to settle for business as usual. He has told me, Gina, put on your sneakers because we are running across the finish line. There is no lame duckery in this Administration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the face of a Congress – how to put this nicely?—that is &lt;em&gt;reluctant&lt;/em&gt; to act, our president has embraced the authorities that are already embedded in our laws and has used them to advance policies that reflect all of our core values. What has made this country so great, what has given us the kind of life that we have enjoyed, and he has taken action to protect our kids, to protect our families, and to protect our planet. This has been an enormous gift to me to be part of this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you think about it, just focus on what we&#039;ve been able to do on climate change. Just look at the historic actions that I have been lucky enough to be a part of, whether working at the state, local, or the federal level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have been driving issues on climate for ages. Finally, the federal government of the United States of America is leading this charge, not just domestically, but internationally. We have EPA’s 2009 end finding that never would have happened had it not been for &lt;em&gt;Massachusetts v. EPA&lt;/em&gt;. I&#039;m so glad that my Commonwealth of Massachusetts kicked the butt out of EPA on that one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You go where the mission drives you. It opened the doors to such incredibly strong climate action in this country, and that door will never be shut again. Greenhouse gas standards for light duty vehicles, heavy-duty vehicles, methane in the oil and gas sector, landfills, and HFCs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We finalized our Clean Power Plan, the nation&#039;s first-ever limits on carbon pollution from power plants. If you haven&#039;t read the briefs we submitted on that Clean Power Plan, read it, it will restore your faith in government. It is strong; it is powerful. We will win all the way up through the Supreme Court. [applause] Our Clean Power Plan changed the dynamic in Paris, and make no mistake about it, we are hanging on to that and we are going to continue to run forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this president is not one of those boring lawyers. He is a bit challenging. And I can say that working on climate change has never been boring. The CPP has generated two first-of-a-kind legal decisions, interesting ones, one from the Supreme Court and a more recent one from the DC Circuit Court. I will admit that I would rather be bored every once in a while, but we will deal with these issues moving forward, and I&#039;m excited about the work that we have to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we all can&#039;t wait for anything to get the work done that we need to do to keep our kids future secure, and to continue to make progress on public health, because after all, EPA is a public health agency. That is what we do for a living. And we have real work to do and real challenges to face, and we are not going to wait for instructions from Congress. They may never come. We are not relying solely on voluntary measures. They ain&#039;t getting the job done. So we’re using the full suite of tools and authorities available to us under the Clean Water Act, the Safe Drinking Water Act, the Clean Air Act, and the other environmental statutes that have led to such tremendous improvements in quality of life for all of us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vermont Law School has given all of you, whether you are a master&#039;s in understanding the policies that are necessary to move us forward, or understanding the toolbox and and skill sets that the law provides, and this college has given you. You are in an interesting position to be really part of this change moving forward. We can set this country on a sustainable course for the future. It’s your time right now. You have to go with this. I agree, anxiety is bad, but embrace this anxiety. Maybe you don&#039;t know how to get it done, but keep moving. Don&#039;t go back. Circles are not fun, either. Try to go forward. [laughter]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can figure it out. Sniff it out. You will know where you are supposed to go. But you are the leaders. You are trained to harness the power of the law to move beyond the status quo. While in a democracy like yours, and I&#039;ve been working in this democracy for 35 years now, it does move slowly, but it does move. And change can happen. It is built layer by layer, action by action. Hardware, science, the law. All of that is the foundation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And don&#039;t forget we are government of the people, for the people, and by the people. You&#039;ve got to make people eventually demand the sustainable change that you think is necessary. So while you may be smarty-pants about where you want to go, smarty-pants about how to get there, you need to bring at least 1000 people with you when you want to accomplish it, because that&#039;s what the United States democracy demands. That&#039;s the system we live in. That is the system we love. That is your challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So tackle tough issues like climate. You can make a difference. You can make it work. There is no challenge more complicated than the challenge of climate change. It&#039;s about the fundamental way that we chose to grow in this country. Talk about the challenge of explaining why one degree matters. People think great, summer will come little earlier. No, not great. But I think people now get it. Most people have gotten it. We have managed to explain it and also manage to understand that they are feeling it already. Climate change impacts all of us. It&#039;s not just about glaciers and polar bears. It is way more personal. It&#039;s about the health of our kids, our health, our economy, our national security. It&#039;s really about our moral responsibility to protect our kids’ future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So even in DC, you can make progress on things like climate change. We even have the Pope on our side. [applause] And he rides around in this little Fiat, or Focus, depending on what country he is driving around in, I think. But we also have incredible solutions today. It is a very interesting point in time for you to be graduating. Not only have we managed to figure out how to double the distance cars can go on a gallon of gasoline; we are now producing a lot of vehicles that don&#039;t need it at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had the opportunity to be at the Tesla manufacturing facility. I met with Elon Musk. I did not understand a word he said. He actually did not understand a word I said, either. [laughter] These things take time to build relationships. Tesla has already received 700,000 orders for their new $35,000 vehicle that is coming out next year. That will triple the number of electric vehicles on the road in the United States. They come with a $1000 check. We have renewable energy systems that are knock-your-socks-off competitive against fossil fuels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have utilities that are buying the energy people are generating on the rooftops. We have a level of innovation that is unprecedented and our markets are shifting with those innovations as they come out in the market and make their way to human beings who care about these issues. In 2015, global investment in renewable energy hit a world record at $286 billion. That&#039;s more than twice the investment that the world spent on fossil fuel. So if you think it&#039;s just the U.S., you are wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The solar industry added jobs nearly 12 times faster than the economy as a whole last year. This is where the jobs of the future are. With a long-term extension of the renewable tax credit, we can continue to see this moving forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are really at a time when you can go out there and make your own way in a world that is changing, and a world where that change is heading in the right direction, and you can make that change sustainable and move that forward, if you continue to have the mission that brought you to this wonderful school. You are the generation that is the most technologically savvy, globally aware, and socially conscious generation in history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You are emerging at a time when there is incredible innovation and progress. Add onto that the arsenal of skills you’ve have learned right here at Vermont Law School and you are already a force to be reckoned with. So don&#039;t slither into a job interview, go there with your head held high and get the job you want to get. [applause]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I end, I want to ask you a couple of things and maybe give a little bit of advice. First I want to ask you to think about going into public service. I have been doing this for a long time. I will readily admit that you will never get rich, so if that is part of your mission, don’t bother. I can&#039;t see that changing over the long haul.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But if you really want a rich life, public service will provide that to you. It&#039;s just amazing. [applause] Think about the choices you have. EPA employs 69 Vermont Law School graduates alone out of about 1000 attorneys that run around doing remarkably crazy but successful things. The phrase “dream team” is how we describe our Office of General Counsel. They&#039;ve been named best in-house environmental team by the Legal 500 for the last two years in a row. [applause]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it is because they get an awful lot of practice, and I will account for much of that. Sometimes it feels like David and Goliath. I was looking at 111d filings, that’s the Clean Power Plan litigation. The list of attorneys representing the plaintiffs went to 22 pages. That is probably as many people as we actually have in EPA. When it is important, -- I guarantee there will be more lawsuits to follow. We are going to keep doing important work, and in the United States, when you do important work, people will sue you. That&#039;s the way it works. [applause]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My last two tiny pieces of advice, I want to give you just two small pieces. First of all, as you are thinking about your future and planning what you want to do next, make sure that as you are looking at opportunities that you are not writing off any that are not in your program plan. I know too many people who think, “I&#039;m going here, and the next thing I&#039;m going to do is there and the next thing is there.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are blinded to incredibly interesting opportunities that they never thought they would want to take. If a door opens to you, walk through it. It may prove to be the most interesting thing you have ever done and shape your future forever. So don&#039;t set a plan that blinds you to the really cool things that are out there. I will absolutely guarantee you I never planned to be EPA Administrator, and I plan to run like hell in January and go to the next interesting thing that comes along. Because you never know your journey in life. So don&#039;t shut doors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last thing is, be comfortable being uncomfortable. I know that sounds stupid. Maybe it is, and I should probably quit here, but this is really sort of, I think about what the dean was talking about, anxiety is really actually great. It keeps you on your toes. If you go out and take a job that you know you can do, just because you know you can do it, then you are selling yourself short. I want you to take the job that you are not sure you can do, because in that job, it&#039;s going to push you. It will force you to learn and grow. It will force you to confront new ideas and challenges. That&#039;s what you want to do every single time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So if you don&#039;t have anxiety in the evening, create anxiety in the daytime. Give yourself credit. You have made it through one of the most prestigious law schools in the world. You have come here because you have a mission where you are going to be a vital cog in our ability to keep our planet safe and to keep my kids’ future and my grandchildren&#039;s future stable and happy with an opportunity to be healthy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You came here to make this society more just. You will succeed as long as you challenge yourself, stick with that mission, and remember where you came from and you never lose it. I&#039;m so grateful that you came here, I&#039;m so thankful that you got through it, and I am so excited to be able to hand over the world to this generation of leaders. Thank you very much. [applause]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;###&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jun 2016 19:39:21 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>jmorin</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">151167 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Administrator Gina McCarthy, Remarks at GE Oil and Gas Annual Meeting, As Prepared</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/speeches/administrator-gina-mccarthy-remarks-ge-oil-and-gas-annual-meeting-prepared</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;02/02/2015&lt;br /&gt;
	Hi, everybody. It’s great to be here. Let me thank Lorenzo and everyone at GE for the opportunity.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	The energy world and the environmental world are in a period of unprecedented transition. I am not talking about recent short term oil prices, which I understand must be on your minds for many reasons.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	The transition I am talking about is more wholesale—the way in which the oil and gas industry is front and center in using innovative methods to open up vast, previously inaccessible and untapped reserves; the way in which science and technology are allowing us to more readily understand the industry’s environmental impact; and the economic opportunity that the industry has if it continues the trend of using technology to ensure your place in what I believe is an essential and clear path forward towards a cleaner, lower carbon future.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	You and I know that our energy and environmental challenges are two sides of the same coin—as are economic prosperity and public health protection. The time has come for us to stop flipping this coin to see which side wins in the short term, and instead recognize the need to focus on building a solid path for sustainable economic growth that depends on clean, reliable, and affordable energy for all. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That path in the US and across the world is exactly what President Obama is charting with the Climate Action Plan that he announced in July 2013. And it’s exactly what EPA and our sister agencies will deliver. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because climate change is not just an environmental challenge; it’s a threat to public health, to our domestic and global economy, and to our national and international security. The US, through our strong and decisive domestic action, has already and will continue to mold the international debate on climate change—from one that focuses on mitigation costs to one that embraces new investment opportunities. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The success of these efforts will depend on how quickly you and the broader energy market deliver cleaner energy supplies using safe and responsible technologies and practices that all of us can take to the bank.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For decades, the US Environmental Protection Agency has set pollution standards for utilities, refineries, fuels, engines, vehicles, and more. Those standards have been built into the marketplace—captured in the cost of electricity, and in the way energy is dispatched and priced. They drive new tools and technologies that are now commonplace—everything from advanced monitoring systems to end-of-pipe pollution controls. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have learned many times over that we don’t set standards to replace or limit a vibrant marketplace—we set standards to fortify it. We provide certainty not just to those who want to know that their kids have clean air to breathe and clean water to drink, but to the broader business community who need risks to be minimized and investment to be maximized. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;President Obama recognizes that climate change is supercharging risks to our health and our economies—and at the same time it is fueling a tremendous transformation in the way we make and use energy. My message today is that we must embrace that transformation. We must seize the opportunity that lies ahead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we do, it will not only be the responsible thing to do, it will be the profitable thing to do. If done right, we can cut the carbon pollution that is fueling climate change; we can prepare for impacts that we can’t avoid; and we will position the business community, its entrepreneurs and its innovators, to lead the world in our global climate fight, while expanding the economy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;President Obama is confident, as am I, that innovation is the key to a stable climate and sustainable economic growth. The good news is that the transition to a low-carbon future is already being embraced by businesses in every sector, in every part of the world. The reasons are simple: no one likes risk, and today, the risk of standing still far outweighs the uncertainty of taking steps to transform to a clean, low carbon future. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA has taken a big step in that direction when last year we announced the Clean Power Plan, the key piece in the President’s effort to cut carbon pollution while offering certainty to markets and investors about what the future holds. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As proposed, the Clean Power Plan seeks to cut carbon pollution from existing power plants, our nation’s largest source, in a smart and pragmatic way. It was designed explicitly to give states the flexibility necessary to create individual, tailored plans to their situation. This includes expanded use of clean fuels like natural gas, expanded use of energy efficiency from plant to plug, and more use of renewable energies. Our hope is that this clarity, this certainty, will allow industry and business to invest accordingly, allowing for economic growth and continued job creation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simply put—more of that kind of certainty means less risk to business operations because it means less risk to public health. And those goals work in tandem—an investment that risks public health is a risky investment to make. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More and more companies are making their support for this effort clear. Just last week, trade groups representing more than more than 200,000 businesses and more than 325,000 individual business leaders, entrepreneurs, and investors wrote an open letter explaining both their strong support for EPA’s Clean Power Plan, and for action in general on climate change. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While it’s obvious that traditional energy companies, along with businesses in the clean tech sector, stand to benefit, other blue chip brands—such as Nike, Nestle, Disney, Unilever, Starbucks, and Sprint—have said, and I quote, “Tackling climate change is one of America’s greatest economic opportunities of the 21st century.” &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is that word—opportunity. And that’s exactly how we all must see this challenge ahead. As an economic growth opportunity. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But with opportunity comes challenges. As we seize new energy frontiers in a carbon-constrained world, an increasing number of energy markets will have the freedom to work the way they should—but only when we can demonstrate that development is safe and responsible. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we can’t be certain of safe and responsible operations, then the freedom and certainty so essential to investment will be lost. The State of New York’s recent ban on fracking makes the point. New York’s decision-makers shut it all down, because they either lacked the confidence to ensure responsible development through regulation, or they lacked the confidence that industry was acting reliably to confront health risks. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Confidence in safe and responsible energy development is not a given. To create that confidence, it’s important to show, either through transparent cooperative action, or through commonsense regulation—that any energy development means safe and responsible development. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have the technology to do it—what is lacking is the confidence that it’s being done—and without that confidence, investment and markets suffer. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you know, an important piece of our national Climate Action Plan is mitigating methane emissions contributing to climate change. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So a few weeks ago, the Obama administration announced a strategy to cut methane emissions from the oil and gas sector—by up to 45 percent from 2012 levels by 2025. That means saving up to 180 billion cubic feet of wasted natural gas in 2025 — enough to heat more than 2 million homes for a year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our efforts build on our 2012 standards to reduce volatile organic compounds from the oil and natural gas industry. These standards will reduce up to 290 thousand tons of VOCs—and as a bonus, they’ll cut methane emissions equal to 33 million tons of carbon pollution per year. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of the strategy, this summer, EPA will propose commonsense standards to cut methane emissions from new and modified oil and gas wells. We’re starting with new sources, because that’s where the growth is happening, and that’s where we can get the most bang for our buck right away. New oil and gas sources being developed have the ability to take advantage of innovative technology already available to the industry. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it’s also about sending signals to existing infrastructure beyond the wellhead. There are opportunities to reduce emissions along the entire delivery and extraction system—compressors, pneumatics, and pipelines—and for new remote monitoring technology that can provide a greater degree of certainty. We need to look at the system in a holistic way that maintains growth and vibrancy for the industry. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it comes to incentives, the oil and gas industry has an edge—because leaking methane isn’t a wasted byproduct. It’s product that’s wasted. Lost methane is lost profits. You all understand that, and it’s why you’re leaders in the industry. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recognizing that reducing costs and reducing carbon pollution go hand in hand, GE and Statoil are launching a research and development partnership called the Last Mile to work on ways to cut greenhouse gas emissions. The two companies are seeking technologies that can reduce emissions and cut costs, for example, by reducing the wasteful flaring of associated gas released during oil production. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are not alone. Other companies, including Pemex, BG Group and Southwestern Energy—all members of the Climate and Clean Air Coalition’s Global Methane Initiative—have demonstrated leadership roles in the industry, taking common sense steps to reduce emissions in smart ways. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the US, the recent trend in resource development has been an economic boon—adding jobs, lowering energy prices, strengthening national security, and enabling cheaper manufacturing. For the first time in decades, we produce more oil than we consume. And we are currently the largest natural gas producer in the world. The natural gas industry alone created more than 150,000 US jobs between 2007 and 2012, while the manufacturing sector added 800,000 jobs since 2009.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The gas boom has changed electricity markets so dramatically that coal is non-competitive in some areas. Does that mean no coal? Not at all. But it does mean that an “all of the above” energy strategy is truly “all of the above.” It means we have a market shift that allows us to cost effectively address toxic air pollution and now carbon pollution in ways that align with market trends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When industry uses best practices to prevent a problem, we are safer, our energy is cleaner, and our global economy is stronger. You don’t have to take my word for it: at EPA, we’re getting strong signals from top US oil and gas industry leaders who want to work with us, to take their own concrete, cooperative action to reduce emissions. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are coming together, for example, to launch initiatives like One Future. And even before last month’s announcement of the administration’s methane blueprint, some companies were exploring with us cooperative strategies to replace high-emitting equipment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their reason is simple: it makes business sense to spend money building market certainty by building confidence with the public—rather than spending it to wage regulatory battles that undermine, rather than reinforce, confidence in safe and responsible development. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That interest rings true up and down the value chain—there’s demand for responsible production from distribution companies, too—so they’ve launched a downstream initiative to look at emissions reduction opportunities at different points in the value chain. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA has programs that facilitate that interest across a wide range of practices and actions, including our Natural Gas STAR program, a voluntary program which certifies improvements in operating efficiency and emissions reductions. Since 1993, the program has helped reduce over 1 trillion cubic feet of methane emissions; that’s equivalent to the space in 10 million hot air balloons. We plan to expand the program with Gas STAR Gold. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While we regulate to reduce pollution and protect public health and the environment, we have to recognize that public health needs double as energy needs, and regulations don’t just drive down pollution. They drive markets, and they shift investments. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we do it well—when we work together—smart regulation levels the playing field, signals certainty, creates markets, and drives new technology, new tools, and new products and services. It sets the parameters for progress. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simply put, in the US free market economy, our job is not to produce regulations; our job is to reduce pollution. Regulation is just one of many tools, not an end in itself. Smart regulation internalizes costs of pollution into the cost of doing business—with standards rooted in science and guided by the law. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Success is judged by how well we send clear market signals for you to clearly see and follow—that’s how we ignite progress. EPA’s long history of success in meeting our mission proves that a healthy economy and a healthy environment go hand in hand. We don’t act despite the economy; we act because of it. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over 40-plus years, EPA has cut US air pollution by 70 percent, while our GDP has tripled in size. From acid rain to lead in our gasoline, EPA has been a standard bearer in the dance between reducing pollution, protecting public health, and growing industries and economies. We’re proud of our work. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Smart climate and environmental policy has to hit the sweet spot: aligning cooperative action with regulation. We set up the ground rules, and get out of the way and let the market do the rest. Success means building a resilient marketplace where businesses thrive and investments are responsive to the risks of environmental hazards and a changing climate. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s not wait to act. We have the tools and the know-how today to seize a low-carbon energy future; a future that’s safer, more prosperous—and more profitable—for businesses and people all over the world. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 28 Apr 2016 20:25:12 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>jmorin</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">148055 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Administrator Gina McCarthy, Remarks at the Council on Foreign Relations, As Prepared</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/speeches/administrator-gina-mccarthy-remarks-council-foreign-relations-prepared</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;03/11/2015&lt;br /&gt;
	Thanks, Sherri. It’s great to be here. Let me start by lowering expectations; I’m at the Council on Foreign Relations, but I’m not a foreign policy expert. In fact, I’ve devoted my whole career to domestic policy. But the thing is, where the environment is concerned, it’s hard to know where domestic policy ends and foreign policy begins.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	At EPA, the challenges we wrestle with are blind to borders. Pollution and environmental degradation, no matter where you find it, strain people’s relationship with the core elements that sustain life: clean air, clean water, and safe, healthy, productive land. And these elements are the foundation on which all other relationships are built, between individuals, societies, and nations. So I guess I can offer some cogent thoughts this morning.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	Let’s start by imagining an environmental crisis so large, it can only be captured by a satellite picture; a crisis so compelling, world leaders heed the advice of world-renowned scientists—and sign a global treaty to protect all people, in all nations. No, I’m not talking about climate change—I’m talking about the decades-old battle to heal the ozone layer. I’m talking about the Montreal Protocol—what Kofi Annan called the “most successful international agreement of any kind.” Decades ago, chemicals in everyday products were destroying the ozone layer, the earth&#039;s shield against the sun’s cancer-causing radiation.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	It was a challenge that plainly showed that our environment does not exist separately from our actions and ambitions—that humanity’s common denominator, demands a common concern for wellbeing, and a common understanding of shared responsibility. That is why I firmly believe that any conversation about relationships between nations, must include our relationship with the environment. And in that conversation—the most complex, urgent, and sweeping challenge we face, is global climate change.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	The message I want to deliver this morning is two-fold: first—climate change fuels instability around the world, by amplifying risks to global health, security, and growth. We have to fight climate change by building it into those existing efforts. That’s what we mean by sustainable development. Approaching climate change in isolation narrows our ability to turn this global challenge into a global opportunity. Second—history proves that U.S. Leadership can unleash global progress. Attitudes in America are changing. People accept the science, and demand action. And EPA plays a vital role in U.S. Climate leadership and in delivering the president’s Climate Action Plan.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	First—let’s talk about instability. On the global stage, the story of resource constraints and human conflict may have different characters, but the plot doesn’t change: strained resources fuel instability. That’s been true for as long as people have walked the earth. And we’ve seen that age-old drama play out today—take water scarcity in Darfur, for example.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	From farming and tourism, to infrastructure and global health—climate risk increases resource risk, and that means increased instability. Don’t take my word for it. The Pentagon calls climate change a “threat multiplier.” President Obama’s National Security Strategy recognizes climate change as a gateway to more “natural disasters, refugee flows, and conflicts.”&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	About a year ago I went to Vietnam, and government officials expressed serious concern about the Mekong River Delta, where scientists say that by 2050, rising seas in the region could force 7 million people from their homes. To put that in perspective—the Syrian conflict has forced 3 million refugees to neighboring countries. Coincidentally, a report published by the National Academy of Sciences links the instability behind the Syrian conflict to a drought worsened by climate change. You get the picture.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	So it’s no surprise that, according to the American security project, 70 percent of the world’s countries explicitly call climate change a national security concern.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	As temperatures and tensions rise, so do insurance premiums, food prices, and the cost of doing business. What doesn’t rise, are tourist visits, investment dollars, job growth, and the opportunity to fight poverty. In short, another global risk comes to the fore—economic instability. Climate change injects volatility into the global marketplace. Volatility leads to instability, especially in economies that depend on agricultural commodities. Take coffee, for example, a temperature sensitive crop. Climate change puts the world’s coffee growing regions at risk. Blue chip, global companies like Nike and Coke see climate impacts disrupt supplies of water, cotton, and sugar. Scarcer inputs mean higher costs passed on to consumers.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	The S&amp;amp;P has already warned that climate risk strains global credit. Put another way: growth depends on a safe environment, and a stable climate. We can no longer accept the false premise that pollution is somehow a growing pain of growth. If that is your premise, then the foundation of that growth was not built to last. It was wrongly designed—treating the environment as window dressing when it is an essential part of the brick and mortar of our lives and our economies. The good news is, there are existing technologies and low-cost strategies that can leapfrog old ways of industrialization.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	That’s the second point I want to make: climate action isn’t just a moral responsibility we must accept—it’s an economic opportunity we can seize, to sharpen our competitive edge, strengthen international ties, and catalyze global action. Just take a look at what I call EPA’s ‘air-monitor-diplomacy.’ A few years ago, we put an air monitor on the roof of the U.S. Embassy in Beijing, and posted air quality data online. We did it so American diplomats could know when air pollution reached dangerous levels—and could protect themselves and their families. Well, it worked—and then some.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	It informed the Chinese public about air pollution risks. And it gave the Chinese government an opportunity to respond—by more effectively capturing data and cutting pollution in ways that align with climate and economic goals. Our embassy air monitor is a textbook example of soft diplomacy. It shows when America extends the environmental olive branch, it can blossom into stronger international cooperation, like the historic joint climate announcement we made with China. And it also shows clearly that no nation can afford to ignore public health risks. That’s why I joined Secretary Kerry a few weeks ago to announce the expansion of our air monitoring program. What works in China can work in other countries, too.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	And from a development standpoint, climate action doesn’t mean we have to cast aside our responsibility to confront poverty—just the opposite: climate action protects those most vulnerable and can lead to more inclusive economies. I recently met with Vatican officials who are working with Pope Francis on a new encyclical on climate change. Pope Francis and many faith leaders across the world see climate as a moral obligation. They see an opportunity for clean energy jobs of the future—for the millions of poor and disenfranchised who’ve been left behind.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	On the development front, many nations—including the U.S.—are pledging money to the Green Climate Fund to promote low-emission, climate-resilient development. That’s an important undertaking; but we need to broaden our thinking even further because we can’t just rely on the GCF. Climate needs to be front and center at the G8. President Obama and Secretary Kerry continue to make that point clear. We need to use a wider lens. Climate, energy, and economic progress lives in the linkages between pollution and global economies.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	So we know the risks. We know the opportunity. We know our moral, civil, and international obligation to act—so what are we doing about it? President Obama made a courageous speech in June 2013.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	He announced a national climate action plan to cut domestic carbon pollution, build resilience to impacts we can’t avoid, and lead the world in our global climate fight. Over the last six years, U.S. Emissions have declined by a larger magnitude than any other country. The U.S. aims to cut carbon emissions by 26 to 28 percent of 2005 levels by 2025. EPA is playing a central role in that progress. With unprecedented advice from states and the power sector—we’re setting first-ever standards to cut carbon pollution from power plants.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	A modern economy needs a modern energy system. Our rule embraces that spirit. It’s not about end-of-pipe pollution controls—it’s about driving investments in renewables and efficiency. It’s about advancing our ongoing clean energy revolution—which unleashes innovation and creates jobs. The global climate fight is a marathon relay race—there’s a lot of ground to cover, and we need everyone to run—EPA’s action gets the U.S. sprinting out of the gate.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	This is what climate leadership looks like. This is what progress looks like. This is what investment, innovation, and reinventing a global economy looks like. Businesses understand that investments in climate action are investments in global economic competitiveness.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	Despite clear evidence, clear economics, and clear advice from the smartest people on the planet, narrow-minded interests hang on to the past. They cling to business models rooted in century-old technology and a century-old understanding of pollution and public health. Climate deniers can put their heads in the sand, but that doesn’t change the world around them.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	Banks like Citi Group are investing hundreds of billions of dollars in climate and clean energy financing. Even energy companies are weaving climate costs into operations—because CEO’s see the value of action. Shell Oil internally prices carbon at $40 dollars a ton. The value of less-polluting energy projects directly translate into value for our health and climate. Successful economies invest in where the world is going—not where it’s been. And that’s good for American companies—because the global demand for clean technology doubles as a demand for American technology.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	When people question our chances against climate change, they must be forgetting where we’ve been. When holes in the ozone layer threated all nations—it took all nations to reverse course toward safety. But it was &lt;i&gt;us&lt;/i&gt;—the United States of America—that paved that path to recovery.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	It was an American university that uncovered the problem—and American industry that innovated solutions. It was American leadership that forged a global market for better, safer products—and American companies that sold solutions to the rest of the world.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	With climate change, the source of pollution may be different, the scope of our challenge may be different—but the principle that compels us to act is the same. This time, the stakes are higher, but once again, we will lead.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	Madeline Albright famously called America “the indispensable nation.” Nowhere is that more true, than our environmental leadership—in development and diplomacy. In protecting global health and promoting global growth. In this century—when it comes to climate action—we truly are the indispensable nation.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	Thank you.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 28 Apr 2016 20:23:32 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>jmorin</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">148053 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  </channel>
</rss>

<!-- Page cached by Boost @ 2017-01-26 04:45:06, expires @ 2017-01-26 16:45:06, lifetime 12 hours -->