<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?><rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.epa.gov/feed/38617/rss.xml" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/" xmlns:og="http://ogp.me/ns#" xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#" xmlns:sioc="http://rdfs.org/sioc/ns#" xmlns:sioct="http://rdfs.org/sioc/types#" xmlns:skos="http://www.w3.org/2004/02/skos/core#" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#">
  <channel>
    <title>E3: Economy, Energy and Environment</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/feed/38617/rss.xml</link>
    <description>Updated E3: Economy, Energy and Environment content from the US Environmental Protection Agency</description>
    <language>en</language>
     <atom:link href="https://www.epa.gov/feed/38617/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      <item>
    <title>E3 Value Stream Mapping - Training Modules</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/e3/e3-value-stream-mapping-training-modules</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;Purpose of the Lean and Environment Toolkit and Training Modules&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Lean and Environment Training Modules (Version 1.0)
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Trains Lean leaders and environmental assistance providers on strategies and tools for integrating Lean and the environment.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/lean/lean-environment-toolkit&quot;&gt;Lean and Environment Toolkit (Version 1.0)&lt;/a&gt;
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Illustrates how considering environmental goals and opportunities in Lean efforts can eliminate waste, improve quality, and maximize value delivered to the customer&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Provides practical strategies and tools for integrating environmental considerations into Lean methods&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Lean and Environment Training Modules address these questions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;What is environmental waste?&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Why should I identify environmental waste in my process?&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;How will I know when I see environmental waste?&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Where should I look for environmental wastes?&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;How do I measure the environmental impacts of a process?&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Where can I find environmentally preferable process options?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-142169&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-06/documents/module_1_intro_lean.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=162134&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Lean and Environment Training Module 1 - Getting Started with Lean and Environment (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(23 pp, 162 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-142171&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-06/documents/module_2_envwastes.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=109916&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Lean and Environment Training Module 2 - Identifying Environmental Wastes (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(25 pp, 110 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-142173&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-06/documents/module_3_vsm.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=246452&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Lean and Environment Training Module 3 - Value Stream Mapping (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(47 pp, 246 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-142175&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-06/documents/module_4_kzn.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=174553&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Lean and Environment Training Module 4 - Kaizen Events (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(49 pp, 175 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-142177&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-06/documents/module_5_6s.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=192683&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Lean and Environment Training Module 5 - 6S (5S+Safety) (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(46 pp, 193 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jun 2015 15:35:33 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>tgelaber</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">88573 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>E3 Sample Energy Bill</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/e3/e3-sample-energy-bill</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;This is an example of a sample energy bill. It is important when looking at the energy use in a manufacturing facility to gather all data that is helpful.  An energy bill is just one of many data points that can be useful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-139381&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-06/documents/sample-elec-bill.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=449618&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Sample Electric Bill (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(2 pp, 450 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jun 2015 14:29:18 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>tgelaber</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">87335 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>E3 Success Story - San Antonio E3 Case Study: UEMC “Now Hiring”</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/e3/e3-success-story-san-antonio-e3-case-study-uemc-now-hiring</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;Texas Manufacturing Assistance Center conducted an E3 assessment as part of the local Lean-Clean-Energy program in October of 2009. E3 is a coordinated federal and local technical assistance initiative that is helping manufacturers across the nation thrive in a new business era focused on sustainability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-139359&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-06/documents/uemc.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=193228&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;UEMC &amp;quot;Now Hiring&amp;quot; E3 Case Study (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(2 pp, 193 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jun 2015 13:21:45 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>tgelaber</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">87311 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>E3 Success Story - Reducing Wolverine&#039;s Cost, Power Demand, and Carbon Footprint: Wolverine Advanced Materials</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/e3/e3-success-story-reducing-wolverines-cost-power-demand-and-carbon-footprint-wolverine-advanced</link>
    <description>&lt;div class=&quot;box simple right&quot;&gt;
	&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Company Basics&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Location: Blacksburg, Virginia&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Assessment Details&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;
				&lt;p&gt; Team Lead: Manufacturing Technology Center&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This case study was written by the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mtcofswva.org/&quot;&gt;Manufacturing Technology Center (MTC)&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more than 75 years, Wolverine has been a leading developer of high-performance, custom-engineered sealing solutions and a trusted supplier of polymer-coated materials to gasket manufacturers around the globe. Their extensive experience with sealing materials and applications allows them to not only identify the problem faster, but also to help you choose the right material for the job. Wolverine, Blacksburg wanted to improve their energy and production efficiency, and reduce the carbon footprint of their production operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The Situation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Manufacturing Technology Center (MTC) received a grant from the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency for the delivery of an Economy, Energy and Environment (E3) pilot project in Southwest Virginia. The MTC partnered with American Electric Power, a service provider of electric energy, to improve Wolverine&#039;s energy demand requirements in order to reduce cost, power demand, and carbon footprint. The MTC experts in lean, environmental, and energy practices performed an E3 technical assessment and Lean and Green Value Steam Mapping (VSM). The experts identified strategies for better efficiencies in energy usage, process flow, and pollution prevention within the selected organization. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The Solution&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The MTC-Wolverine Management team decided that the E3 project would proceed according to the following three distinct sub-projects:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A cross-functional assessment team conducted a two-day event to identify and assess opportunities to reduce the energy power demand of the facility-wide power consumers.&lt;br /&gt;
	The two-day event was conducted by the team to further enhance the facility&#039;s existing procedures and systems to reduce, recover, and reclaim solvent.&lt;br /&gt;
	A thorough review of plant processes was reviewed to identify wastes (non-value added process steps) in order to minimize wasted motion and improve process flow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The VSM process was conducted during a separate two-day event. A typical first step of the process is to define the &quot;current state&quot; of the system. For the coating area key elements of the current state were documented on a current state map.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Current State&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;Power demand spiked above 900 kW at the Cedar Run facility. Something significant occurs usually for a relatively short period of time. The spikes result in a 300 kW charge at $21.21/ kW.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Currently solvent is used to flush coating material from the processes during change over and becomes hazardous waste with minimal reuse.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Minimal TPM systems of keeping all equipment in top working order at all times throughout the facility but especially at the coating lines is occurring.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Future State&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;Reduce power demand through scheduling of equipment during off-peak hours.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Reuse solvent that is reclaimed, reducing solvent cost and disposal cost.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;All equipment operators are responsible for the routine cleaning and performance of P.M.&#039;s on the equipment they run. The employees, with the help of the maintenance staff, create simple, visual procedures for how to properly maintain equipment. Equipment is marked and/or modified as needed to make maintenance simple, easy, and safe.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;MTC interviewed Wolverine staff to determine implementation status and success. A percentage of the recommendation has occurred with plans for additional implementation to occur within one year. The reported numbers are actual implementation savings. Payback for each improvement is less than one year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;box simple&quot;&gt;
	&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Results&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Reduced Power Demand: An immediate savings of $26,725 and an additional savings of $11,453 within one year.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Solvent Reuse: An immediate savings of $43,622 and an additional savings of $43,622 within one year.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Improved Maintenance: An immediate savings of $26,100 and additional savings of $60,900 within one year.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&quot;The E3 project provided a good opportunity to take a fresh look at energy utilization and resource conservation.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;— Sheila McCartan, Vice President Corporate Quality &amp;amp; General Manager N.A. Operations  &lt;br /&gt;
	 &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jun 2015 12:30:23 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>tgelaber</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">87303 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>E3 Success Story - Examining Inefficiencies Facility-wide: Triad Manufacturing</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/e3/e3-success-story-examining-inefficiencies-facility-wide-triad-manufacturing</link>
    <description>&lt;div class=&quot;box simple right&quot;&gt;
	&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Assessment Details&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;
				&lt;p&gt; Date: September 2008&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;Team: Missouri Enterprise, a NIST MEP, David Goebel and Nick Hennen&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Triad Manufacturing is a manufacturer of retail store fixtures used for displaying products. Triad&#039;s customers include Best Buy, Target, Banana Republic, Home Depot, and Pacific Sunwear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The Situation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Missouri Enterprise, a NIST Manufacturing Extension Partnership, approached Triad about participating in the Green Suppliers Network since they were aware that Triad routinely looked for opportunities to improve its operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David Goebel and Nick Hennen of Missouri Enterprise completed Triad&#039;s review in September 2008. Instead of focusing on one product or process line, Triad wanted to examine inefficiencies across its whole facility. The review team prepared high-level value stream maps that captured the entire system, from raw materials entering the facility to finished products exiting. The review process identified two primary opportunities: improved energy efficiency and increased recycling of byproducts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The Solution&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the Green Suppliers Network review, Triad has succeeded in reducing its energy consumption by making four changes. The first two, capturing waste heat off its drying ovens and compressed air system for heating the facility during the winter months and installing infrared heaters to reduce the use of forced air heat, have saved the company an estimated $80,000 annually. The third, installing a new powder coating line, has decreased energy use for the powder coating process line by 40 percent and also reduced hazardous effluent by 10,000 gallons annually. Fourth, Triad implemented a leak detection program for its compressed air system that could potentially save an additional $25,000 annually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Triad is also interested in recycling its sawdust and scrap wood pallets. The company is currently investigating the feasibility of sending its broken wood pallets to a company that manufactures wood pellets for heat. Recycling these wood pallets would eliminate a waste stream of 30,000 pounds annually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;box simple&quot;&gt;
	&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Green Suppliers Network Findings&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Cost Savings: $80,000, with potential for $25,000 in additional savings&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Reduced Hazardous Effluent: 10,000 gallons annually&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Potential Annual Solid Waste Reduction: 30,000 pounds&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jun 2015 12:01:55 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>tgelaber</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">87301 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>E3 Success Story - Tonawanda and E3: Partnership for a Brighter Future</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/e3/e3-success-story-tonawanda-and-e3-partnership-brighter-future</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;The federal, state, and local Economy, Energy, Environment (E3) initiative helped Tonawanda bring together a diverse partnership of manufacturers, community leaders, local stakeholder organizations, state and federal agencies, and many others. Together, the Tonawanda E3 team is working to improve the performance of its manufacturing base and make the town a healthy place to live, work, and play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-139317&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-06/documents/tonawanda.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=2075680&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Tonawanda and E3: Partnership for a Brighter Future (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(11 pp, 2 MB)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jun 2015 11:56:50 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>tgelaber</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">87299 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>E3 Success Story - Path Toward Sustainability Leads to Significant Water Savings: Southwire</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/e3/e3-success-story-path-toward-sustainability-leads-significant-water-savings-southwire</link>
    <description>&lt;div class=&quot;box simple right&quot;&gt;
	&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Company Basics&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Headquarters: Carrollton, Georgia&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Founded in 1950&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Employees: 4,400&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;2008 Sales: $4.5 billion&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;15 manufacturing facilities and 10 customer service distribution centers&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Assessment Details&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Date: February 2008&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Team: Georgia Tech Enterprise Innovation Institute, a NIST MEP, Bob Hitch, Bill Ritsch, and Tom Sammon &amp;amp; Pollution Prevention Assistance Division of Georgia Department of Natural Resources, P.J. Newcomb&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In October 2007, Georgia Governor Sonny Perdue asked industries across the state to voluntarily cut water use by 10 percent to mitigate a drought of exceptional proportion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In response, Southwire—a leading North American manufacturer of residential, commercial, industrial and utility wire and cable products—began searching for opportunities to reduce its water use at the company&#039;s Utility Products Plant in Carrollton, Georgia. During this same year, Southwire launched a sustainability campaign and established company-wide goals to reduce water use by 15 percent and its overall carbon footprint by 10 percent by the end of 2010.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The Situation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pacific Gas and Electric (PG&amp;amp;E) contacted Southwire in late 2007 about participating in a Green Suppliers Network review. As one of PG&amp;amp;E&#039;s key suppliers, Southwire welcomed the opportunity to participate in the Green Suppliers Network, which would complement its ongoing efforts to meet company-wide sustainability goals. Southwire was already incorporating the fundamentals of lean manufacturing into its daily operations. With the help of the Green Suppliers Network, the review would help the company capitalize on the connection between its lean manufacturing initiative and its path toward environmental sustainability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bob Hitch, Bill Ritsch, and Tom Sammon of Georgia Tech Enterprise Innovation Institute, and P.J. Newcomb of the Pollution Prevention Assistance Division of the Georgia Department of Natural Resources, conducted Southwire&#039;s review in February 2008. Southwire&#039;s review team—consisting of plant managers, engineers, materials managers and production personnel—developed comprehensive current and future state value stream maps of its 600-volt cable line. This line was chosen because most manufacturing processes situated at the facility take part in producing the 600-volt cable. Southwire can transfer improvements to this line to many other similar lines throughout the facility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The Solution&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Georgia Tech Enterprise Innovation Institute&#039;s final report confirmed some of Southwire&#039;s initial investigation and helped prioritize the opportunities available to the company. More importantly, the Green Suppliers Network review helped operations managers justify capital investments by estimating the associated cost savings. Jill Morgan, director of operational perfection at Southwire, shared that &quot;having an outside set of eyes look at our processes is one of the benefits of the Green Suppliers Network. They helped us validate our efforts and confirm that we set our priorities appropriately.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the review, the facility implemented a water-looping system that recycled process water without affecting the quality of the wire. Southwire added a filtration system that allowed water to be reused several times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Southwire also added energy efficiency opportunities to the expanding focus of its operational perfection culture. Since the review event, the company has retrofitted its Carrollton facility with high-efficiency light fixtures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The Results&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a result of implementing process-water recycling, Southwire reduced its publicly-supplied water use at the Carrollton Utility Products Plant by more than 9 million gallons annually, which reduced the fcility&#039;s demand on Georgia&#039;s water resources by more than 90 percent—far exceeding the governor&#039;s request and saving more than $70,000 annually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Retrofitting the facility with high-efficiency fluorescent light fixtures allowed the facility to cut its electricity use for lighting in half and take steps forward toward meeting the company&#039;s carbon footprint goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Southwire&#039;s Carrollton facility also reduced scrap from its processes by 30 percent, following the Green Suppliers Network review. While some scrap reductions can be attributed to improved order management through better planning, Emory Barber, the Carrollton plant manger, states that there are no low hanging fruit when it comes to reducing scrap rates. He said the facility now tracks scrap rates by the hour, focuses on the details when filling orders, and proactively makes adjustments to production to optimize efficiency and reduce scrap wastes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Southwire is now well on its way toward meeting its sustainability goals and the company is also striving to achieve a zero-landfill status by 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&quot;The Green Suppliers Network approach complements Southwire&#039;s lean manufacturing culture. Our participation helped us align our goals and initiatives to reduce waste. The success we had in one plant can also be realized at other Southwire facilities resulting in a greener supply chain throughout the company.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;— Jeff Herrin, Executive Vice President of Operations, Southwire&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;box simple&quot;&gt;
	&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Green Suppliers Network Findings&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Water Savings: 9 million gallons&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Cost Savings: $70,000&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Scrap Reduced by 30 percent&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jun 2015 11:52:13 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>tgelaber</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">87297 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>E3 Success Story - Southern Folger Unlocks the Tools to Energy Management</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/e3/e3-success-story-southern-folger-unlocks-tools-energy-management</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;Texas Manufacturing Assistance Center led a team of Southern Folger employees in an eight hour session to learn about how energy conservation fits within the framework of lean manufacturing and pollution prevention. Applying this new knowledge, the team identified several potential opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-139313&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-06/documents/southernfolger.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=383725&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Southern Folger Unlocks Tools to Energy Management (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(1 pg, 384 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jun 2015 11:46:29 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>tgelaber</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">87295 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>E3 Success Story - Holding Lean and Green Assessment Instead of Kaizen Event: Sermatech Connecticut</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/e3/e3-success-story-holding-lean-and-green-assessment-instead-kaizen-event-sermatech-connecticut</link>
    <description>&lt;div class=&quot;box simple right&quot;&gt;
	&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Assessment Details&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Date: 2006&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Team:  CONNSTEP, Inc., a NIST MEP&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sermatech Connecticut, a Green Suppliers Network Partner, specializes in developing and applying engineered, high-performance protective coatings for the aerospace industry. Sermatech initially planned for a lean kaizen event to coincide with the purchase of new equipment, but after learning about the Green Suppliers Network, the company decided this would be a good opportunity to address lean and green in a single event. The facility general manager, John Whalen, noted that &quot;We, at Sermatech, had not yet looked at waste minimization as a cost reduction opportunity. It just made sense to hold a Green Suppliers Network review in place of the scheduled lean kaizen event.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The Situation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Green Suppliers Network team reviewed a Sermatech surface coating process line that sprayed helicopter rotor hubs. The process required the parts to travel a considerable distance, which increased the risk of damage to the coating and required large amounts of rework. The rework cost Sermatech approximately 2 percent of its profit margin, or about $46,000 annually. Wastes identified for this process included coating overspray, air emissions, spray booth filters, solvent, masking tape, and protective gloves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The Solution&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To improve product movement and reduce travel distance for the parts, the Green Suppliers Network review team recommended that Sermatech install an enclosed environment workstation. This workstation would include new &quot;controlled environment&quot; spray booths that would optimize the facility work space and eliminate the need for the part to travel in the ambient air. By installing these new workstations, Sermatech expects to reduce rework by 75 percent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The Results&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sermatech estimates it will reduce hazardous waste, including hexavalent chromium and aluminum from the coating and acetone solvents, by more than 30 percent, equal to 2,000 pounds; it will also save more than $600 in disposal costs. Furthermore, Sermatech expects to reduce volatile organic compound (VOC) emissions by 66 percent, or more than 32 pounds per year per booth, by installing the new spray booths. Sermatech expects to realize more than $35,000 in annual savings from implementing these recommendations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whalen stated that an unexpected benefit of undergoing the Green Suppliers Network review occurred when one of Sermatech&#039;s major customers learned of its efforts through a manufacturing forum. Previously unaware of Sermatech&#039;s efforts to reduce environmental risk, the customer has now signed a preferred supplier agreement with Sermatech.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&quot;Once OEMs [original equipment manufacturers] recognize that you put in additional effort to reduce their environmental footprint, it gives you a leg up on the competition—and you can&#039;t place a dollar value on that!&quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;— John Whalen, Facility General Manager, Sermatech&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jun 2015 11:38:49 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>tgelaber</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">87293 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  </channel>
</rss>

<!-- Page cached by Boost @ 2017-01-25 17:25:51, expires @ 2017-01-26 05:25:51, lifetime 12 hours -->