<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?><rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.epa.gov/feed/107939/rss.xml" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/" xmlns:og="http://ogp.me/ns#" xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#" xmlns:sioc="http://rdfs.org/sioc/ns#" xmlns:sioct="http://rdfs.org/sioc/types#" xmlns:skos="http://www.w3.org/2004/02/skos/core#" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#">
  <channel>
    <title>Pesticides</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/feed/107939/rss.xml</link>
    <description>Updated Pesticides content from the US Environmental Protection Agency</description>
    <language>en</language>
     <atom:link href="https://www.epa.gov/feed/107939/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      <item>
    <title>EPA Releases Final Biological Evaluations of Three Chemicals’ Impacts on Endangered Species</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/pesticides/epa-releases-final-biological-evaluations-three-chemicals-impacts-endangered-species</link>
    <description>&lt;h2&gt;For Release: January 18, 2017&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA has released its final biological evaluations (BEs) for effects of chlorpyrifos, diazinon, and malathion on threatened and endangered species and their designated critical habitat. We have also released a separate document that addresses the comments submitted during the public comment period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under the Endangered Species Act, for those species and designated critical habitats where registered uses of the three pesticides are “likely to adversely affect” the species and/or their habitat, U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service and the National Marine Fisheries Service will incorporate the analyses and data from EPA’s biological evaluations into their final Biological Opinions for each of the three chemicals. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final biological evaluations and the response-to-comments document can be found on our website:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/endangered-species/biological-evaluation-chapters-chlorpyrifos-esa-assessment&quot;&gt;Chlorpyrifos&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/endangered-species/biological-evaluation-chapters-diazinon-esa-assessment&quot;&gt;Diazinon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/endangered-species/biological-evaluation-chapters-malathion-esa-assessment&quot;&gt;Malathion&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2017 21:37:43 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>morganic</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">169463 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Updated List of Human Health Benchmarks for Pesticides in Drinking Water Available</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/pesticides/updated-list-human-health-benchmarks-pesticides-drinking-water-available</link>
    <description>&lt;h2&gt;For Release: January 18,  2017&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA has updated its list of human health benchmarks for pesticides (HHBP) in drinking water. A total of 394 HHBPs are now available for pesticides that are currently registered for use on food crops or other use that could result in exposure through food or drinking water. EPA develops these benchmarks as screening levels for use by states and water systems in determining whether the detection of a pesticide in drinking water or a drinking water source may indicate a potential health risk. All benchmarks were calculated with updated exposure assumptions (related to body weight and drinking water intake). Three pesticides previously listed in the table (d-allethrin, S-bioallethrin, and bioallethrin) were removed due to updated exposure pattern information demonstrating that these pesticides are no longer used on food. The available&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://iaspub.epa.gov/apex/pesticides/f?p=HHBP:home:10911636297819:::::&quot;&gt;View the revised list of human health benchmarks for pesticides&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2017 19:51:05 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>morganic</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">169429 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>EPA Amends Registration for Enlist Duo Herbicide to Add GE Cotton and Additional States</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/pesticides/epa-amends-registration-enlist-duo-herbicide-add-ge-cotton-and-additional-states</link>
    <description>&lt;h2&gt;For Release:  January 12, 2017&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enlist Duo, a formula containing the choline salt of 2,4-D and glyphosate for use in controlling weeds in genetically engineered (GE) crops, was first registered in 2014 for use in GE corn and soybean crops. EPA is amending the registration to include GE cotton and expand the use to an additional 19 states for GE corn, soybean, and cotton and &lt;a href=&quot;/ingredients-used-pesticide-products/registration-enlist-duo#court-ordered&quot;&gt;re-affirming our original decision&lt;/a&gt; before the remand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA did a comprehensive review for the initial registration of Enlist Duo and now again in response to the application to amend the registration. EPA’s protective and conservative human health and ecological risk assessments re-confirmed our 2014 safety findings. The pesticide meets the safety standard for the public, agricultural workers, and non-target plants and animal species, including a “no effects” determination for species listed as threatened or endangered under the Endangered Species Act.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enlist Duo is a low-volatility pesticide formulation and includes the following restrictions: No application from aircraft; no application when the wind speed is over 15 mph; buffer zones to protect sensitive areas; and application only with approved nozzles at specified pressures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enlist Duo was previously registered for use on GE corn and soybean crops in Arkansas, Illinois, Indiana, Iowa, Kansas, Louisiana, Minnesota, Mississippi, Missouri, Nebraska, North Dakota, Oklahoma, Ohio, South Dakota, and Wisconsin. This final decision to expand the use of Enlist Duo will allow use on GE cotton in those states and extend use on GE corn, soybean and cotton crops to include Alabama, Arizona, Colorado, Delaware, Florida, Georgia, Kentucky, Maryland, Michigan, North Carolina, New Jersey, New Mexico, New York, Pennsylvania, South Carolina, Tennessee, Texas, Virginia, and West Virginia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To view the final decision document and other related documents, see EPA docket &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.regulations.gov/docket?D=EPA-HQ-OPP-2016-0594&quot;&gt;EPA‑HQ‑OPP‑2016‑0594&lt;/a&gt; at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.regulations.gov/&quot;&gt;www.regulations.gov&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/ingredients-used-pesticide-products/registration-enlist-duo&quot;&gt;Read more about the Enlist Duo registration&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Fri, 13 Jan 2017 12:46:47 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>dcoleman</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">169029 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>EPA Releases Four Neonicotinoid Risk Assessments for Public Comment</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/pesticides/epa-releases-four-neonicotinoid-risk-assessments-public-comment</link>
    <description>&lt;h2&gt;For Release: January 12, 2017&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The U.S. Environmental Protection Agency has published preliminary pollinator-only risk assessments for the neonicotinoid insecticides clothianidin, thiamethoxam, and dinotefuran and also an update to its preliminary risk assessment for imidacloprid, which we published in January 2016. The updated imidacloprid assessment looks at potential risks to aquatic species, and identifies some risks for aquatic insects.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The assessments for clothianidin, thiamethoxam, and dinotefuran, similar to the preliminary pollinator assessment for imidacloprid showed: most approved uses do not pose significant risks to bee colonies. However, spray applications to a few crops, such as cucumbers, berries, and cotton, may pose risks to bees that come in direct contact with residue. In its preliminary pollinator-only analysis for clothianidin and thiamethoxam, the EPA has proposed a new method for accounting for pesticide exposure that may occur through pollen and nectar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 60-day public comment period will begin upon publication in the Federal Register, which will happen soon. The EPA invites public comment on all of these preliminary assessments, but we are especially interested in getting input from stakeholders on the new method for assessing potential exposure and risk through pollen and nectar. EPA may revise the pollinator assessment based on comments received as well as additional data that we anticipate receiving during 2017. We hope to release the final neonicotinoid risk assessments for public comment by mid-2018.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Along with the risk assessments, the EPA is also issuing an updated registration review schedule for the four neonicotinoids to reflect the data being submitted in 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA encourages stakeholders and interested members of the public to visit the dockets for the neonicotinoid pesticides and sign up for email alerts to be automatically notified when the Agency publishes the next documents for review and comment. View the &lt;a href=&quot;/pollinator-protection/schedule-review-neonicotinoid-pesticides&quot;&gt;neonicotinoid registration review&lt;/a&gt; schedule for links to the individual dockets.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 12 Jan 2017 21:46:15 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>ctran</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">169005 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>EPA Finalizes Steps to Better Protect Bees from Pesticides</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/pesticides/epa-finalizes-steps-better-protect-bees-pesticides</link>
    <description>&lt;h2&gt;For Release: January 12, 2017&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA’s is releasing a final policy which describes methods for addressing acute risks to bees from pesticides.  Applications of acutely toxic pesticides would be prohibited under certain conditions when bees are most likely to be present.  While the restrictions focus on managed bees, EPA believes that these measures will also protect native bees and other pollinators that are in and around treatment areas.  New label language will protect managed bees under contract to provide crop pollination services. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.regulations.gov/document?D=EPA-HQ-OPP-2014-0818-0477&quot;&gt;Policy to Mitigate the Acute Risk to Bees from Pesticide Products&lt;/a&gt; is more flexible and practical than the proposed policy.  For example, a product that retains its toxicity to bees for a shorter time might be allowed to be applied under certain circumstances. Also, in some cases, pesticide application would be allowed when it is unlikely that pollinators will be foraging for crops that have extended bloom periods. The EPA will begin implementing this policy in 2017 by sending letters to registrants describing steps that must be taken to incorporate the new labeling. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA continues to encourage efforts by states and tribes to reduce pesticide exposure to bees and other insect pollinators through locally-based measures, such as through Managed Pollinator Protection Plans (MP3s). EPA will continue to assist the American Association of Pest Control Officials in developing performance measures for MP3s and will continue to monitor the progress and effectiveness of pollinator protection plans in reducing bee exposure to pesticides.  EPA has also engaged the Pesticide Program Dialogue Committee in examining the best ways to measure the effectiveness of MP3s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information on the proposal, its supporting documents, and comments received, please see &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.regulations.gov/docket?D=EPA-HQ-OPP-2014-0818&quot;&gt;regulatory docket EPA-HQ-OPP-2014-0818&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/pollinator-protection/epa-actions-protect-pollinators&quot;&gt;EPA’s Actions to Protect Pollinators&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/pollinator-protection&quot;&gt;Pollinator Protection at EPA&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 12 Jan 2017 20:04:35 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>ctran</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">168969 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Now Available – Final Test Guidelines for Ecological Effects</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/pesticides/now-available-final-test-guidelines-ecological-effects</link>
    <description>&lt;h2&gt;For Release: January 12, 2017&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA’s final test guidelines for ecological effects are now available. The test guidelines, “&lt;a href=&quot;/test-guidelines-pesticides-and-toxic-substances/series-850-ecological-effects-test-guidelines&quot;&gt;Guidelines for Aquatic and Sediment-Dwelling Fauna, Aquatic Microcosm and Field Testing&lt;/a&gt;,” are part of a series of test guidelines established by the EPA for use in testing pesticides and other chemical substances. One of the goals of the project is the formulation of harmonized guidelines between the Toxic Substances Control Act (TSCA), the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (FFDCA), the Federal Insecticide, Fungicide, and Rodenticide Act (FIFRA), and the Organization for Economic Cooperation and Development’s guidelines for the testing of chemicals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The guidelines describe how to develop data for submission to the EPA under TSCA, FFDCA, and FIFRA. The data submitted help to inform the EPA’s regulatory decisions. The guidelines will be used by the EPA, the public, and companies that submit data to the EPA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Go to &lt;a href=&quot;/www.regulations.gov&quot;&gt;www.regulations.gov&lt;/a&gt;, docket &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.regulations.gov/document?D=EPA-HQ-OPPT-2009-0154-0043&quot;&gt;EPA-HQ-OPPT-2009-0154&lt;/a&gt;, for more information and to find the series of test guidelines.&lt;/p&gt;


</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 12 Jan 2017 16:12:16 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>morganic</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">168899 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Register for January 24 Webinar on Controlling Public Health Pests</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/pesticides/register-january-24-webinar-controlling-public-health-pests</link>
    <description>&lt;h2&gt;For Release:  January 10, 2017&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Tuesday, January 24, 2017, at 2:00 p.m. ET, EPA’s Center of Expertise for School IPM will offer a webinar titled, “Pests of Public Health Importance and the Role of Integrated Pest Management in Schools.” Recent developments in pest-borne diseases, such as the emergence of Zika virus and spread of Lyme disease, signal the need to continually assess the threat of pests to public health. Illnesses carried by insects, rodents, and other pests affect all races, ethnicities, ages and cultures. Vector-borne illnesses are an ever-present threat and efforts to prevent them are critical to protecting public health.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We strive to keep our school playgrounds and other outdoor environments free of pests. The control of vector-borne diseases hinges on understanding the pest and how it becomes established in an ecosystem and ultimately infects a susceptible host. Integrated pest management (IPM) is an approach that uses a hierarchy of practices, including education, pest exclusion, sanitation and other biological and mechanical methods, to reduce unnecessary pesticide exposure while providing sustainable pest control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Join us as we discuss the primary pests of public health concern, review control strategies, and describe tactics to reduce exposure in your school district.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;Our presenters will be:&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;Richard Pollack, PhD, Harvard School of Public Health &lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;Pearl English, DNP, Nurse, School District of Philadelphia (PA)&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;Marcia Anderson, PhD, EPA Center of Expertise for School IPM&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;div&gt;Upcoming webinars include:&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;More Than Just a Firm Handshake: Bid and Contract Guidance for Securing IPM-Based Services for Schools – February 21, 2017&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;Feed the Kids, Not the Pests: Effective IPM for Cafeterias and Kitchen – March 14, 2017&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;Contending with Invasive Plants on School Grounds – April 17, 2017&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;div&gt;Actions you can take:&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://epawebconferencing-events.acms.com/content/connect/c1/7/en/events/event/shared/108310290/event_landing.html?sco-id=108310299&amp;amp;_charset_=utf-8&quot;&gt;Register&lt;/a&gt; for the January 24, 2017, webinar&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/managing-pests-schools/webinars-about-integrated-pest-management-schools&quot;&gt;Find information&lt;/a&gt; about upcoming and past School IPM webinars&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/managing-pests-schools&quot;&gt;Learn more&lt;/a&gt; about managing pests in school&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://ischoolpestmanager.org/&quot;&gt;Access school IPM resources&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt; including fact sheets, presentations, training and checklists&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 10 Jan 2017 22:21:18 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>dcoleman</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">168675 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Biotechnology Regulation Framework and Modernization Strategy Available </title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/pesticides/biotechnology-regulation-framework-and-modernization-strategy-available</link>
    <description>&lt;h2&gt;For Release:  January 5, 2017&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The White House has posted a blog unveiling the final Update to the Coordinated Framework for the Regulation of Biotechnology as well as information on the National Strategy for Modernizing the Regulatory System for Biotechnology Products. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.whitehouse.gov/blog/2017/01/04/increasing-transparency-coordination-and-predictability-biotechnology-regulatory&quot;&gt;View the blog announcing these documents&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The White House released the national strategy and draft update of the coordinated framework in September 2016 as part of the Administration’s continuing effort to modernize the federal regulatory system for biotechnology products as well as to clarify various roles of the Environmental Protection Agency, Food and Drug Administration and Department of Agriculture in evaluating new biotechnologies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;The National Strategy for Modernizing the Regulatory System for Biotechnology Products sets forth a vision for ensuring that the federal regulatory system is equipped to assess efficiently the risks, if any, associated with future products of biotechnology.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;The Update to the Coordinated Framework for the Regulation of Biotechnology clarifies current roles and responsibilities.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The updated Framework and the accompanying Strategy offer the public a complete picture of a robust and flexible regulatory structure that provides appropriate oversight for products of modern biotechnology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/regulation-biotechnology-under-tsca-and-fifra/modernizing-regulatory-system-biotechnology-products&quot;&gt;View more information about EPA’s efforts in modernization of regulation of biotechnology.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jan 2017 18:21:30 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>dcoleman</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">168321 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>EPA Finalizes Human Health Risk Assessment for Pesticide Used on Pets </title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/pesticides/epa-finalizes-human-health-risk-assessment-pesticide-used-pets</link>
    <description>&lt;h2&gt;For Release:  January 4, 2017&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA has finalized the human health risk assessment of tetrachlorvinphos (TCVP). TCVP is an organophosphate insecticide used to control fleas, ticks, and other pests on and around pets and livestock. It is used in residential products like pet collars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through the publication of the revised human health risk assessment and related documents, we are addressing a 2009 Natural Resource Defense Council (NRDC) petition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This risk assessment identified potential risks to people, including children, in residential settings and to certain workers applying TCVP, which exceed the Agency’s level of concern.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Agency has contacted the pesticide manufacturers to initiate discussions with them to reduce exposure and resolve potential risks identified in the human health risk assessment. The Agency will issue a Proposed Decision in 2017 for public comment. Until that time, it is important to follow label instructions on proper use of pesticide products.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We advise consumers to take certain precautions when handling TCVP products in residential areas. These precautions are listed on TCVP product labels, including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;not allowing children to play with TCVP pet collar products,&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;keeping TCVP spray and powder products out of reach of children, and&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;washing hands thoroughly with soap and water after handling.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;To view TCVP’s human health risk assessment and other registration review documents, visit &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.regulations.gov/&quot;&gt;regulations.gov&lt;/a&gt;, docket number &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.regulations.gov/docket?D=EPA-HQ-OPP-2008-0316&quot;&gt;EPA-HQ-OPP-2008-0316&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;More information on:&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/ingredients-used-pesticide-products/tetrachlorvinphos-tcvp&quot;&gt;tetrachlorvinphos &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/pets&quot;&gt;protecting your pets form fleas and ticks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/safepestcontrol/reduce-your-childs-chances-pesticide-poisoning&quot;&gt;reducing your child&#039;s chances of pesticide poisoning&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jan 2017 19:25:39 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>dcoleman</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">168215 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  </channel>
</rss>

<!-- Page cached by Boost @ 2017-01-26 04:39:16, expires @ 2017-01-26 16:39:16, lifetime 12 hours -->