<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?><rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.epa.gov/feed/54113/rss.xml" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/" xmlns:og="http://ogp.me/ns#" xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#" xmlns:sioc="http://rdfs.org/sioc/ns#" xmlns:sioct="http://rdfs.org/sioc/types#" xmlns:skos="http://www.w3.org/2004/02/skos/core#" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#">
  <channel>
    <title>Homeland Security</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/feed/54113/rss.xml</link>
    <description>Updated Homeland Security content from the US Environmental Protection Agency</description>
    <language>en</language>
     <atom:link href="https://www.epa.gov/feed/54113/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      <item>
    <title>EPA&#039;s Homeland Security Priorities</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/homeland-security/epas-homeland-security-priorities</link>
    <description>&lt;h2&gt;Maintain Our Preparedness Level&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In recent years the U.S. has faced challenges in responding to national significant incidents, including the Deep Water Horizon oil spill, the Japan nuclear emergency, and Superstorm Sandy.  These catastrophes and the possibility of similar events in the future make it clear that EPA must sustain our protection, prevention, mitigation, response and recovery capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA has worked diligently to achieve our current level of preparedness (e.g. number of responders, equipment procurement, proper training and exercising).  The resources and effort dedicated to improving our operational capabilities were a meaningful investment.  EPA will continue to pursue the most efficient and effective means to sustain our operational readiness for all hazards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Fill Critical Knowledge and Technology Gaps&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scientific uncertainties will impede EPA&#039;s ability to prepare for and respond to major emergency events.  We must ensure that EPA&#039;s decision makers and field responders have the best available science and tools to do their jobs.  We must seek to advance and promote scientific research and technological innovation that enhances the Agency&#039;s, as well as our federal, state, tribal, and local partners&#039;, abilities to protect public health and the environment.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Collaborate to Enhance Capability and Capacity&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA needs the help of others in order to fulfill our mission of protecting human health and safeguarding the natural environment. Likewise, others need EPA&#039;s help to meet their respective missions.  EPA will continue to partner with other federal departments and agencies on homeland security-realted joint planning, research projects, technical demonstrations, field exercises, training and information sharing.  We will continue to collaborate with and seek input from our state, local and tribal counterparts, universities, industry and non-profit organizations.  This inclusive approach will facilitate the application of our collective capabilities and leverage each organization&#039;s unique body of knowledge, authorities, and assets to address common capacity and capability gaps.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Fri, 05 Jun 2015 15:58:47 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cdibbl03</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">87757 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>EPA&#039;s Homeland Security Roles and Responsibilities</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/homeland-security/epas-homeland-security-roles-and-responsibilities</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;EPA&#039;s primary mission is to protect human health and the environment.  This mission remains the same for a wide range of natural and man-made events, hazards and disasters.  In the event of an intentional or unintentional event or disaster that results in biological, chemical or radiological contamination, the nation will look to EPA for expertise in the areas of:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Water and Wastewater Security and Resilience &lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Emergency Response&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Site Characterization&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Decontamination/Waste Management&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Clearance&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Recovery&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;In order to prepare for such events, EPA is working to meet the specific homeland security roles and responsibilities that are laid out in a series of statues, presidential directives and national frameworks. EPA may be assigned lead/co-lead, support or mandatory roles and responsibilities by these authorities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When EPA is identified as having a &quot;lead&quot; or &quot;co-lead&quot;role, EPA is explicitly tasked to lead, direct, or coordinate federal/state/local protection, prevention, preparedness, mitigation, response or recovery efforts.  Sometimes EPA is identified as having a &quot;support&quot; role.  In these cases, EPA is tasked with assisting another Federal lead for specified efforts.  Where EPA is designated as having a &quot;mandatory&quot; role, all federal departments and agencies are required to support or implement specified activities and requirements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Statutory Authorities&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several laws serve as the basis for EPA&#039;s various homeland security roles.  While these laws are the pillars of our core environmental programs, they also define some of EPA&#039;s responsibilities in protection, prevention, mitigation, response and recovery for homeland security incidents.  After 9/11 additional statues were enacted to supplement our traditional statutory authority with new tasks and responsibilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Core Statutes&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Atomic Energy Act&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Clean Air Act&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Clean Water Act&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Comprehensive Environmental Response, Compensation, and Liability Act&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Federal Insecticide, Fungicide, and Rodenticide Act &lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Oil Pollution Act&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Public Health Service Act&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Resource Conservation and Recovery Act&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Robert T. Stafford Disaster Relief and Emergency Assistance Act&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Safe Drinking Water Act&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Toxic Substance Control Act&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Post 9/11 Statutes&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Food Safety Modernization Act&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Homeland Security Act&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Post-Katrina Emergency Management Reform Act&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Public Health Security and Bioterrorism Preparedness and Response Act&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Presidential Directives&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More than 30 presidential directives addressing homeland security have been issued since 9/11.  Presidential directives establish policy and many have the force of law.  Most of the homeland security related directives are known as Homeland Security Presidential Directives (HSPD), Presidential Policy Directives (PPD), and Executive Orders (EO).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of EPA&#039;s homeland security efforts are in response to several major presidential directives:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;PPD-8 National Preparedness&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;PPD-21 Critical Infrastructure Security and Resilience&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;HSPD-9 Defense of U.S. Agriculture and Food&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;HSPD-10 Biodefense for the 21st Century&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;HSPD-22 Domestic Chemical Defense&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;National Frameworks&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The National Planning Frameworks describe how the whole community works together to prevent, protect, mitigate, response to and recover from threats and hazards that pose the greatest risk to our nation.  These frameworks align roles and responsibilities across all levels of government, the private sector and nongovernmental organizations, including defining EPA&#039;s responsibilities before, during and after incidents.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under the National Response Framework, EPA is the primary agency, along with the U.S.. Coast Guard, for Emergency Support Function #10, Oil and Hazardous Materials Response. The primary agencies are responsible for coordinating and managing the overall federal effort to prevent, detect, identify, contain, decontaminate, cleanup and dispose of oil discharges and releases of hazardous materials.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2014 19:42:17 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>swhite06</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">67631 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>EPA&#039;s Role in Disaster Recovery</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/homeland-security/epas-role-disaster-recovery</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;Disaster response and recovery are two separate but coordinated phases of disaster relief that may overlap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Response - which EPA carries out under the National Oil and Hazardous Substances Pollution Contingency Plan and the National Response Framework is typically conducted on a weeks to months timeframe for any large scale events and addresses immediate health and safety needs of the affected community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recovery - which EPA carries out under the National Disaster Recovery Framework is a process that can last years and focuses on long-term restoration of places and communities affected by disaster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA&#039;s objectives for recovery operations:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Build preparedness to mitigate future events - lessen the impacts of disasters by assisting federal, state and local agencies and communities prior to disasters.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Promote sustainable and resilient rebuilding - use EPA&#039;s expertise to inform communities, state and federal partners about rebuilding for the long-term viability of regions&#039; people, economies and natural ecosystems.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Apply EPA knowledge - provide EPA&#039;s expertise to other Federal agencies, state and communities in areas of EPA responsibility such as drinking water and wastewater infrastructure, brownfields, air quality, or oil and hazardous materials clean-up.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Streamline federal action - work with partner agencies to streamline Federal oversight to efficiently fulfill statutory, permitting and/or enforcement requirements in a timely fashion.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Partner with environmental justice/disadvantaged communities - actively engage vulnerable and overburdened communities so they can meaningfully participate and have their issues addressed during recovery operations and planning.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Depending on the nature of the disaster, over 20 EPA existing programs may become involved in disaster recovery operations, including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot; style=&quot;vertical-align:middle&quot;&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
			&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot; style=&quot;vertical-align:middle&quot;&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
			&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot; style=&quot;vertical-align:middle&quot;&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=&quot;vertical-align:middle&quot;&gt;Clean Water State Revolving Fund&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td style=&quot;vertical-align:middle&quot;&gt;ORD/Homeland Security Research&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td style=&quot;vertical-align:middle&quot;&gt;Brownfields&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=&quot;vertical-align:middle&quot;&gt;Drinking Water State Revolving Fund&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td style=&quot;vertical-align:middle&quot;&gt;Climate Showcase Grant Program&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td style=&quot;vertical-align:middle&quot;&gt;NEPA&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=&quot;vertical-align:middle&quot;&gt;Global Climate Change Adaptation&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td style=&quot;vertical-align:middle&quot;&gt;Sustainable Communities&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td style=&quot;vertical-align:middle&quot;&gt;Tribal Affairs&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=&quot;vertical-align:middle&quot;&gt;Agriculture Assistance&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td style=&quot;vertical-align:middle&quot;&gt;Air, including Indoor Air and Fuel Waivers&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td style=&quot;vertical-align:middle&quot;&gt;Energy Star&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=&quot;vertical-align:middle&quot;&gt;Enforcement and Environmental Justice&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td style=&quot;vertical-align:middle&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td style=&quot;vertical-align:middle&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=&quot;vertical-align:middle&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td style=&quot;vertical-align:middle&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td style=&quot;vertical-align:middle&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;p&gt;For more information on general preparedness and response tips, see our page on &lt;a href=&quot;/natural-disasters&quot;&gt;Natural Disasters&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;




</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2014 17:43:52 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>swhite06</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">63093 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Contact Us About Homeland Security at EPA</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/homeland-security/forms/contact-us-about-homeland-security-epa</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Please use the form below to send us comments or questions. Be sure to include your e-mail address if you’d like a response.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Call us at:&lt;/strong&gt; 202-564-6987&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mailing Address:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	Office of Homeland Security&lt;br /&gt;
	1200 Pennsylvania Ave, N.W.&lt;br /&gt;
	Mail Code 1109A&lt;br /&gt;
	Washington, DC 20460&lt;br /&gt;
	 &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;box right&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;box left&quot; href=&quot;/tips&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Report an environmental violation&quot; src=&quot;/sites/all/themes/epa/img/badge.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/tips&quot;&gt;Report a Violation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;Report possible violations of environmental laws and regulations.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
     <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2014 15:58:09 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>swhite06</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">54115 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  </channel>
</rss>

<!-- Page cached by Boost @ 2017-01-25 19:02:17, expires @ 2017-01-26 07:02:17, lifetime 12 hours -->