<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?><rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.epa.gov/feed/10885/rss.xml" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/" xmlns:og="http://ogp.me/ns#" xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#" xmlns:sioc="http://rdfs.org/sioc/ns#" xmlns:sioct="http://rdfs.org/sioc/types#" xmlns:skos="http://www.w3.org/2004/02/skos/core#" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#">
  <channel>
    <title>Enforcement</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/feed/10885/rss.xml</link>
    <description>Updated Enforcement content from the US Environmental Protection Agency</description>
    <language>en</language>
     <atom:link href="https://www.epa.gov/feed/10885/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      <item>
    <title>Reference News Release: United States Reaches Settlement With Meadowvale Dairy of Rock Valley, Iowa, for Clean Water Act Violations</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/enforcement/reference-news-release-united-states-reaches-settlement-meadowvale-dairy-rock-valley</link>
    <description>&lt;div class=&quot;box multi related-info right&quot;&gt;
	&lt;h2 class=&quot;pane-title&quot;&gt;Reference News Release&lt;/h2&gt;

	&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;This is a reference news release copy, posted specially for content linking on this site.&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/newsreleases/epa-doj-state-utah-reach-agreement-salt-lake-county-reduce-polluted-runoff-and-protect&quot;&gt;CLICK HERE to go to the regular EPA news release site.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Release Date: 01/19/2017&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meadowvale Dairy, LLC, has agreed to pay a civil penalty and take actions to prevent illegal discharges to Iowa streams in compliance with the Clean Water Act, officials of the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency and the U.S. Department of Justice announced today. Meadowvale Dairy operates multiple concentrated animal feeding operations in Rock Valley, Iowa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since 2002, the Iowa Department of Natural Resources has identified multiple violations of the dairy’s two National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System permits, which included fish kills in tributaries that lead to the Big Sioux River in 2004 and 2009. State and EPA inspections discovered evidence of additional unauthorized discharges of stormwater runoff into the tributaries in 2013 and 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This settlement sends a clear message that concentrated animal feeding operations must comply with Clean Water Act in order to prevent future discharges into our waters,” said John C. Cruden, Assistant Attorney General for the Justice Department’s Environment and Natural Resources Division. “The agreement requires remedial measures to reduce pollutants and protect aquatic ecosystems in the short term, as well as third party auditing to ensure long-term compliance with the terms of the consent decree and the controlling permits.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The vast majority of animal feeding operations adhere to the law and actively seek to be responsible stewards of the environment,” said Mark Hague, EPA Region 7 regional administrator. “The settlement today helps ensure a level playing field for all operators by holding those who violate environmental regulations accountable.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The scope of the injunctive relief and the size of the civil penalty are a clear signal to Iowa’s CAFOs about the importance of compliance. This settlement demonstrates the Department of Justice&#039;s commitment to enforcing the Clean Water Act as enacted by Congress” said U.S. Attorney for the Northern District of Iowa Kevin Techau.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As outlined in the proposed consent decree lodged today in U.S. District Court for the Northern District of Iowa, in addition to civil penalties Meadowvale Dairy will be required to implement injunctive relief that includes short-term and long-term corrective measures to prevent unpermitted discharges of pollutants into tributaries. Injunctive relief includes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Retain an independent third party to develop and perform an audit, verifying compliance with the requirements of the proposed consent decree.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Comply with all requirements of its National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System permits, including adherence to its Nutrient Management Plan. A Nutrient Management Plan typically outlines management and conservation practices to optimize productivity of the operation while conserving nutrients and protecting the environment. It may include practices such as appropriate manure and fertilizer storage and handling methods, managing the diet of the animals, and/or irrigation practices.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Ensure all production areas are designed, constructed and operated to prevent unpermitted discharges with an exclusion for a 25-year, 24-hour storm event.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;EPA estimates that changes made by Meadowvale required by this proposed settlement will result in a reduction of approximately 200,000 pounds of pollutants discharged annually. These reductions help to protect aquatic ecosystems, decrease sedimentation and improve overall water quality.  The settlement also requires Meadowvale Dairy to pay $160,000 in civil penalties for alleged violations of the Clean Water Act related to mismanagement of animal wastes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meadowvale Dairy operates two NPDES-permitted large concentrated animal feeding operations, confining approximately 10,000 head of cattle on a combined 185 acres in Rock Valley. The operation includes four locations – North Site and South Site (both permitted), a calf barn/hut, and a satellite concrete manure storage structure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The proposed consent decree is subject to a 30-day public comment period and approval by the federal court. Meadowvale Dairy would be required to pay the monetary penalty within 30 days of the court&#039;s approval of the settlement.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jan 2017 13:10:53 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>mnorri03</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">169785 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Consent Decree for Meadowvale Dairy Clean Water Act Settlement</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/enforcement/consent-decree-meadowvale-dairy-clean-water-act-settlement</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;This is the consent decree for Meadowvale Dairy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-347823&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2017-01/documents/meadowvaledairy-cd.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=22042446&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Consent Decree for Meadowvale Dairy (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(47 pp, 22 MB)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Fri, 20 Jan 2017 12:38:50 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>mnorri03</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">169677 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Reference News Release:  Magellan Pipeline Settles Alleged Clean Water Act Violations Related to Spills in Texas, Nebraska and Kansas</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/enforcement/reference-news-release-magellan-pipeline-settles-alleged-clean-water-act-violations</link>
    <description>&lt;div class=&quot;box multi related-info right&quot;&gt;
	&lt;h2 class=&quot;pane-title&quot;&gt;Reference News Release&lt;/h2&gt;

	&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;This is a reference news release copy, posted specially for content linking on this site.&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/newsreleases/search&quot;&gt;CLICK HERE to go to the regular EPA news release site.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;span&gt;CONTACT:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;mailto:press@epa.gov&quot;&gt;press@epa.gov&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;b&gt;FOR IMMEDIATE RELEASE&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	January 19, 2017&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;clearfix&quot;&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;
			&lt;div class=&quot;clearfix&quot;&gt;
				&lt;div&gt;
					&lt;div&gt;
						&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;WASHINGTON&lt;/strong&gt; – The U.S. Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) and the Department of Justice today announced a settlement with Magellan Pipeline Company, L.P., for alleged violations of the Clean Water Act related to gasoline, diesel and jet fuel spills in Texas City, Texas, Nemaha, Neb. and El Dorado, Kan. Magellan has agreed to complete approximately $16 million of injunctive relief across its 11,000-mile pipeline system and pay a $2 million civil penalty.&lt;/p&gt;

						&lt;p&gt;&quot;Fuel spills have real and lasting impacts on clean water for communities,&quot; said Cynthia Giles, Assistant Administrator for EPA&#039;s Office of Enforcement and Compliance Assurance. &quot;Companies need to take the necessary precautions to make sure fuel is transported safely and responsibly. This settlement puts in place important pipeline safety and spill prevention measures that make this industry safer for communities.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;

						&lt;p&gt;“This settlement holds Magellan accountable for multiple petroleum fuel pipeline spills that impacted waterways in three states,” said John C. Cruden, Assistant Attorney General for the Justice Department’s Environment and Natural Resources Division. “The terms of the agreement require Magellan to improve training of its staff and monitoring of its pipeline system’s integrity, and increase public transparency about leaks and responses.”&lt;/p&gt;

						&lt;p&gt;According to a complaint and consent decree filed today in U.S. District Court for the Northern District of Oklahoma, Tulsa, Okla.-based Magellan is responsible for spilling a combined total of approximately 5,177 barrels of petroleum products in three separate incidents. The complaint alleges that Magellan was responsible for the following illegal discharges:&lt;/p&gt;

						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;On Feb. 24, 2011, a Magellan owned 18-inch refined petroleum products pipeline ruptured in an area north of Texas City, Texas, and spilled approximately 482 barrels of gasoline. The spill impacted a local watercourse known as Pierre Bayou. &lt;br /&gt;
								 &lt;/li&gt;
							&lt;li&gt;On Dec. 10, 2011, two of Magellan’s refined petroleum products pipelines were struck by a third-party who was operating heavy machinery while attempting to clear a hedgerow in an agricultural field near the town of Nemaha, Neb. The strikes resulted in the spilling of approximately 650 barrels of diesel fuel from one line, and approximately 655 barrels of jet fuel and 1,529 barrels of gasoline from the other. The spills impacted a local watercourse know as Jarvis Creek. Cleanup efforts are still underway and will be completed as part of the proposed consent decree.&lt;br /&gt;
								 &lt;/li&gt;
							&lt;li&gt;On May 4, 2015, a Magellan owned 10-inch refined petroleum products pipeline ruptured near the City of El Dorado, Kan., and spilled approximately 1,861 barrels of diesel fuel. Diesel fuel form that spill impacted a local watercourse known as Constant Creek.&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The consent decree requires Magellan to: (1) complete an ongoing spill cleanup effort in Nebraska; (2) institute an enhanced annual training program for its third-party damage prevention staff; (3) update and enhance company information resources concerning selective seam corrosion; (4) update its integrity management plan; and (5) create a publicly-accessible web page that will report information about certain types of pipeline releases and Magellan’s responses to them.&lt;/p&gt;

						&lt;p&gt;The requirement to create a publically-accessible web page directly supports EPA’s Next Generation Compliance efforts to expand transparency.&lt;/p&gt;

						&lt;p&gt;The consent decree is subject to a 30-day public comment period and approval by the federal court. Information on how to comment on the consent decree will be available on the Department of Justice’s website: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.justice.gov/enrd/consent-decrees&quot; id=&quot;LPlnk594079&quot;&gt;www.justice.gov/enrd/consent-decrees&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

						&lt;p&gt;To learn more about this settlement:  &lt;a href=&quot;/enforcement/magellan-pipeline-company-lp-clean-water-act-settlement&quot; id=&quot;LPlnk155279&quot;&gt;https://www.epa.gov/enforcement/magellan-pipeline-company-lp-clean-water-act-settlement&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

						&lt;p&gt;For more information about EPA Next Generation Compliance:  &lt;a href=&quot;/compliance/next-generation-compliance&quot; id=&quot;LPlnk635787&quot;&gt;https://www.epa.gov/compliance/next-generation-compliance&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

						&lt;p&gt;Learn more about EPA’s Clean Water Act enforcement:  &lt;a href=&quot;/enforcement/water-enforcement&quot; id=&quot;LPlnk30601&quot;&gt;http://www.epa.gov/enforcement/water-enforcement&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
					&lt;/div&gt;
				&lt;/div&gt;
			&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 19 Jan 2017 17:06:22 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>mnorri03</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">169553 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Consent Decree Magellan Pipeline Company, L.P. </title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/enforcement/consent-decree-magellan-pipeline-company-lp</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;This is the consent decree for Magellan Pipeline Company, L.P. Clean Water Act Settlement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-347471&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2017-01/documents/magellanpipeline-cd.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=2102734&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Consent Decree for Magellan Pipeline Company, L.P.  (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(42 pp, 2 MB)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 19 Jan 2017 16:43:29 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>mnorri03</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">169551 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Reference News Release:  City of Tyler, Texas, Agrees to Extensive Sewer System Upgrades and Operational Improvements to Comply with Clean Water Act</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/enforcement/reference-news-release-city-tyler-texas-agrees-extensive-sewer-system-upgrades-and</link>
    <description>&lt;div class=&quot;box multi related-info right&quot;&gt;
	&lt;h2 class=&quot;pane-title&quot;&gt;Reference News Release&lt;/h2&gt;

	&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;This is a reference news release copy, posted specially for content linking on this site.&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/newsreleases/search&quot;&gt;CLICK HERE to go to the regular EPA news release site.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;01/17/2017&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;clearfix&quot;&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;&lt;span&gt;Contact Information: &lt;/span&gt;

		&lt;div&gt;
			&lt;div class=&quot;clearfix&quot;&gt;
				&lt;div&gt;&lt;span&gt;Jennah Durant and Joe Hubbard&lt;/span&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;mailto:R6Press@epa.gov&quot;&gt;R6Press@epa.gov&lt;/a&gt;)

					&lt;div&gt;214 665-2200&lt;/div&gt;

					&lt;div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;

					&lt;div&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DALLAS&lt;/strong&gt; – (Jan. 17, 2017) Today the U.S. Department of Justice (DOJ) and U.S. Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) announced the city of Tyler, Texas, agreed to significantly upgrade its sanitary sewer system to resolve alleged violations of the federal Clean Water Act (CWA). The city will also undertake extensive operational improvements to its sanitary sewer system and pay a total of $563,000 in civil penalties.&lt;/div&gt;

					&lt;div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;

					&lt;div&gt;DOJ, on behalf of the EPA, and the State of Texas, on behalf of the Texas Commission on Environmental Quality, jointly filed a complaint against the city of Tyler alleging that, since 2005, the city has allowed and continues to allow untreated sewage to overflow from the city’s sanitary sewer system in violation of the CWA and the Texas Water Code. The complaint alleges the city failed to properly operate and maintain its sewer system, resulting in problems including blockages in underground pipes, general system defects and power failures. These problems can impact public health and local water quality by allowing releases of untreated sewage into local waterways and the community. The complaint specifically alleges instances of raw sewage entering into both local waterways and into Tyler residents’ private homes and yards. Many of these sanitary sewer overflows occurred in low-income and minority communities.&lt;/div&gt;

					&lt;div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;

					&lt;div&gt;“The people of Tyler have experienced sewer overflows for the past decade and deserve those conditions to come to an end,” said Acting United States Attorney Brit Featherston. “This agreement ensures that vital infrastructure, required for the very basic of our citizens’ needs, will be upgraded, and the degradation of the city of Tyler’s sewer system will be halted. The agreement’s key provisions will modernize Tyler’s sewer system, substantially reduce the number of sewer overflows and discharges to local waterways, and protect the environment and the health of the citizens of Tyler.”&lt;/div&gt;

					&lt;div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;

					&lt;div&gt;“Providing clean, reliable water service is one of the most important responsibilities cities have to their residents,” said EPA Regional Administrator Ron Curry. “Improvements to the city’s treatment of wastewater has direct benefit to citizens.”&lt;/div&gt;

					&lt;div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;

					&lt;div&gt;To comply with the terms of the settlement and significantly reduce future sanitary sewer overflows, the city must comprehensively assess and improve its sewer system’s physical condition by repairing or replacing damaged assets within a certain time period after their discovery. The city must also analyze sewer system capacity using an updated hydraulic model and undertake a tailored program to implement detailed capacity management, operation and maintenance procedures. The city must keep the public directly informed of its progress when complying with the consent decree by creating a public document repository on the city’s website, where it is required to post any report required by the consent decree and all final EPA-approved plans. The city must also consider, among other things, the location of past sanitary sewer overflows in low income or minority communities when prioritizing the sequence for certain cleaning or remedial work. EPA estimates the combination of these mandated efforts will require the city to spend approximately $65 million over the next 10 years.&lt;/div&gt;

					&lt;div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;

					&lt;div&gt;Tyler’s entire wastewater collection and treatment system includes 690 miles of main lines, 22 lift stations and over 9,000 manholes as part of its sanitary sewer system, which sends untreated wastewater to two wastewater treatment plants. Tyler’s system serves approximately 32,000 customers and 109,000 people.&lt;/div&gt;

					&lt;div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;

					&lt;div&gt;Keeping raw sewage out of the community and the waters of the United States is a national priority for EPA, as sewage overflows can present a significant threat to human health and the environment. These discharges can degrade water quality, spread bacteria and viruses and cause diseases ranging from gastroenteritis to life-threatening conditions such as cholera and dysentery.&lt;/div&gt;

					&lt;div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;

					&lt;div&gt;The settlement, which will be lodged in the U.S. District Court for the Eastern District of Texas, is subject to a federal 30-day public comment period.  The State of Texas also has a required 30-day public comment period. The proposed consent decree can be viewed online at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.justice.gov/enrd/Consent_Decrees.html&quot;&gt;www.justice.gov/enrd/Consent_Decrees.html&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/div&gt;

					&lt;div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;

					&lt;div&gt;More information about EPA’s National Enforcement Initiative: &lt;a href=&quot;/enforcement/national-enforcement-initiative-keeping-raw-sewage-and-contaminated-stormwater-out-our&quot;&gt;https://www.epa.gov/enforcement/national-enforcement-initiative-keeping-raw-sewage-and-contaminated-stormwater-out-our&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

					&lt;div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;

					&lt;div&gt;More information about integrated municipal stormwater and wastewater plans: &lt;a href=&quot;/npdes/integrated-planning-municipal-stormwater-and-wastewater&quot;&gt;https://www.epa.gov/npdes/integrated-planning-municipal-stormwater-and-wastewater&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
				&lt;/div&gt;
			&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2017 21:49:38 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>mnorri03</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">169467 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Consent Decree for The City of Tyler</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/enforcement/consent-decree-city-tyler</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;This is the consent decree for City of Tyler.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-347245&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2017-01/documents/cityoftyler-cd.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=5032464&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Consent Decree for The City of Tyler (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(146 pp, 5 MB)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2017 21:45:07 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>mnorri03</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">169465 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Tauber Oil Company Stipulation of Settlement and Order</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/enforcement/tauber-oil-company-stipulation-settlement-and-order</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;This is the stipulation and order for Tauber Oil Company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-347199&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2017-01/documents/tauberoilcompany-stipulationorder.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=1085749&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Tauber Oil Company Stipulation of Settlement and Order (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(8 pp, 1 MB)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2017 20:31:41 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>mnorri03</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">169445 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Reference News Release:  Bandit Industries, Inc., Settles Alleged Clean Air Act Violations for Manufacturing and Selling Wood Processing Equipment That Failed to Meet Emissions Standards</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/enforcement/reference-news-release-bandit-industries-inc-settles-alleged-clean-air-act-violations</link>
    <description>&lt;div class=&quot;box multi related-info right&quot;&gt;
	&lt;h2 class=&quot;pane-title&quot;&gt;Reference News Release&lt;/h2&gt;

	&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;This is a reference news release copy, posted specially for content linking on this site.&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/newsreleases/search/subject/compliance-and-enforcement&quot;&gt;CLICK HERE to go to the regular EPA news release site.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;07/20/2016&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;span&gt;Tricia Lynn (News media only)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;mailto:lynn.tricia@epa.gov&quot;&gt;lynn.tricia@epa.gov&lt;/a&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
	(202) 564-2615&lt;br /&gt;
	(202) 564-4355&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;clearfix&quot;&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;
			&lt;div class=&quot;clearfix&quot;&gt;
				&lt;div&gt;
					&lt;div&gt;
						&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;WASHINGTON — &lt;/strong&gt;The U.S. Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) today announced a settlement with Bandit Industries, Inc., for alleged violations of the Clean Air Act for selling non-road diesel engines and equipment used to process wood and waste that do not meet federal standards. Bandit, based in Remus, Michigan, will pay a $3 million civil penalty. &lt;/p&gt;

						&lt;p&gt;Bandit is a manufacturer of self-powered, industrial-strength wood and waste processing equipment, such as wood chippers. The complaint alleges that Bandit sold non-road diesel-fueled engines and equipment that were neither covered by the certificates of conformity required by the Clean Air Act, nor exempt from that certification requirement under the requirements of the Transition Program for Equipment Manufacturers (TPEM). Additionally, as alleged, Bandit built and sold equipment with engines using older emission standards in exceedance of normal inventory restrictions, commonly referred to as “stockpiling.”&lt;/p&gt;

						&lt;p&gt;To meet current diesel-fuel emissions standards, equipment manufacturers generally modify their equipment designs to accommodate engines with additional and improved emissions control devices. In the TPEM program, EPA adopted transition provisions for equipment manufacturers to provide flexibility to selectively delay compliance with current emissions standards for up to seven years. The complaint alleges that Bandit did not transition to the current emissions standards in time, and sold equipment with older noncompliant engines, creating a competitive advantage over manufacturers offering compliant products.&lt;/p&gt;

						&lt;p&gt;Use of equipment that does not meet current more stringent emissions standards increases emissions of particulate matter, among other pollutants. Particulate matter has been linked to a range of serious respiratory health problems that include premature mortality, aggravation of respiratory and cardiovascular disease, aggravated asthma, acute respiratory symptoms including aggravated coughing and difficult or painful breathing, chronic bronchitis and decreased lung function that can be experienced as shortness of breath. Symptoms of immunological effects such as wheezing and increased allergenicity have also been observed. In addition, EPA’s Clean Air Scientific Advisory Committee has concluded that diesel exhaust is likely to be carcinogenic to humans. &lt;/p&gt;

						&lt;p&gt;A stipulation of judgment and a complaint were simultaneously filed in the Western District of Michigan. Since there is no injunctive relief in the stipulation, there is no public comment period.&lt;/p&gt;
						For more information on this settlement:  &lt;a href=&quot;/enforcement/bandit-industries-inc-clean-air-act-settlement&quot;&gt;https://www.epa.gov/enforcement/bandit-industries-inc-clean-air-act-settlement&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
				&lt;/div&gt;
			&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2017 17:43:12 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>mnorri03</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">169399 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Reference News Release:  Tauber Oil Company Settles Allegations of Selling Unregistered Fuel Additive in Violation of Clean Air Act</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/enforcement/reference-news-release-tauber-oil-company-settles-allegations-selling-unregistered-fuel</link>
    <description>&lt;div class=&quot;box multi related-info right&quot;&gt;
	&lt;h2 class=&quot;pane-title&quot;&gt;Reference News Release&lt;/h2&gt;

	&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;This is a reference news release copy, posted specially for content linking on this site.&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/newsreleases/search&quot;&gt;CLICK HERE to go to the regular EPA news release site.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;01/18/2017&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;clearfix&quot;&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
		&lt;div class=&quot;clearfix&quot;&gt;
			&lt;div&gt;&lt;span&gt;Contact Information: &lt;/span&gt;

				&lt;div&gt;
					&lt;div class=&quot;clearfix&quot;&gt;
						&lt;div&gt;&lt;span&gt;Tricia Lynn&lt;/span&gt; (&lt;a href=&quot;mailto:lynn.tricia@epa.gov&quot;&gt;lynn.tricia@epa.gov&lt;/a&gt;)

							&lt;div&gt;(202) 564-2615&lt;/div&gt;

							&lt;div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;

							&lt;div&gt;&lt;strong&gt;WASHINGTON -- &lt;/strong&gt;The U.S. Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) today announced a settlement with Tauber Oil Company, resolving alleged Clean Air Act violations stemming from the company&#039;s sale of a fuel additive that was not registered with the EPA. Tauber stopped selling the unregistered fuel additive and will pay a $700,000 civil penalty.&lt;/div&gt;

							&lt;div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;

							&lt;div&gt;The settlement resolves claims that Tauber produced a fuel additive called Mixed Alcohol by blending together various alcohol streams, then sold approximately 1.9 million gallons of Mixed Alcohol without first registering it as a fuel additive with the EPA or meeting the Clean Air Act requirement that fuel and fuel additives are substantially similar to what was used in the certification of motor vehicles. Tauber is a manufacturer and marketer of petroleum and petrochemical products based in Houston, Texas.&lt;/div&gt;

							&lt;div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;

							&lt;div&gt;The Clean Air Act establishes fuel quality and emissions standards, including requirements relating to the registration and sale of fuel additives, to reduce air pollution from motor vehicles, like passenger cars. These requirements provide EPA with information on fuel additive composition to prevent potential increases in harmful pollutants that may result either directly from the combustion of additive-containing fuel or indirectly due to the degradation of vehicle emission control systems that additive-containing fuel can cause.  &lt;/div&gt;

							&lt;div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;

							&lt;div&gt;The Clean Air Act requires that a fuel additive manufacturer must register the fuel additive with the EPA before selling, offering for sale, or introducing the additive into commerce. Also, the Clean Air Act makes it unlawful for fuel additive manufacturers to first introduce into commerce, or to increase the concentration in use of, any fuel or fuel additive in motor vehicles that is not substantially similar to any fuel or fuel additive utilized in engine certification. &lt;/div&gt;

							&lt;div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;

							&lt;div&gt;The stipulation of settlement and order, lodged in the U.S. District Court for the Southern District of Texas, will undergo a 30-day public comment period and approval by the federal court. Information about submitting a public comment is available at:  &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.justice.gov/enrd/consent-decrees&quot;&gt;https://www.justice.gov/enrd/consent-decrees&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

							&lt;div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;

							&lt;div&gt;For more information on this settlement: &lt;a href=&quot;/enforcement/tauber-oil-company-clean-air-act-settlement&quot;&gt;https://www.epa.gov/enforcement/tauber-oil-company-clean-air-act-settlement&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
						&lt;/div&gt;
					&lt;/div&gt;
				&lt;/div&gt;
			&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2017 17:40:27 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>mnorri03</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">169397 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  </channel>
</rss>

<!-- Page cached by Boost @ 2017-01-26 03:58:10, expires @ 2017-01-26 15:58:10, lifetime 12 hours -->