<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?><rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.epa.gov/feed/105729/rss.xml" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/" xmlns:og="http://ogp.me/ns#" xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#" xmlns:sioc="http://rdfs.org/sioc/ns#" xmlns:sioct="http://rdfs.org/sioc/types#" xmlns:skos="http://www.w3.org/2004/02/skos/core#" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#">
  <channel>
    <title>Drinking Water Contaminants – Standards and Regulations</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/feed/105729/rss.xml</link>
    <description>Updated Drinking Water Contaminants – Standards and Regulations content from the US Environmental Protection Agency</description>
    <language>en</language>
     <atom:link href="https://www.epa.gov/feed/105729/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      <item>
    <title>Federal Register Notices for National Drinking Water Advisory Council (NDWAC) Lead and Copper Rule Working Group (LCRWG) Meetings</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/dwstandardsregulations/federal-register-notices-national-drinking-water-advisory-council-ndwac-lead</link>
    <description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/dwstandardsregulations/lead-and-copper-rule-long-term-revisions&quot;&gt;Link to the LCR Long-Term Revisions Home Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;The NDWAC Lead and Copper Rule Working Group was formed to provide advice to EPA in considering Long-Term Revisions to the Lead and Copper Rule. &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gpo.gov/fdsys/pkg/FR-2015-06-17/html/2015-14938.htm&quot;&gt;LCRWG Meeting- June 24-25, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gpo.gov/fdsys/pkg/FR-2015-06-08/html/2015-13677.htm&quot;&gt;LCRWG Webinar- June 22, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gpo.gov/fdsys/search/pagedetails.action?st=FRL%E2%80%939925%E2%80%9326%E2%80%93OW&amp;amp;granuleId=2015-07112&amp;amp;packageId=FR-2015-03-30&quot;&gt;LCRWG Meeting- April 23-24, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gpo.gov/fdsys/search/pagedetails.action?browsePath=2015%2F01%2F01-15/%2F5%2FEnvironmental+Protection+Agency&amp;amp;granuleId=2014-30495&amp;amp;packageId=FR-2015-01-15&amp;amp;fromBrowse=true&quot;&gt;LCRWG Meeting- February 5-6, 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://federalregister.gov/a/2014-24096&quot;&gt;LCRWG Meeting- November 12-13, 2014&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://federalregister.gov/a/2014-20274&quot;&gt;LCRWG Meeting- September 18-19, 2014&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://federalregister.gov/a/2014-10677&quot;&gt;LCRWG Meeting- May 29-30, 2014&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://federalregister.gov/a/2014-04891&quot;&gt;LCRWG Meeting- March 25-26, 2014&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2017 13:55:36 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>rperkins</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">169361 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Lead Modeling Peer Review</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/dwstandardsregulations/lead-modeling-peer-review</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;EPA is initiating a peer review of draft scientific modeling approaches to inform EPA’s evaluation of potential health-based benchmarks for lead in drinking water. The agency is seeking nominations of peer reviewers, providing draft charge questions and including a report related to draft scientific modeling approaches. The focus of the peer review will be on gathering expert scientific input on the use of draft modeling approaches for developing health-based benchmarks for lead in drinking water. The report will discuss modeling approaches, propose input parameters, and review various exposure scenarios for the peer reviewers to consider.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Model values presented in the draft report are included to better illustrate the draft approaches for the peer reviewers. EPA will not be asking the peer reviewers to select a specific value or to provide input on the specific role for a health-based value in proposed revisions to the Lead and Copper Rule (LCR).  EPA will consider the specific role for a health-based value in the proposed revisions to the LCR after the peer review of the modeling effort has been completed. EPA expects to propose revisions to the Lead and Copper Rule in 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-345481&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2017-01/documents/final_drinking_water_pag_frn_1.11.17_0.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=235117&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Pre-Publication Federal Register Notice: Request for Nominations for Peer Reviewers and for Public Comment on Peer Review Materials to Inform the Derivation of a Water Concentration Value for Lead in Drinking Water (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(8 pp, 235 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-345485&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2017-01/documents/lead_in_drinking_water_modeling_external_peer_review_charge_questions_final.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=178957&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Draft Charge Questions: Lead in Drinking Water Modeling External Peer Review  (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(3 pp, 179 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-345501&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2017-01/documents/report_proposed_modeling_approaches_for_a_health_based_benchmark_for_lead_in_drinking_water_final_0.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=1956770&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Report: Proposed Modeling Approaches for a Health Based Benchmark for Lead in Drinking Water (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(82 pp, 2 MB)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 12 Jan 2017 16:47:21 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cwadling</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">168905 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Federal Register Notice - Use of Lead Free Pipes, Fittings, Fixtures, Solder and Flux for Drinking Water</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/dwstandardsregulations/federal-register-notice-use-lead-free-pipes-fittings-fixtures-solder-and-flux</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;The EPA Administrator, Gina McCarthy, signed the following proposed rule on 1/4/2017, and EPA is submitting it for publication in the Federal Register (FR). While we have taken steps to ensure the accuracy of this Internet version of the proposed rule, it is not the official version of the proposed rule for purposes of public comment. Please refer to the official version in a forthcoming FR publication, which will appear on the Government Printing Office’s FDsys website (https://www.gpo.gov/fdsys/). It will also appear on Regulations.gov (https://www.regulations.gov/) in Docket No. EPA-HQ-OW-2015-0680. Once the official version of this document is published in the FR, this version will be removed from the Internet and replaced with a link to the official version.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-343183&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2017-01/documents/lead_free_proposed_rule_pre-pub.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=289030&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Proposed Rule Pre-publication Version - Use of Lead Free Pipes, Fittings, Fixtures, Solder and Flux for Drinking Water (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(69 pp, 289 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jan 2017 13:11:53 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>rperkins</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">168263 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Frequent Questions and Answers About the Proposed Lead Free Rule</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/dwstandardsregulations/frequent-questions-and-answers-about-proposed-lead-free-rule</link>
    <description>&lt;h2&gt;To whom does this rule apply?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This rule would apply to anyone who manufactures or uses plumbing materials (e.g. water systems, plumbers, construction and renovation companies), as well as anyone who sells or distributes these materials, such as plumbing material wholesalers, distributors, and re-sellers, as well as retailers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Why did EPA lower the amount of lead allowed in plumbing products?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA is issuing this proposal based on the Reduction of Lead in Drinking Water Act, which Congress enacted in 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;How long is the comment period for this proposal?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA will be accepting comments for 90 days from the publication date of this proposed regulation.  You can submit your comments through Regulations.gov.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;When will manufacturers be required to ensure their plumbing products are below the standard?  &lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pipes, fittings and fixtures have been required to meet the 0.25% definition of lead free since January 2014 as required by Congress in the Reduction of Lead in Drinking Water Act.  Today’s proposal would require labeling of certain plumbing products and product certification to communicate to consumers which products are designed for use in drinking water systems.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 22 Dec 2016 14:36:46 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>rperkins</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">167717 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Lead and Copper Rule Revisions White Paper</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/dwstandardsregulations/lead-and-copper-rule-revisions-white-paper</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;The LCR Revisions White Paper provides examples of regulatory options to improve the existing rule. The paper highlights key challenges, opportunities, and analytical issues presented by these options. Options include lead service line replacement, improving optimal corrosion control treatment requirements, consideration of a health-based benchmark, the potential role of point-of-use filters, clarifications or strengthening of tap sampling requirements, increased transparency, and public education requirements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-326927&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-10/documents/508_lcr_revisions_white_paper_final_10.26.16.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=680976&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Lead and Copper Rule Revisions White Paper (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(18 pp, 681 K, 
  October 26, 2016)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 26 Oct 2016 13:15:43 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cwadling</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">163509 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Perchlorate Peer Review Frequent Questions  </title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/dwstandardsregulations/perchlorate-peer-review-frequent-questions</link>
    <description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/dwstandardsregulations/perchlorate-drinking-water&quot;&gt;Return to Perchlorate Home Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Why is EPA conducting a peer review?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div&gt;EPA will ask peer reviewers to comment on products that the agency will use to derive a Maximum Contaminant Level Goal (MCLG) for perchlorate. The MCLG is a non-enforceable goal defined under the Safe Drinking Water Act (SDWA) as “the level at which no known or anticipated adverse effects on the health of persons occur and which allows an adequate margin of safety.” The MCLG is one of the considerations in developing the enforceable maximum contaminant level (MCL) for a regulated contaminant.&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;EPA believes that peer review is an important component of the scientific process. The critical feedback, suggestions, and new ideas provided by the peer reviewers stimulate creative thought, strengthen the interpretation of the reviewed material, and confer credibility on the product. The peer review objective is to provide advice to EPA on steps that will yield a highly credible scientific product that is supported by the scientific community.&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Where can I find the review products?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div&gt;All documents in the docket are listed on the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.regulations.gov/&quot;&gt;http://www.regulations.gov&lt;/a&gt; website under Docket ID Numbers EPA-HQ-OW-2016-0438 and EPA-HQ-OW-2016-0439.&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Can I provide comments on the review products?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div&gt;Yes. The public will have an opportunity to review and comment on charge questions and the draft reports undergoing review. Additionally, we intend to allow for people to make brief statements during the peer review meeting. Also, any Safe Drinking Water Act regulation on perchlorate will be subject to public notice and comment. &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Are there other reports that will be peer reviewed before EPA proposes a regulation?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div&gt;Yes after the peer review of the Biologically Based Dose-Response (BBDR) report is complete, the Agency plans to conduct peer review of another report that describes methodologies for deriving a Maximum Contaminant Level Goal (MCLG Report) using the BBDR model. EPA plans to consider the peer review comments on the BBDR model before we present this next MCLG report for peer review. We expect peer review of the MCLG Report will take place in the spring of 2017.&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;When will EPA establish a national drinking water standard for perchlorate?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div&gt;EPA will consider public comments and peer reviewer comments submitted in accordance with the Federal Register notice when finalizing the peer review products. After the peer review is complete, EPA will take the next appropriate steps.&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2016 13:08:21 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>rperkins</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">161343 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Perchlorate in Drinking Water Frequent Questions</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/dwstandardsregulations/perchlorate-drinking-water-frequent-questions</link>
    <description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/dwstandardsregulations/perchlorate-drinking-water&quot;&gt;Return to Perchlorate Home page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;On this page:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#where-found&quot;&gt;Where is perchlorate found?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#why-health-concern&quot;&gt;Why is perchlorate in drinking water a health concern?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

	&lt;div&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#how-gets-drinking&quot;&gt;How does perchlorate get into my drinking water?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

	&lt;div&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#how-else-exposed&quot;&gt;Besides drinking water, how else can people be exposed to perchlorate?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#how-know-in-water&quot;&gt;How do I know if perchlorate is in my water?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#can-be-boiled&quot;&gt;Can perchlorate be boiled out of my water?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#how-remove&quot;&gt;How does a utility reduce/remove perchlorate?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#well-water&quot;&gt;I get my tap water from a private well. How can I find out if perchlorate is in my water?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#why-regulate&quot;&gt;Why did EPA decide to regulate perchlorate?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#has-safe-level- determined&quot;&gt;Has a safe level of exposure for perchlorate been established?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;where-found&quot; name=&quot;where-found&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;Where is perchlorate found?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div&gt;Perchlorate occurs naturally in arid states in the Southwest United States, in nitrate fertilizer deposits in Chile, and in potash ore in the United States and Canada. It also forms naturally in the atmosphere. Perchlorate can be manufactured and used as an industrial chemical and can be found in rocket propellant, explosives, fireworks and road flares. It has also been found in some public drinking water systems and in food.&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;why-health-concern&quot; name=&quot;why-health-concern&quot;&gt;Why is perchlorate in drinking water a health concern?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div&gt;Perchlorate can disrupt the normal function of the thyroid gland in both children and adults. In adults, the thyroid plays an important role in metabolism, making and storing hormones that help regulate the heart rate, blood pressure, body temperature, and the rate at which food is converted into energy. In fetuses and infants, thyroid hormones are critical for normal growth and development of the central nervous system. Perchlorate can interfere with the human body&#039;s ability to absorb iodine into the thyroid gland which is a critical element in the production of thyroid hormones.&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;how-gets-drinking&quot; name=&quot;how-gets-drinking&quot;&gt;How does perchlorate get into my drinking water?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div&gt;Perchlorate dissolves easily, is relatively stable and is mobile in water. While it has often been detected in water supplies in close proximity to sites where solid rocket fuel is manufactured or used, there are also locations in the United States lacking a clearly defined source.&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;how-else-exposed&quot; name=&quot;how-else-exposed&quot;&gt;Besides drinking water, how else can people be exposed to perchlorate?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div&gt;People are exposed to perchlorate primarily through eating contaminated food or drinking water. The Food and Drug Administration (FDA) Total Diet Study combines nationwide sampling and analysis of hundreds of food items along with national surveys of food intake to develop comprehensive dietary exposure estimates for a variety of demographic groups in the U.S. The complete set of FDA perchlorate data can be found here: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fda.gov/Food/FoodborneIllnessContaminants/ChemicalContaminants/ucm077685.htm&quot;&gt;http://www.fda.gov/Food/FoodborneIllnessContaminants/ChemicalContaminants/ucm077685.htm&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;how-know-in-water&quot; name=&quot;how-know-in-water&quot;&gt;How do I know if perchlorate is in my water?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div&gt;Contact your local water supplier to find out if perchlorate is in  your drinking water and what steps your utility is taking to reduce your exposure. If you don&#039;t know who your local water supplier is, the information should be included in your latest water bill. &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;can-be-boiled&quot; name=&quot;can-be-boiled&quot;&gt;Can perchlorate be boiled out of my water?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div&gt;No, perchlorate cannot be removed by heating or boiling water.&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;how-remove&quot; name=&quot;how-remove&quot;&gt;How does a utility reduce/remove perchlorate?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div&gt;A number of options are available to drinking water systems to lower concentrations of perchlorate in the drinking water supply. In some cases, drinking water systems may be able to reduce concentrations of perchlorate by closing contaminated wells or changing rates of blending of water sources.&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;Perchlorate can be removed using a number of advanced treatment technologies. Each technology has advantages and disadvantages depending on the level of perchlorate present in the source water, removal goals, other water quality parameters, competing treatment objectives, and treatment waste disposal options. Regenerable and single-pass ion exchange, reverse osmosis, and fixed- and fluidized-bed biological treatment can all remove perchlorate from drinking water sources.&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;These treatment technologies are used by some public water systems today and should be carefully designed and maintained to ensure that they are effective for treating perchlorate. &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;well-water&quot; name=&quot;well-water&quot;&gt;I get my tap water from a private well. How can I find out if perchlorate is in my water?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div&gt;If you are concerned about the possibility of perchlorate in your drinking water and you are served by a private well, EPA recommends testing your drinking water. Approved laboratories can analyze a sample of your water to determine whether perchlorate is present and at what concentrations. More information about private wells can be found here: &lt;a href=&quot;/privatewells&quot;&gt;http://www.epa.gov/privatewells&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;why-regulate&quot; name=&quot;why-regulate&quot;&gt;Why did EPA decide to regulate perchlorate?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div&gt;The Safe Drinking Water Act (SDWA) requires that once every five years, EPA issue a Contaminant Candidate List (CCL). The CCL is a list of contaminants that are currently not subject to any proposed or promulgated national primary drinking water regulations, but are known or anticipated to occur in public water systems. Perchlorate was a part of CCL1 (1998), CCL2 (2005) and CCL3 (2009). In addition, EPA issues an Unregulated Contaminant Monitoring Rule (UCMR) to identify up to 30 unregulated contaminants to be monitored by large public water systems (PWSs) and a subset of small PWSs across the U.S. The UCMR provides EPA and other interested parties with nationally representative data on the occurrence of particular contaminants in drinking water.  This data set lets the Agency assess the number of people potentially being exposed and provides an estimate of the levels of that exposure. Perchlorate was included in UCMR 1 (2001- 2005).  &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;After issuing a CCL, EPA must decide whether to regulate at least five or more contaminants on the list (called Regulatory Determination). A Regulatory Determination is a formal decision on whether (or not) EPA should initiate a rulemaking process to develop a regulation for a specific contaminant or group of contaminants. In 2011, EPA announced its decision to regulate perchlorate under the Safe Drinking Water Act (SDWA). Specifically, EPA determined that perchlorate meets SDWA&#039;s criteria for regulating a contaminant--that is, perchlorate may have an adverse effect on the health of persons; perchlorate is known to occur or there is a substantial likelihood that perchlorate will occur in public water systems with a frequency and at levels of public health concern; and in the sole judgment of the Administrator, regulation of perchlorate in drinking water systems presents a meaningful opportunity for health risk reduction for person served by public water systems.&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;             &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;has-safe-level- determined&quot; id=&quot;has-safe-level- determined&quot;&gt;Has a safe level of exposure for perchlorate been established?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div&gt;EPA has not yet established a maximum contaminant level goal for perchlorate. The MCLG is the maximum level of a contaminant in drinking water at which no known or anticipated adverse effect on the health of persons would occur, allowing an adequate margin of safety. On February 11, 2011, EPA determined that perchlorate meets the Safe Drinking Water Act criteria for regulation as a contaminant. The Agency found that perchlorate may have an adverse effect on the health of persons and is known to occur in public drinking water systems with a frequency and at levels that present a public health concern. Since that time, EPA has been reviewing the best available scientific data on a range of issues related to perchlorate in drinking water including its occurrence, treatment technologies, analytical methods and the costs and benefits of potential standards.&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;There also have been state actions on perchlorate such as standards, guidelines and advisories. In 2006, Massachusetts adopted a drinking water standard for perchlorate of 2 µg/L, and in 2007, California promulgated a standard of 6 µg/L. Twelve other states have established non-enforceable guidance, action or advisory levels. Depending on the state, a particular level may require a public water system to notify the public, serve as a screening tool for further action, or guide clean-up actions.&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;Customers that are served by a public water system can contact their local water supplier and ask for information on perchlorate in their drinking water.&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Mon, 26 Sep 2016 18:56:35 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>rperkins</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">161181 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Hydrant Sampler</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/dwstandardsregulations/hydrant-sampler</link>
    <description>&lt;div class=&quot;box multi related-info right&quot;&gt;
	&lt;h2 class=&quot;pane-title&quot;&gt;Related Information&lt;/h2&gt;

	&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/dwstandardsregulations/optimization-program-drinking-water-systems&quot;&gt;Optimization program for drinking water systems: Area-Wide Optimization Program (AWOP)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hydrant sampler allows for the efficient collection of samples throughout a water distribution system. The tool provides drinking water systems an approach to assess distribution system water quality which can lead to an increased level of public health protection.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When collecting water quality samples, indoor taps (that is, at a residence or business) are not always available or accessible in some areas of the distribution system, so hydrants must be used. Dry barrel hydrants, the most common type of hydrant, are designed to be operated with their valves fully open. The hydrant sampler was designed to allow the hydrant valve to be fully open, while collecting samples in a controlled, safe manner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, determining an appropriate time to flush the service line prior to sampling for indoor taps can be challenging when sampling because the configuration of the premise plumbing is often unknown. However, utilization of the hydrant sampler allows samplers to determine the appropriate flush time because the length and diameter of the hydrant service line may be easily estimated. Once the volume of line has been estimated, the flush time can be determined based on the 20 gallon per minute flow regulator on the hydrant sampler.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hydrant sampler may be constructed out of common plumbing materials that can be purchased at a local hardware store.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe name=&quot;How to use a Hydrant Sampler&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/4RWrrMxbwac?rel=0&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; id=&quot;How to use a Hydrant Sampler&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-279401&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-04/documents/hydrant-sampler-parts-list.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=259238&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Hydrant Sampler Parts List (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(3 pp, 259 K, 
  April 2016, 
  815-B-16-002)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-283531&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-05/documents/hydrant-sampler-procedure.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=730693&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Hydrant Sampler Procedure (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(7 pp, 731 K, 
  May 2016, 
  815-B-16-005)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 26 Apr 2016 18:28:04 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>twells03</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">147641 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Do You Wear Contact Lenses?</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/dwstandardsregulations/do-you-wear-contact-lenses</link>
    <description>&lt;h2&gt;There&#039;s something you should know…&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More than 34 million people in the U.S. and 71 million people in the world wear contact lenses. Contact lens wearers include athletes, actors, musicians, and people in occupations where glasses get in the way. Some people wear contacts for cosmetic reasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#whatis&quot;&gt;What is Acanthamoeba?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#symptoms&quot;&gt;What are the symptoms of Acanthamoeba eye infection?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#howdo&quot;&gt;How do you get Acanthamoeba on your contact lenses?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#whocan&quot;&gt;Who can get infected?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#cantreat&quot;&gt;Can Acanthamoeba eye infection be treated?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#canprevent&quot;&gt;How can I prevent an Acanthamoeba eye infection?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#epa&quot;&gt;What is EPA doing about Acanthamoeba?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#guidance&quot;&gt;Additional Materials and Guidance&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;whatis&quot;&gt;What is Acanthamoeba?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pronounced A·can·tha·moe·ba, acanthamoeba is a microbe that is very common in the environment, including in tap water. It has two forms: the trophozoite and the cyst. The infective form is the trophozoite, which can change into a cyst and survive a long time. These trophozoites and cysts can stick to the surface of your contact lenses and then infect your eye.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;symptoms&quot;&gt;What are the symptoms of Acanthamoeba eye infection?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Symptoms include severe pain in the eye, the sensation of a foreign body in the eye, and a whitish halo at the periphery of the eye. The infection cal last weeks to months, and it never fully heals despite treatment. See your doctor immediately if you experience any of these symptoms. You can locate a contact lens doctor by visiting the website for the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.contactlensdocs.com/&quot;&gt;Contact Lens Association of Ophthalmologists&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;!-- EPA Exit Link Disclaimer Begin --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;howdo&quot;&gt;How do you get Acanthamoeba on your contact lenses?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Acanthamoeba gets on your lens when you use contaminated or homemade lens solutions to rinse or store your lenses. Eye infections often result when the microbe attaches to the surface of the lens and the contact case. You can also get infected when you swim while wearing your contact lenses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;whocan&quot;&gt;Who can get infected?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Anyone who wears contact lenses and does not use proper lens care.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Teens who share and swap their colored lenses.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;People who use homemade saline solutions for contact lenses.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;People who do not disinfect their contact lenses.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;People who use saliva to wet their contacts.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;People who buy contacts at beach shops and flea markets without going to the eye doctor for a prescription.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;cantreat&quot;&gt;Can Acanthamoeba eye infection be treated?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This infection is difficult to treat. A doctor can successfully treat it with a combination of topical ointments such as Brolene and PHMB. You can locate a contact lens doctor by visiting the website for the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.contactlensdocs.com/&quot;&gt;Contact Lens Association of Ophthalmologists&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;!-- EPA Exit Link Disclaimer Begin --&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;canprevent&quot;&gt;How can I prevent an Acanthamoeba eye infection?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Practice good personal hygiene when handling your contact lenses.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Remind young contact lens wearers about proper lens handling.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Clean, rinse, and disinfect lenses with commercially made sterile solutions before placing them in the eyes.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Clean lens cases with commercially made sterile solutions.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Don’t use tap water, homemade solutions, and other non-sterile solutions to disinfect and store contacts.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Don’t wet lenses with saliva.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Follow manufacturer instructions in rinsing and storing contact lenses.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Don’t swim while wearing your contacts.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Don’t trade, share, or borrow another person’s lenses.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Replace lenses and lens cases as often as possible.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Only wear contact lenses prescribed by an eye care professional.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;epa&quot;&gt;What is EPA doing about Acanthamoeba?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have issued a guidance for vision care and health care providers on Acanthamoeba in contact lens wearers. An EPA fact sheet also provides condensed information for public awareness on Acanthamoeba.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;guidance&quot;&gt;Additional Materials and Guidance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cdc.gov/parasites/acanthamoeba/&quot;&gt;Centers for Disease Control (CDC) has good information on acanthanmoeba&lt;/a&gt;, including frequent questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Guidance Documents&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;“&lt;a href=&quot;http://nepis.epa.gov/Exe/ZyNET.exe/20003KD0.txt?ZyActionD=ZyDocument&amp;amp;Client=EPA&amp;amp;Index=2000%20Thru%202005&amp;amp;Docs=&amp;amp;Query=Health%20Effects%20Support%20Document%20&amp;amp;Time=&amp;amp;EndTime=&amp;amp;SearchMethod=2&amp;amp;TocRestrict=n&amp;amp;Toc=&amp;amp;TocEntry=&amp;amp;QField=&amp;amp;QFieldYear=&amp;amp;QFieldMonth=&amp;amp;QFieldDay=&amp;amp;UseQField=&amp;amp;IntQFieldOp=0&amp;amp;ExtQFieldOp=0&amp;amp;XmlQuery=&amp;amp;File=D%3A%5CZYFILES%5CINDEX%20DATA%5C00THRU05%5CTXT%5C00000007%5C20003KD0.txt&amp;amp;User=ANONYMOUS&amp;amp;Password=anonymous&amp;amp;SortMethod=f%3Atitle&amp;amp;MaximumDocuments=15&amp;amp;FuzzyDegree=-1&amp;amp;ImageQuality=r85g16/r85g16/x150y150g16/i500&amp;amp;Display=hpfr&amp;amp;DefSeekPage=x&amp;amp;SearchBack=ZyActionE&amp;amp;Back=ZyActionS&amp;amp;BackDesc=Results%20page&amp;amp;MaximumPages=1&amp;amp;ZyEntry=1&amp;amp;SeekPage=x&quot;&gt;Health Effects Support Document for Acanthamoeba&lt;/a&gt;” (EPA-822-R-03-012)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;“Acanthamoeba Guidance Document” (EPA-822-B-04-001)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Fact Sheets&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;“Acanthamoeba: What Vision Care and Health Care Providers Should Know” (EPA-822-F-04-003)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;“Lo que deben saber quienes cuidan de la vista y de la salud” (EPA-822-F-04-004)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Brochures for the Public&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;“Preventing Acanthamoeba Eye Infection in Contact Lens Wearers” (EPA-822-F-04-005)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;“Do You Wear Contact Lenses? There’s Something You Should Know” (EPA-822-F-04-006)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;“¿Usas Lentes de Contacto? Hay Algo Que Debes Saber” (EPA-822-F-04-007)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Mon, 30 Nov 2015 14:04:38 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>rkearney</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">127531 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  </channel>
</rss>

<!-- Page cached by Boost @ 2017-01-25 16:28:25, expires @ 2017-01-26 04:28:25, lifetime 12 hours -->