<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?><rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.epa.gov/feed/127871/rss.xml" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/" xmlns:og="http://ogp.me/ns#" xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#" xmlns:sioc="http://rdfs.org/sioc/ns#" xmlns:sioct="http://rdfs.org/sioc/types#" xmlns:skos="http://www.w3.org/2004/02/skos/core#" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#">
  <channel>
    <title>Lead Designations</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/feed/127871/rss.xml</link>
    <description>Updated Lead Designations content from the US Environmental Protection Agency</description>
    <language>en</language>
     <atom:link href="https://www.epa.gov/feed/127871/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      <item>
    <title>2008 Lead Standards - Tribal Recommendations and EPA Responses</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/lead-designations/2008-lead-standards-tribal-recommendations-and-epa-responses</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;Some tribes submitted an initial round of recommendations to the EPA for lead attainment and nonattainment in 2009. Some tribes submitted additional recommendations in 2010 based on more recent or new monitoring data. Those recommendations and the EPA&#039;s responses are presented below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The EPA completed lead designations in two rounds. In the first round, the EPA designated as &quot;nonattainment&quot; any area that violated the 2008 lead standards based on data from 2007 - 2009.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The EPA took an additional year to make final designations decisions for all other areas of the country to allow additional lead air quality data to be collected and evaluated. No tribal areas are in nonattainment. State information is available on the &lt;a href=&quot;/lead-designations/2008-lead-standards-state-recommendations-and-epa-responses&quot;&gt;State Recommendations&lt;/a&gt; page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://ntec.org/&quot;&gt;National Tribal Environmental Council&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt; and that Tribal Council&#039;s workgroup, The National Designation &amp;amp; Implementation Work Group have been addressing tribal issues with respect to the designation process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The documents listed below are tribes&#039; responses to EPA&#039;s request for recommendations on the designation of areas for the lead standard. These responses are provided here in PDF format for INFORMATIONAL PURPOSES ONLY and do not represent EPA&#039;s views on the appropriateness or adequacy of a tribe&#039;s recommendations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The quality of these PDF files are quite variable, and are the result of the quality of the documents provided by the tribes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tribal recommendations received by EPA and EPA&#039;s Response&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table summary=&quot;This table lists documents related to recommendations and designations for states and tribes within the region.&quot;&gt;&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;Tribe&lt;/th&gt;
			&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
			&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td scope=&quot;row&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/lead-designations/lead-designations-fond-du-lac-band-lake-superior-chippewa-tribal-recommendations&quot;&gt;Fond du Lac Band of Lake Superior Chippewa&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td scope=&quot;row&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td scope=&quot;row&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/lead-designations/lead-designations-pala-band-mission-indians-tribal-recommendations-and-epa&quot;&gt;Pala Band of Mission Indians&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td scope=&quot;row&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/lead-designations/lead-designations-forest-county-potawatomi-community-tribal-recommendations-and&quot;&gt;Forest County Potawatomi Community&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td scope=&quot;row&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td scope=&quot;row&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/lead-designations/lead-designations-st-regis-mohawk-tribe-tribal-recommendations-and-epa-responses&quot;&gt;St. Regis Mohawk Tribe&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td scope=&quot;row&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/lead-designations/lead-designations-lone-pine-paiute-shoshone-reservation-tribal-recommendations-and&quot;&gt;Lone Pine Paiute Shoshone Reservation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td scope=&quot;row&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td scope=&quot;row&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/lead-designations/lead-designations-torres-martinez-desert-cahuilla-indians-tribal-recommendations&quot;&gt;Torres Martinez Desert Cahuilla Indians&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 25 May 2016 18:29:19 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>rcopland</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">150453 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Map of Nonattainment Areas for the 2008 Lead Standards</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/lead-designations/map-nonattainment-areas-2008-lead-standards</link>
    <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-gif center view-mode-full caption&quot; style=&quot;width:750px;&quot;&gt;&lt;a
    href=&quot;/sites/production/files/2016-05/national_map.gif&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Nonattainment Areas for the 2008 Lead Standards&quot; height=&quot;420&quot; width=&quot;750&quot; class=&quot;center media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2016-05/national_map.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;figcaption&quot;&gt;Nonattainment Areas for the 2008 Lead Standards&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 25 May 2016 17:48:50 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>rcopland</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">150441 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Fact Sheet - Modifications to State and Tribal Recommendations for Areas Not Meeting the National Ambient Air Quality Standards for Lead Established in 2008</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/lead-designations/fact-sheet-modifications-state-and-tribal-recommendations-areas-not-meeting</link>
    <description>&lt;h2&gt;ACTION&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;On June 15, 2010 the Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) sent letters to state and tribal representatives responding to their initial recommendations for areas meeting and not meeting the National Ambient Air Quality Standards (NAAQS) for lead (Pb). The letters indicate either agreement with the initial recommendations, EPA’s intent to modify the initial recommendations, or deferral of a decision on the recommendations until June 2011. States and tribes now have the opportunity to comment on EPA’s modifications to their recommendations, and to provide new information and analyses to EPA if appropriate.&lt;br /&gt;
		 &lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;On October 15, 2008, EPA revised the NAAQS for Pb by significantly strengthening the standard from 1.5 micrograms per cubic meter (μg/m&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;) to 0.15 μg/m&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;. Lead exposure can cause a range of adverse health effects, most notably in children. Exposures to low levels of lead early in life have been linked to effects on IQ, learning, memory and behavior. Reducing levels of lead pollution is an important part of EPA’s commitment to a clean, healthy environment.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;br /&gt;&lt;li&gt;After EPA sets a new NAAQS or revises an existing NAAQS, the Agency formally identifies or “designates” areas as “attainment/unclassifiable” (meeting the standard or expected to be meeting the standard despite a lack of monitoring data), “nonattainment” (not meeting the standard), or “unclassifiable” (insufficient information to classify).&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;br /&gt;&lt;li&gt;EPA will provide the public with an opportunity to comment on the Agency’s proposed modifications to the state and tribal recommendations and offer additional information that may help establish the final nonattainment area boundaries. EPA will issue a Federal Register notice announcing the start of this comment period shortly. EPA will accept public comment through August 16, 2010.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;br /&gt;&lt;li&gt;States and tribes had previously provided EPA with their initial designation recommendations based on the most recent three years of air quality monitoring data available at that time – generally 2006 to 2008. These data are from the network of monitors that existed prior to EPA’s revision to the Pb NAAQS. In areas where EPA plans to make final designations in October 2010, EPA will base the designations on existing air quality monitoring data from 2007, 2008 and 2009.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;br /&gt;&lt;li&gt;In conjunction with strengthening the lead NAAQS, EPA also established new criteria for siting ambient lead monitors. The pre-existing ambient lead monitoring network was inadequate for determining whether many areas are meeting the revised lead NAAQS. Monitors meeting the new network siting requirements were to begin operation January 1, 2010.&lt;br /&gt;
		 &lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;EPA intends to extend the designation process for some areas by up to one year to consider information from newly deployed monitors. For these areas EPA intends to provide responses to state and tribal recommendations by June 2011, and complete a second round of final designations in October 2011. States and tribes may provide updated recommendations for the second round of designations by December 15, 2010.&lt;br /&gt;
		 &lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;EPA will be making designations for all areas in the country, both for state lands and for Indian country. Unlike states, tribes are not obligated to submit designation recommendations but are invited to participate in the designations process by submitting a designation recommendation for Indian country and/or by engaging in formal or informal consultation with EPA and states.&lt;br /&gt;
		 &lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Once designations take effect, they become an important component of state, local and tribal governments’ efforts to reduce lead pollution. The designations govern what subsequent regulatory actions states and EPA must take in order to improve or preserve air quality in each area.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2&gt;ABOUT DESIGNATIONS&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;EPA will make final nonattainment designations for some areas by October 2010 based air monitoring data from 2007 - 2009. All other areas will be designated as nonattainment, attainment/unclassifiable, or unclassifiable by October 2011. Areas designated nonattainment will be required to take action to improve their air quality.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;br /&gt;&lt;li&gt;The Clean Air Act requires states to take steps to control lead pollution in nonattainment areas. Those steps may include stricter controls on industrial facilities.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;br /&gt;&lt;li&gt;States must detail control requirements in plans demonstrating how they will attain and maintain the 2008 lead NAAQS. Those plans are known as state implementation plans, or SIPs. States must submit their plans to EPA within eighteen months after the Agency’s final designations become effective. Nonattainment areas are required to meet the standards within five years of being designated.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;br /&gt;&lt;li&gt;Tribes also may submit plans, known as tribal implementation plans (TIPS), but are not required to do so. EPA will develop federal requirements, as appropriate, where a tribe does not develop a TIP.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;br /&gt;&lt;li&gt;Once designated, nonattainment areas also are subject to nonattainment new source review requirements. Nonattainment New Source Review is a permitting program for industrial facilities to ensure that new and modified sources of pollution do not impede progress toward cleaner air.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;br /&gt;&lt;li&gt;Areas that are designated attainment/unclassifiable or unclassifiable will not have to take steps to improve air quality but they must take steps to help prevent their air quality from deteriorating to unhealthy levels. For example, Prevention of Significant Deterioration (PSD) is a permitting program for industrial facilities to ensure that new and modified sources of pollution do not cause or contribute to violations of air quality standards.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;br /&gt;&lt;li&gt;In November 2008, EPA provided guidance to states and tribes for recommending nonattainment area boundaries for the lead standard. EPA’s proposed decisions on lead designations are based on that guidance and on EPA’s consideration of information and recommendations submitted by States.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2&gt;FOR MORE INFORMATION&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;For more information on the designation process for the lead standards, and to view individual letters from EPA to states and tribes, go to EPA’s Web site at www.epa.gov/lead-designations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 25 May 2016 16:45:31 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>rcopland</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">150435 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Lead Designations Guidance</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/lead-designations/lead-designations-guidance</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;EPA provided guidance for making the lead designations process in the preamble for the lead National Ambient Air Quality Standards (NAAQS) final rulemaking (73 FR 6694; November 12, 2008). On August 21, 2009, EPA provided additional information on the timeline for designating areas and identified where key designation – related subjects can be found in the lead NAAQS preamble.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gpo.gov/fdsys/pkg/FR-2008-11-12/pdf/E8-25654.pdf&quot;&gt;Lead NAAQS Final Rule (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(100 pp, 688 K, &lt;a href=&quot;/home/pdf-files&quot;&gt;About PDF&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; - Federal Register - November 12, 2008&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-287985&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-05/documents/pb_designations_memo_to_epa_regions.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=749241&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Lead Designations Guidance Memo (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(3 pp, 749 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 25 May 2016 16:29:01 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>jcortely</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">150433 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>EPA Completes Second Round of Lead Nonattainment Designations</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/lead-designations/epa-completes-second-round-lead-nonattainment-designations</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;November 8, 2011 - EPA designated all remaining areas as meeting or not meeting the 2008 lead standards based on data from 2008 - 2010. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gpo.gov/fdsys/pkg/FR-2011-11-22/pdf/2011-29460.pdf&quot;&gt;Final Rule (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(24 pp, 229 K, &lt;a href=&quot;/home/pdf-files&quot;&gt;About PDF&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; - Federal Register - November 22, 2011&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/lead-designations/map-nonattainment-areas-2008-lead-standards&quot;&gt;Map of nonattainment areas for 2008 lead standards&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/lead-designations/lead-designations-final-nonattainment-designations-rounds-1-and-2&quot;&gt;List of areas designated as nonattainment&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.regulations.gov/#!docketBrowser;rpp=25;po=0;s=response%252Bto%252Bcomments;dct=N%252BFR%252BPR%252BO%252BSR;D=EPA-HQ-OAR-2009-0443&quot;&gt;Response to Comment&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-287813&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-05/documents/factsheet4finalpbv3.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=92798&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Fact Sheet (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(3 pp, 93 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 25 May 2016 13:31:28 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>rcopland</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">150379 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Lead Designations - Final Nonattainment Designations Rounds 1 and 2</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/lead-designations/lead-designations-final-nonattainment-designations-rounds-1-and-2</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;See also - &lt;a href=&quot;/lead-designations/2008-lead-standards-state-recommendations-and-epa-responses&quot;&gt;state recommendations and EPA responses&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;State&lt;/th&gt;
			&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;Area Name&lt;/th&gt;
			&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;County Name&lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Alabama&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Troy&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Pike (p)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;California&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Los Angeles County within the South Coast Air Basin,&lt;br /&gt;
				excluding San Clemente and Santa Catalina Islands&lt;br /&gt;
				(Southern Los Angeles County)&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Los Angeles (p)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Florida&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Tampa&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Hillsborough (p)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Illinois&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Granite City&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Madison (p)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Chicago&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Cook (p)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Indiana&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Muncie&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Delaware (p)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Iowa&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Pottawattamie County&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Pottawattamie (p)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Kansas&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Saline County&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Saline (p)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Michigan&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Belding&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Ionia (p)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Minnesota&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Eagan&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Dakota (p)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Missouri&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Iron, Dent, and Reynolds Counties&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Iron (p)&lt;br /&gt;
				Dent (p)&lt;br /&gt;
				Reynolds (p)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Jefferson County&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Jefferson (p)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Ohio&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Bellefontaine&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Logan (p)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Cleveland&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Cuyahoga (p)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Delta&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Fulton (p)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Pennsylvania&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Lower Beaver Valley&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Beaver (p)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Lyons&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Berks (p)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;North Reading&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;&lt;span&gt;Berks (p)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Puerto Rico&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Arecibo&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Arecibo (p)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Tennessee&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Bristol&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Sullivan (p)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Texas&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Frisco&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Collin (p)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td colspan=&quot;3&quot;&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;15 states&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;21 Nonattainment Areas&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;22 partial counties&lt;br /&gt;
				(parts of Berks County, PA fall in 2 areas)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 24 May 2016 21:07:39 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>rcopland</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">150355 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Lead Designations - Table of EPA Initial Nonattainment Designations</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/lead-designations/lead-designations-table-epa-initial-nonattainment-designations</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;This table identifies all counties EPA designated as nonattainment in the initial round of designations. Each is a partial county and is identified by a (p). EPA deferred final designations decisions on all other areas of the country until October 2011 so that additional lead air quality data could be collected and evaluated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See also - &lt;a href=&quot;/lead-designations/2008-lead-standards-state-recommendations-and-epa-responses&quot;&gt;state recommendations and EPA responses&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table summary=&quot;EPA Initial Nonattainment Designations&quot;&gt;&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;State &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
			&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Area Name&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
			&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;State Recommended Nonattainment Counties&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
			&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;EPA Recommended Nonattainment Counties&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
			&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;EPA Designated Nonattainment Counties&lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Alabama&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Troy&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;None&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Pike (p)&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Pike (p)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;California&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Los Angeles County within the South Coast Air Basin, excluding San Clemente and Santa Catalina Islands (Southern Los Angeles)&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Los Angeles (p)&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Los Angeles (p)&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Los Angeles (p)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Florida&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Tampa&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;None&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Hillsborough (p)&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Hillsborough (p)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Illinois&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Granite City&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Madison (p)&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Madison (p)&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Madison (p)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Indiana&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Muncie&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Delaware (p)&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Delaware (p)&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Delaware (p)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Minnesota&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Eagan&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Dakota (p)&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Dakota (p)&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Dakota (p)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td rowspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;Missouri&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Iron&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Dent (p)&lt;br /&gt;
				Iron (p)&lt;br /&gt;
				Reynolds (p)&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Dent (p)&lt;br /&gt;
				Iron (p)&lt;br /&gt;
				Reynolds (p)&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Dent (p)&lt;br /&gt;
				Iron (p)&lt;br /&gt;
				Reynolds (p)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Jefferson&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Jefferson (p)&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Jefferson (p)&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Jefferson (p)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td rowspan=&quot;3&quot;&gt;Ohio&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Bellefontaine&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Logan (p)&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Logan (p)&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Logan (p)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Cleveland&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Cuyahoga (p)&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Cuyahoga (p)&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Cuyahoga (p)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Delta&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Fulton (p)&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Fulton (p)&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Fulton (p)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td rowspan=&quot;3&quot;&gt;Pennsylvania&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Lower Beaver Valley&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Beaver (p)&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Beaver (p)&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Beaver (p)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Lyons&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Berks (p)&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Berks (p)&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Berks (p)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;North Reading&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Berks (p)&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Berks (p)&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Berks (p)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Tennessee&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Bristol&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Sullivan (p)&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Sullivan (p)&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Sullivan (p)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Texas&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Frisco&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Collin (p)&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Collin (p)&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Collin (p)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td colspan=&quot;5&quot;&gt;
				&lt;div&gt;
					&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;11 states&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;16 Nonattainment Areas&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;15 Partial Counties (2 parts of Berks County, PA are in 2 separate areas)&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;17 Partial Counties (2 parts of Berks County, PA are in 2 separate areas)&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;17 Partial Counties (2 parts of Berks County, PA are in 2 separate areas)&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 24 May 2016 20:52:46 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>jcortely</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">150351 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Lead Designations - Where You Live</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/lead-designations/lead-designations-where-you-live</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;On this Page:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#state&quot;&gt;State designations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#tribal&quot;&gt;Tribal designations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#maps&quot;&gt;Area designation maps&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;state&quot; name=&quot;state&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;State designations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Round 1&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On November 16, 2010, EPA designated parts of 17 counties in 11 states as nonattainment for the 2008 lead standards. EPA deferred all other designations decisions until October 2011 so that additional lead air quality data could be collected and evaluated.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/lead-designations/lead-designations-table-epa-initial-nonattainment-designations&quot;&gt;Learn more about this action&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Round 2&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On November 8, 2011, EPA designated the remaining areas as meeting or not meeting the 2008 lead standards based on data from 2008 - 2010.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/lead-designations/lead-designations-final-nonattainment-designations-rounds-1-and-2&quot;&gt;Learn more about this action&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;tribal&quot; name=&quot;tribal&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Tribal designations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Six tribes submitted an initial round of recommendations to EPA in 2009. Some tribes submitted additional recommendations in 2010 based on more recent or new monitoring data. After carefully reviewing the tribal recommendations and all associated technical information, EPA designated all of these areas as unclassifiable/attainment. EPA uses this designation to identify areas that have data indicating attainment, or where there is no evidence of a violation of the National Ambient Air Quality Standards and the area has not been determined to contribute to a violation in a nearby area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/lead-designations/2008-lead-standards-tribal-recommendations-and-epa-responses&quot;&gt;Learn more about this action&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;maps&quot; name=&quot;maps&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Area designation maps&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/lead-designations/map-nonattainment-areas-2008-lead-standards&quot;&gt;Designation map for rounds 1 and 2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 24 May 2016 17:50:30 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>jcortely</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">150317 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Lead Designations Regulatory Actions</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/lead-designations/lead-designations-regulatory-actions</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;This page contains a chronological listing of all regulatory actions related to designations for the 2008 lead standard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;EPA Announces Proposal to Retain Current Lead National Ambient Air Quality Standards (NAAQS)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;January 5, 2015 - Proposed Rule to Retain the Current NAAQS for Lead
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gpo.gov/fdsys/pkg/FR-2015-01-05/pdf/2014-30681.pdf&quot;&gt;Federal Register Notice (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(48 pp, 596 K, &lt;a href=&quot;/home/pdf-files&quot;&gt;About PDF&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2&gt;EPA Completes Second Round of Lead Nonattainment Designations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;November 8, 2011 - EPA designated all remaining areas as meeting or not meeting the 2008 lead standards based on data from 2008 - 2010.
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/lead-designations/epa-completes-second-round-lead-nonattainment-designations&quot;&gt;Learn More&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2&gt;EPA Shares Plans for Second Round of Lead Designations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;June 15, 2011 - In response to recommendations from state and local tribal representatives, EPA sent letters outlining the areas it is considering designating as “nonattainment,” &quot;unclassifiable/attainment,&quot; or &quot;unclassifiable&quot; for the second round of designations for the lead standards.
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gpo.gov/fdsys/pkg/FR-2011-06-21/pdf/2011-15415.pdf&quot;&gt;Federal Register Notice (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(3 pp, 156 K, &lt;a href=&quot;/home/pdf-files&quot;&gt;About PDF&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; - June 21, 2011&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2&gt;EPA Completes Initial Round of Lead Nonattainment Designations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;November 16, 2010 - EPA completed initial round of lead nonattainment designations
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gpo.gov/fdsys/pkg/FR-2010-11-22/pdf/2010-29405.pdf&quot;&gt;Federal Register Notice (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(12 pp, 184 K, &lt;a href=&quot;/home/pdf-files&quot;&gt;About PDF&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; - November 22, 2010&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Recommendations for Areas to be Designated Nonattainment for the 2008 Lead National Air Quality Standards&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;June 15, 2010 – In response to recommendations from state and local tribal representatives, EPA sent letters outlining the areas it is considering designating as “nonattainment” for the lead standards.
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/lead-designations/fact-sheet-modifications-state-and-tribal-recommendations-areas-not-meeting&quot;&gt;Fact Sheet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 24 May 2016 16:46:22 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>jcortely</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">150309 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  </channel>
</rss>

<!-- Page cached by Boost @ 2017-01-25 19:04:09, expires @ 2017-01-26 07:04:09, lifetime 12 hours -->