<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?><rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.epa.gov/feed/43853/rss.xml" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/" xmlns:og="http://ogp.me/ns#" xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#" xmlns:sioc="http://rdfs.org/sioc/ns#" xmlns:sioct="http://rdfs.org/sioc/types#" xmlns:skos="http://www.w3.org/2004/02/skos/core#" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#">
  <channel>
    <title>Federal Technology Transfer Act (FTTA)</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/feed/43853/rss.xml</link>
    <description>Updated Federal Technology Transfer Act (FTTA) content from the US Environmental Protection Agency</description>
    <language>en</language>
     <atom:link href="https://www.epa.gov/feed/43853/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      <item>
    <title>Materials Transfer Agreement template (fillable form)</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/ftta/materials-transfer-agreement-template-fillable-form</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;This is EPA&#039;s standard template for the Materials Transfer Agreement template (fillable form).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-341681&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-12/documents/model_epa_mta_fillable_12-20-16.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=100778&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Materials Transfer Agreement template (fillable form) (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(6 pp, 101 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Fri, 14 Oct 2016 14:49:52 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cbooker</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">162681 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>EPA Technology Available for Licensing: Portable Device to Concentrate Water Samples for Microorganism Analysis</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/ftta/epa-technology-available-licensing-portable-device-concentrate-water-samples-microorganism</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg right view-mode-medium caption&quot; style=&quot;width:300px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Water Concentrator inventors&quot; height=&quot;300&quot; width=&quot;300&quot; class=&quot;right media-element file-medium right&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/medium/public/2016-10/water_concentrator_group_photo-2009.jpg&quot; title=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;figcaption&quot;&gt;From back left:&amp;nbsp; Paul Tremblay, Alan Lindquist, Michael Carpenter.&amp;nbsp; From front left:&amp;nbsp; Vicente Gallardo, Lyle Roybal.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Inventors:&lt;/strong&gt; Alan Lindquist, Vicente Gallardo, Michael V. Carpenter, Lyle G. Roybal&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Owned by EPA&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://appft.uspto.gov/netacgi/nph-Parser?Sect1=PTO2&amp;amp;Sect2=HITOFF&amp;amp;p=1&amp;amp;u=%2Fnetahtml%2FPTO%2Fsearch-bool.html&amp;amp;r=4&amp;amp;f=G&amp;amp;l=50&amp;amp;co1=AND&amp;amp;d=PG01&amp;amp;s1=695432.APN.&amp;amp;OS=APN/695432&amp;amp;RS=APN/695432&quot;&gt;Patent Information from the U.S. Patent and Trademark Office&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Summary of the Technology&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The transportation and handling of a large volume of potentially contaminated water is a safety concern for the transporters, laboratory personnel, and the public.  To improve upon this situation, EPA teamed up with the Department of Energy’s Idaho National Laboratory (INL) to develop a rugged and automated field deployable sample concentration (ultrafiltration) device. The device significantly reduces the sample volume by concentrating the microorganisms contained in a large sample into a small volume of water. The device can concentrate the microbes contained in a 26-gallon sample into less than 2 cups of water, often in under an hour. Following concentration, the smaller, concentrated sample can be more easily and safely transported to a laboratory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the development of this filtration device, EPA and INL researchers received a 2009 R&amp;amp;D 100 Award from &lt;em&gt;R&amp;amp;D Magazine&lt;/em&gt;. Each year, the editors of &lt;em&gt;R&amp;amp;D Magazine &lt;/em&gt;bestow the prestigious R&amp;amp;D 100 Award to help new products compete in the marketplace. As stated by &lt;em&gt;R&amp;amp;D Magazine&lt;/em&gt;, “the winning of an R&amp;amp;D 100 Award provides a mark of excellence known to industry, government, and academia as proof that the product is one of the most innovative ideas of the year”. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg right view-mode-medium caption&quot; style=&quot;width:400px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Water Concentrator&quot; height=&quot;300&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; class=&quot;right media-element file-medium right&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/medium/public/2016-10/water-concentrator2.jpg&quot; title=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;figcaption&quot;&gt;An inside view of the Water Concentrator device.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;The possibility of terrorists or criminals intentionally contaminating drinking water with pathogenic microorganisms is a significant public health concern.  This concern has given rise to the need to rapidly and effectively sample water to detect small concentrations of potentially dangerous microorganisms.  A large volume (i.e., 100 liters or 26 gallons) water sample is necessary to detect low concentrations of microorganisms in water. The larger the sample, the greater likelihood of capturing microorganisms present at low levels.  The conventional practice has been to transport the large volume sample to a laboratory for concentration and analysis.  This can be cumbersome for lab and field personnel, and the transport of a large volume sample that may contain a biological hazard can be prohibitively expensive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;How the Technology is Different&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using a computer controlled system, this ultrafiltration device automates the process of concentrating a water sample and can be operated in the field. The system was also designed to reduce human exposure to potentially contaminated water and to generate samples that are appropriate for the analyses of several types of microorganisms. The underlying technology has been tested by several laboratories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ultrafiltration device:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Reduces sample collection and concentration time and cost &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;– Sample concentration processes are automated, which reduces the time it takes to determine pathogen concentration. Because only a concentrated sample is shipped to a laboratory, the cost of transport is less. A one hundred liter water sample can often be processed and concentrated in about an hour.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Improves accuracy and consistency – &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;By using a large sample volume, analytical sensitivities may be improved by as much as 250 percent over smaller volume assays. Concentrated samples help ensure that low concentrations of microorganisms are accurately identified. The automation of processes that were previously performed manually in the laboratory should help improve the consistency of sample preparation.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Requires minimal setup and training &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Allows for real-time monitoring &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;– The computer screen provides a virtual display of the filtration process, allowing operators to monitor the status and quickly respond to operational issues during sampling.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Eliminates cross-contamination &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;– All device parts that come in contact with the sample water (e.g., tubing, fittings, pressure transducer) are single use items. This ensures that there is no cross-contamination between samples. The device includes quick disconnects for sample removal.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Increased safety &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;– The shipment and handling of a small water sample, compared with a high volume sample, is less likely to result in spillage, which decreases risk to the transporters, laboratory personnel and general public.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The approximate dimensions of the ultrafiltration device are 31 x 20 x 16 inches (795 x 518 x 393 millimeters), which allows it to fit into the trunk of a car. It consists of a pump, valves, sensors, electronic controls, a hollow fiber filter cartridge and a sample bottle. The device is controlled by software that can be installed on a personal computer. The device works by pumping water through a filter, while maintaining 10 to 25 pounds per square inch pressure difference between the filter inlet and outlet. This pressure difference forces the majority of the water to be discarded through a hollow fiber filter, while the microorganisms remain suspended in the concentrated sample.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Additional Uses&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ultrafiltration device could be used by water utilities during their routine regulatory compliance sampling. This routine sampling includes testing for several different microorganisms in drinking water.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ultrafiltration device may also be useful for sampling:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Bilge water on shipping vessels&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Process control liquids from the brewing and pharmaceutical industries&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Surface water for environmental studies&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Decontamination water from cleanup areas.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Although not yet confirmed, the ultrafiltration device might be useful in concentrating samples for large molecular weight toxins such as ricin, as well as yeasts, fungi, viruses, protozoa and helminths, which are targeted pathogens in EPA’s new water reuse guidelines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2016 18:40:26 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cbooker</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">161861 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Mutual Confidentiality Agreement</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/ftta/mutual-confidentiality-agreement</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;This is a fillable Mutual Confidentiality Agreement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-320323&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-09/documents/fillable_mutual_nda_final_9-8-16.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=1117137&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Mutual Confidentiality Agreement (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(3 pp, 1 MB)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Fri, 30 Sep 2016 20:44:50 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cbooker</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">161761 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>FTTA Hightlighted Patents</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/ftta/ftta-hightlighted-patents</link>
    <description>&lt;ul class=&quot;roomy&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/sFEZ6YoeyMI&quot;&gt;Video:  EPA&#039;s Patented Microbial Source Tracking Technology Wins Award from the Federal Laboratory Consortium for Technology Transfer (FLC)&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot; class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/ftta/epa-technology-available-licensing-portable-device-concentrate-water-samples-microorganism&quot;&gt;&lt;ins data-date=&quot;2016,10,3&quot;&gt;Spotlight on Portable Device to Concentrate Water Samples for Microorganism Analysis&lt;/ins&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;ins data-date=&quot;2016,2,25&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/ftta/epa-technology-available-licensing-optical-remote-sensing-fugitive-releases&quot;&gt;Spotlight on Optical Remote Sensing of Fugitive Releases&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/ins&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/ftta/epa-technology-available-licensing-biological-filter-oxidizing-ammonia-drinking-water&quot;&gt;Spotlight on Biological Filter for Oxidizing Ammonia in Drinking Water&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 25 Feb 2016 20:01:38 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>kgraham</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">136815 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>EPA Technology Available for Licensing: Optical Remote Sensing of Fugitive Releases</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/ftta/epa-technology-available-licensing-optical-remote-sensing-fugitive-releases</link>
    <description>&lt;div class=&quot;figure image mode-full caption right&quot; style=&quot;width:160px&quot;&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:150px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Cary Secrest&quot; height=&quot;191&quot; width=&quot;150&quot; class=&quot;media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2016-02/secrest.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;div class=&quot;figcaption&quot;&gt;Inventor: Cary Secrest&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;figure image mode-full caption right&quot; style=&quot;width:160px&quot;&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:150px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;William Squier&quot; height=&quot;191&quot; width=&quot;150&quot; class=&quot;media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2016-02/squier.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;div class=&quot;figcaption&quot;&gt;Inventor: William Squier&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Inventors:&lt;/strong&gt; Eben Thoma, Cary Secrest, William Mitchell, William Squier&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Owned by EPA&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://patft.uspto.gov/netacgi/nph-Parser?Sect1=PTO2&amp;amp;Sect2=HITOFF&amp;amp;p=1&amp;amp;u=%2Fnetahtml%2FPTO%2Fsearch-bool.html&amp;amp;r=1&amp;amp;f=G&amp;amp;l=50&amp;amp;co1=AND&amp;amp;d=PTXT&amp;amp;s1=8445850.PN.&amp;amp;OS=PN/8445850&amp;amp;RS=PN/8445850&quot;&gt;Patent Information from the U.S. Patent and Trademark Office website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/ftta/forms/contact-us-about-federal-technology-transfer-act&quot;&gt;Federal Technology Transfer Act (FTTA) staff&lt;/a&gt;: Contact us if you are interested in learning more about how to license this technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Summary of the Technology&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many benefits to reducing fugitive emissions of hazardous air pollutants (HAPs) from industrial facilities.  These benefits include enhanced protection of human health, improved worker safety, and the realization of cost savings by companies.  Unlike stack emissions, fugitive releases are difficult to detect. Fenceline monitoring using optical remote sensing can augment existing leak detection and repair programs by helping workers to quickly pinpoint and repair leaks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ultraviolet (UV) form of this open-path optical sensor technology is called the deep UV optical sensor (DUVOS).  DUVOS assists in detection and measurement of fugitive emissions of hazardous air pollutants (HAPs) in industrial settings and other sensor applications.  The approach relies on the strong broad-band optical absorption of many HAPs in the deep UV spectral region. This provides a robust measurement approach that has the following characteristics: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Integrated compound detection (non-speciating)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;High sensitivity (strong optical absorption)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;High speed (real-time measurements)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Low maintenance (no sample handing or lab analysis)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Low cost (eliminates spectrometer)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Multiple configurations
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Extended open-path (fenceline or in-plant monitoring),&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Open-cage optical cell (high speed point monitoring)&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Building ventilation monitoring (cross-vent)&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Miniature optical cell (low cost sensor applications)&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Mobile monitoring (mobile leak detection)&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA recently amended the National Emission Standards for Hazardous Air Pollutants from Petroleum Refineries.  EPA is now requiring fenceline measurements for benzene as a surrogate for facility fugitive emissions using time-integrated passive samplers.  Simple and cost effective time-resolved fenceline monitoring strategies can assist in execution of these requirements.  Additionally, there is growing interest in lower cost technologies to detect HAPs in building ventilation and in homes, or with personal sensors. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The DUVOS approach can assist in development of next generation, lower cost HAP measurement systems for a variety of applications.  Improved detection and mitigation of fugitive emissions of HAPs is an important emerging topic in many industrial sectors.  Also important is the development of low cost, small format HAP sensor approaches. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;How the Technology is Different&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Typical UV optical spectroscopic measurement approaches speciate the individual compounds present in the air.  For example, commercially available open-path UV differential optical absorption spectrometers may spectrally resolve and report the individual path-averaged concentration of compounds such as benzene, toluene, ethylbenzene, or isomers of xylene (collectively referred to as BTEX).  In addition to the optics and light source, this process requires a high-resolution spectrometer, computer, and analysis system.   The spectrally resolved measurement of any specific BTEX component is accomplished somewhere in the 240 nm to 270 nm spectral region (see figure) where compound-specific “finger print” spectral absorption features occur. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-png center view-mode-medium caption&quot; style=&quot;width:448px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Graph of spectral absorption&quot; height=&quot;233&quot; width=&quot;448&quot; class=&quot;center media-element file-medium center&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/medium/public/2016-02/spectral_absorption.png&quot; title=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;figcaption&quot;&gt;The principle of operation is differential absorption of light in the 200 nm range compared to the 280 nm range.&amp;nbsp; Numerous inorganic and organic hazardous air pollutants possess strong broadband absorption in the 200 nm spectral region.&amp;nbsp; These absorption features terminate in the 210 nm to 230 nm region depending on the compound and are very difficult to speciate due to lack of fine structure with the exception of a few compounds.&amp;nbsp; The DUVOS system is based on balanced differential comparison of light throughput in two spectral regions using a broadband detection scheme employing bandpass filters and solar blind dual channel detection.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The DUVOS approach operates in the integrated deep UV optical band (200 nm - 220 nm).  Many HAP compounds have strong broad-band absorption features in this area of the spectrum, the integrated value of which greatly exceeds their “finger print” absorptions in other areas of the spectrum.  Using a simple, on-band / off-band filter-based approach, high sensitivity discrimination of the deep UV integrated absorption band is readily accomplished.  No spectrometer or computerized spectral analysis is required. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 25 Feb 2016 16:51:07 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>kgraham</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">136747 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Engineering Design and Operation Report: Biological Treatment Process for the Removal of Ammonia from a Small Drinking Water System in Iowa: Pilot to Full-Scale</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/ftta/engineering-design-and-operation-report-biological-treatment-process-removal-ammonia-small</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;The objective of this study was to document the operation and treatment effectiveness of the city of Palo’s innovative full-scale biological ammonia removal drinking water treatment plant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-90777&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2014-11/documents/palo_full_scale_report_9-23-14.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=2700753&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Engineering Design and Operation Report: Biological Treatment Process for the Removal of Ammonia from a Small Drinking Water System in Iowa: Pilot to Full-Scale (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(53 pp, 3 MB, 
  600-R-14-336)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Mon, 03 Nov 2014 15:05:24 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cbooker</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">66303 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>EPA Reports to Congress on Technology Transfer</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/ftta/epa-reports-congress-technology-transfer</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;Agencies are required to report to Congress annually on their technology transfer activities. These reports summarize technology transfer activities of EPA’s federal laboratories, by fiscal year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Combined Federal Laboratories Reports&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nist.gov/sites/default/files/documents/2016/10/26/fy2014_federal_tech_transfer_report.pdf&quot;&gt;Combined Federal Laboratories Report to Congress (PDF) &lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(176 pp, 3.7 MB)&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;a title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot; class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Annual EPA Reports&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-262561&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-03/documents/annual_report_fy15.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=59715&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;EPA Annual Report to Congress on Technology Transfer (FY 2015) (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(3 pp, 60 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-123421&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-04/documents/annual_report_fy14.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=57262&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;EPA Annual Report to Congress on Technology Transfer (FY 2014) (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(3 pp, 57 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-85567&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2014-09/documents/annual_report_fy13.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=41223&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;EPA Annual Report to Congress on Technology Transfer (FY 2013)  (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(2 pp, 41 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-90037&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2014-10/documents/ftta_epa_fy12_report_all_data_-_clean.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=1482910&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;EPA Annual Report to Congress on Technology Transfer (FY 2012) (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(9 pp, 1 MB)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Fri, 20 Jun 2014 20:13:19 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>kgraham</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">55513 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>EPA Laboratories that Collaborate with Non-Federal Partners through the Federal Technology Transfer Act Program</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/ftta/epa-laboratories-collaborate-non-federal-partners-through-federal-technology-transfer-act</link>
    <description>&lt;div class=&quot;figure image mode-full caption right&quot; style=&quot;width:300px&quot;&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg view-mode-full&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Examining algae growth in simulated stream system.&quot; class=&quot;media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2014-11/cincinnatilab2_029.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;div class=&quot;figcaption&quot;&gt;Examining algae growth in a simulated stream system at EPA&#039;s National Risk Management Research Laboratory in Cincinnati, OH.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;External partners work directly with EPA laboratories and staff on collaborative research and development projects through the Federal Technology Transfer Act (FTTA) program. For the purposes of FTTA a laboratory is broadly considered to be:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;a research laboratory (i.e., part of the Office of Research and Development);&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;an EPA program office or a laboratory supporting an EPA program or headquarters office; or&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;a laboratory or office that serves any of EPA&#039;s ten regional offices located throughout the nation. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Laboratories demonstrate the breadth of research and development conducted by EPA, providing ideas about collaboration opportunities with potential partners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;roomy&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/aboutepa#pane-5&quot;&gt;EPA Laboratories and Research Centers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/research&quot;&gt;EPA Research Programs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
     <pubDate>Mon, 16 Jun 2014 20:09:34 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>kgraham</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">55003 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>EPA Patents Available for Licensing: Waste</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/ftta/epa-patents-available-licensing-waste</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;The links below will take you to the relevant page in the U.S. Patent and Trademark Office’s Patent Application Full Text and Image Database.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table class=&quot;tablesorter&quot;&gt;&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot; style=&quot;width:125px&quot;&gt;Patent #&lt;/th&gt;
			&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;Patent Title&lt;/th&gt;
			&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;Issue Date&lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;7,335,307&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://patft.uspto.gov/netacgi/nph-Parser?Sect1=PTO2&amp;amp;Sect2=HITOFF&amp;amp;p=1&amp;amp;u=/netahtml/PTO/search-bool.html&amp;amp;r=1&amp;amp;f=G&amp;amp;l=50&amp;amp;co1=AND&amp;amp;d=PTXT&amp;amp;s1=7335307.PN.&amp;amp;OS=PN/7335307&amp;amp;RS=PN/7335307&quot;&gt;Method for Removing Contaminants from Water Using Ruthenium Based Sorbents and Oxidizers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;02/26/2008&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;7,320,753&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://patft.uspto.gov/netacgi/nph-Parser?Sect1=PTO2&amp;amp;Sect2=HITOFF&amp;amp;p=1&amp;amp;u=/netahtml/PTO/search-bool.html&amp;amp;r=1&amp;amp;f=G&amp;amp;l=50&amp;amp;co1=AND&amp;amp;d=PTXT&amp;amp;s1=7320753.PN.&amp;amp;OS=PN/7320753&amp;amp;RS=PN/7320753&quot;&gt;Anaerobic Digester System for Animal Waste Stabilization and Biogas Recovery&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;01/22/2008&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;6,881,364&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://patft.uspto.gov/netacgi/nph-Parser?Sect1=PTO2&amp;amp;Sect2=HITOFF&amp;amp;p=1&amp;amp;u=/netahtml/PTO/search-bool.html&amp;amp;r=1&amp;amp;f=G&amp;amp;l=50&amp;amp;co1=AND&amp;amp;d=PTXT&amp;amp;s1=6881364.PN.&amp;amp;OS=PN/6881364&amp;amp;RS=PN/6881364&quot;&gt;Hydrophilic Mixed Matrix Materials Having Reversible Water Absorbing Properties&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;04/19/2005&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;6,821,425&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://patft.uspto.gov/netacgi/nph-Parser?Sect1=PTO2&amp;amp;Sect2=HITOFF&amp;amp;p=1&amp;amp;u=/netahtml/PTO/search-bool.html&amp;amp;r=1&amp;amp;f=G&amp;amp;l=50&amp;amp;co1=AND&amp;amp;d=PTXT&amp;amp;s1=6821425.PN.&amp;amp;OS=PN/6821425&amp;amp;RS=PN/6821425&quot;&gt;Biomass Concentrator Reactor&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;11/23/2004&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;6,670,145&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://patft.uspto.gov/netacgi/nph-Parser?Sect1=PTO2&amp;amp;Sect2=HITOFF&amp;amp;p=1&amp;amp;u=/netahtml/PTO/search-bool.html&amp;amp;r=1&amp;amp;f=G&amp;amp;l=50&amp;amp;co1=AND&amp;amp;d=PTXT&amp;amp;s1=6670145.PN.&amp;amp;OS=PN/6670145&amp;amp;RS=PN/6670145&quot;&gt;Method for Detection of Total Coliforms and E. Coli&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;12/30/2003&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;6,387,652&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://patft.uspto.gov/netacgi/nph-Parser?Sect1=PTO2&amp;amp;Sect2=HITOFF&amp;amp;p=1&amp;amp;u=/netahtml/PTO/search-bool.html&amp;amp;r=1&amp;amp;f=G&amp;amp;l=50&amp;amp;co1=AND&amp;amp;d=PTXT&amp;amp;s1=6387652.PN.&amp;amp;OS=PN/6387652&amp;amp;RS=PN/6387652&quot;&gt;Method of Identifying and Quantifying Specific Fungi and Bacteria&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;05/14/2002&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;6,306,621&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://patft.uspto.gov/netacgi/nph-Parser?Sect1=PTO2&amp;amp;Sect2=HITOFF&amp;amp;p=1&amp;amp;u=/netahtml/PTO/search-bool.html&amp;amp;r=1&amp;amp;f=G&amp;amp;l=50&amp;amp;co1=AND&amp;amp;d=PTXT&amp;amp;s1=6306621.PN.&amp;amp;OS=PN/6306621&amp;amp;RS=PN/6306621&quot;&gt;Membrane Filter Agar Medium for Simultaneous Detection of Total Coliforms and E. Coli&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;10/23/2001&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;6,306,301&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://patft.uspto.gov/netacgi/nph-Parser?Sect1=PTO2&amp;amp;Sect2=HITOFF&amp;amp;p=1&amp;amp;u=/netahtml/PTO/search-bool.html&amp;amp;r=1&amp;amp;f=G&amp;amp;l=50&amp;amp;co1=AND&amp;amp;d=PTXT&amp;amp;s1=6306301.PN.&amp;amp;OS=PN/6306301&amp;amp;RS=PN/6306301&quot;&gt;Silica-Based Membrane Sorbent for Heavy Metal Sequestration&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;10/23/2001&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;6,139,742&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://patft.uspto.gov/netacgi/nph-Parser?Sect1=PTO2&amp;amp;Sect2=HITOFF&amp;amp;p=1&amp;amp;u=/netahtml/PTO/search-bool.html&amp;amp;r=1&amp;amp;f=G&amp;amp;l=50&amp;amp;co1=AND&amp;amp;d=PTXT&amp;amp;s1=6139742.PN.&amp;amp;OS=PN/6139742&amp;amp;RS=PN/6139742&quot;&gt;Membrane-Based Sorbent for Heavy Metal Sequestration&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;10/31/2000&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;6,103,121&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://patft.uspto.gov/netacgi/nph-Parser?Sect1=PTO2&amp;amp;Sect2=HITOFF&amp;amp;p=1&amp;amp;u=/netahtml/PTO/search-bool.html&amp;amp;r=1&amp;amp;f=G&amp;amp;l=50&amp;amp;co1=AND&amp;amp;d=PTXT&amp;amp;s1=6103121.PN.&amp;amp;OS=PN/6103121&amp;amp;RS=PN/6103121&quot;&gt;Membrane-Based Sorbent for Heavy Metal Sequestration&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;08/15/2000&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;8,791,044&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://patft.uspto.gov/netacgi/nph-Parser?Sect1=PTO2&amp;amp;Sect2=HITOFF&amp;amp;p=1&amp;amp;u=%2Fnetahtml%2FPTO%2Fsearch-bool.html&amp;amp;r=1&amp;amp;f=G&amp;amp;l=50&amp;amp;co1=AND&amp;amp;d=PTXT&amp;amp;s1=8791044.PN.&amp;amp;OS=PN/8791044&amp;amp;RS=PN/8791044&quot;&gt;Doped Titanium Dioxide as a Visible and Sun Light Photocatalyst&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;07/29/2014&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;7,335,246&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://patft.uspto.gov/netacgi/nph-Parser?Sect1=PTO2&amp;amp;Sect2=HITOFF&amp;amp;p=1&amp;amp;u=%2Fnetahtml%2FPTO%2Fsearch-bool.html&amp;amp;r=1&amp;amp;f=G&amp;amp;l=50&amp;amp;co1=AND&amp;amp;d=PTXT&amp;amp;s1=7335246.PN.&amp;amp;OS=PN/7335246&amp;amp;RS=PN/7335246&quot;&gt;Contaminant Adsorption and Oxidation Via the Fenton Reaction&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;02/26/2008&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;6,039,878&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://patft.uspto.gov/netacgi/nph-Parser?Sect1=PTO2&amp;amp;Sect2=HITOFF&amp;amp;p=1&amp;amp;u=/netahtml/PTO/search-bool.html&amp;amp;r=1&amp;amp;f=G&amp;amp;l=50&amp;amp;co1=AND&amp;amp;d=PTXT&amp;amp;s1=6039878.PN.&amp;amp;OS=PN/6039878&amp;amp;RS=PN/6039878&quot;&gt;Recovery of Volatile Organic Compounds From Emulsion of Volatile Organic Compounds in Water by Pervaporation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;03/21/2000&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;</description>
     <pubDate>Fri, 30 May 2014 14:33:23 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cbooker</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">53323 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  </channel>
</rss>

<!-- Page cached by Boost @ 2017-01-26 12:06:00, expires @ 2017-01-27 12:06:00, lifetime 1 day -->