<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?><rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.epa.gov/feed/105737/rss.xml" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/" xmlns:og="http://ogp.me/ns#" xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#" xmlns:sioc="http://rdfs.org/sioc/ns#" xmlns:sioct="http://rdfs.org/sioc/types#" xmlns:skos="http://www.w3.org/2004/02/skos/core#" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#">
  <channel>
    <title>Sustainable Management of Electronics</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/feed/105737/rss.xml</link>
    <description>Updated Sustainable Management of Electronics content from the US Environmental Protection Agency</description>
    <language>en</language>
     <atom:link href="https://www.epa.gov/feed/105737/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      <item>
    <title>Frequent Questions about the Sustainable Materials Management (SMM) Electronics Challenge</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/smm-electronics/frequent-questions-about-sustainable-materials-management-smm-electronics-challenge</link>
    <description>&lt;div class=&quot;box multi related-info right&quot;&gt;
	&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/smm-electronics/sustainable-materials-management-smm-electronics-challenge&quot;&gt;Learn more about the SMM Electronics Challenge&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On September 22, 2012, EPA launched the SMM Electronics Challenge. The Challenge encourages electronics manufacturers, brand owners and retailers to strive to send 100 percent of the used electronics they collect from the public, businesses and within their own organizations to &lt;a href=&quot;/smm-electronics/certified-electronics-recyclers&quot;&gt;third-party certified electronics refurbishers and recyclers&lt;/a&gt;. The Challenge’s goals are to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Ensure responsible recycling through the use of third-party certified recyclers.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Increase transparency and accountability through public posting of electronics collection and recycling data.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Encourage outstanding performance through awards and recognition.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;On this page:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#goals&quot;&gt;What are the goals of the SMM Electronics Challenge?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#changes&quot;&gt;Have there been any changes to the SMM Electronics Challenge from 2015 to 2016?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#results&quot;&gt;What are the 2016 SMM Electronics Challenge results?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#recyclingrate&quot;&gt;What was the contribution of SMM Electronics Challenge participants to the national electronics recycling total in 2014?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#reuserecycle&quot;&gt;Why should we reuse and recycle used electronics?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#epapost&quot;&gt;Does EPA post the data for each participant in the SMM Electronics Challenge? What information does EPA publicly post?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#add&quot;&gt;Does EPA plan to involve new OEMs, brand owners and retailers in the Challenge?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h3&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;goals&quot; name=&quot;goals&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;What are the goals of the SMM Electronics Challenge?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The goals of the SMM Electronics Challenge are to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Ensure responsible recycling through the use of third-party certified recyclers;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Increase the amount of used electronics collected by participants annually;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Increase transparency and accountability through public posting of electronics collection and recycling data;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Encourage outstanding performance through awards and recognition; and&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Highlight best practices that can be scaled up and transferred both within the electronics sector and across other sectors.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;SMM Electronics Challenge participants may be recognized in two ways – through the Tier Awards, which recognize participants for their robust used electronics collection programs, are given at the Bronze, Silver, and Gold levels; and the Champion Awards, which recognize participants for unique contributions to electronics sustainability throughout the life cycle, are given in the Product, Non-Product, and Cutting Edge categories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h3&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;changes&quot; name=&quot;changes&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Have there been any changes to the SMM Electronics Challenge from 2015 to 2016?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes. Our first brand owner, VIZIO Inc., was welcomed to the Challenge. Additionally, a new category called &lt;em&gt;Cutting Edge&lt;/em&gt; has been added to the Champion Awards alongside the Product and Non-Product categories. The Cutting Edge category focuses on bold ideas with the potential to make a significant impact on the future of sustainable electronics management across the life cycle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h3&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;results&quot; name=&quot;results&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;What are the 2016 SMM Electronics Challenge results?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2015 SMM Electronics Challenge participants collected a total of 256,822.52 tons of electronics. Of this, 256,614.53 tons – 99.92% – were sent to third-party certified recyclers. This prevented the emission of more than 673,000 tons of carbon dioxide equivalent, which is equivalent to taking over 129,000 passenger vehicles off the road for one year, or generating enough electricity for more than 90,000 U.S. homes for one year, or diverting more than 194,000 tons of solid waste from landfills. Based on these results, &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bronze Tier&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; awards are being given to Sony and VIZIO, and &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Gold Tier&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; awards are being given to Best Buy, Dell, LG, Samsung, Sprint, and Staples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SMM Electronics Challenge Champion Awards are being given in the following categories:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Product category&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: The Champion Award in the Product category is given for new products or changes to the way that existing products are used that contribute to electronics sustainability throughout the life cycle. This year’s Champion Award in the Product category goes to &lt;strong&gt;Dell&lt;/strong&gt; for their pioneering use of post-industrial recycled carbon filled polycarbonate in laptops.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Non-Product category&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: The Champion Award in the Non-Product category is given for strategies, plans, and policies implemented by a company that address electronics sustainability throughout the life cycle. This year’s Champion Award in the Non-Product category goes to &lt;strong&gt;Staples&lt;/strong&gt; for their “Make More Happen” public outreach initiative.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cutting Edge category&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;: The Champion Award in the Cutting Edge category focuses on bold ideas with the potential to make a huge impact on the future of sustainable electronics management across the life cycle. These bold ideas can include products, services, and policies. This year’s Champion Award in the Cutting Edge category goes to &lt;strong&gt;Samsung&lt;/strong&gt; for their cadmium-free quantum dot ultra-HDTVs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h3&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;recyclingrate&quot; name=&quot;recyclingrate&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;What was the contribution of SMM Electronics Challenge participants to the national electronics recycling total in 2014?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SMM Electronics Challenge participants contributed &lt;strong&gt;17.2% &lt;/strong&gt;of total U.S. electronics recycling by weight in 2014 (2014 Challenge total of 240,289.12 tons collected / national total of 1,400,000 tons).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h3&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;reuserecycle&quot; name=&quot;reuserecycle&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Why should we reuse and recycle used electronics?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An important part of the Sustainable Materials Management approach is reducing our consumption of raw materials by maximizing product lifespans and recycling materials from one product to another. Electronic products are made from valuable resources and highly engineered materials, including metals, plastics, and glass, all of which require energy to mine and manufacture. If not properly managed, some of the materials in our electronics may pose a risk to human health and the environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mdpi.com/1996-1944/7/6/4555/pdf&quot;&gt;One metric ton of circuit boards (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(12 pp, 503 K, &lt;a href=&quot;/home/pdf-files&quot;&gt;About PDF&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt; can contain 40 to 800 times the amount of gold and 30 to 40 times the amount of copper mined from one metric ton of ore in the US.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Recycling facilities can recover 35,000 pounds of copper, 772 pounds of silver, 75 pounds of gold, and 33 pounds of palladium &lt;a href=&quot;http://pubs.usgs.gov/fs/2006/3097/fs2006-3097.pdf&quot;&gt;for every one million cell phones (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(4 pp, 324 K, &lt;a href=&quot;/home/pdf-files&quot;&gt;About PDF&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h3&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;epapost&quot; name=&quot;epapost&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Does EPA post the data for each participant in the SMM Electronics Challenge? What information does EPA publicly post?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA does not post individual participant’s baseline data or annual data on the EPA website. EPA will post aggregate data from all SMM Electronics Challenge participants on its website. However, EPA does require participants to publicly post &lt;em&gt;almost&lt;/em&gt; all baseline and annual data elements (with the exception of the names of certified recyclers used, which may be kept private) on their respective websites. EPA may choose to link to Challenge participants’ websites, particularly for awards and recognition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h3&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;add&quot; name=&quot;add&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Does EPA plan to involve new OEMS, brand owners and retailers in the Challenge?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA is always open to additional original equipment manufacturers (OEMs), brand owners and electronics retailers joining the Challenge. We applaud the efforts by our current participants and look forward to continuing to work with them. If other OEMs, brand owners and retailers are interested in joining the Challenge, they should contact Kelly McAllister (&lt;a href=&quot;mailto:mcallister.kelly@epa.gov&quot;&gt;mcallister.kelly@epa.gov&lt;/a&gt;, 703-308-6811) or Brandon Bray (&lt;a href=&quot;mailto:Bray.Brandon@epa.gov&quot;&gt;Bray.Brandon@epa.gov&lt;/a&gt;, 703-308-7253).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 22 Dec 2016 20:00:35 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>tbuhrman</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">167767 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Sustainable Materials Management (SMM) Electronics Challenge: Recognition and Awards</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/smm-electronics/sustainable-materials-management-smm-electronics-challenge-recognition-and-awards</link>
    <description>&lt;div class=&quot;box multi related-info right&quot;&gt;
	&lt;h2 class=&quot;pane-title&quot;&gt;New Highlights&lt;/h2&gt;

	&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
		&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
			&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/smm-electronics/frequent-questions-about-sustainable-materials-management-smm-electronics-challenge&quot;&gt;Frequent Questions about the SMM Electronics Challenge&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.epa.gov/blog/2017/01/electronics-the-next-frontier-in-sustainability/&quot;&gt;Blog on the 2016 Electronics Challenge Awards&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/newsreleases/epa-recognizes-electronics-manufacturers-retailers-and-brand-owners-making-electronics&quot;&gt;News release for 2016 SMM Electronics Challenge Awards&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;li&gt; &lt;ins data-date=&quot;2017,1,13&quot;&gt; &lt;/ins&gt; VIDEO: &lt;a href=&quot;http://ces-innovation-policy.yourbrandlive.com/c/sustainability-issues/&quot;&gt;Can Sustainability Pay Off in Tech?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt; panel at the Consumer Electronics Show&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recognition is a key element of the EPA&#039;s Sustainable Materials Management (SMM) Program and the Electronics Challenge. EPA is providing public recognition and awards to SMM Electronics Challenge participants for their commitment to recycling electronics responsibly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On this page:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#public&quot;&gt;Public Recognition&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#awards&quot;&gt;Awards&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#2015&quot;&gt;2016 Challenge Results and Award Winners&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#2014 challenge information&quot;&gt;2015 Challenge Information&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;public&quot;&gt;Public Recognition&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Participants will be publicly recognized on EPA&#039;s website as a registrant, new participant or active participant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;Stage Participation&lt;/th&gt;
			&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;Status Posted on EPA website&lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Completion of SMM Electronics &lt;a href=&quot;/smm-electronics/sustainable-materials-management-smm-electronics-challenge-participation-agreement&quot;&gt;online registration&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Registrant&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Baseline data submitted&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;New Participant&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Annual data submitted and reviewed by EPA&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Active Participant&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;awards&quot;&gt;Awards&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Electronics Challenge Awards are offered in two categories: Tier and Champion. Tier Awards are given in recognition of achieving of all the requirements under a &lt;a href=&quot;/smm-electronics/fact-sheet-about-tiered-structure-sustainable-materials-management-smm-electronics&quot;&gt;Gold, Silver or Bronze Tier&lt;/a&gt;. Champion Awards are given in three categories: &lt;em&gt;Product&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Non-Product, &lt;/em&gt;and, new in 2016, &lt;em&gt;Cutting Edge&lt;/em&gt;. For the purposes of the Champion awards, a &lt;em&gt;product&lt;/em&gt; is an item that is manufactured, developed or refined for sale and is in the marketplace; a &lt;em&gt;non-product&lt;/em&gt; is an internal or external plan, strategy or policy for an organization or a service, program or item that is intended for individual sale to a consumer. The &lt;em&gt;Cutting Edge&lt;/em&gt; award recognizes participants for their new, game-changing ideas in electronics sustainability&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/smm-electronics/sustainable-materials-management-smm-electronics-challenge-champion-award&quot;&gt;Apply for an Electronics Challenge Champion Award&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;2014&quot;&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;2015&quot; name=&quot;2015&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;2016 Challenge Results and Award Winners&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2015, the combined efforts of the Sustainable Materials Management (SMM) Electronics Challenge participants achieved notable environmental results. By rethinking business as usual and committing to innovative and responsible end-of-life electronics management, Electronics Challenge participants collectively:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Diverted 256,822 tons of end-of-life electronics from the landfill;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Sent 256,614 tons of end-of-life electronics to third-party certified recyclers; and&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Avoided the emission of more than 673,000 tons of carbon dioxide equivalent.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is equal to any one of the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Taking over 129,000 passenger vehicles off of the road for one year;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Generating enough electricity for more than 90,000 U.S. homes for one year; or&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Replacing more than 21.6 million incandescent lamps with LEDs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Environmental benefits calculated using the following tools:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;EPA&#039;s &lt;a href=&quot;/energy/greenhouse-gas-equivalencies-calculator&quot;&gt;Greenhouse Gas Equivalencies Calculator&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;University of Tennessee at Knoxville &lt;a href=&quot;http://isse.utk.edu/ccp/projects/benefitscalculator/elecbenecalc.html&quot;&gt;Electronics Environmental Benefits Calculator&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3&gt;EPA is pleased to announce the 2016 Electronics Challenge Tier Award winners and Champion Award winners:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;accordion&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#pane-1&quot; title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot;&gt;Tier Awards&lt;/a&gt;

		&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;pane-1&quot;&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;Electronics Challenge Tier Awards are given in recognition of achieving all the requirements under a &lt;a href=&quot;/smm-electronics/fact-sheet-about-tiered-structure-sustainable-materials-management-smm-electronics&quot;&gt;Gold, Silver or Bronze Tier&lt;/a&gt;. Participants join at the level that best suits their organization, experience and ability. By meeting Tier requirements, participants receive Gold, Silver or Bronze award designations. We are pleased to recognize the following companies for their outstanding efforts in 2015 to advance the responsible management of used electronics through third-party certified recycling. The companies listed received the following Tier Awards.&lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;table&gt;&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;Active Participants&lt;/th&gt;
						&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;Tier Award&lt;/th&gt;
					&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Best Buy Co., Inc.&lt;/td&gt;
						&lt;td&gt;Gold&lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Dell Inc.&lt;/td&gt;
						&lt;td&gt;Gold&lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;LG Electronics USA, Inc.&lt;/td&gt;
						&lt;td&gt;Gold&lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Samsung Electronics&lt;/td&gt;
						&lt;td&gt;Gold&lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Sony Electronics Inc.&lt;/td&gt;
						&lt;td&gt;Bronze&lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Sprint&lt;/td&gt;
						&lt;td&gt;Gold&lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Staples, Inc.&lt;/td&gt;
						&lt;td&gt;Gold&lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;VIZIO, Inc.&lt;/td&gt;
						&lt;td&gt;Bronze&lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#pane-2&quot; title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot;&gt;Champion Awards&lt;/a&gt;
		&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;pane-2&quot;&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;Champion Awards are given to Electronics Challenge participants who demonstrate the highest level of vision, coalition-building, and execution of programs and policies related to responsible used electronics management. Electronics Challenge Participants must &lt;a href=&quot;/smm-electronics/sustainable-materials-management-smm-electronics-challenge-champion-award&quot;&gt;apply for Champion Awards&lt;/a&gt;, which are given in three categories: &lt;em&gt;Product&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Non-Product&lt;/em&gt;, and, new in 2016, &lt;em&gt;Cutting Edge&lt;/em&gt;. For the purposes of the Champion Awards, a &lt;em&gt;Product&lt;/em&gt; is an item that is manufactured, developed or refined for sale and is in the marketplace, while a &lt;em&gt;Non-Product&lt;/em&gt; is an internal or external plan, strategy, or policy for an organization, or a service, program or item that is intended for individual sale to a consumer. The &lt;em&gt;Cutting Edge&lt;/em&gt; award recognizes participants for their new, game-changing ideas in electronics sustainability. EPA is pleased to announce the following recipients of the 2016 Electronics Challenge Champion Awards:&lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;table&gt;&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;Company&lt;/th&gt;
						&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;Champion Award&lt;/th&gt;
					&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Dell Inc.&lt;/td&gt;
						&lt;td&gt;Product&lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Staples&lt;/td&gt;
						&lt;td&gt;Non-Product&lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Samsung Electronics&lt;/td&gt;
						&lt;td&gt;Cutting Edge&lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#pane-3&quot; title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot;&gt;Details on the 2016 Award Winners&lt;/a&gt;
		&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;pane-3&quot;&gt;
			&lt;h2&gt;Dell Inc., Winner, Product Category&lt;/h2&gt;

			&lt;p&gt;Dell Inc. is recognized for the use of post-industrial recycled (PIR) carbon filled polycarbonate in the Latitude E7450 laptop, the first laptop to use this material. By using PIR material, it has kept 170,000 pounds of carbon fiber from being landfilled in 2015. This material was developed in response to a specific technical challenge: to maintain strength and reliability of enclosures as mobility products become thinner and lighter. The design solution also needed to be in line with Dell’s Legacy of Good goals without adding cost. In the end, the choice of PIR recycled carbon fiber proved an ideal fit, showing there does not need to be a compromise between design and sustainability – the two can be integrated and mutually serve each other. Life cycle assessment (LCA) results show that reclaimed carbon fiber has approximately a 10% smaller carbon footprint than that of virgin carbon fiber weave and 76% smaller carbon footprint than magnesium alloy – two industry-standard notebook enclosure materials.&lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;p&gt;To continue to decrease their products’ environmental footprint, Dell is working to develop a post-consumer recycled (PCR) polycarbonate-based carbon fiber-reinforced plastic. Also, with Dell’s closed loop recycling program, products containing these resins can be recovered and recycled again as they come back into Dell’s consumer and commercial recycling programs in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;h2&gt;Staples, Winner, Non-Product Category&lt;/h2&gt;

			&lt;p&gt;Staples is recognized for an outreach and public education initiative, which reached over 6 million consumers with information on their Technology Recycling Program. Through their efforts, Staples attained a significant increase in the tons collected per store from 2014 to 2015 and then ensured that 100% of the e-waste collected from consumers was sent to a certified recycler. Staples global goal is to recycle 40 million pounds of e-waste each year by 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;p&gt;Staples has made a commitment on behalf of its customers to ensure their electronics are recycled to the highest environmental standards. The strategic alignment of program partners has bridged their entire value chain for customers by aligning Staples’ retailer program with original equipment manufacturer support and responsible electronics recycling.&lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;p&gt;Staples understands that U.S. consumers and businesses across the country are in need of opportunities to recycle their electronic devices. By effectively marketing the Staples programs to consumers, Staples has provided current and future customers with a direct link between easy purchasing and easy recycling.&lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;h2&gt;Samsung, Winner, Cutting Edge&lt;/h2&gt;

			&lt;p&gt;Samsung is recognized for the Cadmium-free Quantum Dot ultra-high definition televisions, an industry first. The resulting TVs are free of cadmium – a hazardous heavy metal – and use less materials and energy than other HDTVs, with properties that allow for better light efficiency and improved durability.&lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;p&gt;Cadmium has unique electrical, optical, and performance properties. Without the use of cadmium, the optical efficiency of a device is typically reduced. In order to make up for this, LED control circuitry usually must be added which increased the price as well as the energy consumption. Therefore, manufacturers pushed to have exemptions in environmental regulations to continue using cadmium in these types of applications. Samsung has overcome that technical difficulty by developing a new, more environmentally friendly approach in delivering better performance and value than the cadmium-containing devices. Samsung’s Quantum Dots are based on indium and (according to Samsung) are the only company that produces Cadmium-free Quantum Dot displays.&lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;p&gt;To further the technology and expand the scientific impact, Samsung has brought together top academic and R&amp;amp;D institutions for the continued performance improvement of cadmium-free Quantum Dot material and application development. Most recently, in 2016, Samsung hosted a Quantum Dot forum and invited international scholars to share the innovation direction of Cd-free Quantum Dot technology. This has strengthened further their ties to the academic world and is helping them scale other green innovations.&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;2014 challenge information&quot; id=&quot;2014 challenge information&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;2015 Challenge Information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2014, the efforts of the SMM Electronics Challenge participants resulted in the following achievements:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Diverted 224,263 metric tons of end-of-life electronics from the landfill;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Sent 223,743 metric tons of end-of-life electronics to third-party certified recyclers; and&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Avoided the emission of more than 588,000 tons of carbon dioxide equivalent in 2014.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;This increase is equal to any one of the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Taking over 112,000 passenger vehicles off of the road for one year;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Saving enough energy to power more than 73,000 U.S. homes for one year; or&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;The amount of carbon sequestered annually by more than 437,000 acres of U.S. forest.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul class=&quot;accordion&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#pane-4&quot; title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot;&gt;2015 Challenge Results&lt;/a&gt;

		&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;pane-4&quot;&gt;
			&lt;h3&gt;Tier Awards&lt;/h3&gt;

			&lt;p&gt;Electronics Challenge Tier Awards are given in recognition of achieving all the requirements under a &lt;a href=&quot;/smm-electronics/fact-sheet-about-tiered-structure-sustainable-materials-management-smm-electronics&quot;&gt;Gold, Silver or Bronze Tier&lt;/a&gt;. Participants join at the level that best suits their organization, experience and ability. By meeting Tier requirements, participants receive Gold, Silver or Bronze award designations. We are pleased to recognize the following companies for their outstanding efforts in 2014 to advance the responsible management of used electronics through third-party certified recycling. The companies listed received the following Tier Awards.&lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;table&gt;&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;Active Participants&lt;/th&gt;
						&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;Tier Award&lt;/th&gt;
					&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Best Buy Co., Inc.&lt;/td&gt;
						&lt;td&gt;Gold&lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Dell Inc.&lt;/td&gt;
						&lt;td&gt;Gold&lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;LG Electronics USA, Inc.&lt;/td&gt;
						&lt;td&gt;Gold&lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Samsung Electronics&lt;/td&gt;
						&lt;td&gt;Gold&lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Sony Electronics Inc.&lt;/td&gt;
						&lt;td&gt;Bronze&lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Sprint&lt;/td&gt;
						&lt;td&gt;Gold&lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Staples, Inc.&lt;/td&gt;
						&lt;td&gt;Gold&lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Champion Awards&lt;/h3&gt;

			&lt;p&gt;Champion Awards are given to Electronics Challenge participants who demonstrate the highest level of vision, coalition-building, and execution of programs and policies related to responsible used electronics management. Electronics Challenge Participants must &lt;a href=&quot;/smm-electronics/sustainable-materials-management-smm-electronics-challenge-champion-award&quot;&gt;apply for Champion Awards&lt;/a&gt;, which are given in two categories: &lt;em&gt;Product&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Non-Product&lt;/em&gt;. For the purposes of the Champion Awards, a &lt;em&gt;Product&lt;/em&gt; is an item that is manufactured, developed or refined for sale and is in the marketplace, while a &lt;em&gt;Non-Product&lt;/em&gt; is an internal or external plan, strategy, or policy for an organization, as well as a service, program or item that is intended for individual sale to a consumer. EPA is pleased to announce the following recipients of the 2015 Electronics Challenge Champion Awards:&lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;table&gt;&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;Company&lt;/th&gt;
						&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;Champion Award&lt;/th&gt;
					&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Dell Inc.&lt;/td&gt;
						&lt;td&gt;Non-product&lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Samsung Electronics&lt;/td&gt;
						&lt;td&gt;Product&lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Details on the 2015 Award Winners&lt;/h3&gt;

			&lt;h2&gt;Dell Inc., Winner, Non-Product Category&lt;/h2&gt;

			&lt;p&gt;Dell Inc. is recognized for its development of a closed loop program that uses plastics recovered from the Dell Reconnect recycling partnership with Goodwill in the U.S. to make new computers through the company’s manufacturing partner, Wistron. Wistron uses state-of-the-art technology to mix the recycled plastics with virgin materials that are then used for plastic parts in select Dell computers. This project is part of Dell’s long-term sustainability plan to achieve a waste-free packaging stream by 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;p&gt;Dell brought together worldwide recycling, logistics, and manufacturing partners for this program. Dell has partnered with Wistron to develop closed loop plastics, Goodwill to collect e-waste, YFY Jupiter to create wheat straw packaging, and United Nations Industrial Development Organization (UNIDO) to identify sustainable solutions for e-waste management. Using recycled resin is not always as easy as expected since recycled resin is not a direct substitute for a virgin resin. Dell set an ambitious goal to use 50 million pounds of recycled content and other sustainable materials in its products by the year 2020 and has recycled 11 million pounds of closed loop plastics in displays and OptiPlex desktops in 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;p&gt;Best Buy also implements a number of internal and external communication efforts about the value of recycling. Best Buy trains and motivates employees through its Standard Operating Procedures and through a video entitled, &quot;Why Best Buy Recycles.&quot; These programs ensure that all employees understand Best Buy&#039;s recycling program and can communicate it to its customers. The recent launch of the video &quot;Why Best Buy Recycles&quot; to the public has received more than 800,000 views to-date, indicating the message about the importance of recycling is being widely distributed. In addition, Best Buy&#039;s webpage not only makes it easy to find collection points, but also notes how much material was collected in each state.&lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;p&gt;By closing the loop for plastics, Dell achieved the following environmental benefits in 2014:&lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Avoided 198,776 kilograms of CO2 equivalent or about 500,000 miles driven by an average passenger car;&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;li&gt;Reused 2.89 million pounds of materials taken from the e-waste stream;&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;li&gt;Collected 230.9 million pounds of used electronics from residential and business programs globally; and&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;li&gt;Reduced costs, as a result of lower logistics and operations costs of processing plastics from e-waste.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Dell demonstrated that this program is replicable by other electronics manufacturers. Not only does it provide easy take-back solutions for consumers through Goodwill, but it also helps to create jobs for people in need of work. For every computer donated, 6.8 hours of job training are provided to Goodwill employees. Dell’s leadership extends to closing the digital divide by building positive e-scrap collection in Africa. For example, Dell finances a woman entrepreneur who employs 27 trained women to safely collect e-waste from local businesses and homes in Nairobi’s Mukuru informal settlement.&lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;h2&gt;Samsung Electronics, Winner, Product Category&lt;/h2&gt;

			&lt;p&gt;Samsung Electronics is recognized for its vision to make the Galaxy S6 mobile phone, its packaging, and its accessories meet high environmental standards while maintaining its status as a high-end product. Samsung has reduced the carbon emissions in each consecutive S Series phone by an annual average of 14%. This aggregates to 58 billion kg CO2 since 2011— the equivalent of planting 4.7 million trees. The S6’s environmental features are highlighted below:&lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;h3&gt;Packaging made with recycled materials&lt;/h3&gt;

			&lt;p&gt;While many of today’s electronics come in packaging made from non-recyclable plastics, Samsung found a simple solution to the problem by making 100% of its packaging from recycled cardboard, from the box to the user’s manual. This feature is anticipated to prevent the logging of 77,000 trees (based on 2014 sales numbers).&lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;h3&gt;Labels printed with soy ink&lt;/h3&gt;

			&lt;p&gt;Instead of using petroleum-based inks, Samsung uses soy-based inks in their packaging labels. Soy-based inks are:&lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Made from a renewable resource&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;li&gt;Biodegradable&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;li&gt;Easier to remove before recycling paper&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Battery chargers partially made of recycled plastic&lt;/h3&gt;

			&lt;p&gt;Samsung took an important stride by making the S6’s battery charger with 20 percent recycled plastic. Due to the research and development team’s perseverance and ingenuity, the charger’s durability was not compromised and Samsung was able to overcome an “engineering preference for virgin materials.”&lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;h3&gt;Features for longer life&lt;/h3&gt;

			&lt;p&gt;Samsung’s design team worked to overcome a hurdle in the battery capability of the phone that resulted in greater innovation and improved battery charging. The Galaxy S6 allows users to conserve power when they want by using the Power Saving Mode and Ultra Power Saving Mode, which disables most apps and changes screen colors to grayscale. Increasing the warranty to two years is also a clear signal to consumers that cell phones do not have to be replaced annually. Since the most common reason for replacing a mobile phone is a cracked screen from impact damage, Samsung used the new Gorilla Glass 4, which is more durable and resistant to scratches. This will further extend the life of the phone.&lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;h3&gt;Responsible End of Life Management&lt;/h3&gt;

			&lt;p&gt;Samsung’s Recycling Direct program ensures that waste processed will not be exported to developing countries, will not use forced child or prison labor in processing, and will not be dumped in municipal landfills. In addition to supporting a responsible network of recyclers, Samsung developed the Galaxy S6 with a recyclability rate of 99.9% and provides an online prepaid cell phone return option for customers to ship the phone back to Samsung for responsible recycling free of charge.&lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;p&gt;Samsung achieved its vision by collaborating with a diverse group of internal and external stakeholders, and through a wide variety of approaches including forums, inquiries, surveys, advisory groups, and specialized internal communications departments that address the needs and expectations of each stakeholder.&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Mon, 08 Feb 2016 19:19:57 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>tbuhrman</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">134581 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Implementation Study of the Electronics Recycling Standards: R2 and e-Stewards</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/smm-electronics/implementation-study-electronics-recycling-standards-r2-and-e-stewards</link>
    <description>&lt;div class=&quot;box multi related-info right&quot;&gt;
	&lt;h2 class=&quot;pane-title&quot;&gt;Related Link&lt;/h2&gt;

	&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://yosemite.epa.gov/opa/admpress.nsf/bd4379a92ceceeac8525735900400c27/7c21d5c65cfca09785257f4f006b2aef!OpenDocument&quot;&gt;EPA Study Finds Electronics Recycling Standards are Well Implemented and Makes Recommendations for Further Improvement &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA’s Implementation Study of the Responsible Recycling (&quot;R2&quot;) Standard for Electronics Recyclers and the e-Stewards&lt;sup&gt;®&lt;/sup&gt; Standard for Responsible Recycling and Reuse of Electronic Equipment&lt;sup&gt;©&lt;/sup&gt; (&quot;e-Stewards&lt;sup&gt;®&lt;/sup&gt;&quot;) recycling standards fulfills a key commitment under the &lt;a href=&quot;/smm-electronics/national-strategy-electronics-stewardship-nses&quot;&gt;2011 National Strategy for Electronics Stewardship&lt;/a&gt;, which tasks the federal government to lead by example in encouraging the greener design and responsible management of used electronics. The study found that overall, the e-Stewards&lt;sup&gt;®&lt;/sup&gt; and R2 certification programs are generally being implemented well with opportunities for improvement identified in many of the topic areas assessed in the study. EPA offers suggested strategies and recommendations for improving implementation of the Standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/smm-electronics/frequent-questions-about-implementation-study-r2-and-e-stewards-certification&quot;&gt;Frequent Questions about the Implementation Study of the R2 &amp;amp; e-Stewards&lt;sup&gt;®&lt;/sup&gt; Electronics Recycling Certification Programs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-253339&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-02/documents/u_s_epa_fact_sheet_implementation_study_1.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=286219&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Fact Sheet: Implementation Study of the R2 &amp;amp; e-Stewards® Electronics Recycling Certification Programs (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(4 pp, 286 K, 
  February 2016)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-253143&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-02/documents/u_s_epa_implementation_study_final_report_february_2016.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=1991777&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Full Report: Implementation Study of the R2 and e-Stewards® Electronics Recycling Certification Programs (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(96 pp, 2 MB, 
  February 2016, 
  EPA-530-R-16-008)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 03 Feb 2016 17:35:56 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>Anonymous</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">133991 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Certified Electronics Recyclers</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/smm-electronics/certified-electronics-recyclers</link>
    <description>&lt;h4&gt;On this page:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#01&quot;&gt;What are certified electronics recyclers?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#02&quot;&gt;Benefits of becoming a certified recycler&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#04&quot;&gt;Map of certified electronics recyclers in the United States&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#implementation study&quot;&gt;Implementation Study of the R2 &amp;amp; e-Stewards&lt;sup&gt;®&lt;/sup&gt; Recycling Standards&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;01&quot; name=&quot;01&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;What Are Certified Electronics Recyclers?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA encourages all electronics recyclers to become certified by demonstrating to an accredited, independent third-party auditor that they meet specific standards to safely recycle and manage electronics. Currently two accredited certification standards exist: the &lt;a href=&quot;https://sustainableelectronics.org/&quot;&gt;Responsible Recycling (&quot;R2&quot;) Standard for Electronics Recyclers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&quot;http://e-stewards.org/&quot;&gt;e-Stewards&lt;sup&gt;®&lt;/sup&gt;Standard for Responsible Recycling and Reuse of Electronic Equipment&lt;span style=&quot;vertical-align:baseline&quot;&gt;©&lt;/span&gt;(&quot;e-Stewards&lt;sup&gt;®&lt;/sup&gt;&quot;)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt; standards. Both of these programs provide the following benefits:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Advance best management practices&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Offer a way to assess the environmental, worker health, and security practices of entities managing used electronics&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Are based on strong environmental standards that maximize reuse and recycling, minimize exposure to human health or the environment, ensure safe management of materials by downstream handlers, and require destruction of all data on used electronics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Certified electronics recyclers have demonstrated through audits and other means that they continually meet specific high environmental standards and safely manage used electronics. Once certified, continual oversight by the independent accredited certifying body holds the recycler to the particular standard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ANSI-ASQ National Accreditation Board (ANAB) is the organization that accredits certifying bodies in the United States. They provide an &lt;a href=&quot;http://anabdirectory.remoteauditor.com/&quot;&gt;updated list of which certifying body has attained accreditation to which standard&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;02&quot; name=&quot;02&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Benefits of Becoming a Certified Recycler&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Responsible electronics recycling provides important benefits, such as the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Reducing environmental and human health impacts from improper recycling&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Increasing access to quality reusable and refurbished equipment to those who need it&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Reducing energy use and other environmental impacts associated with mining and processing of virgin materials, conserving our limited natural resources&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;04&quot; name=&quot;04&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Map of Certified Electronics Recyclers in the United States&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;box multi related-info right&quot;&gt;
	&lt;h2 class=&quot;pane-title&quot;&gt;Helpful definitions&lt;/h2&gt;

	&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Services Included&lt;/strong&gt;. Refers to services the company includes as part of its electronics recycling operations. Examples of services include but are not limited to, data security, asset management.&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Certification Program&lt;/strong&gt;. Currently two accredited certification standards exist: R2 and the e-Stewards&lt;sup&gt;®&lt;/sup&gt; standards. Both programs advance best management practices and offer a way to assess the environmental, worker health, and security practices of entities managing used electronics.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Facility Contact Information&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;Click on the indicator to get information on the facility. For each facility, the map offers some or all of the following information:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Services Included&lt;/strong&gt;. Refers to services the company includes as part of its electronics recycling operations. Examples of services include, but are not limited to, data security and asset management.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Certification Program&lt;/strong&gt;. Currently two accredited certification standards exist: the R2 Practices and the e-Stewards&lt;sup&gt;®&lt;/sup&gt; standards. Both programs advance best management practices and offer a way to assess the environmental, worker health, and security practices of entities managing used electronics.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Facilities Certified to e-Stewards® or R2&lt;iframe height=&quot;600&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; src=&quot;https://epa.maps.arcgis.com/home/webmap/templates/OnePane/basicviewer/embed.html?webmap=&amp;#10;534098623f0945f5aafcd6f3691ce7a2&amp;amp;gcsextent=-135.281,10.1799,-46.5994,57.2524&amp;amp;displayslider=true&amp;amp;displaylegend=&amp;#10;true&amp;amp;displaydetails=true&amp;amp;displaysearch=true&quot; width=&quot;940&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://epa.maps.arcgis.com/home/webmap/viewer.html?webmap=534098623f0945f5aafcd6f3691ce7a2&amp;amp;extent=-135.281,10.1799,-46.5994,57.2524&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;View Larger Map&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;Last Updated: July 18, 2016 &lt;/small&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Facilities Certified to both e-Stewards® and R2&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe height=&quot;600&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; src=&quot;https://epa.maps.arcgis.com/home/webmap/templates/OnePane/basicviewer/embed.html?webmap=be7cf61b7acd420cb7f427d561f96fdd&amp;amp;gcsextent=-141.2089,7.717,-52.5273,55.8787&amp;amp;displayslider=true&amp;amp;displaylegend=true&amp;amp;displaydetails=true&amp;amp;displaysearch=true&quot; width=&quot;940&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://epa.maps.arcgis.com/home/webmap/viewer.html?webmap=be7cf61b7acd420cb7f427d561f96fdd&amp;amp;extent=&amp;#10;-141.2089,7.717,-52.5273,55.8787&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;View Larger Map&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Disclaimers and Limitations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;box multi related-info right&quot;&gt;
	&lt;h2 class=&quot;pane-title&quot;&gt;Data Sources for Certified Electronics Recyclers&lt;/h2&gt;

	&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://e-stewards.org/find-a-recycler/&quot;&gt;e-Stewards®&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://sustainableelectronics.org/recyclers&quot;&gt;Sustainable Electronics Recycling International (SERI)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Disclaimer of Endorsement:&lt;/strong&gt; This map is provided for informational purposes only. Inclusion on this map does not imply endorsement by the EPA or any of its employees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; Inclusion on this map does not imply compliance with applicable federal and state laws and regulations; only that these facilities have met the requirements of a third-party electronics recycling certification program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What are the limitations of interactive maps?&lt;/strong&gt; Interactive mapping tools are a challenge for accessibility due to the inherent visual aspects of mapping. These maps cannot be made fully accessible under Section 508 of the Rehabilitation Act of 1973 (as amended in 1998). For the Certified Electronics Refurbisher and Recycler Map, if a person needs accommodations due to a disability, please access the links below for a complete list of certified recyclers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;implementation study&quot; id=&quot;implementation study&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Implementation Study of the R2 &amp;amp; e-Stewards® Recycling Standards&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA completed a limited study evaluating the implementation of the two third-party certification programs for electronic waste recyclers in the U.S. - R2 and e-Stewards&lt;sup&gt;®&lt;/sup&gt;. The goal of the study is to assess whether the Standards are being implemented transparently and consistently, and are achieving the desired results. Where appropriate, the final report provides suggested strategies and recommendations for improving implementation using input from stakeholder interviews and certification audit observations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/smm-electronics/frequent-questions-about-implementation-study-r2-and-e-stewards-certification&quot;&gt;Frequent Questions about the Implementation Study of the R2 and e-Stewards&lt;sup&gt;®&lt;/sup&gt; Electronics Recycling Certification Programs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/smm-electronics/implementation-study-electronics-recycling-standards-r2-and-e-stewards&quot;&gt;Full Report and Fact Sheet for the Implementation Study of the R2 and e-Stewards&lt;sup&gt;®&lt;/sup&gt; Electronics Recycling Certification Programs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Mon, 01 Feb 2016 17:00:15 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>Anonymous</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">133673 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Frequent Questions about the Implementation Study of R2 and e-Stewards Certification Programs</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/smm-electronics/frequent-questions-about-implementation-study-r2-and-e-stewards-certification</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;On this page:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;box multi related-info right&quot;&gt;
	&lt;h2 class=&quot;pane-title&quot;&gt;Related Link&lt;/h2&gt;

	&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/smm-electronics/implementation-study-electronics-recycling-standards-r2-and-e-stewards&quot;&gt;Full Report and Fact Sheet for the Implementation Study of Electronics Standards: R2 &amp;amp; e-Stewards&lt;sup&gt;®&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#external 1&quot;&gt;Why did EPA conduct this study?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#external 2&quot;&gt;How was the study designed? &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#external 3&quot;&gt;What are the limitations of the study?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#external 4&quot;&gt;Did EPA assess both versions of the Standards (2008 &amp;amp; 2013) in the study?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#external 5&quot;&gt;How did EPA select the facilities whose audits were observed?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#external 6&quot;&gt;What are the key findings and recommendations of the study?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#external 7&quot;&gt;Are the recommendations directed at any organization in particular?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#external 8&quot;&gt;Is one of the standards being implemented more successfully than the other? &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;external 1&quot; id=&quot;external 1&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Question: Why did EPA conduct this study?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Answer: &lt;/strong&gt;EPA conducted this study to fulfill a key commitment under the &lt;a href=&quot;/smm-electronics/national-strategy-electronics-stewardship&quot;&gt;2011 National Strategy for Electronics Stewardship&lt;/a&gt;, which tasks the federal government to lead by example in encouraging the greener design and responsible management of used electronics. The goals of the study are to assess whether the Standards are being implemented transparently and consistently, and are achieving the desired results. Where appropriate, the study’s final report provides recommendations for improving the system using input from stakeholder interviews and certification audit observations. The study was conducted in collaboration with the U.S. General Services Administration and the ANSI-ASQ National Accreditation Board (ANAB).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;external 2&quot; id=&quot;external 2&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Question: How was the study designed? &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Answer:&lt;/strong&gt; To achieve the objectives of the study, EPA:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Conducted interviews with key stakeholders across the electronics recycling system to obtain their perspective on areas of strength and opportunities for improvement;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Observed audits of reuse and recycling facilities performed by the certifying bodies to assess the consistency and rigorousness of the audits; and&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Analyzed the results and developed findings, conclusions and recommendations which are documented in the final report.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;EPA also relied on a team of qualified contractors for technical support in conducting the study. The contractors possessed expert knowledge of the Standards as well as experience auditing recycling/reuse facilities to the Standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;external 3&quot; id=&quot;external 3&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Question: What are the limitations of the study?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Answer:&lt;/strong&gt; The study’s findings are based on 39 stakeholder interviews EPA conducted and nine audits EPA observed. The nine facility audits reflect a small percentage of all certified electronics recycling facilities and auditors working in the electronics recycling industry in the U.S. However, the interviews included all of the organizations essential to implementing the Standards, such as the ANAB, R2 and e-Stewards&lt;sup&gt;®&lt;/sup&gt;, and all of the certification bodies responsible for certifying facilities to the standards across the country. Though limited in number, the audits EPA observed reflected the range of audit types, facility sizes, and services offered by facilities seeking to obtain or maintain certification to the Standards. For additional discussion of the study’s limitations, please see the final report.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;external 4&quot; id=&quot;external 4&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Question: Did EPA assess both versions of the Standards (2008 &amp;amp; 2013) in the study?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Answer:&lt;/strong&gt; Both the e-Stewards&lt;sup&gt;®&lt;/sup&gt; and R2 standards were updated during the course of the study, in the latter half of 2013. EPA modified the scope of the study to include additional audits and interviews to ensure both versions of the standards were included in the study.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;external 5&quot; id=&quot;external 5&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Question: How did EPA select the facilities whose audits were observed?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Answer:&lt;/strong&gt; When considering potential facilities for inclusion in the audit observation portion of the study, EPA aimed to include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;A cross-section of the different types of facilities that are seeking to obtain or maintain their certification in the United States, both in terms of the kinds of audits that are typically conducted by the certifying bodies, which are the organizations accredited to certify facilities to one or both standards, as well as the range of services offered by facilities seeking certification.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;An equal number of R2 and e-Stewards&lt;sup&gt;®&lt;/sup&gt; audits, as well as one combined audit where a facility was seeking certification to both Standards; and&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Audits to both versions of the Standards (2008 and 2013).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;With these criteria in mind, EPA worked closely with the certifying bodies to identify candidate facilities to participate in the study. For all nine audits observed, the certifying bodies contacted the facilities in advance of EPA’s arrival and the facilities agreed to let EPA attend the audit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;external 6&quot; id=&quot;external 6&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Question: What are the key findings and recommendations of the study?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Answer: &lt;/strong&gt;The study suggests that the accreditation, certification and implementation process of the R2 and e-Stewards&lt;sup&gt;®&lt;/sup&gt; standards is working well. Though limited in scope, the study also identifies opportunities for improvement in key areas, including improving stakeholders’ knowledge of health and safety risks, understanding of legal requirements, and awareness of hazardous substances in electronics. EPA’s top recommendations for improving overall implementation include (but are not limited to) providing additional training and guidance materials in key topic areas, regularly updating the Standards, and increasing audit times to allow for more thorough audits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;external 7&quot; id=&quot;external 7&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Question: Are the recommendations directed at any organization in particular?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Answer:&lt;/strong&gt; In practice, many stakeholders will continue to influence and shape the development of responsible recycling in the U.S. and therefore have been considered when drawing the Study’s conclusions and making recommendations. As such, EPA encourages all organizations that have a role to play in shaping the standards and certification process to consider the suggested strategies for improvement and top recommendations in the study. This broader group of stakeholders includes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;The Standards owners (Sustainable Electronics Recycling International and the Basel Action Network)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;The Certifying Bodies&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Federal and state regulators&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Trade associations&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;ANAB&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;EPA and other federal agencies, including the Occupational Safety and Health Administration, the National Institute for Occupational Safety and Health, and the Department of Transportation&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Original equipment manufacturers&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Academic researchers&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Non-governmental organizations&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Private sector companies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;EPA remains committed to continuing the dialogue started by this study and supporting the continual improvement of the implementation of the electronics recycling Standards, and will provide assistance and support to stakeholders in discussing and implementing the suggested strategies and recommendations outlined in the final report.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;external 8&quot; id=&quot;external 8&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Question: Is one of the standards being implemented more successfully than the other? &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Answer:&lt;/strong&gt; The study intentionally does not compare the two standards or draw conclusions about whether one standard is being implemented more successfully than the other. The purpose of the study is to assess whether the Standards as a whole are being implemented transparently, consistently, and are achieving the desired results. To this end, the assessment focused on the implementation processes and procedures shared by both Standards, as well as 20 key topic areas that are addressed in both Standards, such as training and communication, health and safety requirements, and export issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Mon, 01 Feb 2016 16:38:38 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>esundin</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">133665 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Sustainable Materials Management (SMM) Electronics Challenge: Champion Award Application</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/smm-electronics/sustainable-materials-management-smm-electronics-challenge-champion-award</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;Champion Award Application Step-by-Instructions: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1. Read entire application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2. Determine eligibility (all current SMM Electronics Challenge Participants that have submitted their 2015 annual data results to EPA by the June 30, 2016 deadline are eligible).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3. Decide on award category (you may choose Product or Non-Product or both).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4. Write Abstract (up to 250 words) and Narrative (up to 4,000 words) that addresses the four judging criteria: Vision, Coalition Building, Execution and Impact and reflects work completed in calendar year 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;5. Gather optional supplemental information (not to exceed four pages).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;6. Fill out contact information at the end of the application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;7. Submit completed form online via the SMM Data Management System no later than May 15, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-202837&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-09/documents/elec_chall_award_applic_2015.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=366192&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;SMM Electronics Challenge Champion Awards Application (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(4 pp, 366 K, 
  2015)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2015 18:50:21 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>esundin</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">117583 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Sustainable Materials Management (SMM) Electronics Challenge: List of Participants</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/smm-electronics/sustainable-materials-management-smm-electronics-challenge-list-participants</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;Below are SMM Electronics Challenge participants in the consumer electronics and used electronics industries. &lt;span&gt;By striving to send 100 percent of used electronics collected to certified recyclers and refurbishers, these Challenge participants helped to ensure that the used electronics they collected were responsibly managed by &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;recyclers &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;that maximize reuse and recycling, minimize exposure to human health and the environment, ensure the safe management of materials by downstream handlers, and require destruction of all data on used electronics.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;&lt;caption&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;SMM Electronics Challenge Active Participants&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/caption&gt;
	&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;Organization&lt;/th&gt;
			&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;Status&lt;/th&gt;
			&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;City, State&lt;/th&gt;
			&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;EPA Region&lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Best Buy Co., Inc.&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Active Participant&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;South Richfield, MN&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Dell Inc.&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Active Participant&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Round Rock, TX&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;LG Electronics USA, Inc.&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Active Participant&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Englewood Cliffs, NJ&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Samsung Electronics&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Active Participant&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Ridgefield Park, NJ&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Sony Electronics, Inc.&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Active Participant&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;San Diego, CA&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;9&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Sprint&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Active Participant&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Overland Park, KS&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Staples, Inc.&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Active Participant&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Framingham, MA&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;VIZIO, Inc.&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Active Participant&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Irvine, CA&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;9&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;p&gt;What participants are saying:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-png left view-mode-thumbnail&quot; style=&quot;width:96px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;official logo of Best Buy&quot; title=&quot;Best Buy logo&quot; height=&quot;72&quot; width=&quot;96&quot; class=&quot;left media-element file-thumbnail left&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/thumbnail/public/2015-09/2000px-best_buy_logo.svg.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&quot;On behalf of Best Buy, we applaud EPA&#039;s leadership to encourage even greater, more convenient options for consumers to recycle electronics. From our Trade-In program, to convenient in-store recycling programs and our ENERGY STAR partnership, we’re committed to ensuring that everyone has access to easy, sustainable technology choices that make a positive social and environmental impact. Best Buy has long offered the most comprehensive electronics recycling options, and continue to work only with certified recyclers. Consumers recycle more consumer electronics and appliances with Best Buy than any other retailer - an average of 387 pounds are recycled each minute at Best Buy. And recycling is free, with few restrictions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have seen first-hand that demand for these services continues to grow. We look forward to continuing to work with EPA to expand initiatives that benefit consumers and meet this demand.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;- George Sherman, Senior Vice President for Services&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg left view-mode-thumbnail&quot; style=&quot;width:96px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;official logo for Dell&quot; title=&quot;Dell logo&quot; height=&quot;54&quot; width=&quot;96&quot; class=&quot;left media-element file-thumbnail left&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/thumbnail/public/2015-09/dell.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&quot;Dell is helping its customers worldwide protect the environment by offering electronics recycling programs that are easy-to-use, convenient, effective and secure. We’re proud to join the EPA for a second year of the Electronics Challenge, and we’re committed to continuing to promote and lead responsible reuse and recycling to extend the life of our products and keep e-waste out of landfills.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;- Trisa Thompson, Vice President of Corporate Responsibility&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg left view-mode-thumbnail&quot; style=&quot;width:96px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Official logo for LG (Life&amp;#039;s Good)&quot; title=&quot;LG logo&quot; height=&quot;56&quot; width=&quot;96&quot; class=&quot;left media-element file-thumbnail left&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/thumbnail/public/2015-09/lg-logo.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&quot;LG is proud to support the EPA’s Electronics Challenge, and we are pledging to achieve Gold status in this important program. By joining the Challenge, we’re committing to refurbishing and recycling even more used electronics. And, by using third-party certified recyclers we’re are helping to drive the use of environmentally protective practices. We look forward to participating in the Electronics Challenge and other activities under the National Strategy for Electronics Stewardship.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;- William Cho, President and CEO, LG Electronics USA&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-png left view-mode-thumbnail&quot; style=&quot;width:96px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Official logo for Samsung Electronics&quot; title=&quot;Samsung Electronics logo&quot; height=&quot;25&quot; width=&quot;96&quot; class=&quot;left media-element file-thumbnail left&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/thumbnail/public/2015-09/samsung_electronics_logo_english.svg.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&quot;Samsung has long been committed to sustainability and is proud to be among the first to show our support for the EPA whose initiative aligns perfectly with our commitment to protect the people and the environment through responsible recycling.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;- Yangkyu (Y.K.) Kim, President and CEO&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-png left view-mode-thumbnail&quot; style=&quot;width:96px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Official logo for Sprint&quot; title=&quot;Sprint logo&quot; height=&quot;40&quot; width=&quot;96&quot; class=&quot;left media-element file-thumbnail left&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/thumbnail/public/2015-09/sprint-logo.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&quot;Responsible electronic waste management is a priority for Sprint and voluntary commitments like those attained through the (SMM) Electronics Challenge pushes all industries forward.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;- Bill White, Senior Vice President, Corporate Communications and Corporate Responsibility&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-png left view-mode-thumbnail&quot; style=&quot;width:96px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img height=&quot;24&quot; width=&quot;96&quot; class=&quot;left media-element file-thumbnail left&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/thumbnail/public/2016-08/vizio_logo.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&quot;VIZIO takes its role in protecting the environment very seriously and encourages responsible recycling and reuse of electronics. We’re thrilled to join EPA as a committed participant in its Electronics Challenge. Proper recycling and refurbishment of electronic equipment is of paramount importance when evaluating environmental responsibility. With over 100,000,000 lbs. of devices recycled since 2014, VIZIO is looking forward to its continued role as a steward of sustainable practices.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;—&lt;/em&gt;Rob Brinkmann, Chief Administrative Officer&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;DISCLAIMER: EPA may not endorse the products or services of commercial companies. Any quotes or references to a specific commercial product or service by trade name, trademark, manufacturer, company, or otherwise does not constitute or imply the endorsement or recommendation of EPA.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2015 17:26:14 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>esundin</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">117527 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Sustainable Materials Management (SMM) Electronics Challenge: Participation Agreement</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/smm-electronics/sustainable-materials-management-smm-electronics-challenge-participation-agreement</link>
    <description>&lt;div&gt;On this page:&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#section 1&quot;&gt;Section I: Program Goals for the SMM Electronics Challenge&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#section 2&quot;&gt;Section II: Participant Pledge&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#section 3&quot;&gt;Section III: EPA Commitment to SMM Electronics Challenge Participants&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#section 4&quot;&gt;Section IV: Challenge General Terms and Disclaimers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;section 1&quot; id=&quot;section 1&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Section I: Program Goals for the SMM Electronics Challenge&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The goal of EPA&#039;s Sustainable Materials Management (SMM) Electronics Challenge is to advance the responsible management of used electronics by challenging manufacturers, brand owners and retailers of electronics to voluntarily strive to send 100 percent of used electronics collected for reuse and recycling to &lt;a href=&quot;/smm-electronics/certified-electronics-recyclers&quot;&gt;third-party certified recyclers&lt;/a&gt;, increase the total amount of used electronics collected for reuse and recycling, and publicly post information and data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*&lt;strong&gt;Note&lt;/strong&gt;: Currently, &lt;a href=&quot;http://e-stewards.org/&quot;&gt;e-Stewards®&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.call2recycle.org/r2/&quot;&gt;Responsible Recycling Practices (R2)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;are the only recognized certification standards for recyclers. However, EPA may recognize additional standards at a later date.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;section 2&quot; id=&quot;section 2&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Section II: Participant Pledge&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an EPA SMM Electronics Challenge participant, my organization shares EPA’s goals as outlined above, and commits to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;Strive to send 100 percent of used electronics collected from all collection streams (e.g., consumer, warranty and return, business to business and internal equipment) to recyclers or refurbishers that have been certified to a recognized third-party certification program.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Submit baseline data within 6 months of registration.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Submit annual data, according to participation tier, to EPA.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Post commitments, policies and data on the participant’s web site using the EPA-provided templates.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;With this agreement, my organization also intends to reach the following tier category as described in the &lt;a href=&quot;/smm-electronics/fact-sheet-about-tiered-structure-sustainable-materials-management-smm-electronics&quot;&gt;SMM Electronics Challenge Tiers of Participation&lt;/a&gt; document: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;b&gt;Bronze, Silver, Gold &lt;/b&gt;(send form to contact information located at the bottom of this page).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;section 3&quot; id=&quot;section 3&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Section III: EPA&#039;s Commitment to SMM Electronics Challenge Participants&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;Respond promptly to registrant and participant requests for information or clarification on EPA’s SMM Electronics Challenge.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Provide public recognition by listing all organizations who sign the Pledge as REGISTRANTS on EPA’s website.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Review each participant’s baseline data, goals and public posting to verify eligibility to be listed as a new participant on the EPA&#039;s &lt;a href=&quot;/smm-electronics/sustainable-materials-management-smm-electronics-challenge&quot;&gt;SMM Electronics Challenge&lt;/a&gt; website.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Routinely assess each participant’s submission and public posting of annual data and information to verify eligibility to receive recognition as a Bronze, Silver or Gold active participant on SMM website.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Provide access to and maintenance of an online reporting and data management system.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;section 4&quot; id=&quot;section 4&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Section IV: Challenge General Terms and Disclaimers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;Either party can terminate this agreement at any time without prior notification and with no further obligation. EPA will not comment publicly regarding the withdrawal of participants.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Participant agrees that the activities it undertakes connected with this voluntary agreement are not intended to provide services to the federal government and that the participant will not seek compensation from a federal agency.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Participant agrees that it will not claim or imply that its participation constitutes EPA approval or endorsement of anything other than its participation in the SMM Electronics Challenge and will not make statements or imply that EPA endorses the participant or the purchase or sale of the participant’s products and services or the views of the participant’s organization.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;EPA may publish information about the participant’s accomplishments.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;EPA may use the participant’s logo in certain EPA communication materials.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;EPA may periodically revise eligibility requirements.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Failure to comply with any of the terms of this agreement can result in EPA removing a registrant or participant from the SMM Electronics Challenge and terminating access to its benefits, including use of the online data management system.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;All commitments made by EPA are subject to the availability of appropriated funds.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/smm-electronics/forms/contact-us-about-sustainable-management-electronics&quot;&gt;Contact us &lt;/a&gt;to learn how to submit an SMM Electronics Challenge Participation Agreement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Fri, 25 Sep 2015 14:31:49 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>esundin</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">117407 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Summary Report about the Sustainable Materials Management (SMM) Electronics Reuse and Recycling Forum</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/smm-electronics/summary-report-about-sustainable-materials-management-smm-electronics-reuse-and</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;On September 23 and 24, 2014, the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) hosted a forum to “harness the collective power of the electronics community and identify shared priorities that will advance domestic end-of-life electronics management.”  EPA developed a summary report about the forum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-200001&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-09/documents/smm_elctronics_reuserecycling_forum.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=1825066&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;SMM Electronics Reuse and Recycling Forum (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(28 pp, 2 MB, 
  September 2014)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 23 Sep 2015 17:47:07 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>carcari</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">116367 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  </channel>
</rss>

<!-- Page cached by Boost @ 2017-01-26 04:09:41, expires @ 2017-01-26 16:09:41, lifetime 12 hours -->