<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?><rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.epa.gov/feed/61637/rss.xml" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/" xmlns:og="http://ogp.me/ns#" xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#" xmlns:sioc="http://rdfs.org/sioc/ns#" xmlns:sioct="http://rdfs.org/sioc/types#" xmlns:skos="http://www.w3.org/2004/02/skos/core#" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#">
  <channel>
    <title>EPA in Pennsylvania</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/feed/61637/rss.xml</link>
    <description>Updated EPA in Pennsylvania content from the US Environmental Protection Agency</description>
    <language>en</language>
     <atom:link href="https://www.epa.gov/feed/61637/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      <item>
    <title>EPA Reviews Cleanup Enterprise Ave, Philadelphia, PA, PAD980552913</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/pa/epa-reviews-cleanup-enterprise-ave-philadelphia-pa-pad980552913</link>
    <description></description>
     <pubDate>Fri, 20 Jan 2017 11:51:22 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>tscipion</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">169675 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>EPA Reviews Cleanup Hranica Landfill, Buffalo Township, PA, PAD980508618</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/pa/epa-reviews-cleanup-hranica-landfill-buffalo-township-pa-pad980508618</link>
    <description></description>
     <pubDate>Fri, 20 Jan 2017 11:40:32 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>tscipion</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">169673 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Notice of Intent to Assess Administrative Penalty and Opportunity for Public Comment: The City of Wilkes Barre, Pennsylvania, CWA-03-2017-0017</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/pa/notice-intent-assess-administrative-penalty-and-opportunity-public-comment-city-wilkes-barre</link>
    <description></description>
     <pubDate>Fri, 23 Dec 2016 12:52:28 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>tscipion</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">167793 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Additional Documents pertaining to the City pf Wilkes Barre, Pennsylvania  Public Notice</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/pa/additional-documents-pertaining-city-pf-wilkes-barre-pennsylvania-public-notice</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;The Formal Public Notice and the Consent Agreement and Final Order&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-341321&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-12/documents/wilkesbarre-publicnotice.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=17752&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;City of Wilkes Barre, PA Public Notice (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(2 pp, 18 K, 
  December 23, 2016)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-341323&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-12/documents/wilkesbarrecafo.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=175287&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;City of Wilkes Barre, PA Consent Agreement and Final Order (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(11 pp, 175 K, 
  December 23, 2017)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Fri, 23 Dec 2016 12:43:33 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>tscipion</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">167791 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>EPA Seeks Public Comments on BoRit Asbestos Superfund Site – Proposed Remedial Action Plan, Ambler, PA, PAD981034887</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/pa/epa-seeks-public-comments-borit-asbestos-superfund-site-proposed-remedial-action-plan-ambler-pa</link>
    <description></description>
     <pubDate>Mon, 05 Dec 2016 13:30:29 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>tscipion</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">166373 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Time-Of-Travel Tool Protects Drinking Water</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/pa/time-travel-tool-protects-drinking-water</link>
    <description>&lt;h2&gt;Stories of Progress in Achieving Healthy Waters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;U.S. EPA Region 3 Water Protection Division&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Conewago Township, Pennsylvania • July 30, 2016&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Lower Susquehanna Source Water Protection (SWP) Partnership utilizes the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.horizon-systems.com/nhdplus/applications/ICWater_Factsheet.pdf&quot;&gt;Incident Command Tool for Drinking Water Protection (ICWater)&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot; class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt; to support the Pennsylvania Department of Environmental Protection (PADEP) with real-time spill tracking information to protect drinking water sources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ICWater tool is a geographic information system (GIS)-based model developed by the U.S. Geological Survey and EPA which provides real-time assessment of time-of-travel and contaminant dispersion in rivers and streams. With the support of CWA 106 funding, the Lower Susquehanna SWP Partnership has customized the model to include important source water information, including drinking water intake sites. The funding also enabled training of four ICWater operators to support the Susquehanna River Basin Early Warning System.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tool was used to track contaminants from a chemical fire which occurred in the early morning hours of June 8, 2015 at the Miller Chemical and Fertilizer warehouse in Conewago Township near Hanover, PA. Miller Chemical, a nutritional agrochemical company, manufactures many water soluble fertilizers used for commercial agriculture. Polluted runoff from firefighting efforts reached Conewago Creek within a few hours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.srbc.net/&quot;&gt;Susquehanna River Basin Commission&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot; class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt; has been developing the ICWater tool for five years, and in the past two years, the Lower Susquehanna SWP Partnership has committed to support the PADEP with spill tracking and time-of-travel estimates in emergency response.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few hours after the Miller Chemical fire, responders realized that fire retardant foam and fertilizer compounds had washed into Slagle Run and posed a threat to water resources in Conewago Creek, the main source of drinking water for the New Oxford Municipal Authority.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this time, the South Central Pennsylvania Emergency Response Team called upon the Partnership to run the ICWater model. Based on the model’s time-of-travel estimates, PADEP’s Emergency Response Team advised local drinking water utilities to close Conewago Creek intakes and use alternate supplies. Over the following days, the Partnership continued to run the model, supporting PADEP with updated information on estimated contaminant dispersion, which aided decision-making for downstream water supplies in Pennsylvania and Maryland.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Lower Susquehanna SWP Partnership’s utilization of ICWater is an example of how EPA CWA funding can be leveraged to develop integrated tools that support the protection of drinking water resources, and how collaboration enhances comprehensive source water protection efforts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg left view-mode-medium&quot; style=&quot;width:448px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Map highlighting the location of Conewago Township, Pennsylvania&quot; height=&quot;346&quot; width=&quot;448&quot; class=&quot;left media-element file-medium left&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/medium/public/2016-11/pa_conewagotownship.jpg&quot; title=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-342835&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2017-01/documents/pa_progress_-_time-of-travel_tool_protects_drinking_water1.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=633682&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Time-Of-Travel Tool Protects Drinking Water (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(1 pg, 634 K, 
  07/30/2016)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Mon, 28 Nov 2016 17:21:21 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>nholomuz</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">165779 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>EPA Team Helps Water Systems Comply with New Bacteria Monitoring Rule</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/pa/epa-team-helps-water-systems-comply-new-bacteria-monitoring-rule</link>
    <description>&lt;h2&gt;Stories of Progress in Achieving Healthy Waters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;U.S. EPA Region 3 Water Protection Division&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Pennsylvania, Virginia • November 10, 2016&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An EPA team issued nearly 200 Administrative Orders in support of Pennsylvania and Virginia to ensure that small public water systems followed new requirements for more frequent bacteria monitoring of their water supplies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The team, led by the EPA Mid-Atlantic Region’s Water Protection Division, issued the orders in connection with EPA’s &lt;a href=&quot;/dwreginfo/revised-total-coliform-rule-and-total-coliform-rule&quot;&gt;Revised Total Coliform Rule (RTCR)&lt;/a&gt;, which became effective in April 2016. Among other provisions, the rule requires thousands of small public water systems to increase regular monitoring for bacterial contaminants from quarterly to monthly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As of October 2016, nearly 80 percent of the water systems that were issued Administrative Orders are back in compliance. EPA is working with the Pennsylvania Department of Environmental Protection (PADEP) and the Virginia Department of Health (VDH) to address the remaining cases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to more frequent monitoring, the RTCR calls for assessments to more accurately identify issues and deficiencies in water systems that have total coliform and/or E. coli positive samples. Also, systems that operate seasonally, such as camp grounds, have new start-up procedures to ensure good water quality when they open in the spring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In June 2016, Virginia and Pennsylvania had not yet promulgated state regulations for the new rule. Working with PADEP and VDH, EPA identified nearly 200 public water systems – all but four located in Pennsylvania – that were not in compliance with the new monitoring requirements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA took the lead in enforcing the new RTCR. In addition to issuing the Administrative Orders, EPA staff made phone calls to the water systems, many of which needed assistance to understand the new requirements. Based on EPA inquiries, PADEP was able to update records for many rural public water systems, especially businesses that closed or changed names.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In one area of Pennsylvania, a local laboratory had ceased to provide microbial testing services to small systems. EPA and PADEP provided public water systems with updated lists of certified laboratories to encourage the systems to make sampling arrangements promptly. In Virginia, the limited cases were mostly characterized by the new start-up requirements for seasonal systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The region’s Office of Regional Counsel and Office of Enforcement, Compliance and Environmental Justice supported the Water Protection Division in the effort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg left view-mode-medium&quot; style=&quot;width:448px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;A map of Pennsylvania highlighting the locations of open and closed enforcement cases related to the Revised Total Coliform Rule.&quot; height=&quot;373&quot; width=&quot;448&quot; class=&quot;left media-element file-medium left&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/medium/public/2016-11/rtcr_enforcement_map.jpg&quot; title=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-334195&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-11/documents/pa_and_va_progress_-_ensuring_water_systems_monitor_for_contaminants.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=667464&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;EPA Team Helps Water Systems Comply with New Bacteria Monitoring Rule (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(1 pg, 667 K, 
  11/10/2016)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 23 Nov 2016 15:02:59 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>nholomuz</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">165629 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Underwater Grass Comeback Helps Chesapeake Bay</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/pa/underwater-grass-comeback-helps-chesapeake-bay</link>
    <description>&lt;h2&gt;Stories of Progress in Achieving Healthy Waters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;U.S. EPA Region 3 Water Protection Division&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Susquehanna Flats• January 21, 2016&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fortified Susquehanna Flats, the largest bed of underwater grasses in the Chesapeake Bay and a popular fishing spot, seems able to withstand a major weather punch. Its resilience is contributing to an overall increase in the Bay’s submerged aquatic vegetation (SAV), a key indicator of ecosystem health.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.chesapeakebay.net/presscenter/release/chesapeake_bays_underwater_grass_abundance_rises_27_percent_in_2014&quot;&gt;latest figures available&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot; class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt; show that between 2013 and 2014, underwater grass abundance in the Chesapeake Bay rose 27 percent to 75,835 acres, an achievement of 41 percent of the Chesapeake Bay Program’s 185,000-acre goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Susquehanna Flats, spanning some 10 square miles near the mouth of the Susquehanna River, research indicates that the grasses continue to recover from Hurricane Irene and Tropical Storm Lee in 2011 and are proving resilient to stresses. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=FbE4AUN3k_4&quot;&gt;ability to survive those twin blows&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot; class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt; has been linked to a “subtle trend’ in reduced nitrogen pollution, a series of dry years of limited flow, and a process known as a “positive feedback loop,” where the bed’s ability to clear the water and absorb light perpetuates its own growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Once the bed got established because of reductions in nutrient loadings and those dry years, it was able to help itself grow even more,” said Cassie Gurbisz of the University of Maryland Center for Environmental Science’s Horn Point Laboratory. “It’s kind of cool.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.chesapeakebay.net/issues/issue/bay_grasses&quot;&gt;Underwater grasses&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot; class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt; are important because they offer food to small invertebrates and migratory waterfowl; shelter young fish and blue crabs; and keep the water clear and healthy by absorbing excess nutrients, trapping suspended sediment and slowing shoreline erosion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike in 1972 when the Susquehanna Flats, already stressed by nutrient pollution from a fast-developing watershed, was practically wiped out by Tropical Storm Agnes and didn’t recover for nearly three decades, the Flats maintained a sizeable portion of its bed after the major floods of 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gurbisz, the lead author of a study exploring the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.umces.edu/hpl/release/2014/sep/02/underwater-grass-comeback-bodes-well-chesapeake&quot;&gt;comeback of underwater grasses in the Flats&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot; class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;, said the ability to withstand floods “probably has a lot to do with how well the bed is doing leading up to the flood, and that has a lot to do with water quality trends.” Scientists attributed the boost in 2014 bay grasses to the rapid expansion of widgeongrass in the moderately salty waters of the mid-Bay, even in areas where vegetation had not been observed before. They also found a modest recovery of eelgrass in very salty waters and the continuing return of aquatic vegetation to freshwater areas, like the Flats, impacted by the 2011 storms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg view-mode-medium caption&quot; style=&quot;width:448px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;2013 data visualization of Susquehanna Flats submerged aquatic vegetation. &quot; height=&quot;371&quot; width=&quot;448&quot; class=&quot;media-element file-medium&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/medium/public/2016-06/sav_data.jpg&quot; title=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;figcaption&quot;&gt;2013 &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.chesapeakebay.net/visualization/baygrasses/&quot;&gt;data visualization&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&amp;#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;of Susquehanna Flats SAV shown in green. Credit: Chesapeake Bay Program.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-334185&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-11/documents/multi_state_progress_-_underwater_grass_comeback_helps_chesapeake_bay_-_20160121.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=660194&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Underwater Grass Comeback Helps Chesapeake Bay (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(1 pg, 660 K, 
  2016-01-21)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 23 Nov 2016 14:34:02 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>apruzins</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">165627 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Green Streets Transforming Communities</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/pa/green-streets-transforming-communities</link>
    <description>&lt;h2&gt;Stories of Progress in Achieving Healthy Waters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;U.S. EPA Region 3 Water Protection Division&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Harrisburg, Pennsylvania • July 7, 2016&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In its six years, the Green Streets, Green Jobs, Green Towns (G3) Partnership grants program has generated nearly $18 million for over 90 projects throughout the Chesapeake Bay watershed, including work that has created a collective eight miles of green streets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the &lt;a href=&quot;http://g3partnership.org/&quot;&gt;G3 program&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot; class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;, sponsored by EPA’s Mid-Atlantic Region and the Chesapeake Bay Trust, in partnership with the Maryland Department of Natural Resources, has always been about more than numbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At an event in Harrisburg to announce the 2016 round of G3 funding, speakers noted the transformative nature of the program – reducing a major source of water pollution and improving the livability and vitality of communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Harrisburg project – &lt;a href=&quot;/newsreleases/seventeen-projects-unveiled-green-local-communities&quot;&gt;one of 17 awards announced&lt;/a&gt; at the event – was a good example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Salvation Army Harrisburg Capital Region will use its funding to design a stormwater management system at the proposed site of its new building at the corner of 29th Street and Rudy Road. The site is now an empty parking lot flanked by dilapidated and abandoned buildings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The green stormwater features planned for the project, including 20,000 feet of rain gardens, 100 trees, 1,100 native plants, a walking trail, cisterns and other items, will capture an estimated 6 million gallons of rainwater each year that would otherwise gush from the property with pollutants in tow, impacting local waters that eventually flow to the Chesapeake Bay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the Salvation Army complex will give a boost to the neighborhood. The organization said the site is ideally situated near those most in need of its services, is accessible via a central bus route, and is in close proximity to several local schools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 17 G3 grantees in 2016 include nine in Maryland, five in central Pennsylvania and one each in the District of Columbia, Virginia and West Virginia. Ten are implementation/construction grants, six are for design and one is for research/tool building.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the 2016 round of G3 grants, EPA ($515,000) and the Chesapeake Bay Trust ($288,489) provided a total of $803,489, with a more than 7-1 local match of $5.82 million.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg left view-mode-medium&quot; style=&quot;width:448px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Map of Pennsylvania highlighting the location of Harrisburg&quot; height=&quot;346&quot; width=&quot;448&quot; class=&quot;left media-element file-medium left&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/medium/public/2016-07/pa_harrisburg_20160226.jpg&quot; title=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-334133&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-11/documents/multi_state_progress_-_green_streets_transforming_communities_-_20160707.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=673253&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Green Streets Transforming Communities (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(1 pg, 673 K, 
  2016-07-07)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 23 Nov 2016 13:56:57 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>apruzins</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">165621 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  </channel>
</rss>

<!-- Page cached by Boost @ 2017-01-26 04:53:22, expires @ 2017-01-26 16:53:22, lifetime 12 hours -->