<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?><rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.epa.gov/feed/87853/rss.xml" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/" xmlns:og="http://ogp.me/ns#" xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#" xmlns:sioc="http://rdfs.org/sioc/ns#" xmlns:sioct="http://rdfs.org/sioc/types#" xmlns:skos="http://www.w3.org/2004/02/skos/core#" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#">
  <channel>
    <title>Regulation of Biotechnology under TSCA and FIFRA</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/feed/87853/rss.xml</link>
    <description>Updated Regulation of Biotechnology under TSCA and FIFRA content from the US Environmental Protection Agency</description>
    <language>en</language>
     <atom:link href="https://www.epa.gov/feed/87853/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      <item>
    <title>Update to the Coordinated Framework for the Regulation of Biotechnology </title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/regulation-biotechnology-under-tsca-and-fifra/update-coordinated-framework-regulation-biotechnology</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;The 2017 Update to the Coordinated Framework for the Regulation of Biotechnology represents the first time in 30 years that the federal government has produced a comprehensive summary of the roles and responsibilities of the three principal regulatory agencies with respect to regulating biotechnology products. In order to help product developers and the public understand what the regulatory pathway for products might look like, this 2017 update to the coordinated framework presents information about agency roles and responsibilities in several forms, including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;graphics that illustrate agency-specific overviews of regulatory roles;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;case studies that demonstrate how a product developer might navigate the regulatory framework; and&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;a comprehensive table that summarizes the current responsibilities and the relevant coordination across EPA, &lt;abbr title=&quot;Food and Drug Administration&quot;&gt;FDA&lt;/abbr&gt;, and &lt;abbr title=&quot;U.S. Department of Agriculture&quot;&gt;USDA&lt;/abbr&gt; for the regulatory oversight of an array of biotechnology product areas.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/regulation-biotechnology-under-tsca-and-fifra/modernizing-regulatory-system-biotechnology-products&quot;&gt;View more information about modernizing the regulatory system for biotechnology products&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-342967&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2017-01/documents/2017_coordinated_framework_update.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=1567749&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;2017 Update to the Coordinated Framework for the Regulation of Biotechnology (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(14 pp, 2 MB)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jan 2017 19:44:47 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>morganic</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">168221 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Memorandum on Modernizing the Regulatory System for Biotechnology Products</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/regulation-biotechnology-under-tsca-and-fifra/memorandum-modernizing-regulatory-system-biotechnology</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;The director of the Office of Science and Technology Policy sent this memorandum to the heads of the Food and Drug Administration, the Environmental Protection Agency and the U.S. Department of Agriculture on July 2, 2015. It initiated a process to modernize the federal regulatory system for the products of biotechnology and to establish mechanisms for periodic updates of that system. The objectives are to ensure public confidence in the regulatory system and to prevent unnecessary barriers to future innovation and competitiveness by improving the transparency, coordination, predictability, and efficiency of the regulation of biotechnology products while continuing to protect health and the environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/regulation-biotechnology-under-tsca-and-fifra/modernizing-regulatory-system-biotechnology-products&quot;&gt;Read more about modernizing the regulatory system for biotechnology products&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-341179&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-12/documents/modernizing_the_reg_system_for_biotech_products_memo_final.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=88412&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Memorandum from OSTP on Modernizing the Regulatory System for Biotechnology Products (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(5 pp, 88 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 22 Dec 2016 18:49:03 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>morganic</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">167759 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>National Strategy for Modernizing the Regulatory System for Biotechnology Products</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/regulation-biotechnology-under-tsca-and-fifra/national-strategy-modernizing-regulatory-system</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;This &lt;em&gt;National Strategy for Modernizing the Regulatory System for Biotechnology Products&lt;/em&gt; (Strategy) sets forth a vision and goals for ensuring that the Federal regulatory system is prepared to efficiently assess the risks, if any, of the future products of biotechnology while supporting innovation, protecting health and the environment, promoting public confidence in the regulatory process, increasing transparency and predictability, and reducing unnecessary costs and burdens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/regulation-biotechnology-under-tsca-and-fifra/modernizing-regulatory-system-biotechnology-products&quot;&gt;More information about modernizing the regulatory system for biotechnology products&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-341175&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-12/documents/biotech_national_strategy_final.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=602442&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;National Strategy for Modernizing the Regulatory System for Biotechnology Products (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(19 pp, 602 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 22 Dec 2016 18:39:44 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cgesalma</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">167757 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Plant-Incorporated Protectants Data Symposium</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/regulation-biotechnology-under-tsca-and-fifra/plant-incorporated-protectants-data-symposium</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;EPA held a public symposium on data that support registration of plant incorporated protectants (PIPs) in September 2016, which is being rebroadcast on November 18, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/pesticides/public-symposium-regulation-plant-incorporated-protectants-rebroadcast-live-webcast&quot;&gt;View information about the rebroadcast&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The symposium provided a forum for PIP developers, the agricultural sector and the general public to receive information firsthand on the scope of the scientific review process that determines the safety of PIPs and on the pesticide registration process as a whole. The majority of PIPs registered in the past 20-plus years use insecticidal traits of bacterial proteins to enhance the plant’s resistance to insect herbivores. EPA, FDA and USDA representatives gave an overview of the regulatory system that applies to biotechnology in the United States in the context of the &lt;a href=&quot;/regulation-biotechnology-under-tsca-and-fifra/modernizing-regulatory-system-biotechnology-products&quot;&gt;Coordinated Framework for Regulation of Biotechnology&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.regulations.gov/docket?D=EPA-HQ-OPP-2016-0427&quot;&gt;View the presentation materials from the symposium&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We plan to provide a recording of the webinar in early December 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/regulation-biotechnology-under-tsca-and-fifra&quot;&gt;More information about regulation of biotechnology&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Fri, 28 Oct 2016 15:36:58 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>morganic</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">163727 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>PIP Symposium Information</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/regulation-biotechnology-under-tsca-and-fifra/pip-symposium-information</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;See below for more information about the flyer and agenda. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-310887&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-08/documents/symposium-flyer.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=155909&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;PIP Symposium Flyer (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(1 pg, 156 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-317493&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-09/documents/pip-symposium-agenda_9-22-16.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=126454&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;PIP Symposium Agenda (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(2 pp, 126 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 23 Aug 2016 21:23:57 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>Fdarasen</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">158453 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>TSCA Experimental Release Applications (TERAs) for five intergeneric strains of photosynthetic green algae Scenedesmus dimorphus, R-13-0003 through R-13-0007 </title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/regulation-biotechnology-under-tsca-and-fifra/tsca-experimental-release-applications-teras-five</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;On August 1, 2013, EPA received TSCA Experimental Release Applications (TERAs) R-13-0003, -0004, -0005, -0006 and -0007 from Sapphire Energy, Inc. to test five different intergeneric strains of the photosynthetic green algae &lt;em&gt;Scenedesmus dimorphus&lt;/em&gt; in open ponds. The purpose of the field test is to (1) evaluate the translatability of the genetically modified strains from the laboratory to an outdoor setting, and (2) to characterize the potential ecological impact (dispersion and invasion) of the genetically-modified microalgae. The introduced intergeneric DNA sequences include certain metabolism genes and an intergeneric marker gene that enables detection of the microorganism from environmental samples. Also, different regulatory elements controlling expression of the genes were used, resulting in the five intergeneric strains. The field trials are to be conducted at the University of California San Diego Biology Field Station (BFS) in La Jolla, CA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Proposed Use and Field Study&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The submission algal strains were created within the lab space in an enclosed building that is subject to an NIH R&amp;amp;D exemption (40 CFR parts 725.234 and 725.235). The strains will be transported on solid agar media to the BFS (3.3 miles away). The recipient and subject microorganisms will be grown up in culture flasks and then scaled up in hanging bag photobioreactors contained within one of the four greenhouses at the BFS. When the appropriate density is reached in the photobioreactor bags, they will be used to inoculate the outdoor miniponds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The five algal strains are to be grown semi-continuously in up to eight 1,200 L capacity miniponds and the biomass will be harvested from the ponds. Ponds will operate with volumes of 600-800 L. The production volume (PV) for each of the five submission strains is estimated by EPA to be 9.8 x 10&lt;sup&gt;13&lt;/sup&gt; cfu for the 2-month long field test for a total algal cell production volume of 4.9 x 10&lt;sup&gt;14&lt;/sup&gt; cfu, based on the data provided by the submitter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Algal samples will be sent for analysis/testing at the Sapphire Energy facility in San Diego, CA. As part of its program to characterize the potential ecological impact, the submitter will test the ability of the subject microorganisms to disperse aerially into trap ponds positioned at various distances at the field site, In addition they will perform a series of incubation experiments in the laboratory inoculating the subject microorganism into intact wild communities in water obtained from local lakes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Samples will be taken periodically during the 2-month field test. Once the field experiment has been terminated, all biomass will be inactivated by bleaching or autoclaving. The submitter performed inactivation tests by bleaching and/or autoclaving, and EPA determined that all treatments are sufficient to inactivate the algal strains. Any pond spill will be contained within the secondary containment and treated with bleach, and liquid disposed of in the sewage system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusions of EPA&#039;s Review&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA granted these TERA submissions on September 25, 2013. EPA determined that the proposed field tests will not present unreasonable risks to human health or the environment. This small-scale field test is necessary to test the outdoor growth of the algal strains, and to generate data regarding dispersal and competition. These data will be required before future larger scale field tests are approved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a copy of the original nonconfidential TERAs and the nonconfidential approval letter, please contact the TSCA Non-Confidential Information Center (NCIC) by phone at (202) 566-0280, or by fax at (202) 566-9744.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 09 Aug 2016 13:15:21 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>kboswell</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">156919 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>TSCA Experimental Release Application (TERA) for modified Gordonia terrae, R-13-0001 and modified Rhodococcus jostii, R-13-0002 </title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/regulation-biotechnology-under-tsca-and-fifra/tsca-experimental-release-application-tera-modified</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;On April 24, 2013, the Office of Pollution Prevention and Toxics approved the TSCA Experimental Release Applications (TERAs) under the biotechnology regulations promulgated under the Toxic Substances Control Act (TSCA). The TERAs, submitted by the US Army Engineer Research and Development Center, Vicksburg, MS and US Army Corps of Engineers, Seattle, WA, involves field trials of modified strains of &lt;em&gt;Gordonia terrae&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Rhodococcus jostii&lt;/em&gt;. The strains were given the tracking designations of R13-0001 and -0002, respectively. These microorganisms will be used in a field demonstration of bioaugmentation to enhance hexahydro-1,3,5-trinitro-1,3,5-triazine (RDX) degradation in contaminated groundwater.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Proposed Use and Field Study&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The proposed bioremediation demonstration will be performed in three phases. Phase I, which has been completed, consisted of field site characterization and laboratory testing to select a suitable bioaugmentation culture(s) and optimization of conditions that facilitate growth, RDX-degrading activity, and cell transport under field conditions at the Umatilla Chemical Depot (UMCD) in Hermiston, OR. The UMCD has been identified as an ideal demonstration site. Explosives-contaminated sludge and liquid wastes generated at the UMCD Washout Plant were discharged to unlined lagoons, where infiltration through ~ 50 ft of unsaturated site soil to groundwater resulted in a ~ 300 acre RDX groundwater plume. Maximum RDX and TNT concentrations within the plume have been ~ 200 μg/L and 70 μg/L, respectively, in recent years. A groundwater pump and treat facility with activated carbon adsorption began full-time operations at the site in 1997. Treatment efficiency of the pump and treat facility has significantly declined over the years, which has prompted consideration of bioremediation technology for its potential to optimize the existing remedy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Phases II and III are the field tests which are the subject of TERAs R-13-0001 and R-13-0002.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A mixed microbial culture of &lt;em&gt; Gordonia terrae&lt;/em&gt; KTR9 pGTK2:Km&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; (R13-0001) and &lt;em&gt;Rhodococcus jostii&lt;/em&gt; RHA1 pGTK2:Km&lt;sup&gt;+&lt;/sup&gt; (R13-0002), capable of aerobically biodegrading RDX, will be injected into the aerobic RDX plume. For Phase II, in July 2013, a forced-gradient culture transport experiment will be conducted by injecting a tracer/culture (≈ 10&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt; cells/ml) solution in the bioaugmentation well with extraction pumping and sampling from a down-gradient well. This test will confirm that field test parameters previously determined in 2012 are suitable for distributing cells at the field-scale. Phase III, planned for 2014, consists of a bioaugmentation demonstration with subsequent push-pull tests to obtain field-scale performance data on bioaugmentation culture transport, viability, and xplA gene transfer, as well as RDX degradation rates. A field-scale demonstration of the application of the bioaugmentation plot (≈ 100 m&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;) will be compared with aerobic and anaerobic biostimulation plots. The demonstration will use low concentration (≈ 10 mM fructose) substrate injections in the aerobic biostimulation and aerobic bioaugmentation field plots and culture injection in the bioaugmentation plot only, followed by high concentration (50-100 mM corn syrup or ethanol) substrate injections in the anaerobic biostimulation field plot. &lt;em&gt;In situ&lt;/em&gt; RDX degradation rates will be determined by triplicate push-pull tests in injection wells and down-gradient wells within the treatment plots twice over a ≈ 3 month period. Injections will occur at least 190 feet below the surface. The field-scale demonstration will assess bioaugmentation culture transport, viability, &lt;em&gt;xplA&lt;/em&gt; gene transfer to other indigenous microorganisms, RDX degradation rates over time, as well as generate data needed to perform a cost-benefit analysis for implementation of the aerobic bioaugmentation approach for RDX treatment at UMCD.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusions of EPA&#039;s Review&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA decided to grant these TERA submissions on June 17, 2013. The potential hazards posed by the submission microorganism in the proposed field tests are low, as are potential exposures. Thus, the small-scale testing of this microorganism for RDX degradation in this contaminated aquifer poses low risk to human health and the environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a condition of EPA approval of these TERAs, quarterly progress reports including descriptions of field methods and preliminary findings for the activities described in the TERA will be provided to the EPA. Microbial data submitted will include polymerase chain reaction (PCR) results and colony forming units (CFUs) per milliliter of groundwater. In addition to the quarterly reports, detailed reports including all field, laboratory, and microbial analysis methods and results will be provided upon completion of Phase II and again upon completion of Phase III, as described in the TERAs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the required reporting of Phase II and III data, EPA recommended monitoring of metabolites of concern to assess on-site subsurface concentrations and the potential for aerobically-generated metabolites that migrate beyond the injection well locations: 4-nitro-2,4-diazabutanal (NDAB) and formaldehyde could be monitored. If TNT is present at the test area, then monitoring for 2-amino-4,6-dinitrotoluene, 2-nitro-4,6-diaminotoluene, and methylenedinitramine (MEDINA) may also be of value. The periodicity of metabolite sampling should allow an evaluation of the potential for effects on ecological and human receptors at current and/or future sites. Finally, data-gathering to assess the potential for spread of the introduced bacteria beyond the injection site should be assessed. This data may be beneficial in addressing concerns that may arise in future field tests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a copy of the original nonconfidential TERAs and the nonconfidential approval letter, please contact the TSCA Non-Confidential Information Center (NCIC) by phone at (202) 566-0280, or by fax at (202) 566-9744.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 09 Aug 2016 13:09:16 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>kboswell</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">156917 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>TSCA Experimental Release Application (TERA) for Pseudomonas putida TVA8, R07-0001 </title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/regulation-biotechnology-under-tsca-and-fifra/tsca-experimental-release-application-tera-pseudomonas</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;On April 20, 2007, the Office of Pollution Prevention and Toxics approved the TSCA Experimental Release Application (TERA) under the biotechnology regulations promulgated under the Toxic Substances Control Act (TSCA). The TERA, submitted by Micro Systems Technologies (MST), Dayton, OH, and the Purdue University, West Lafayette, IN, involves field trials of a modified strain of &lt;em&gt;Pseudomonas putida strain TV8&lt;/em&gt;. The strain was given the tracking designation of R07-0001. The objective of the application is to update approved TERA R04-0001 and -0002, and Premanufacture Notice (PMN) P-95-1601, and to obtain an extension form EPA for the demonstration and continued testing of biosensor systems that use genetically-engineered bioluminescent microorganisms. This microorganism will be used in an enclosed biosensor device for detection of trichloroethylene (TCE).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Proposed Use and Field Study&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The parental microorganism &lt;em&gt;Pseudomonas putida&lt;/em&gt; was chosen for its indigenous &lt;em&gt;tod&lt;/em&gt; (toluene dioxygenase) operon, which is a multicomponent enzyme system responsible for the degradation of toluene in &lt;em&gt;P. putida&lt;/em&gt; strains. This strain was modified by the introduction of a promoter - &lt;em&gt;luxCDABE&lt;/em&gt; gene fusion that allows for bioluminescence in the presence of TCE, as well as BTEX compounds (benzene, toluene, ethylbenzene, and xylene). These &lt;em&gt;lux&lt;/em&gt; genes are from the marine bacterium &lt;em&gt;Vibrio fischeri&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A small quantity of the microorganism is to be encapsulated onto a membrane which is enclosed within a metal capsule sampling device that also contains electronic circuitry for the detection of the bioluminescence. Since the bacteria are first encapsulated in an alginate matrix, then enclosed within a 0.45 μm filter unit, and finally enclosed in metal capsule devices, there is no direct release of the microorganisms to the environment expected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The proposed field tests, demonstrations for a number of government agencies (DOD, CDC, EPA, DOE, DOT) and contractors (System Research Development Corp. and Northrup Grumman, Boeing, Cartwright, etc.), are similar to field tests of a different intergeneric microorganism (HK44) in a previous MST submission (R02-0001), and to tests conducted, again with HK44 and another intergeneric strain 5RL, in another submission (R04-0001).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Regulatory Background&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The EPA requirements concerning microbial products subject to TSCA (15 U.S.C. Section 2601, et seq.) are set forth in &quot;Microbial Products of Biotechnology; Final Regulation under the Toxic Substances Control Act&quot; (62 FR 17910 (April 11, 1997)) and codified at 40 C.F.R. Part 725. Microorganisms resulting from the deliberate combination of genetic material originally isolated from organisms of different taxonomic genera (intergeneric microorganisms) constitute &quot;new&quot; microorganisms subject to TSCA Section 5 notification requirements. Persons who manufacture, import, or process intergeneric microorganisms for commercial purposes subject to EPA jurisdiction under TSCA, are required to submit a Microbial Commercial Activity Notice (MCAN). Persons conducting commercial research and development activities may submit a TERA, instead of an MCAN, before initiation of such testing. EPA conducts a review of these submissions to determine whether the intergeneric microorganisms present an unreasonable risk to health or the environment. The Agency can impose regulatory controls under Section 5 of TSCA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Summary of the Risk Assessment&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The proposed field tests using the intergeneric bacterium &lt;em&gt;P. putida&lt;/em&gt; TVA8 pose low risk to human health and the environment. The parent &lt;em&gt;P. putida&lt;/em&gt; F1 does not pose concerns for human health; it is not a frank human pathogen, and like many other microorganisms in the environment, is capable of causing infection only in immunocompromised individuals. &lt;em&gt;P. putida&lt;/em&gt; is widespread in the environment, occurring predominately in soils, particularly rhizosphere soil, and in water. It is not a frank pathogen to animals or plants. The strain F1 has a long history of study for its metabolic capabilities in degradation of chlorinated compounds and other xenobiotics, especially BTEX compounds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The genetic modifications made to the parental microorganism to create the bioluminescent reporter bacterium TVA8 do not pose great concern. The presence in the microorganism of the &lt;em&gt;lux&lt;/em&gt; genes from &lt;em&gt;Vibrio fishceri&lt;/em&gt; does not pose any risk. The inclusion of a kanamycin resistance gene as a selection marker is not necessarily desirable for microorganisms intended to release to the environment. Transfer of an antibiotic resistance gene to pathogenic microorganisms whose infections are treated with that particular antibiotic may compromise the antibiotic&#039;s therapeutic value, not only for humans, but also for animals and plants. However, in strain TVA8, the introduced genes are stably incorporated into the chromosome of the recipient microorganism which lessens the potential for horizontal gene transfer. Of course, concern over any potential gene transfer is alleviated by the fact that there is actually no release of TVA8 to the environment, and consequently, no exposure to other microorganisms to which genes might potentially be transferred.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The design of the biosensor capsule units prevents release of the microorganism into the environment by three levels of containment. First, the bacterium is encapsulated in a gel matrix on a membrane which is then sandwiched between 0.45 Φm membranes that prevent passage of the bacterial cells outside the inner chamber. The membrane unit with the bacterial cells, along with the electronic circuitry for light detection, is then enclosed in a stainless steel housing with a screw-on top portion. Only small holes in the metal housing allow for air transport through the device (to detect volatilized TCE).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA decided to grant the TERA submission R07-0001 on April 20, 2007. There is low risk of injury to human health and the environment with the proposed field tests for TCE detection using the submission microorganism TVA8, as both the potential hazards associated with the submission microorganism and potential exposures to the submission microorganism are low.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a copy of the original nonconfidential TERAs and the nonconfidential approval letter, please contact the TSCA Non-Confidential Information Center (NCIC) by phone at (202) 566-0280, or by fax at (202) 566-9744.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 09 Aug 2016 13:01:48 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>kboswell</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">156915 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>TSCA Environmental Release Application (TERA) for Alcaligenes xylosoxidans subspecies denitrificans strain AL6.1, R05-01</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/regulation-biotechnology-under-tsca-and-fifra/tsca-environmental-release-application-tera-5</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;On May 26, 2005, the Office of Pollution Prevention and Toxics approved the TSCA Environmental Release Application (TERA) under the biotechnology regulations promulgated under the Toxic Substances Control Act (TSCA). The TERA, submitted by the University of California, Riverside, involves field trials of a modified strain of &lt;em&gt;Alcaligenes xylosoxidans&lt;/em&gt; subspecies &lt;em&gt;denitrificans&lt;/em&gt; (Axd) strain AL6.1. The strain was given the tracking designation of R05-0001 (previously reviewed under the tracking designations R03-0001 and R04-0003). The microorganism will be tested at the same three test sites as TERA R04-0003 in California to determine its biology and behavior in vineyard ecosystems as part of a research program to prevent or cure Pierce&#039;s disease in grapes. Pierce’s disease is an infection caused by the bacterium Xylella fastidiosa (X. fastidiosa) and is transmitted by leafhopper insects, the glassy-winged sharpshooter (GWSS). The TERA microorganism is considered a pesticide intermediate. The field trials were set for May 2005 through the growing season until pruning in the fall of 2005, with continued field data analysis through the winter to the target end date of March 2006.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Proposed Use and Field Study&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bacterium will be used for small-scale research and development field trails to continue studying its biology and behavior in vineyard ecosystems at the three sites used in the previous submission, R04-0003. The X. fastidiosa pathogen is spread throughout grape growing regions by the glassy-winged sharpshooter (GWSS), a large leafhopper insect. Since the parental strain of Axd AL6.1 was originally isolated from the GWSS, the researchers ultimately plan to use the GWSS as a delivery vector of Axd carrying a pesticidal gene antagonist to X. fastidiosa to the xylem of grapevines where the pathogenic bacterium resides.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This field study differs from the two previous years (R03-0001 and R04-0003) for two reasons. First, the researchers are requesting that the experimental grapevines be left intact after harvest (fall 2005) so that sampling can continue throughout the winter and into the spring (March 2006). Secondly, they are requesting that the previous termination procedures not be required for the current submission since they have concluded that strain AL6.1 does not survive for long, less than two week, in the xylem of grapevines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Regulatory Background&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The EPA requirements concerning microbial products subject to TSCA (15 U.S.C. Section 2601, et seq.) are set forth in “Microbial Products of Biotechnology; Final Regulation under the Toxic Substances Control Act” (62 FR 17910 (April 11, 1997)) and codified at 40 C.F.R. Part 725. Microorganisms resulting from the deliberate combination of genetic material originally isolated from organisms of different taxonomic genera (intergeneric microorganisms) constitute “new” microorganisms subject to TSCA Section 5 notification requirements. Persons who manufacture, import, or process intergeneric microorganisms for commercial purposes subject to EPA jurisdiction under TSCA, are required to submit a Microbial Commercial Activity Notice (MCAN). Persons conducting commercial research and development activities may submit a TERA, instead of an MCAN, before initiation of such testing. EPA conducts a review of these submissions to determine whether the intergeneric microorganisms present an unreasonable risk to health or the environment. The Agency can impose regulatory controls under Section 5 of TSCA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Summary of the Risk Assessment&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on available data and the two previous submissions (R03-0001 and R04-0003), there is low concern for potential toxicity of the recipient microorganism and the introduced genetic material. Although there are some uncertainties associated with the genetic construct, the risk to humans or the environment is low due to the low exposure conditions of the contained field tests. Additionally, the recipient species, Axd, is not a frank pathogen, although it has been associated with some opportunistic infections. No data is available regarding the toxicity associated with exposure to the DsRed fluorescent protein. However, the DsRed fluorescent protein may present some cytotoxicity when expressed in certain cells.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA has determined that a potential for widespread dissemination of the TERA bacterium exists if the field study were conducted according to the protocol described in the TERA. Specifically, at the end of the field study, if the containment procedures were no longer employed the small-scale field study could then be considered a large-scale field release. Available information does not support a conclusion that the TERA bacterium will have died off by the following year; therefore, the remaining population may be transported off site by the insect vector GWSS to the large numbers and variety of crops that the GWSS feeds on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA recommends that the TERA submission R05-0001 be granted with two conditions. First, the pot in which the sweet orange tree is planted should be covered as part of the containment protocol. To satisfy this requirement, a separate fabric enclosing the pot should be connected to the above ground fabric enclosure. To reduce deterioration of the fabric due to contact with moist soil, the enclosed pot can be placed into an empty pot. Secondly, termination procedures following the conclusion of the field study should include three processes: fumigation of all the &quot;cages&quot; to kill the GWSS; incineration or autoclaving of all experimental plants inoculated with the TERA bacterium; and removal or autoclaving of the soil surrounding the root system of all experimental plants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a copy of the original nonconfidential TERAs and the nonconfidential approval letter, please contact the TSCA Non-Confidential Information Center (NCIC) by phone at (202) 566-0280, or by fax at (202) 566-9744.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 09 Aug 2016 12:51:21 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>kboswell</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">156911 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
