<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?><rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.epa.gov/feed/82845/rss.xml" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/" xmlns:og="http://ogp.me/ns#" xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#" xmlns:sioc="http://rdfs.org/sioc/ns#" xmlns:sioct="http://rdfs.org/sioc/types#" xmlns:skos="http://www.w3.org/2004/02/skos/core#" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#">
  <channel>
    <title>National Air Toxics Assessment</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/feed/82845/rss.xml</link>
    <description>Updated National Air Toxics Assessment content from the US Environmental Protection Agency</description>
    <language>en</language>
     <atom:link href="https://www.epa.gov/feed/82845/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      <item>
    <title>Instructions for Viewing the 2005 Google Earth NATA Risk Maps</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/national-air-toxics-assessment/instructions-viewing-2005-google-earth-nata-risk-maps</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;This file provides step-by-step instructions for accessing the data in these interactive Google Earth maps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-278997&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-04/documents/instructions_google_earth.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=84677&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Instructions for Viewing the 2005 NATA Results Using Google Earth (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(2 pp, 85 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Mon, 25 Apr 2016 14:09:25 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>rcopland</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">147489 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Census Tracts with 2005 NATA Estimated Total Cancer Risk Greater Than 100 in a Million</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/national-air-toxics-assessment/census-tracts-2005-nata-estimated-total-cancer-risk-greater-100</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;This map and attached list outline core-based statistical areas (CBSA) that have at least one &lt;a href=&quot;/national-air-toxics-assessment/nata-glossary-terms#census-tract&quot;&gt;census tract&lt;/a&gt; with an estimated lifetime cancer risk greater than 100 in a million. Note that the estimated 100 in a million cancer risk does not apply to the entire CBSA, but rather the specific census tract(s) identified on the map and counted in the list.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-278989&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-04/documents/2005nata-cancer-risks-cbsa.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=289034&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Census Tracts with 2005 NATA Estimated Total Cancer Risk Greater Than 100 in a Million (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(2 pp, 289 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Mon, 25 Apr 2016 13:40:52 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>rcopland</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">147485 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>2011 NATA: Summary of Results</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/national-air-toxics-assessment/2011-nata-summary-results</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;The following document provides a summary of results for the 2011 National Air Toxics Assessment (NATA).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-241567&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-12/documents/2011-nata-summary-results.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=130170&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;2011 NATA: Summary of Results (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(5 pp, 130 K, 
  December 2015)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 17 Dec 2015 18:05:28 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>rcopland</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">129945 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>2011 NATA: Fact Sheet</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/national-air-toxics-assessment/2011-nata-fact-sheet</link>
    <description>&lt;h2&gt;OVERVIEW OF EPA&#039;S 2011 NATIONAL AIR TOXICS ASSESSMENT&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;div class=&quot;box multi related-info right&quot;&gt;
			&lt;h2 class=&quot;pane-title&quot;&gt;More Information&lt;/h2&gt;

			&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
				&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#print&quot;&gt;Download and print this fact sheet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
		On December 17, 2015, the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) released the fifth version of the National Air Toxics Assessment (NATA) – a state-of-the-science screening tool that provides information on the potential risks from breathing air toxics. This tool can inform efforts to identify and prioritize air toxic pollutants, source types, and locations of potential concern.  &lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;EPA suggests that the results of this assessment be used cautiously, as the overall quality and uncertainties of the assessment will vary from location to location as well as from pollutant to pollutant.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;The 2011 NATA is based on emissions for the 2011 calendar year – the most complete and up-to-date emissions data available at the time of the assessment.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;The 2011 NATA assessed 180 air toxics such as benzene, formaldehyde and acrolein, plus diesel particulate matter (PM) (181 total),  from the following types of emissions sources:
		&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type:circle&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Stationary sources&lt;/strong&gt;, e.g., industrial facilities such as coke ovens for the steel industry, refineries and smaller sources like gas stations&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mobile sources&lt;/strong&gt;, e.g., cars, trucks and off-road vehicles like construction equipment and trains&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Events&lt;/strong&gt;, e.g., wildfires, prescribed burning&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Biogenics&lt;/strong&gt;, e.g., naturally-occurring emissions&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;In addition, NATA includes:
		&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type:circle&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Secondary formation&lt;/strong&gt;, e.g., pollutants that form from chemical reactions from other pollutants emitted into the air such as formaldehyde&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Background&lt;/strong&gt;, e.g., long-range transport from distant sources&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;The emissions data were then modeled to make broad estimates of health risks (both cancer and non-cancer risks) over geographic areas of the country to provide a snapshot of air quality in 2011.  Estimated health risks are provided for about 140 air toxics for which we have health benchmarks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3&gt;HIGHLIGHTS&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2011 NATA uses improved emissions and modeling methods that help better characterize risks across the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Monitoring data and emissions inventories show overall reductions in air toxics across the country as a result of Clean Air Act programs.  Results from the 2011 NATA support this downward trend.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Emissions from fires and biogenic sources are included in this version of NATA and more detailed location information was available for some sources, such as oil and gas wells and airports.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Two air quality models - a long range transport and chemistry model and a near-field model - were combined to estimate ambient air concentrations of air toxics across the country. &lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;By combining the two models, EPA is able to provide an improved air quality prediction that accounts for air pollution transport across regions, secondary pollution formation in the atmosphere, and local conditions near specific sources. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pollutants&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Nationwide, the key pollutants that contribute most to overall cancer risks are formaldehyde, benzene, and acetaldehyde.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;The key pollutants that contribute most to overall nationwide non-cancer risk are acrolein, diesel PM, and chlorine.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Key pollutants in some local areas vary depending on local industrial emissions and the amount and type of emissions from transportation.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;The 2011 NATA includes diesel PM for non-cancer health effects only.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sources&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Secondary formation is the largest contributor to cancer risks nationwide, accounting for 47 percent of the risk.   On-road mobile sources contribute the most risk from directly emitted pollutants (about 18 percent).&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Nationally, on-road mobile sources contribute the largest amount to non-cancer risks (34 percent). Nonroad mobile sources and nonpoint sources also contributed to the non-cancer risks in nearly equal amounts (15 percent).&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Contributing sources in some areas may be local industry sources.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Geographic Areas&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;According to the 2010 U.S. census, there are approximately 78,000 census tracts in the country. Based on the 2011 NATA, EPA estimates there are approximately 130 tracts (or less than one percent) with cancer risks greater than 100-in-1 million.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;For census tracts with risk greater than 100-in-1 million, the risks are due to large and small industry, as well as mobile sources and secondary formation.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Urban areas tend to have higher overall estimates of cancer and non-cancer risks than rural areas because there are more air toxics emissions from varied sources, in addition to higher population densities. Secondary formation also tends to occur more in urban areas because of the complex mixture of emitted pollutants.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;EPA developed NATA because there is not a large, nationwide monitoring network in place for the 187 pollutants identified as air toxics. To understand potential health risks from breathing air toxics, the agency developed the model-based NATA.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;NATA is useful in informing national and localized efforts to collect air toxics information, characterize emissions and prioritize pollutants and geographic areas for more refined data collection and analyses, and other activities designed to reduce pollution and risks to public health. However, it should not be used to single out or rank areas of the country as having the highest risk.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;EPA collaborates extensively with industry, state, local and Tribal air agencies to develop and quality assure the information contained in the assessment.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;For more information on NATA, visit the website at: &lt;a href=&quot;/ace/national-air-toxics-assessment-nata&quot;&gt;www.epa.gov/national-air-toxics-assessment&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;To view the interactive mapping tool, visit: &lt;a href=&quot;/national-air-toxics-assessment/2011-nata-map&quot;&gt;www.epa.gov/national-air-toxics-assessment/2011-nata-map&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;For additional questions and answers regarding NATA, go to: &lt;a href=&quot;/national-air-toxics-assessment/nata-frequent-questions&quot;&gt;www.epa.gov/national-air-toxics-assessment/nata-frequent-questions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;print&quot; name=&quot;print&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Printable version of the fact sheet:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-241499&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-12/documents/2011-nata-fact-sheet.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=387809&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;EPA Fact Sheet: Overview of EPA&amp;#039;s 2011 National Air Toxics Assessment (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(3 pp, 388 K, 
  December 2015)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 17 Dec 2015 15:54:53 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>rcopland</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">129931 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>2011 NATA: Errata and Emissions Update</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/national-air-toxics-assessment/2011-nata-errata-and-emissions-update</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;The following document, 2011 NATA Errata and Emissions Update Sheet, provides a list of some of the known issues and updates that were not addressed during the review of the &lt;a href=&quot;/national-air-toxics-assessment/2011-nata-assessment-results&quot;&gt;2011 NATA&lt;/a&gt;. Reviewing this file will provide a better understanding of the results and help in determining how best to use them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-241489&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-12/documents/2011-nata-errata.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=72363&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;2011 NATA Errata and Emissions Update Sheet (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(1 pg, 72 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 17 Dec 2015 15:37:22 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>rcopland</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">129921 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>2011 NATA: Explanation of Data Elements</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/national-air-toxics-assessment/2011-nata-explanation-data-elements</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;The following document provides an explanation of the data elements found in the 2011 NATA files.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-241467&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-12/documents/2011-nata-file-explanations.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=133161&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;2011 NATA: Explanation of Data Elements in NATA Files (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(7 pp, 133 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 17 Dec 2015 14:01:26 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>rcopland</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">129903 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>2011 NATA Map</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/national-air-toxics-assessment/2011-nata-map</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;The 2011 NATA app is a mapping application available on the web and on mobile devices that displays risks, emissions, and monitoring data on a map.  It also allows the querying and downloading of data.  Map layers include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://gispub.epa.gov/NATA/&quot;&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-png right view-mode-medium&quot; style=&quot;width:400px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Thumbnail image of NATA Application GIS map&quot; height=&quot;281&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; class=&quot;right media-element file-medium right&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/medium/public/2015-12/map-app.png&quot; title=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;all emissions sources modeled in NATA,&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;cancer risks and respiratory hazard indices,&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;annual ambient concentrations, and&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;air toxics monitoring sites with monitoring data spanning the years 2005 to 2013.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Map popups for the risk layers provide information on contributions to risk from each source group and each pollutant.  Popups for the emissions layers provide all the emissions from the sources, in tons per year.  There are query options for cancer risk and respiratory hazard index by risk level, by state, by county, and by census tract number.  Point sources can be queried by EIS ID and spatially by user-defined shapes.  The monitoring data can be queried by pollutant and state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h3&gt;QUICK START GUIDE:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-240989&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-12/documents/2011-nata-map-user-guide.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=970759&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Quick Start Guide to the 2011 NATA Map Application (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(7 pp, 971 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 16 Dec 2015 18:27:59 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>rcopland</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">129861 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Previous NATA Assessments</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/national-air-toxics-assessment/previous-nata-assessments</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;As part of EPA&#039;s National Air Toxics Assessment activities, EPA conducted its first national-scale assessment (NATA) for 1996. That assessment included 32 air toxics on the Clean Air Act&#039;s list of 187 air toxics plus diesel PM (non-cancer results only). In February of 2006, EPA released the second of its NATA assessments. This assessment was based on emissions from the 1999 National Emission Inventory and included results for 177 air toxics plus diesel PM (non-cancer results only). In June of 2009, EPA released its third NATA, which was based on emissions estimated for 2002. This assessment included results for 181 air toxics plus diesel PM (non-cancer results only). In 2010, EPA released the fourth NATA, based on emissions in the 2005 National Emissions Inventory.  This assessment include results for 179 of the 187 Clean Air Act toxics, including diesel PM (non-cancer results only). The &lt;a href=&quot;/national-air-toxics-assessment/2011-nata-assessment-results&quot;&gt;2011 NATA assessment&lt;/a&gt; is the fifth NATA EPA has conducted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The previous NATA, released in 2011, is the 2005 National-Scale Air Toxics Assessment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/national-air-toxics-assessment/2005-nata-assessment-results&quot;&gt;2005 National-Scale Air Toxics Assessment&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Previous versions of NATA are available in the EPA Archives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.epa.gov/nata2002/web/html/index.html&quot;&gt;2002 National-Scale Air Toxics Assessment&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.epa.gov/airtoxics/nata1999/web/html/index.html&quot;&gt;1999 National-Scale Air Toxics Assessment&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.epa.gov/airtoxics/nata/web/html/index-2.html&quot;&gt;1996 National-Scale Air Toxics Assessment&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2015 15:16:54 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>rcopland</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">129593 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>2011 NATA: List of Air Pollutants in the Assessment</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/national-air-toxics-assessment/2011-nata-list-air-pollutants-assessment</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;The following is a list of 180 of the 187 Clean Air Act toxic air pollutants, plus diesel particulate matter (for 181 total), that are part of the 2011 National Air Toxics Assessment (NATA).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-238617&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-12/documents/2011-nata-pollutants.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=233095&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;List of Air Pollutants Modeled in the 2011 NATA (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(6 pp, 233 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 08 Dec 2015 20:11:06 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>rcopland</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">128625 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  </channel>
</rss>

<!-- Page cached by Boost @ 2017-01-26 04:48:53, expires @ 2017-01-26 16:48:53, lifetime 12 hours -->