<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?><rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.epa.gov/feed/40897/rss.xml" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/" xmlns:og="http://ogp.me/ns#" xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#" xmlns:sioc="http://rdfs.org/sioc/ns#" xmlns:sioct="http://rdfs.org/sioc/types#" xmlns:skos="http://www.w3.org/2004/02/skos/core#" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#">
  <channel>
    <title>Minimum Risk Pesticides</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/feed/40897/rss.xml</link>
    <description>Updated Minimum Risk Pesticides content from the US Environmental Protection Agency</description>
    <language>en</language>
     <atom:link href="https://www.epa.gov/feed/40897/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      <item>
    <title>Active Ingredients Eligible for Minimum Risk Pesticide Products</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/minimum-risk-pesticides/active-ingredients-eligible-minimum-risk-pesticide-products</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;The following active ingredients can be used in pesticide products that are exempt from the requirements of the Federal Insecticide, Fungicide, and Rodenticide Act under the minimum risk exemption regulations in 40 CFR 152.25(f). They can be used alone or in combination with other substances listed in this paragraph, provided that all of the &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/minimum-risk-pesticides/conditions-minimum-risk-pesticides&quot;&gt;criteria for minimum risk exemption&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; are met.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-240703&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-12/documents/minrisk-active-ingredients-tolerances-2015-12-15.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=335924&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Eligible Active Ingredients (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(3 pp, 336 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 16 Dec 2015 13:45:53 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>ctran</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">129767 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Letter on Active and Inert Ingredients in Minimum Risk Pesticides</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/minimum-risk-pesticides/letter-active-and-inert-ingredients-minimum-risk-pesticides</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;In November 2005, EPA sent a letter to state pesticide agencies to explain why certain products were not eligible for the exemption from regulation under FIFRA Section 25(b). Specifically, the letter addresses the issue of an ingredient listed as an active ingredient not actually being the ingredient that would kill the target pest, even though it is on the active ingredient list in the exemption criteria. The actual “active” ingredient is listed as an inert and is not eligible to be used as an active ingredient in a minimum risk product.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-97023&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2014-12/documents/m-laws-letter-2005.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=181994&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Rodenticides Marketed as Exempt Under 25(b) Active Ingredient: Corn Oil (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(2 pp, 182 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2014 16:18:00 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cgesalma</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">69095 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Current and Proposed Regulations Related to Minimum Risk Pesticides</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/minimum-risk-pesticides/current-and-proposed-regulations-related-minimum-risk-pesticides</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;EPA&#039;s regulations on pesticides are found in the Code of Federal Regulations. These regulations include the requirements for registration, exemptions from registration, and pesticide tolerances and exemptions from the requirement of a tolerance (a tolerance is the limit on pesticide residue that may remain in or on a food commodity).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ecfr.gov/cgi-bin/text-idx?SID=1e758d7334fa8245d1c4d19a6af9d877&amp;amp;node=pt40.24.152&amp;amp;rgn=div5&quot;&gt;Exemptions for minimum risk pesticides - 40 CFR 152.25&lt;/a&gt;   &lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ecfr.gov/cgi-bin/text-idx?SID=1e758d7334fa8245d1c4d19a6af9d877&amp;amp;node=pt40.24.152&amp;amp;rgn=div5&quot;&gt;All pesticide registration regs - 40 CFR Part 152&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ecfr.gov/cgi-bin/text-idx?SID=43701f7e0ba6d50158dd5bfdaea63562&amp;amp;node=pt40.24.180&amp;amp;rgn=div5&quot;&gt;Tolerance exemptions for minimal risk active and inert ingredients - 40 CFR 180.950&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;On December 28, 2015, EPA published a final rule titled, “&lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.regulations.gov/document?D=EPA-HQ-OPP-2010-0305-0047&quot;&gt;Pesticides; Revisions to Minimum Risk Exemption&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt;.” Under this rule, 40 CFR 152.25(f) more clearly describes the active and inert ingredients that are permitted in minimum risk products and updates labeling requirements for minimum risk pesticide products. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


</description>
     <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2014 12:21:25 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>morganic</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">69059 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Minimum Risk - Addition of an Inert Ingredient or Active Ingredient to the Exemption</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/minimum-risk-pesticides/minimum-risk-addition-inert-ingredient-or-active-ingredient-exemption</link>
    <description>&lt;h2&gt;I want to make an exempted product using an active or inert ingredient that is not eligible for the exemption. Can EPA add an ingredient to the exemption?  &lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p id=&quot;p-34&quot;&gt;Stakeholders may want to add or remove ingredients from the ingredient lists for various reasons. EPA has been examining ways to make the process of adding or removing an ingredient from the exemption as streamlined as possible while meeting the requirements of notice and comment rulemaking. For example, EPA is considering developing guidance that would describe the process and types of information EPA may need for a stakeholder to request the addition or removal of an ingredient from the lists. Any guidance that EPA may develop in the future for minimum risk pesticides would be available on EPA&#039;s Web page for &lt;a href=&quot;/minimum-risk-pesticides&quot;&gt;minimum risk pesticides&lt;/a&gt;&lt;i&gt;.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p id=&quot;p-35&quot;&gt;Companies may at any time petition the Agency to add or remove an ingredient from the active or inert ingredient lists under the Administrative Procedure Act, even in the absence of guidance. EPA cannot predict in advance what the response will be to any particular petition. If the Agency were to grant such a petition, the changes to the ingredient lists will be subject to notice and comment rulemaking.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 22 Oct 2014 20:41:27 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>ryarger</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">65665 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Minimum Risk Pesticides - Inert Ingredient and Active Ingredient Eligibility under 40 CFR 152.25(f)</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/minimum-risk-pesticides/minimum-risk-pesticides-inert-ingredient-and-active-ingredient-eligibility</link>
    <description>&lt;h2&gt;If a minimum risk pesticide contains as an active ingredient a chemical that is also eligible under 40 CFR 152.25(f) as an inert ingredient, will the product still be eligible as a minimum risk product?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;Ingredients that are included on both the &lt;a href=&quot;/minimum-risk-pesticides/active-ingredients-allowed-minimum-risk-pesticide-products&quot;&gt;Minimum Risk Active Ingredient list&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&quot;/minimum-risk-pesticides/inert-ingredients-approved-use-minimum-risk-pesticide-products&quot;&gt;List 4A &quot;Inert Ingredients of Minimal Concern&quot;&lt;/a&gt; may be used either as an active ingredient or an inert ingredient. However, t&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;he active ingredient and inert ingredient lists are not interchangeable. Unless the &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;ingredient appears on both lists, it can only be used based on the list it appears on.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;span&gt;Y&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;ou may not use an inert ingredient as an active ingredient unless the ingredient is included on both the active ingredient list and the inert ingredient list. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;span&gt;Similarly, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;you may not use one of the active ingredients as an inert unless it appears on both lists. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt; Examples:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
	&lt;ul class=&quot;roomy&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;Citric acid, malic acid, corn oil, cottonseed oil, sodium chloride, and other chemical substances are examples of minimum risk pesticide ingredients that can be found on both the minimum risk active ingredient list and inert ingredient list.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;Vinegar (maximum of 8% acetic acid in solution), a commonly consumed food commodity, can be used as an &lt;strong&gt;inert ingredient&lt;/strong&gt; in minimum risk products. As an inert ingredient, vinegar provides manufacturers a means of controlling (buffering) pH in minimum risk pesticide products.
			&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;We selected the maximum of 8% because that is the concentration of some vinegars sold in grocery stores.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;li&gt;When the concentration of the acetic acid is greater than 8%, the chemical substance is generally not referred to as vinegar and is not eligible for use as a minimum risk ingredient.
					&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;At these higher percentages, the acetic acid can cause severe burns and eye damage.&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;li&gt;Also, acetic acid is a potent herbicide.&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;li&gt;&lt;span&gt;Because of this potential safety concern, vinegar is not listed as a minimum risk &lt;strong&gt;active ingredient&lt;/strong&gt; and may not be used as an active ingredient in unregistered, minimum risk pesticides.&lt;/span&gt;
					&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;The same is true of any minimum risk inert ingredient that coincidentally has some sort of pesticidal property. If it is not on the minimum risk active ingredient list, it may not be used as an active ingredient in minimum risk pesticides.&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those chemicals that can be used as either an inert or active ingredient, the ingredient must be properly designated on the label according to its role in the product. &lt;a href=&quot;/minimum-risk-pesticides/letter-active-and-inert-ingredients-minimum-risk-pesticides&quot;&gt;See EPA letter on differentiation of active and inert ingredients&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 22 Oct 2014 20:31:45 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cgesalma</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">65659 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Active Ingredients Allowed in Minimum Risk Pesticide Products</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/minimum-risk-pesticides/active-ingredients-allowed-minimum-risk-pesticide-products</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;The following active ingredients can be used in pesticide products that are exempt from the requirements of the Federal Insecticide, Fungicide, and Rodenticide Act under the minimum risk exemption regulations in 40 CFR 152.25(f). They can be used alone or in combination with other substances listed in this paragraph, provided that all of the &lt;a href=&quot;/minimum-risk-pesticides/conditions-minimum-risk-pesticides&quot;&gt;criteria for minimum risk exemption&lt;/a&gt; are met.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;How to Use This List&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The list contains all the eligible active ingredients under 40 CFR 152.25(f)(1).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;All listed active ingredients may be used in non-food-use products.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Products intended for use on food-use sites (i.e., used on food, food crops, food-contact surfaces, or animal feed commodities) can only include active ingredients with applicable tolerances or tolerance exemptions in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ecfr.gov/cgi-bin/text-idx?SID=c2e3e56933c018161036212965994dc4&amp;amp;node=pt40.24.180&amp;amp;rgn=div5&quot;&gt;40 CFR 180&lt;/a&gt;. These requirements fall u&lt;span&gt;nder section 408 of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act and EPA&#039;s implementing regulations at 40 CFR 180.&lt;/span&gt;
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Before labeling a minimum risk product for a food use, verify that the use you are labeling has been approved in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ecfr.gov/cgi-bin/text-idx?SID=c2e3e56933c018161036212965994dc4&amp;amp;node=pt40.24.180&amp;amp;rgn=div5&quot;&gt;40 CFR 180&lt;/a&gt; for each ingredient used in the product.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/minimum-risk-pesticides/active-ingredients-eligible-minimum-risk-pesticide-products&quot;&gt;Eligible Active Ingredients List&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Finalized Regulation Changes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA finalized a rule on December 28, 2015 to clarify this list with specific chemical identifier (i.e., the Chemical Abstract Service or CAS number) and the name that will be required to be on the label (i.e., the label display name) for each of the active ingredients.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.federalregister.gov/documents/2015/12/28/2015-32325/pesticides-revisions-to-minimum-risk-exemption&quot;&gt;Read the final rule&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.regulations.gov/#!searchResults;rpp=25;po=0;s=epa-hq-opp-2010-0305;dct=FR%252BPR%252BN%252BO%252BSR&quot;&gt;More information on the final rule&lt;/a&gt;. (Docket number EPA-HQ-OPP-2010-0305 at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.regulations.gov&quot;&gt;www.regulations.gov&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;For More Information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See: &lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ecfr.gov/cgi-bin/retrieveECFR?gp=&amp;amp;SID=69440ce5a203b1b965485809036fa4d0&amp;amp;n=sp40.24.152.b&amp;amp;r=SUBPART&amp;amp;ty=HTML&quot;&gt;Exemptions for pesticides of a character not requiring FIFRA regulation&lt;/a&gt; (40 CFR Part &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;52.25) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 22 Oct 2014 20:30:42 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>morganic</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">65657 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Disclaimer about Minimum Risk Pesticide Web Content</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/minimum-risk-pesticides/disclaimer-about-minimum-risk-pesticide-web-content</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;These Web pages provide guidance to persons who are interested in manufacturing, selling or distributing minimum risk pesticides under 40 CFR 152.25(f). This guidance does not create any binding requirements, although it refers to existing statutory and regulatory requirements and guidance. The guidance is not intended to and cannot be relied on to create rights, substantive or procedural, enforceable by any party in litigation with the United States.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Agency reserves the right to change this guidance at any time without public notice. In addition, EPA published a final rule that clarifies the list of ingredients eligible for the minimum risk exemption (December 28, 2015). The guidance on these Web pages pertains to the current minimum risk regulations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.federalregister.gov/documents/2015/12/28/2015-32325/pesticides-revisions-to-minimum-risk-exemption&quot;&gt;Read the 2015 final rule clarifying minimum risk exemption-eligible ingredients&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2014 12:51:19 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>morganic</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">64519 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Commonly Consumed Food Commodities</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/minimum-risk-pesticides/commonly-consumed-food-commodities</link>
    <description>&lt;div class=&quot;box special&quot;&gt;
	&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
		&lt;h3&gt;Disclaimer about Minimum Risk Pesticide Web Content&lt;/h3&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;These Web pages provide guidance to persons who are interested in manufacturing, selling or distributing minimum risk pesticides under 40 CFR 152.25(f). This guidance does not create any binding requirements, although it refers to existing statutory and regulatory requirements and guidance. &lt;a href=&quot;/minimum-risk-pesticides/disclaimer-about-minimum-risk-pesticide-web-content&quot;&gt;More…&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On this page:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#commonly&quot;&gt;What is a “commonly consumed food commodity?”&lt;/a&gt;

		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#add-guidance&quot;&gt;Additional guidance on defining “commonly consumed food commodity&quot;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#common&quot;&gt;Examples of commonly consumed food commodities&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#not--common&quot;&gt;Examples of food commodities designated as not commonly consumed&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#allergenic&quot;&gt;Can wheat and other allergenic food commodities be used in minimum risk products?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#animalfeed&quot;&gt;What is an “animal feed item?”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#edible&quot;&gt;What is an “edible fat and oil?”&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;commonly&quot; id=&quot;commonly&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;What is a “commonly consumed food commodity?&quot;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commonly consumed foods are those ingested for their nutrient properties. Food commodities can be either raw agricultural commodities or processed commodities, provided that they are the forms that are sold or distributed for human consumption. The criteria supporting this definition are found in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ecfr.gov/cgi-bin/text-idx?SID=e1c510ac27eadde69cbf2af8db86bdd2&amp;amp;node=pt40.24.180&amp;amp;rgn=div5&quot;&gt;40 CFR 180.950(a)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a substance meets the criteria, it can be used in any minimum risk product as an inert ingredient. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;add-guidance&quot; id=&quot;add-guidance&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Additional Guidance on Defining “Commonly Consumed Food Commodity”&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA has received questions that indicate the need for additional guidance related to this topic. There is confusion on the exact meaning of “processed commodity.” That is, when does a substance extracted from a food stop being a food, or is every chemical in the processed commodity considered to be a commonly consumed food?  This distinction is important for a substance to have a tolerance exemption under 40 CFR 180.950(a). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is general agreement on what has been considered to be a raw agricultural commodity.  EPA regulations at 40 CFR 180.1(d) defined a raw agricultural commodity (RAC) to include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
	&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;“among other things, fresh fruits, whether or not they have been washed and colored or otherwise treated in their unpeeled natural form;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;vegetables in their raw or natural state, whether or not they have been stripped of their outer leaves, waxed, prepared into fresh green salads, etc;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;grain, nuts, eggs, raw milk, meats, and similar agricultural produce.” &lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That same paragraph also excluded from the definition of a RAC any foods that have been processed, fabricated, or manufactured by cooking, freezing, dehydrating, or milling. This can be used as a starting point to understand the processed food commodities that can be used as inert ingredients in minimum risk products.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In determining if a substance is a processed food commodity for the purposes of 40 CFR 180.950, we have considered: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
	&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;What foods are available in a typical U.S. grocery store.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;What is advertised as a food for human consumption.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;What substances are consumed in significant amounts in the United States.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;The nutrition of the substance. &lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To a significant extent, we have relied on various definitions included in Food and Drug Administration (FDA) regulations (see 21 CFR 70.3 and 170.3) as well as in the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (FFDCA). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
	&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Under 21 CFR 170.3(n), FDA described 43 food categories. Among these are:
			&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;baked goods and baking mixes (including flours);&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;li&gt;breakfast cereals;&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;li&gt;coffee and tea;&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;li&gt;condiments and relishes;&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;li&gt;fats and oils;&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;li&gt;fresh fruits and fruit juices;&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;li&gt;fresh vegetables;&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;li&gt;herbs and spices;&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;li&gt;jams and jellies;&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;li&gt;meat products;&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;li&gt;snack foods;&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;li&gt;soups; and&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;li&gt;sugars.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These categories are immediately recognizable to most consumers as the foods that they purchase and consume. These categories also provide information to the specification under 40 CFR 180.950(a) that a commonly consumed food is the “form the commodity is sold or distributed to the public for consumption.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
	&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;FFDCA section 201(s) defines a food additive as “any substance the intended use of which results or may reasonably be expected to result, directly or indirectly, in its becoming a component or otherwise affecting the characteristics of any food…”&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;On its website, FDA responds to the question of “What is a Food Additive?” with:
			&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;“In its broadest sense, a food additive is any substance added to food.” &lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, a food additive is a substance that is added to a food and thereby becomes a component of the processed form of the food. The food additive is not a food.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
	&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;FFDCA section 201(t)(1) describes that a color additive is added or applied to a food.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;On its website, FDA responds to the question of “What is a Color Additive?” using the same phrasing:  “A color additive is any dye, pigment or substance which when added or applied to a food…”&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;Thus, a color additive is not a food.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read more about &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fda.gov/food/ingredientspackaginglabeling/foodadditivesingredients/ucm094211.htm&quot;&gt;food ingredients, additives and colors at FDA&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;common&quot; id=&quot;common&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Examples of Commonly Consumed Food Commodities&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following are examples of substances that are a commonly consumed food commodity for the purposes of 40 CFR 180.950(a). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
	&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Coffee and tea&lt;/strong&gt; are highly processed commodities that are sold in the grocery store, and the water extract of these processed commodities is quite commonly consumed (by the cupful) even though not supplying significant nutrients or calories. Given the high volume consumption, both the coffee and tea (that we drink) are considered to be a “commonly consumed food commodity” under 40 CFR 180.950(a).&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;br /&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Water&lt;/strong&gt; is sold in the grocery store. Water is quite commonly consumed and is needed for continued human existence, even though it does not supply significant nutrients or calories. Water can be used as a cooking method (boiling) and is an ingredient in many recipes. Given the high volume consumption, water is considered to be a “commonly consumed food commodity” under 40 CFR 180.950(a).&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;br /&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rice&lt;/strong&gt; (a food commodity) can be milled into rice flour (only a change to the physical form: a processed commodity), which can then be baked into crackers (processed commodity). The rice, the rice flour, and the rice crackers are considered to be a “commonly consumed food commodity” under 40 CFR 180.950(a).&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;br /&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Corn&lt;/strong&gt; (a food commodity) can be milled into cornmeal (only a change to the physical form: a processed commodity), or processed as cornstarch (processed commodity). Corn, cornmeal, and cornstarch are considered to be a “commonly consumed food commodity” under 40 CFR 180.950(a).&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;br /&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sugarcane&lt;/strong&gt; can be consumed, although it would not be considered to be widely consumed in the United States.
			&lt;ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;li&gt;Sugarcane is processed into molasses and sugar, both commonly consumed foods.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;li&gt;Molasses can be dehydrated or thickened (physical change), but would still be considered to be “chemically” molasses.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;li&gt;All of these substances are considered to be a “commonly consumed food commodity” under 40 CFR 180.950(a).&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;li&gt;However, molasses can also be extracted to obtain betaine, which is not a commonly consumed food, and due to the extraction procedure is considered by EPA to be significantly removed from molasses.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;li&gt;In fact, betaine has a separate CAS Reg. No. Therefore, betaine is not considered to be a “commonly consumed food commodity” under 40 CFR 180.950(a).&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;br /&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spices and herbs&lt;/strong&gt; are usually sold in the grocery store in small glass or plastic jars, or cellophane packs.
			&lt;ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;li&gt;These are seeds, roots, barks, or leaves of plants used for flavoring and garnish.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;li&gt;They can be sold as freshly-picked or dried (whole or ground).&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;li&gt;Some spices have been used for flavoring foods for hundreds of years, and other herbs and spices have been cited in various mainstream cookbooks for many years.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;li&gt;Examples include pepper, cinnamon, oregano, rosemary, bay leaf, basil, and ginger.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;li&gt;Such spices and herbs are used in cooking and baking, or can be sprinkled on top of food before serving.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;li&gt;They are considered to be a “commonly consumed food commodity” under 40 CFR 180.950(a).&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;not--common&quot; id=&quot;not--common&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Examples of Food Commodities Designated as Not Commonly Consumed&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following are examples of substances that are not a &quot;commonly consumed food commodity&quot; for the purposes of 40 CFR 180.950(a). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
	&lt;ul class=&quot;roomy&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Coffee grounds and tea leaves&lt;/strong&gt; are highly processed commodities that are sold in the grocery store, and the water extract of these processed commodities is quite commonly consumed (by the cupful) even though not supplying significant nutrients or calories. However, the leftover grounds and leaves once the brewing process is complete are not consumed. These are not considered to be a “commonly consumed food commodity” under 40 CFR 180.950(a). Note that there is a tolerance exemption for “coffee grounds (CAS Reg. No. 68916-18-7)” established in 40 CFR 180.950(e), which is an additional indication that these are not commonly consumed foods.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wheat&lt;/strong&gt;, as a food commodity and also as a processed commodity (such as bread or crackers), is excluded because of the number of individuals who are allergic. Wheat is therefore not considered to be a “commonly consumed food commodity” under 40 CFR 180.950(a).&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Food additives&lt;/strong&gt; are not food commodities. Under section 201(s) and 409 of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act, any substance that is intentionally added to food is a food additive. These are chemicals added to processed foods as anti-caking agents, bulking agents, emulsifiers, preservatives, stabilizers or multiple other uses. While these chemical substances are included as ingredients in many processed commodities, these chemical substances are not advertised as a food for human consumption, are not likely to be consumed in significant amounts, may not supply nutrition, and have a Chemical Abstracts Service Registry Number (CAS Reg. No.). They are not considered to be a “commonly consumed food commodity” under 40 CFR 180.950(a).
			&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Note that some chemicals found in processed foods (e.g., glycerin, lecithin, malic acid, maltodextrin, potassium chloride) have been approved by EPA for use in minimum risk pesticide products.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;li&gt;Each of these approvals is based on the available information on the safety of the chemical substance.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Certain chemicals used in food production&lt;/strong&gt; have been evaluated by the Food and Drug Administration. A chemical substance that has been shown to be safe under the conditions of its intended use, as recognized by qualified experts, is categorized by FDA as “generally recognized as safe” (GRAS). A GRAS determination is made according to the intended use since under FFDCA section 201(s), it is the use of the chemical, not the chemical, itself, that is eligible for the GRAS determination. Thus, the conditions that may be placed on the GRAS chemical can range from:
			&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;a particular use (e.g., dough strengthener, pH control agent), numerical limitation (with a limit of 0.4 percent for gelatins and puddings),&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;li&gt;to unlimited (with no limitations other than current good manufacturing practice), that is, for all uses.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;indented&quot;&gt;GRAS chemical substances are not advertised as a food for human consumption, are not likely to be consumed in significant amounts, may not supply nutrition, and have a CAS Reg. No. They are not considered to be a “commonly consumed food commodity” under 40 CFR 180.950(a).&lt;/p&gt;

	&lt;ul class=&quot;roomy&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dyes or color additives&lt;/strong&gt; are used in food production to impart color to a food commodity.

			&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;FDA has regulatory oversight for color additives used in food, drugs, cosmetics, and medical devices.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;li&gt;Color additives are not advertised as a food for human consumption, are not likely to be consumed in significant amounts, may not supply nutrition, and have a CAS Reg. No.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;li&gt;They are not considered to be a “commonly consumed food commodity” under 40 CFR 180.950(a).&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vitamins, dietary supplements, medicines, and cosmetics&lt;/strong&gt; are not food commodities.
			&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;These substances may be edible, but are not advertised as a food for human consumption, are not consumed in significant amounts, and may not supply nutrition.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;li&gt;Additionally, many of these are sold in child-proof packaging, and/or carry warnings concerning consumption by children.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;li&gt;They are not considered to be a “commonly consumed food commodity” under 40 CFR 180.950(a).&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;li&gt;Note that dietary supplements are specifically excluded under 40 CFR 180.950(a)(2)(iv).&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;allergenic&quot; id=&quot;allergenic&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Can wheat and other allergenic food commodities be used in minimum risk products?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most common allergenic food commodities are: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
	&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;peanuts;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;tree nuts;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;milk;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;soybeans;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;eggs;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;fish;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;crustaceans (many shellfish are crustaceans); and&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;wheat.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These food commodities have been deliberately excluded from the description of a “commonly consumed food commodity” per 40 CFR 180.950(a)(2)(ii). This exclusion affects which minimum risk products can include these allergenic food commodities as an inert ingredient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These eight allergenic food commodities can be used in any minimum risk product with only non-food-use sites (e.g., ornamental plants, highway right-of-ways, rodent control).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, these eight allergenic food commodities can be used in food-use products applied to certain food-use sites. The tolerance exemption in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ecfr.gov/cgi-bin/text-idx?SID=589d492989837a061e795717f72fdb20&amp;amp;node=40:24.0.1.1.27.4.19.37&amp;amp;rgn=div8&quot;&gt;40 CFR 180.1071&lt;/a&gt; specifies 14 use patterns appropriate for peanuts, tree nuts, milk, soybeans, eggs, fish, crustaceans (many shellfish are crustaceans), and wheat food commodities as an inert ingredient in a minimum risk product.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;animalfeed&quot; id=&quot;animalfeed&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;What is an “animal feed item?”&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA’s description of an “animal feed item” is specified in &lt;a href=&quot;http://http://www.ecfr.gov/cgi-bin/text-idx?SID=fa93f16bf0d22dcc0054211a5f33c2d3&amp;amp;tpl=/ecfrbrowse/Title40/40cfr180_main_02.tpl&quot;&gt;40 CFR 180.950(b)&lt;/a&gt;. If a substance meets the criteria specified, then that “animal feed item” can be used in any minimum risk product as an inert ingredient.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most agricultural crops and their corresponding raw agricultural and processed commodities can be, and are, fed to livestock. Due to differences in their metabolisms, animals can obtain nutrition from parts of plants that are not digested by humans such as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;hays;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;forages; &lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;seeds;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;leaves;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;hulls and shells; and&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;stovers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Animals also consume plants that are not consumed by humans. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The significant feed items consumed by animals are listed in Table 1, entitled ‘‘Raw Agricultural and Processed Commodities and Feedstuffs Derived From Crops’’ included in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.regulations.gov/#!documentDetail;D=EPA-HQ-OPPT-2009-0155-0002&quot;&gt;OPPTS Test Guideline, Residue Chemistry, Guideline 860.1000, Background&lt;/a&gt;. There are other feed items not listed in Table 1, such as pineapple forage and fodder, or sugarcane forage and fodder, that are consumed by animals, but not in amounts considered to be significant feed items on a national basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Included within the definition of an “animal feed item” are the hulls and shells of the most common allergenic food commodities. This means that, for example, peanut shells, almond hulls, and walnut shells are considered to be “animal feed items” under 40 CFR 180.950 (b).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;edible&quot; id=&quot;edible&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;What is an “edible fat and oil?”&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ecfr.gov/cgi-bin/text-idx?SID=fa93f16bf0d22dcc0054211a5f33c2d3&amp;amp;tpl=/ecfrbrowse/Title40/40cfr180_main_02.tpl&quot;&gt;EPA’s description of an “edible fat and oil” is specified in 40 CFR 180.950(c)&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a substance meets the criteria, then that “edible fat and oil” can be used in any minimum risk product as an inert ingredient.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to several on-line dictionaries, a substance that is edible can be described as “fit to be eaten.” Thus, an edible fat or oil is a food commodity. Most fats and oils are composed of fatty acids and glycerol, i.e., triglycerides. Some of the most frequently consumed oils are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;canola;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;cottonseed;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;olive;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;coconut; and&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;corn.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fats would include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;lard; and&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;beef tallow.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The exemption was phrased as “whether or not commonly consumed” to account for fats and oils that are not widely consumed, such as avocado, pumpkin seed, macadamia, and walnut.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The term edible fat or oil also includes products derived from hydrogenating (food or feed) oils or liquefying (food or feed) fats. This would include, for example, hydrogenated rapeseed oil or hydrogenated soybean oil.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Included within the definition of an “edible fat and oil” are the edible fats and oils of the most common allergenic food commodities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


</description>
     <pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2014 15:17:34 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>morganic</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">64465 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Consumer Specialty Products Association Letter and EPA Response re: Minimum Risk Pesticide Exemption Petition</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/minimum-risk-pesticides/consumer-specialty-products-association-letter-and-epa-response-re-minimum</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;In 2006, the Consumer Specialty Products Association (CSPA) petitioned EPA requesting that we exclude from the minimum risk pesticide exemption those pesticides that claim to control “pests of significant public health importance” and require an abbreviated registration for minimum risk products that are to be used for the control of public health pests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.regulations.gov/#!documentDetail;D=EPA-HQ-OPP-2010-0227-0015&quot;&gt;View this petition in the docket&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2007, CSPA wrote a letter to EPA with more information on its suggestions. Also in 2007, EPA responded to this letter and the petition:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-86103&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2014-10/documents/cspa_petition.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=3622287&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;2007 Letter from CSPA regarding the 2006 Petition (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(6 pp, 4 MB)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-86107&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2014-10/documents/epa_response.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=97779&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;EPA Response to CSPA Petition and Followup Letter (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(2 pp, 98 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2014 15:05:43 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>morganic</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">64463 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  </channel>
</rss>

<!-- Page cached by Boost @ 2017-01-26 04:10:05, expires @ 2017-01-26 16:10:05, lifetime 12 hours -->