<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?><rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.epa.gov/feed/99443/rss.xml" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/" xmlns:og="http://ogp.me/ns#" xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#" xmlns:sioc="http://rdfs.org/sioc/ns#" xmlns:sioct="http://rdfs.org/sioc/types#" xmlns:skos="http://www.w3.org/2004/02/skos/core#" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#">
  <channel>
    <title>Green Vehicle Guide</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/feed/99443/rss.xml</link>
    <description>Updated Green Vehicle Guide content from the US Environmental Protection Agency</description>
    <language>en</language>
     <atom:link href="https://www.epa.gov/feed/99443/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      <item>
    <title>Choose a Path to Lower GHG Passenger Travel</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/greenvehicles/choose-path-lower-ghg-passenger-travel</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;Think you can put us on the path to lower greenhouse gas emissions? Now’s your chance! Follow the steps below to set a GHG target and then try to reach it by designing your own 2050 scenario. Did the two sides of the bridge connect? If not, try again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe height=&quot;950&quot; name=&quot;Choose a Path Tool&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/widgets/gvg/choose-a-path-widget.htm&quot; title=&quot;Choose a Path Tool&quot; width=&quot;950&quot; id=&quot;Choose a Path Tool&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jun 2016 22:50:13 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>abunker</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">153747 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Archives of Fast Facts: U.S. Transportation Sector Greenhouse Gas Emissions</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/greenvehicles/archives-fast-facts-us-transportation-sector-greenhouse-gas-emissions</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;disclaimer pdf&quot;&gt;You will need Adobe Reader to view some of the files on this page. See &lt;a href=&quot;/home/pdf-files&quot;&gt;EPA’s About PDF page&lt;/a&gt; to learn more.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Emissions estimates in the &lt;em&gt;Inventory of U.S. Greenhouse Gas Emissions and Sinks&lt;/em&gt; are recalculated each year for the entire time range of the inventory (1990 to present). Estimates for past years are often revised as better methods and data sources become available. To find the most up-to-date estimates of U.S. transportation GHG emissions, please see the current version of &lt;a href=&quot;http://nepis.epa.gov/Exe/ZyPDF.cgi?Dockey=P100ONBL.pdf&quot;&gt;Fast Facts (PDF)&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(5 pp, 362 K, EPA-420-F-16-020, June 2016)&lt;/span&gt; or the &lt;a href=&quot;/ghgemissions/us-greenhouse-gas-inventory-report-1990-2014&quot;&gt;U.S. GHG Inventory Report&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Previous versions of Fast Facts are available below for reference purposes only.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://nepis.epa.gov/Exe/ZyPDF.cgi?Dockey=P100NNQ9.pdf&quot;&gt;1990-2013 Fast Facts (PDF)&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(5 pp, 928 K, EPA-420-F-15-032, October 2015)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://nepis.epa.gov/Exe/ZyPDF.cgi?Dockey=P100M2GU.pdf&quot;&gt;1990-2012 Fast Facts (PDF)&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(5 pp, 819K, EPA-420-F-15-002, March 2015)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://nepis.epa.gov/Exe/ZyPDF.cgi?Dockey=P100GYH6.pdf&quot;&gt;1990-2011 Fast Facts (PDF)&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt; (5 pp. 1.7MB, EPA-420-F-13-033a, September 2013) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;For older versions of Fast Facts, please search &lt;a href=&quot;/nscep&quot;&gt;https://www.epa.gov/nscep&lt;/a&gt;, using the search terms “Fast Facts Transportation”.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jun 2016 13:39:15 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>nsun</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">153609 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Travel: Learn More about Travel Assumptions in the Choose a Path Tool</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/greenvehicles/travel-learn-more-about-travel-assumptions-choose-path-tool</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;disclaimer pdf&quot;&gt;You will need Adobe Reader to view some of the files on this page. See &lt;a href=&quot;/home/pdf-files&quot;&gt;EPA’s About PDF page&lt;/a&gt; to learn more.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/greenvehicles/choose-path-lower-ghg-passenger-travel&quot;&gt;Back to Choose-A-Path Tool&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Driving less and driving more efficiently can both reduce your household greenhouse gas emissions significantly. Some ways to drive less include walking, biking, carpooling, or taking public transit for certain trips.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;commute&quot; id=&quot;commute&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-png left view-mode-thumbnail&quot; style=&quot;width:56px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Commute thumbnail&quot; title=&quot;Commute&quot; height=&quot;56&quot; width=&quot;56&quot; style=&quot;margin-top:5px;margin-bottom:32px&quot; class=&quot;left media-element file-thumbnail left&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/thumbnail/public/2016-06/vis-tool-button-commute.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;b&gt;We use cars less to commute to work&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	Instead, workers can start telecommuting, taking clean transit, biking, or walking. The &lt;a href=&quot;http://nhts.ornl.gov/2009/pub/stt.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;2009 National Household Travel Survey&lt;/a&gt; found that 28% of vehicle miles took place on trips to and from work. If this trend continues, people could reduce GHGs from personal travel by up to 28% by using their car less to commute to work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;shop&quot; id=&quot;shop&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-png left view-mode-thumbnail&quot; style=&quot;width:56px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Shop thumbnail&quot; title=&quot;Shop&quot; height=&quot;56&quot; width=&quot;56&quot; style=&quot;margin-top:5px;margin-bottom:48px&quot; class=&quot;left media-element file-thumbnail left&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/thumbnail/public/2016-06/vis-tool-button-shop.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;b&gt;We use cars less to shop and run errands&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	Instead, people could walk or bike; take clean public transit; or have their goods/services arrive on their doorstep by clean delivery vehicles. The 2009 National Household Travel Survey found that 33% of average annual household vehicle miles took place shopping and running errands. If this trend continues, people could reduce GHGs from personal travel by up to 33% by using their cars less to shop and run errands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;social&quot; id=&quot;social&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-png left view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:56px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Social thumbnail&quot; title=&quot;Social&quot; height=&quot;56&quot; width=&quot;56&quot; style=&quot;margin-top:5px;margin-bottom:48px&quot; class=&quot;left media-element file-thumbnail file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2016-06/vis-tool-button-social.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;b&gt;We use cars less to reach social and recreational activities&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	Instead, people could walk, bike, or take clean public transit to reach social and recreational activities. The 2009 National Household Travel Survey found that 24% of average annual household vehicle miles took place shopping and running errands. If this trend continues, people could reduce GHGs from personal travel by up to 24% by using their cars less to reach social and recreational activities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;school&quot; id=&quot;school&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-png left view-mode-thumbnail&quot; style=&quot;width:56px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;School thumbnail&quot; title=&quot;School&quot; height=&quot;56&quot; width=&quot;56&quot; style=&quot;margin-top:5px;margin-bottom:48px&quot; class=&quot;left media-element file-thumbnail left&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/thumbnail/public/2016-06/vis-tool-button-school.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;b&gt;We use cars less for other trips, such as trips to school&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	Instead, people could walk, bike, or take clean public transit for other trips (besides commute, shopping, errand, and recreational trips), such as school trips. The 2009 National Household Travel Survey found that 15% of average annual household vehicle miles took place on other trips. If this trend continues, people could reduce GHGs from personal travel by up to 15% by using their cars less to make these types of trips.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;drive&quot; id=&quot;drive&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-png left view-mode-thumbnail&quot; style=&quot;width:56px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Drive thumbnail&quot; title=&quot;Drive&quot; height=&quot;56&quot; width=&quot;56&quot; style=&quot;margin-top:5px&quot; class=&quot;left media-element file-thumbnail left&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/thumbnail/public/2016-06/vis-tool-button-drive.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;b&gt;We drive cars more efficiently&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	Driving more efficiently can significantly reduce GHG emissions. Strategies include going easy on the gas pedal and brakes, observing the speed limit, removing excess weight, and avoiding excessive idling. We assume potential reductions are around 10%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;community&quot; id=&quot;community&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-png left view-mode-thumbnail&quot; style=&quot;width:56px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Community thumbnail&quot; title=&quot;Community&quot; height=&quot;56&quot; width=&quot;56&quot; style=&quot;margin-top:5px;margin-bottom:48px&quot; class=&quot;left media-element file-thumbnail left&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/thumbnail/public/2016-06/vis-tool-button-community.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;b&gt;Community design&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	Community design can help reduce the need for all types of light duty vehicle travel by making jobs, goods, services, and social and recreational activities more accessible via walking, biking, clean transit, clean freight delivery, and shorter car trips. Learn more about &lt;a href=&quot;/smartgrowth&quot;&gt;smart growth&lt;/a&gt;. Think about how convenient it would be to have your job, school, parks, stores, and library close by!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Assumptions and Calculations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;baseline&quot; id=&quot;baseline&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;b&gt;2050 baseline assumption:&lt;/b&gt; The 2050 scenario starts at 21% below today’s GHG levels because existing fuel economy and GHG emissions standards will more than offset projected increase in miles traveled by U.S. passenger vehicles. For more information about the fuel economy and GHG standards, which should increase new vehicle fleet average fuel economy to 40 MPG by 2025, see &lt;a href=&quot;/greenvehicles/technology-learn-more-about-technology-assumptions-choose-path-tool&quot;&gt;Learn More - Technologies&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We project U.S. light-duty vehicle travel will grow from roughly 2.7 trillion miles in 2015 to about 4.0 trillion miles in 2050 in part due to projected population growth. This estimate is based on travel data from &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.eia.gov/outlooks/archive/aeo15/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;DOE’s Annual Energy Outlook (AEO) 2015 reference case&lt;/a&gt;. 2050 estimates are an extrapolation of AEO 2040 data using the 2013-2040 average annual compound growth rate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Other links:&lt;/b&gt; For breakdown by trip purpose of average annual VMT per household, see Table 6 of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://nhts.ornl.gov/2009/pub/stt.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;2009 National Household Travel Survey&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;See &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fueleconomy.gov/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;fueleconomy.gov&lt;/a&gt; for driving tips to improve fuel economy.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jun 2016 07:45:12 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>abunker</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">153585 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Technology: Learn More about Technology Assumptions in the Choose a Path Tool</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/greenvehicles/technology-learn-more-about-technology-assumptions-choose-path-tool</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/greenvehicles/choose-path-lower-ghg-passenger-travel&quot;&gt;Back to Choose-A-Path Tool&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-png left view-mode-thumbnail&quot; style=&quot;width:96px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Tire thumbnail&quot; title=&quot;Tire&quot; height=&quot;96&quot; width=&quot;96&quot; class=&quot;left media-element file-thumbnail left&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/thumbnail/public/2016-06/vis-tool-tire.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;b&gt;MPG values&lt;/b&gt; shown on the tire are miles per gallon of gasoline equivalent (MPGe). Non-liquid fuels, like electricity and hydrogen, are not measured in gallons, so using conversion factors allows them to be displayed on an energy-equivalent basis using the familiar MPG measurement. For example, an electric vehicle with fuel consumption of 30 kilowatt-hours/100 miles has a fuel efficiency of 112 MPGe (based on the conversion factor of 33.705 kilowatt-hours/gallon of gasoline equivalent).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Certain scenarios will increase, rather than decrease, GHG emissions. For instance, if you select an MPG that is below today&#039;s average fuel economy (22 MPG), you are selecting a fuel economy that is worse than today and will result in increased emissions compared to today&#039;s emissions levels. You can offset those emissions through activity or fuel-GHG reductions, or by increasing fuel economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Examples of how different fuel economy levels could be achieved:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;40 MPGe&lt;/b&gt;

		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Gasoline vehicles are improving every year due to federal fuel economy and GHG emissions standards. The tire starts at 40 MPGe because new vehicles are projected to get about 40 MPGe in 2025 due to the these standards. &lt;a href=&quot;/regulations-emissions-vehicles-and-engines/regulations-greenhouse-gas-emissions-passenger-cars-and&quot;&gt;Learn more&lt;/a&gt; about fuel economy and GHG standards.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;50 MPGe&lt;/b&gt;
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Gasoline vehicles are improving every year due to federal fuel economy and GHG emissions standards. New vehicles are projected to get about 40 MPGe in 2025 due to these standards.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;If vehicle fuel economy keeps improving 2% each year after 2025, we’ll hit 50 MPGe by 2050.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;100 MPGe&lt;/b&gt;
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Almost half of all cars and trucks are plug-in hybrid electric vehicles that run on both gasoline and electricity while the rest are hybrid vehicles that just operate on gasoline.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;The use of strong lightweight materials cuts the weight of new vehicles in half and both wind and road resistance are significantly reduced through improved aerodynamics and better tires.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;150 MPGe&lt;/b&gt;
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Hybrid cars running on gasoline could hit 150 MPGe if vehicle weight is reduced by 75%, road and wind resistance are halved, and engine and drivetrain improvements start to approach their realistic limits.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;A fleet average of 150 MPGe could also be achieved with less extreme—though still very aggressive—improvements if most cars are all-electric vehicles.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Visit EPA’s &lt;a href=&quot;/greenvehicles&quot;&gt;Green Vehicle Guide&lt;/a&gt; to find the most efficient cars that meet your needs today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*The average fuel economy of today’s cars and trucks is about 21.6 MPG according to recent highway statistics. (See the 2013 Highway Statistics, Table VM-1, available at: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fhwa.dot.gov/policyinformation/statistics/2013/vm1.cfm&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;http://www.fhwa.dot.gov/policyinformation/statistics/2013/vm1.cfm&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jun 2016 07:12:06 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>abunker</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">153583 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Fuels: Learn More about Fuel Assumptions in the Choose a Path Tool</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/greenvehicles/fuels-learn-more-about-fuel-assumptions-choose-path-tool</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/greenvehicles/choose-path-lower-ghg-passenger-travel&quot;&gt;Back to Choose-A-Path Tool&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-png left view-mode-thumbnail&quot; style=&quot;width:72px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Fuel pump thumbnail&quot; title=&quot;Fuel pump&quot; height=&quot;130&quot; width=&quot;72&quot; class=&quot;left media-element file-thumbnail left&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/thumbnail/public/2016-06/vis-tool-pump-example.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;Vehicles that operate primarily on gasoline or diesel have historically accounted for over 99% of cars and passenger truck sales. However, sales of cars that operate on &lt;a href=&quot;/greenvehicles/alternative-vehicle-fuels&quot;&gt;alternative fuels&lt;/a&gt; like ethanol, natural gas, and electricity are growing. Many alternative fuels &quot;burn&quot; cleaner than gasoline or diesel, so there are fewer tailpipe emissions. Total emissions from fuel also accounts for how they are produced. For example, electricity produced by coal has much higher emissions than electricity produced from wind or solar power, which we count as a &lt;i&gt;zero emissions fuel&lt;/i&gt; in this tool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Fuel volumes are shown as billion gallon gasoline equivalents (BGGe), an energy-equivalent metric. For example, 33.705 kilowatt-hours of electricity contains the same energy as 1 gallon of gasoline; therefore 1 BGGe of electricity is equal to 33.705 billion kilowatt-hours of electricity.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Certain scenarios will increase, rather than decrease, GHG emissions. For instance, if you select a fuels mix that has lifecycle emissions that are worse than today, it will increase overall emissions, unless you have offset those emissions through activity reductions or MPG improvements.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Assumptions &amp;amp; Calculations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Baseline assumption:&lt;/b&gt; We calculate GHG reductions relative to today’s fuel mix, based on DOE’s Annual Energy Outlook (AEO) 2015 reference case for 2015, adjusted to ensure that the 2015 volumes required by the &lt;a href=&quot;#RSF2&quot;&gt;Renewable Fuel Standard&lt;/a&gt; program are met. As a simplifying assumption, the categories for advanced, cellulosic, and biomass-based diesel are all considered as “advanced biofuels” for the purpose of the tool. We made a further simplifying assumption that three-quarters of the 2015 biofuel volumes (on an energy basis) are consumed by passenger cars and trucks while the other quarter is consumed by freight trucks and other vehicles not covered by the tool. This results in a fuel mix of roughly 92.5% gasoline, 5.5% conventional biofuels, 1.1% advanced biofuels, and &amp;lt;1% each of diesel, natural gas, propane, and electricity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Lifecycle GHG assumptions:&lt;/b&gt; The fuel lifecycle GHG estimates in the table below represent a combination of tailpipe emissions and upstream emissions from individual motor fuels. Upstream emissions include emissions associated with fuel production such as feedstock extraction, feedstock transport to a processing plant, and conversion of feedstock to motor fuel, as well as distribution of the motor fuel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th&gt;Fuels&lt;/th&gt;
			&lt;th&gt;% Reduction Compared to 2015 Baseline&lt;/th&gt;
			&lt;th&gt;gCO2e/KJ&lt;/th&gt;
			&lt;th&gt;Sources&lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Baseline Fuel Mix&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;0%&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;0.091&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;See lifecycle GHG estimates for individual fuels in the baseline mix below. For the 0.1% of propane in the baseline fuel mix, we assume an emissions factor of 0.082 gCO2e/KJ.&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Gasoline&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;-2%&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;0.093&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td rowspan=&quot;2&quot;&gt;Gasoline and diesel lifecycle GHG estimates are based on a 2005 baseline from Renewable Fuel Standard (RFS2) Program: Final Rule (March 2010).&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Diesel&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;-1%&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;0.092&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Compressed Natural Gas&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;17%&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;0.076&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Approximate based on estimates from Argonne National Laboratory’s GREET Model, GREET1_2015, available at: &lt;a href=&quot;https://greet.es.anl.gov/&quot;&gt;https://greet.es.anl.gov/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Conventional biofuel&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;19%&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;0.074&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Conventional biofuels may include corn ethanol, ethanol and biodiesel from other feedstocks, or other fuels generated from renewable biomass. The emissions factor represents a 20% reduction below 2005 gasoline lifecycle GHG emissions, which is the threshold for fuels to qualify for the “Renewable fuel” category in the RFS2 program. Some conventional biofuels may have significantly lower emissions. However, biofuels with emissions at least 50% lower than gasoline or diesel are counted as advanced biofuels (described below).&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Electricity&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;21%&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;0.072&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;There are no tailpipe emissions. Upstream emissions rate is based on e-GRID (eGRID2012 Version 1.0, available at: &lt;a href=&quot;/energy/emissions-generation-resource-integrated-database-egrid&quot;&gt;eGRID&lt;/a&gt;) and represents a long-term 2% reduction per year in the upstream grid GHG emissions rates.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
				Electricity can be generated from many feedstocks including natural gas, coal, wind, solar, and hydropower as well as biomass. Electricity generated from biomass may qualify as renewable fuel under the RFS2 program and count toward minimum advanced biofuel requirements.&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Hydrogen&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;7%&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;0.085&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;There are no tailpipe emissions. Upstream emissions rate is based on the GREET1_2015 estimate of hydrogen produced from steam-methane reforming of natural gas and represents our assumption of a long-term 1% reduction per year in GHG emissions rates due to improvements in hydrogen production process.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
				Hydrogen can be produced from sources other than natural gas, including water electrolysis and biomass. The latter may qualify as renewable fuel under the RFS2 program and count toward minimum advanced biofuel requirements.&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Advanced biofuel&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;49%&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;0.047&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Represents a 50% reduction below 2005 gasoline lifecycle GHG emissions, which is the threshold GHG reduction for fuels to qualify for the “Advanced biofuel” category in the RFS2 program. For the purposes of this tool we also count cellulosic biofuels, which are required to meet a 60% reduction under RFS2, in this category. Some advanced and cellulosic biofuels may have significantly lower GHG emissions rates than assumed here.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
				Note that this category can include both ethanol and biodiesel as well as hydrogen, electricity, natural gas, or other fuels produced from biomass that meet the GHG reduction targets.&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Zero-emissions fuel&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;100%&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;0.000&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Renewably produced hydrogen and electricity, as well as certain fuels produced from biomass could have zero or near-zero emissions. Fuels produced from biomass could also help meet RFS2 requirements.&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;RSF2&quot; id=&quot;RSF2&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;b&gt;Renewable Fuel Standard (RFS2) requirements:&lt;/b&gt; EPA is responsible for developing and implementing regulations to ensure that transportation fuel sold in the United States contains a minimum volume of renewable fuel. The Energy Independence and Security Act of 2007 (EISA) established four categories of renewable fuel, and set separate volume requirements for each one. EISA requires EPA to apply lifecycle greenhouse gas performance threshold standards to ensure that each category of renewable fuel emits fewer greenhouse gases than the petroleum fuel it replaces. These categories are: renewable fuel (20% GHG reduction), advanced biofuel (50% GHG reduction), biodiesel (50% GHG reduction), and cellulosic biofuel (60% reduction). As a simplifying assumption, the categories for advanced, cellulosic, and biomass-based diesel are all considered as “advanced biofuels” for the purpose of the tool and are assumed to meet a 50% GHG reduction threshold. &lt;a href=&quot;/renewable-fuel-standard-program&quot;&gt;Learn more&lt;/a&gt; about RFS2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We made a further simplifying assumption that 3/4 of the biofuels (on an energy basis) required by the 2015 Renewable Fuel Standard are consumed by passenger vehicles while the other quarter is consumed by freight trucks and other vehicles not covered by the tool. Therefore the default fuel mix at the start of the tool includes approximately 7 BGGE of conventional biofuels and 1 BGGE of advanced biofuels. We intend to update this tool as new biofuel volume thresholds are set in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We additionally assumed biofuels will generally displace gasoline (rather than diesel) in the light-duty sector and therefore estimate lifecycle GHG emissions rates for biofuels based on a reduction relative to the 2005 gasoline baseline.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jun 2016 05:59:16 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>abunker</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">153581 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>We Can Do Big Things (Text Only)</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/greenvehicles/we-can-do-big-things-text-only</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;See: &lt;a href=&quot;/greenvehicles/we-can-do-big-things&quot;&gt;Infographic version of this information&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;We&#039;ve done big things&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Cars replaced horses in 20 years 1900-1920&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;U.S. Interstate Highway System built 35 years 1955-1990&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Miles per gallon (MPG) set to double for passenger cars in 15 years 2010-2025&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Mobile data becomes widely available 2000-201&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2&gt;The Future of Transportation&lt;br /&gt;
	 &lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;What do you think transportation will be like in the future? See what awaits us “down the road” . . .&lt;br /&gt;
	 &lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Information technology makes travel easier, allowing people to get to their destination faster, with less downtime waiting for buses and trains, or stuck in traffic.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Many buses run on clean hydrogen fuel and electricity, resulting in cleaner and quieter engines.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Sales of bunny slippers are at an all-time high as more people telecommute to work.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Instead of driving to the store, families can have packages and groceries delivered to their doorstep by quiet, zero-emissions delivery trucks.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;People have easy access to multiple modes of clean travel (trains, bikes, car shares, you name it). Schools, parks, grocery stores, and restaurants are a short walk, skip, or bike ride away.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Everyone has easy access to fuels, whether their cars run on gasoline, diesel, hydrogen, biofuels, or electricity. Some electric and hydrogen refueling stations produce fuel onsite using overhead solar power—a clean, renewable option.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Clean and comfortable high-speed rail connects communities to others across the region, reducing emissions and traffic congestion.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;In the future, many cars can park themselves. This technology makes it easier for cars to squeeze into tight spaces, which reduces the amount of real estate needed for parking.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Surface parking disappears to create more space for playing, socializing, and taking in the arts. Compact growth, transit, car shares, self-parking cars, and underground lots make it possible.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Self-driving vehicles get you where you need to go in the most efficient way by smooth driving, platooning, and smart routing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 24 Mar 2016 13:45:10 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>nsun</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">141213 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Fuel Economy &amp; Environment Label Widgets</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/greenvehicles/fuel-economy-environment-label-widgets</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;Add these widgets to your web page to help users find information on the label.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Two types of widgets are available&lt;/strong&gt;, including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;A small label that links to additional information at &lt;a href=&quot;http://fueleconomy.gov/&quot;&gt;fueleconomy.gov&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;A larger label in which you can read about the different features of the label as you roll-over them with your mouse.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Both types of widget are available for Gasoline, Electric, and Plug-in Hybrid Electric vehicles. Click on each to try them out, and then &lt;a href=&quot;http://developer.epa.gov/fuel-economy-environment-label-widgets/&quot;&gt;click here for the code to add a widget to your web page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;h3&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gasoline &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

	&lt;div&gt;
		&lt;p class=&quot;caption center&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Small&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;iframe height=&quot;150&quot; id=&quot;gassmall&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/widgets/fueleconomy-gas-small.html&quot; width=&quot;210&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;

	&lt;div&gt;
		&lt;p class=&quot;caption center&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Large&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;iframe height=&quot;390&quot; id=&quot;gaslarge&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/widgets/fueleconomy-gas-large.html&quot; width=&quot;570&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;h3&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Electric &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

	&lt;div&gt;
		&lt;p class=&quot;caption center&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Small&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;iframe height=&quot;150&quot; id=&quot;evsmall&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/widgets/fueleconomy-ev-small.html&quot; width=&quot;210&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;

	&lt;div&gt;
		&lt;p class=&quot;caption center&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Large &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;iframe height=&quot;390&quot; id=&quot;evlarge&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/widgets/fueleconomy-ev-large.html&quot; width=&quot;570&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;h3&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Plug-in Hybrid Electric &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

	&lt;div&gt;
		&lt;p class=&quot;caption center&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Small &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;iframe height=&quot;150&quot; id=&quot;phevsmall&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/widgets/fueleconomy-phev-small.html&quot; width=&quot;210&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;

	&lt;div&gt;
		&lt;p class=&quot;caption center&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Large &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;iframe height=&quot;390&quot; id=&quot;phevlarge&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/widgets/fueleconomy-phev-large.html&quot; width=&quot;570&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Mon, 07 Mar 2016 17:24:06 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>psuarez</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">137665 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Transportation Down the Road</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/greenvehicles/transportation-down-road</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;We’ve come a long way from the horse and buggy, and we think the transportation system will continue to change down the road. We can already chart many paths forward to a lower carbon transportation future. Come explore, be inspired, and see what may lie ahead.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 03 Mar 2016 16:13:59 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>nsun</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">137467 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>We Can Do Big Things</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/greenvehicles/we-can-do-big-things</link>
    <description>&lt;h2&gt;The Future of Transportation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What do you think transportation will be like in the future? Click on the highlighted areas in the image to see what awaits us “down the road” . . .&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Big Things&quot; id=&quot;imgBigThings&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/2016-03/dtr-big-things.png&quot; usemap=&quot;#Map&quot; /&gt;&lt;map id=&quot;Map&quot; name=&quot;Map&quot;&gt;&lt;area alt=&quot;busDepot&quot; coords=&quot;175,500,310,500,310,530,175,530,175,500&quot; id=&quot;busDepot&quot; shape=&quot;poly&quot; title=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;area alt=&quot;busLink&quot; coords=&quot;175,535,310,535,310,590,175,590,175,535&quot; id=&quot;busLink&quot; shape=&quot;poly&quot; title=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;area alt=&quot;telecommuter&quot; coords=&quot;435,490,500,490,500,525,435,525,435,490&quot; id=&quot;telecommuter&quot; shape=&quot;poly&quot; title=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;area alt=&quot;grocery&quot; coords=&quot;630,615,685,615,685,645,630,645,630,615&quot; id=&quot;grocery&quot; shape=&quot;poly&quot; title=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;area alt=&quot;carShare&quot; coords=&quot;45,590,185,590,185,665,45,665,45,590&quot; id=&quot;carShare&quot; shape=&quot;poly&quot; title=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;area alt=&quot;fuel&quot; coords=&quot;695,640,760,640,760,700,695,700,695,640&quot; id=&quot;fuel&quot; shape=&quot;poly&quot; title=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;area alt=&quot;train&quot; coords=&quot;500,435,650,435,650,485,500,485,500,435&quot; id=&quot;train&quot; shape=&quot;poly&quot; title=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;area alt=&quot;parking&quot; coords=&quot;5,710,45,710,45,755,5,755,5,710&quot; id=&quot;parking&quot; shape=&quot;poly&quot; title=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;area alt=&quot;space&quot; coords=&quot;270,680,340,680,340,735,270,735,270,680&quot; id=&quot;space&quot; shape=&quot;poly&quot; title=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;area alt=&quot;selfDriving&quot; coords=&quot;530,650,655,650,655,705,530,705,530,650&quot; id=&quot;selfDriving&quot; shape=&quot;poly&quot; title=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/map&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;mode-callOut&quot; id=&quot;busDepotCallout&quot;&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;Information technology makes travel easier, allowing people to get to their destination faster, with less downtime waiting for buses and trains, or stuck in traffic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;mode-callOut&quot; id=&quot;busLinkCallout&quot;&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;Many buses run on clean hydrogen fuel and electricity, resulting in cleaner and quieter engines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;mode-callOut&quot; id=&quot;telecommuterCallout&quot;&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;Sales of bunny slippers are at an all-time high as more people telecommute to work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;mode-callOut&quot; id=&quot;groceryCallout&quot;&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;Instead of driving to the store, families can have packages and groceries delivered to their doorstep by quiet, zero-emissions delivery trucks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;mode-callOut&quot; id=&quot;carShareCallout&quot;&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;People have easy access to multiple modes of clean travel (trains, bikes, car shares, you name it). Schools, parks, grocery stores, and restaurants are a short walk, skip, or bike ride away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;mode-callOut&quot; id=&quot;fuelCallout&quot;&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;Everyone has easy access to fuels, whether their cars run on gasoline, diesel, hydrogen, biofuels, or electricity. Some electric and hydrogen refueling stations produce fuel onsite using overhead solar power—a clean, renewable option.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;input id=&quot;btnLearnMore&quot; type=&quot;button&quot; value=&quot;Learn More&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;mode-callOut&quot; id=&quot;trainCallout&quot;&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;Clean and comfortable high-speed rail connects communities to others across the region, reducing emissions and traffic congestion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;mode-callOut&quot; id=&quot;parkingCallout&quot;&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;In the future, many cars can park themselves. This technology makes it easier for cars to squeeze into tight spaces, which reduces the amount of real estate needed for parking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;mode-callOut&quot; id=&quot;spaceCallout&quot;&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;Surface parking disappears to create more space for playing, socializing, and taking in the arts. Compact growth, transit, car shares, self-parking cars, and underground lots make it possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;mode-callOut&quot; id=&quot;selfDrivingCallout&quot;&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;Self-driving vehicles get you where you need to go in the most efficient way by smooth driving, platooning, and smart routing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/greenvehicles/we-can-do-big-things-text-only&quot;&gt;Text-only version of this infographic&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2016 00:02:33 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>nsun</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">137085 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  </channel>
</rss>

<!-- Page cached by Boost @ 2017-01-26 11:07:52, expires @ 2017-01-27 11:07:52, lifetime 1 day -->