<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?><rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.epa.gov/feed/61611/rss.xml" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/" xmlns:og="http://ogp.me/ns#" xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#" xmlns:sioc="http://rdfs.org/sioc/ns#" xmlns:sioct="http://rdfs.org/sioc/types#" xmlns:skos="http://www.w3.org/2004/02/skos/core#" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#">
  <channel>
    <title>EPA in Delaware</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/feed/61611/rss.xml</link>
    <description>Updated EPA in Delaware content from the US Environmental Protection Agency</description>
    <language>en</language>
     <atom:link href="https://www.epa.gov/feed/61611/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      <item>
    <title>Sewer Connection Solves Mobile Homes Health Threats</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/de/sewer-connection-solves-mobile-homes-health-threats</link>
    <description>&lt;h2&gt;Stories of Progress in Achieving Healthy Waters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;U.S. EPA Region 3 Water Protection Division&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Dover, Delaware • July 21, 2016&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Three mobile home communities in Dover, Delaware, now have a sewer line financed through EPA after their failing septic systems had triggered public health concerns and state enforcement action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new gravity wastewater collection system has eliminated the equivalent of 117 septic systems and provided significantly higher levels of wastewater treatment prior to discharge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The former on-site wastewater treatment and disposal systems at the Oak Grove Estates, Grandview Mobile Home Park and M&amp;amp;S Mobile Home Park in East Dover were in need of constant maintenance and repair.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The parks border an unnamed tributary of Morgan Branch, which drains to the St. Jones River and into the Delaware Bay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The faulty systems had created sewer backups and overflows and had prompted an enforcement order from the Delaware Department of Natural Resources and Environmental Control (DNREC) requiring the parks to be connected to central sewer service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The faulty systems had created sewer backups and overflows and had prompted an enforcement order from the Delaware Department of Natural Resources and Environmental Control (DNREC) requiring the parks to be connected to central sewer service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The systems were in such bad shape that prior to the new construction Kent County had to pump out and haul sewage from the systems on a weekly basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kent County received $1.4 million through DNREC from EPA’s Clean Water State Revolving Fund to construct the sewer project. The bulk of those funds - $1 million – were essentially a grant, while the remainder were provided in the form of a low-interest loan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The work consisted of 9,000 feet of sewer pipe, the upgrade of an existing pumping station acquired from the City of Dover, and other repairs. The wastewater is now conveyed from the mobile home parks and nearby lots to the Kent County Regional Wastewater Treatment Facility for advanced treatment that includes nutrient removal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project, initiated by Kent County, is “providing a cleaner and safer environment” for the residents of the mobile home parks, according to Andy Riggi, engineering project manager for the Kent County Public Works Department.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg left view-mode-medium&quot; style=&quot;width:448px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;A map of Delaware highlighting the location of Dover.&quot; height=&quot;346&quot; width=&quot;448&quot; class=&quot;left media-element file-medium left&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/medium/public/2016-09/de_dover_20160226.jpg&quot; title=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-319353&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-09/documents/de_progress_-_sewer_line_for_dover_mobile_communities.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=370532&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Sewer Connection Solves Mobile Home Health Threats (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(1 pg, 371 K, 
  07/21/2016)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;field field-name-field-document-description field-type-text field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    Three mobile home communities in Dover, Delaware, now have a sewer line financed through EPA after their failing septic systems had triggered public health concerns and state enforcement action  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2016 19:18:29 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>nholomuz</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">161443 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>EPA News and Events for Delaware</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/de/epa-news-and-events-delaware</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;Click on data points for more information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;930&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; title=&quot;Delaware State Map&quot; src=&quot;https://epa.maps.arcgis.com/apps/Embed/index.html?webmap=98cf65ad800445ee928da6b2af8a0dd7&amp;amp;extent=-76.9711,38.4011,-73.8593,39.8878&amp;amp;zoom=true&amp;amp;scale=true&amp;amp;scroll=true&amp;amp;theme=light&amp;amp;level=8&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 21 Sep 2016 18:48:47 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>jgrave04</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">160851 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Turning the Tide in the Delaware: Reducing a Legacy Pollutant</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/de/turning-tide-delaware-reducing-legacy-pollutant</link>
    <description>&lt;h2&gt;Stories of Progress in Achieving Healthy Waters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;U.S. EPA Region 3 Water Protection Division&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Wilmington, Delaware • April 9, 2015&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A strategic approach to identifying and reducing sources of toxic discharges to the Delaware River is beginning to show results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recent studies indicate that an EPA pollution budget, or Total Maximum Daily Load (TMDL), is having its desired effect in reducing the pollution discharges of polychlorinated biphenyls (PCBs) that impact fish health and water quality in the Delaware River.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.state.nj.us/drbc/&quot;&gt;Delaware River Basin Commission (DRBC)&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt; reported earlier this year that PCB loadings, or discharges, were down significantly and that a fish consumption advisory had been eased in the C&amp;amp;D Canal in Delaware – signs that a collaborative approach to implementing the TMDL is working.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The TMDL and its associated Implementation Plan have required municipalities and industry to identify sources of PCBs, develop and execute Pollutant Minimization Plans to reduce PCBs on a fixed schedule, and report annually on progress&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Pollutant Minimization Plans are now required by DRBC regulations and incorporated in federally enforceable Clean Water Act permits through the National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA Regions 2 and 3 established the TMDL in cooperation with the DRBC and the states of Delaware, Pennsylvania and New Jersey in 2003 to reduce the legacy of PCB contamination in the Delaware.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PCBs, classified by EPA as a probable human carcinogen, were popularly used as coolants and lubricants in transformers and other electrical equipment. The U.S. banned the manufacture, sale and most uses of PCBs in the late 1970s, but the toxic compound is still found in the environment and can enter the Delaware through wastewater discharges, stormwater runoff, air pollution, contaminated sites and other means. In water, PCBs bind to sediments and are taken up by small organisms and fish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recent DRBC data analyses of annual discharger reports find that: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;More than 90% of dischargers are implementing plans to minimize PCB pollution. &lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;The 10 largest single point sources – representing 90% of the total point source loadings – reduced PCB pollution by 71% between 2005 and 2013.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;While the sediment quality and fish health issues are far from solved, the incremental progress in reducing PCB pollution is an encouraging sign to those involved in writing a cleaner chapter for the iconic river. EPA Regions 2 and 3 continue to work with DRBC and member states on an update to the PCB TMDL and Implementation Plan in order to continue the progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg left view-mode-medium&quot; style=&quot;width:448px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;A map highlighting the location of Wilmington Delaware&quot; height=&quot;346&quot; width=&quot;448&quot; class=&quot;left media-element file-medium left&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/medium/public/2016-06/de_wilmington_20160226_0.jpg&quot; title=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-298929&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-07/documents/de_progress_-_turning_the_tide_in_the_delaware_-_20150409.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=600282&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Turning the Tide in the Delaware: Reducing a Legacy Pollutant (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(1 pg, 600 K, 
  2015-04-09)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jun 2016 17:16:44 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>nholomuz</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">153707 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Ferry Engine Repower to Provide Benefits for Air and Water</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/de/ferry-engine-repower-provide-benefits-air-and-water</link>
    <description>&lt;h2&gt;Stories of Progress in Achieving Healthy Waters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;U.S. EPA Region 3 Water Protection Division&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Delaware Bay • October 15, 2015&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA’s Diesel Emission Reduction Act (DERA) grant to the Delaware River and Bay Authority (DRBA) is bringing new clean air technology to the Cape May-Lewes Ferry, thereby reducing air pollution emissions and contributing to cleaner water in the Chesapeake Bay and its tributaries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The DRBA grant supports repowering the ferry’s propulsion engines with EPA-certified engines that are anticipated to reduce fuel use by 39,600 gallons and reduce nitrogen oxide (NOx) emissions by 39.7 tons each year. While the new engines will assist in cleaning the air, they will also help to reduce atmospheric deposition of nitrogen – air pollution that ultimately settles out of the atmosphere to land or water and impacts water quality in the Chesapeake Bay, the Delaware Bay estuary and other sensitive coastal areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The DRBA runs a year-round ferry that transports approximately 800,000 passengers and 300,000 vehicles annually on a 14-mile route between Cape May, New Jersey and Lewes, Delaware. In December 2014, the DRBA received a DERA grant from EPA to supplement the repowering of two Tier 0 marine propulsion engines in the ferry boat M/V Delaware with cleaner-running EPA Tier 3-certified engines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After repower, the annual fuel use is expected to decrease, on average, by nearly 12% due to the higher efficiency of the new electronically-controlled engines. It is anticipated that over the next 10 years this project will cut overall air emissions from the M/V Delaware by almost 40%, including nearly 400 tons of NOx. The project will have a secondary impact as well, reducing atmospheric deposition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The M/V Delaware’s route is within the Chesapeake Bay’s NOx airshed, the area from which most of the atmospheric deposition of nitrogen reaching the Bay watershed is generated. By reducing the nitrogen making its way into the air, the repowered engines will also be reducing the nitrogen that makes its way into the Bay and other waterbodies in the region.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Air sources account for about one third of the total nitrogen loads delivered to the lands and tidal waters of the Bay watershed. Actions by EPA and its state partners to implement the Clean Air Act have led to a steady decline in that airborne pollution and have been a key factor in the overall progress to date in meeting water quality goals of the &lt;a href=&quot;/chesapeake-bay-tmdl&quot;&gt;Chesapeake Bay Total Maximum Daily Load (TMDL). &lt;/a&gt;To learn more about how reductions in air pollution impact the Bay watershed, including a &lt;a href=&quot;/sites/production/files/2015-06/documents/cb_airwater_fact_sheet_jan2015.pdf&quot;&gt;fact sheet&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://gis.chesapeakebay.net/air/&quot;&gt;story map&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;, visit &lt;a href=&quot;/chesapeake-bay-tmdl/air-pollution-chesapeake-bay-watershed&quot;&gt;http://www.epa.gov/chesapeake-bay-tmdl/air-pollution-chesapeake-bay-watershed&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg left view-mode-medium&quot; style=&quot;width:295px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;A map showing the Delaware Bay and parts of the states of Pennsylvania, Maryland, Delaware, and New Jersey that surround it.&quot; height=&quot;399&quot; width=&quot;295&quot; class=&quot;left media-element file-medium left&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/medium/public/2016-06/delaware_watershed.jpg&quot; title=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-298933&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-07/documents/de_progress_-_ferry_engine_repower_to_provide_benefits_for_air_and_water_-_20151015.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=670374&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Ferry Engine Repower to Provide Benefits for Air and Water (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(1 pg, 670 K, 
  2015-10-15)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jun 2016 12:47:41 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>nholomuz</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">153595 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Repairs Ease Strain on Pumps at Top State Park</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/de/repairs-ease-strain-pumps-top-state-park</link>
    <description>&lt;h2&gt;Stories of Progress in Achieving Healthy Waters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;U.S. EPA Region 3 Water Protection Division&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Lewes, Delaware • November 5, 2015&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An EPA-funded sewer line project helped sharply reduce pressure on the aging wastewater pump station at Cape Henlopen – Delaware’s most visited state park.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Delaware Division of Parks and Recreation tapped the &lt;a href=&quot;/cwsrf&quot;&gt;EPA Clean Water State Revolving Fund (CWSRF)&lt;/a&gt; to fix more than 6,200 feet of crack-marred sewer pipes leading to the park’s century-old wastewater treatment plant. The cracks were allowing groundwater and stormwater to infiltrate the lines, forcing the pumps to work overtime to handle the increased flow – driving up costs and risking system failure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“When the flows increase due to infiltration and inflow, your pumps overwork themselves and the flows increase operation and treatment costs at the wastewater treatment plant,” said Dr. Davison Mwale of the Delaware Department of Natural Resources and Environmental Control (DNREC).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And since the state’s busiest state park – with an estimated 1 million visitors a year – relies on the treatment plant to handle wastewater from its cabins, camp sites, beach bathhouses, signature fishing pier and other facilities, it’s critical that the pumps don’t fail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This was huge funding for us,” said Cindy Todd, construction project administrator for DNREC’s Division of Parks and Recreation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Todd provided figures showing a steep drop in flows to the treatment plant since repairs to the sewer lines were completed in January 2015. This February, for example, the plant processed 74,000 gallons of wastewater compared to more than 1 million gallons in February 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sewage collection and treatment systems at the park have been in place since Cape Henlopen served as a military fort between 1914 and 1945. Water was entering through broken joints and cracks in the pipes, requiring the antiquated plant to process a volume it wasn’t designed to handle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The state used more than $630,000 from a CWSRF low-interest loan to reline the pipes – the second phase of a three-phase project to revamp the system. The loan will be repaid through park fees and, if necessary, state appropriations. In Phase 1, a series of pipes were replaced. Phase III will involve plans within the next four years for a new pump station. In addition to reducing the flow to the system, the pipe relining project is preventing untreated sanitary sewage from leaking into the local groundwater supply and is helping the plant address its nitrogen and phosphorus effluent limits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg left view-mode-medium&quot; style=&quot;width:448px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;A map highlighting the location of Lewes, Delaware&quot; height=&quot;346&quot; width=&quot;448&quot; class=&quot;left media-element file-medium left&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/medium/public/2016-06/de_lewes_20160226.jpg&quot; title=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-298939&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-07/documents/de_progress_-_repairs_ease_strain_on_pumps_at_top_state_park_-_20151105.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=608920&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Repairs Ease Strain on Pumps at Top State Park (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(1 pg, 609 K, 
  2015-11-05)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jun 2016 17:35:51 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>nholomuz</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">153491 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Stories of Progress in Achieving Healthy Waters in Delaware</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/de/stories-progress-achieving-healthy-waters-delaware</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;These Delaware snapshots show how EPA and partners are improving the environment and making a difference in waterways, communities, drinking water and more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/de/sewer-connection-solves-mobile-homes-health-threats&quot;&gt;Sewer Connection Solves Mobile Homes Health Threats&lt;/a&gt; &lt;small&gt;(July 21, 2016)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/de/protecting-planet-and-pocketbook&quot;&gt;Protecting the Planet and Pocketbook&lt;/a&gt; &lt;small&gt;(April 28, 2016)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/de/repairs-ease-strain-pumps-top-state-park&quot;&gt;Repairs Ease Strain on Pumps at Top State Park&lt;/a&gt; &lt;small&gt;(November 5, 2015)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/de/ferry-engine-repower-provide-benefits-air-and-water&quot;&gt;Ferry Engine Repower to Provide Benefits for Air and Water&lt;/a&gt; &lt;small&gt;(October 15, 2015)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/de/energy-efficiency-team-helping-delaware-towns-find-savings&quot;&gt;Energy Efficiency Team Helping Delaware Towns Find Savings&lt;/a&gt; &lt;small&gt;(May 7, 2015)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/de/turning-tide-delaware-reducing-legacy-pollutant&quot;&gt;Turning the Tide in the Delaware: Reducing a Legacy Pollutant&lt;/a&gt; &lt;small&gt;(April 9, 2015)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/de/mirror-lake-reflects-significant-improvement&quot;&gt;Mirror Lake Reflects ‘Significant Improvement’&lt;/a&gt; &lt;small&gt;(February 26, 2015)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jun 2016 14:21:56 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>jgrave04</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">153403 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Protecting the Planet and Pocketbook</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/de/protecting-planet-and-pocketbook</link>
    <description>&lt;h2&gt;Stories of Progress in Achieving Healthy Waters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;U.S. EPA Region 3 Water Protection Division&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Wilmington, Delaware • April 28, 2016&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two EPA-funded projects at a Wilmington, Delaware water filtration plant are reducing the equivalent of 71 cars worth of greenhouse gases, generating nearly 500,000 kWh in annual energy savings and cutting costs by $876,000 a year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The improvements at the Porter Street Water Filtration Plant include the installation of rows of solar panels and the placement of a new pump station to reduce costs associated with drawing raw water for processing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The solar panels, or photovoltaic arrays, provide power through the plant’s electrical distribution network. The green energy cuts greenhouse gases by almost 400 metric tons each year and generates an average of $116,368 in annual savings through reduced electric costs and the sale of solar credits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new “low head” pump station allows the plant to draw a full complement of water – not just the top 4 million gallons – from its onsite 36 million gallon raw water reservoir. When it could only skim the top layer, the plant was forced to continually pump water to the reservoir from the Brandywine River during the day – when electric rates are the highest – to keep up with drinking water demand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The projects demonstrate how a community can make a difference with both offsetting its greenhouse gas emissions and reducing ratepayer costs. In a March 2016 analysis of the two projects, the Kash Srinivasan Group reported that, “the results to date have met the operational and financial performance expectations.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;                                                     Solar Panels       Low HeadPS        Combined &lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cost                                                     $5,910,000            $2,990,000            $8,900,000 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;KWh Saved/Year                                 575,900                 (84,686)                  491,214 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GHG Reduced, Metric Tons                  397                       (58.4)                       338.6 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Annual Savings                                   $116,368              $759,853                 $876,221 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-298941&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-07/documents/de_progress_-_protecting_the_planet_pocketbook_-_20160428.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=698620&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Protecting the Planet and Pocketbook (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(1 pg, 699 K, 
  2016-04-28)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jun 2016 20:13:35 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>nholomuz</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">152315 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Mirror Lake Reflects ‘Significant Improvement’</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/de/mirror-lake-reflects-significant-improvement</link>
    <description>&lt;h2&gt;Stories of Progress in Achieving Healthy Waters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;U.S. EPA Region 3 Water Protection Division&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Dover, Delaware • February 26, 2015&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Delaware officials report a 60 percent baseline reduction of contaminants in fish, water and sediment one year after an EPA-aided restoration project at Mirror Lake in Dover, Delaware.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scientists from the Delaware Department of Natural Resources and Environmental Control (DNREC) like what they see when they look into Mirror Lake. Only one year after completing an innovative restoration project, tests are showing “significant improvement” in the lake’s health – progress that DNREC says would have taken nature alone at least two decades to achieve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA’s Mid-Atlantic Water Protection Division provided $73,800 in Section 319 funds for wetland restoration and other improvements as part of the project by Delaware to clean up and restore Mirror Lake – considered a gateway to the state capital.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mirror Lake had been in decline for several decades due, in large part, to contaminants (PCBs, mercury and PAHs) in bottom sediments that are transferred to fish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the fall of 2013, contractors applied nearly 80 tons of an activated carbon product – the same technology used in many water filters – to bind contaminants in the lake’s sediments. Scientists did baseline testing immediately prior to the work and then went back a year later to test again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They found a 60 percent reduction in the contaminants, “well on the way” to attaining the targeted decline of 70-90 percent within three to five years, according to DNREC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over that timeframe, the project is expected to result in the reduction or removal of the fish consumption advisory for Mirror Lake and the St. Jones River downstream to Court Street in Dover.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out this new &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=wQMfH6L5fYI&amp;amp;feature=youtu.be&quot;&gt;DNREC YouTube video&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt; for more on the project’s success so far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The EPA funds were used to convert a sandbar into a landscaped wetland; supply stakes, native plants and trees; and protect the shoreline from erosion with artificial coir logs made of coconut husks and hulls wrapped in netting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Mirror Lake project is just a few miles downstream of the Silver Lake Park stream restoration project completed in 2012 with more than $200,000 in Section 319 funds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-298949&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-07/documents/de_progress_-_mirror_lake_reflects_significant_improvement_-_20150226.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=636883&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Mirror Lake Reflects ‘Significant Improvement’ (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(1 pg, 637 K, 
  2015-02-26)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jun 2016 18:18:27 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>nholomuz</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">152301 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Energy Efficiency Team Helping Delaware Towns Find Savings</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/de/energy-efficiency-team-helping-delaware-towns-find-savings</link>
    <description>&lt;h2&gt;Stories of Progress in Achieving Healthy Waters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;U.S. EPA Region 3 Water Protection Division&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Selbyville, Delaware • May 7, 2015&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The wastewater treatment plant in Selbyville, Delaware, is benefitting from an EPA-Delaware partnership designed to help water and wastewater facilities save energy and money while cutting pollution that contributes to climate change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Treatment plants use large amounts of energy to process and move either drinking water or wastewater. These facilities are typically a municipal government’s largest energy user, accounting for up to 30 percent of a town’s total energy consumption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Selbyville plant has generated savings by changing a key process at its biosolids facility, installing a timer to run a large aerator intermittently rather than 24/7. The adjustment is helping to reduce power needs and still meet treatment requirements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The operational change – the first in what may be a series of energy-saving steps at the plant – followed an energy assessment by the Delaware Water/Wastewater Energy Efficiency Partnership.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The partnership includes the Net Zero Energy team in EPA’s Mid-Atlantic Water Protection Division, the Delaware Department of Natural Resources and Environmental Control, Delaware Health and Social Services, the University of Delaware, Delaware Technical &amp;amp; Community College and others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Selbyville review was one of five conducted at treatment plants in Delaware over the past year. The assessments have helped operators and managers better understand energy usage at their plants, and identified low- or even no-cost options for achieving reductions – from adjusting treatment techniques to minimizing electricity use. These energy-saving practices have been shared with a wider audience through three workshops for key plant personnel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bettina Stern, operations manager at the Selbyville plant, says that while the exact cost savings of the process changes are being calculated, she’s looking for additional ways to save energy. “I’d like to do more,” she said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The EPA energy team is next scheduled to work with treatment plants in Maryland and Virginia. The focus on energy efficiency and renewable energy at the plants is consistent with &lt;a href=&quot;/www.epa.gov/climatechange&quot;&gt;EPA’s efforts to combat climate change&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg left view-mode-medium&quot; style=&quot;width:448px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Map showing the location of Selbyville, Delaware. &quot; height=&quot;346&quot; width=&quot;448&quot; class=&quot;left media-element file-medium left&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/medium/public/2016-06/de_selbyville_20160226.jpg&quot; title=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-298945&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-07/documents/de_progress_-_energy_efficiency_team_helping_delaware_towns_find_savings_-_20150507.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=681149&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Energy Efficiency Team Helping Delaware Towns Find Savings (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(1 pg, 681 K, 
  2015-05-07)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jun 2016 17:06:34 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>nholomuz</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">152283 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  </channel>
</rss>

<!-- Page cached by Boost @ 2017-01-26 04:26:49, expires @ 2017-01-26 16:26:49, lifetime 12 hours -->