<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?><rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.epa.gov/feed/61869/rss.xml" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/" xmlns:og="http://ogp.me/ns#" xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#" xmlns:sioc="http://rdfs.org/sioc/ns#" xmlns:sioct="http://rdfs.org/sioc/types#" xmlns:skos="http://www.w3.org/2004/02/skos/core#" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#">
  <channel>
    <title>EPA in Kansas</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/feed/61869/rss.xml</link>
    <description>Updated EPA in Kansas content from the US Environmental Protection Agency</description>
    <language>en</language>
     <atom:link href="https://www.epa.gov/feed/61869/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      <item>
    <title>Wiebe Farms, Inc - Clean Water Act Public Notice</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/ks/wiebe-farms-inc-clean-water-act-public-notice</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;UNITED STATES ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION AGENCY&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In accordance with Section 309(g)(4)(A) of the Clean Water Act (“CWA”), 33 U.S.C. § 1319(g)(4)(A), and 40 C.F.R. § 22.45 of the Consolidated Rules of Practice Governing the Administrative Assessment of Civil Penalties and the Revocation/Termination or Suspension of Permits (“Consolidated Rules”), the Environmental Protection Agency (“EPA”) is providing notice of a proposed Administrative Penalty Assessment against Wiebe Farms, Inc., a beef cattle feeding operation located at 13232 NW Prairie Creek Road in Whitewater, Kansas, for alleged CWA violations at its facility at the same address.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under Section 309(g) of the CWA, 33 U.S.C. § 1319(g), the EPA is authorized to issue orders assessing civil penalties for various violations of the CWA.  The EPA may issue such orders after filing a Complaint commencing either a Class I or Class II penalty proceeding.  The EPA provides notice of the proposed assessment of a Class II civil penalty pursuant to 33 U.S.C. § 1319(g)(4)(A).  Class II proceedings are conducted under the EPA’s Consolidated Rules, 40 C.F.R. Part 22.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this case, the EPA alleges that Respondent confined between 300 and 999 head of beef cattle at its facility and discharged manure and process wastewater through a culvert into waters of the United States without National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System permit authorization, in violation of Section 301 of the CWA, 33 U.S.C. § 1311.  Respondent has reached agreement with the EPA on the terms of a proposed Consent Agreement and Final Order (“CA/FO”), which would resolve Respondent’s liability for federal civil penalties as to the CWA violations alleged therein following Respondent’s payment of a $35,000 civil penalty.  Final approval of the proposed CA/FO is subject to the requirements of 40 C.F.R. § 22.45.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The EPA will receive written comments on the proposed Administrative Penalty Assessment for a period of thirty (30) days from the date of publication of this notice.  All such comments shall be submitted to the Regional Hearing Clerk at the address provided below.  The procedures by which the public may submit written comments on a proposed Class II order or participate in a Class II proceeding, and the procedures by which a respondent may request a hearing, are set forth in the Consolidated Rules.  Persons wishing to obtain additional information on the proceeding, receive a copy of the EPA’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gpo.gov/fdsys/pkg/CFR-2003-title40-vol1/pdf/CFR-2003-title40-vol1.pdf&quot;&gt;Consolidated Rules&lt;/a&gt;, review the proposed CA/FO, comment upon the proposed penalty assessment, or otherwise participate in the proceeding should contact Kathy Robinson, Regional Hearing Clerk, U.S. Environmental Protection Agency, Region 7, 11201 Renner Blvd, Lenexa, Kansas  66219.  Please reference Docket No. CWA-07-2016-0067.  In order to provide opportunity for public comment, the EPA will issue no final order assessing a penalty in this proceeding prior to forty (40) days from the date of this notice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
			&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=&quot;vertical-align:top; width:50%&quot;&gt;1-17-17&lt;br /&gt;
				Date&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td style=&quot;vertical-align:top; width:50%&quot;&gt;/s/&lt;br /&gt;
				Karen A. Flournoy&lt;br /&gt;
				Director&lt;br /&gt;
				Water, Wetlands and Pesticides Division&lt;br /&gt;
				U.S. EPA, Region 7&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;box multi related-info right&quot;&gt;
	&lt;h2 class=&quot;pane-title&quot;&gt;How to Comment&lt;/h2&gt;

	&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Comments due date&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
			02/17/2017&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;div&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How to comment&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
			Persons wishing to obtain additional information on the proceeding, receive a copy of EPA’s Consolidated Rules, review the prorposed Consent Agreement/Final Order, comment upon the proposed penalty assessment, or otherwise participate in the proceeding should contact Kathy Robinson, Regional Hearing Clerk, U.S. Environmental Protection Agency, Region 7, 11201 Renner Boulevard, Lenexa, Kansas, 66219.  Please reference Docket No. CWA-07-2016-0067.&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Summary&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The EPA is providing notice of a proposed Administrative Penalty Assessment against Wiebe Farms, Inc., a beef cattle feeding operation located at 13232 NW Prairie Creek Road in Whitewater, KS, for alleged CWA violations at its facility at the same address.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;​&lt;strong&gt;Program/Statute:&lt;/strong&gt;  Clean Water Act (CWA)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Applicant/Respondent(s):&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wiebe Farms, Inc.&lt;br /&gt;
	Whitewater, Kansas&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Proposed action:&lt;/strong&gt; Public Notice of Clean Water Act Adminstrative Penalty Settlement&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Docket ID: &lt;/strong&gt;CWA-07-2016-0067&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-346799&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2017-01/documents/wiebe-cafo.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=1205200&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Wiebe Farms, Inc. proposed Consent Agreement Final Order (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(11 pp, 1 MB)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2017 13:43:15 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>mpropst</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">169357 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Douglas L. Smith Middle Basin Facility, Johnson County Wastewater, Johnson County, Kansas – Public Notice</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/ks/douglas-l-smith-middle-basin-facility-johnson-county-wastewater-johnson-county-kansas-public</link>
    <description>&lt;h2 class=&quot;highlighted&quot;&gt;EPA to Hold Public Hearing Regarding Objection to Draft NPDES Permit&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Notice of Public Hearing regarding EPA objection to the Douglas L. Smith Middle Basin Facility Draft NPDES permit, based on contribution to sanitary sewer overflows, failure to meet full secondary treatment limits, and standard conditions not being as stringent as federal regulations (public notice issuance date: Dec. 31, 2016)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The U.S. Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) Region 7 is announcing, pursuant to 40 Code of Federal Regulations (CFR) Sections 123.44, 124.10 and 124.12(c) and (d), that it will hold a Public Hearing to allow interested persons to submit oral or written comments and data regarding EPA’s specific objections to the Kansas Department of Health and Environment (KDHE) draft National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System (NPDES) permit for the Johnson County Wastewater, Douglas L. Smith Middle Basin Facility. The Douglas L. Smith Facility is located in Johnson County, Kansas, and is assigned NPDES permit number KS0119601.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DATES AND LOCATION&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Public Hearing will be held February 2, 2017, starting at 1:00 p.m. at the EPA Region 7 Office at 11201 Renner Blvd., Lenexa, Kansas 66219.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;KDHE is the permitting authority for NPDES permits issued in the state of Kansas, pursuant to the federal Clean Water Act (CWA). KDHE issues NPDES permits through its Bureau of Water Division. Without such a permit, discharge of pollutants into waters of the United States by a point source is generally prohibited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under the CWA, states are required to submit draft or proposed NPDES permits to EPA for review. EPA has the authority to review a state’s draft or proposed NPDES permits for compliance with the requirements of the CWA, and to submit to the state its comments, objections and/or recommendations regarding the draft permits. During 2009, KDHE sent to EPA for review many draft CWA NPDES permits, including the draft permit for the facility listed above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Nov. 2, 2009, EPA issued a specific objection on the Douglas L. Smith Facility permit. EPA’s objection was based on the following substantive issues: (1) EPA Region 7 objected to the draft permit because it did not contain limits for biochemical oxygen demand (BOD) and total suspended solids (TSS) which comply with the secondary treatment standards set forth in 40 CFR 133 for all discharges from Outfall 002A1; (2) The permit did not contain limits for &lt;em&gt;E. coli&lt;/em&gt; that comply with the water quality criteria for Indian Creek; (3) The permit authorized bypasses from Outfall 002A1 without compliance with the requirements of 40 CFR 122.41(m); (4) KDHE’s Standard Condition (Paragraph 9) was less stringent than the federal requirement for approval of a bypass, as set forth at 40 CFR 122.41(m); and (5) The permit allowed for transfers of sewage to the  Kansas City, Mo. (KCMO) separate sanitary system when the Interceptor does not have the capacity to accept flows from the Blue River South Basin. Accordingly, the sewage transferred by Johnson County to the Interceptor Line during wet weather events will not all reach the Blue River Wastewater Treatment Plant (WWTP) for treatment, and will inevitably cause and/or contribute to the sanitary sewer overflow (SSO) discharges within KCMO.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA is required by CWA Section 402(d)(4) and 40 CFR Section 123.44(e) to hold a hearing on its specific objections, whenever the state requests such a hearing within 90 days of receipt of EPA’s specific objection. In the case of the listed facility, KDHE timely requested a Public Hearing regarding EPA’s objection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following EPA’s objection, KDHE and Johnson County worked together to address the issues raised in the objection. KDHE will put on Public Notice a draft permit for the Douglas L. Smith Facility that it believes addresses EPA’s objection. EPA will consider the revised draft permit and any other information submitted during the hearing process to determine whether the issues raised in the objection have been adequately resolved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;HEARING PROCEDURES AND COMMENTS&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All persons interested in EPA’s specific objection to the draft Douglas L. Smith Facility permit are invited to attend the Public Hearing. If you wish to contribute comments, statements, data, and other information to EPA regarding the specific objections, you may: (1) Mail or hand deliver written comments to EPA at this address: Chief, Water Infrastructure Management Branch, U.S. Environmental Protection Agency Region 7, Mail code: WWPD/WIMB, 11201 Renner Blvd., Lenexa, KS 66219; (2) Submit written comments electronically to EPA at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:curtis.glenn@epa.gov&quot;&gt;curtis.glenn@epa.gov&lt;/a&gt;; (3) Fax comments to 913-551-7726; or (4) Present oral comments or written materials at the hearing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hearing will be presided over by the EPA Regional Administrator’s authorized representative, the EPA Hearing Officer. If you are interested in attending the hearing, EPA encourages you to pre-register at least 72 hours before the hearing via an email notice to &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:porter.donna@epa.gov&quot;&gt;porter.donna@epa.gov&lt;/a&gt;, or by calling 913-551-7929 or toll-free at 1-800-223-0425. Pre-registering for the hearing will allow EPA to improve meeting planning and maximize opportunities for interested parties to provide oral comments. You may request in advance to speak at the hearing or request to speak when you arrive at the hearing.  EPA will generally assign speaking slots in the order received, but may make adjustments to the speaking order to accommodate requests to speak within the time available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hearing will begin with brief presentations by EPA, followed by oral comments from interested persons. Oral comments will generally be limited to 10 minutes each to ensure more opportunities for interested persons to speak. Though every effort will be made to accommodate all requests for a speaking time, EPA cannot guarantee that all persons will have an opportunity to contribute oral comments. As noted above, EPA also encourages you to provide written comments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;FOR FURTHER INFORMATION&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA has a record of the basis for the objection to the Douglas L. Smith Facility permit, including copies of KDHE’s 2009 draft permit and fact sheet, EPA’s specific objection letter, and other relevant documents, including KDHE’s revised draft permit and fact sheet for the Douglas L. Smith Facility. Electronic copies of these documents can be found &lt;a href=&quot;/ks/public-hearing-douglas-l-smith-middle-basin-wwtp-objection&quot;&gt;online&lt;/a&gt;. Hard copies of these documents are also on file and may be inspected at the following address anytime between 8:30 a.m. and 4:00 p.m., Monday through Friday: EPA Region 7, KDHE Hearing Record, 11201 Renner Blvd., Lenexa, Kansas. You may also contact EPA Region 7 at 913-551-7929 (Ms. Donna Porter) or toll-free at 1-800-223-0425, or by writing to EPA Region 7 at the above address (under Hearing Procedures and Comments).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;FOLLOWING THE PUBLIC HEARINGS&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The period for public comment on EPA’s specific objections will close upon the end of the Public Hearing. The EPA Hearing Officer may extend the comment period for written statements and data by so stating at the hearing. A tape recording or written transcript of the hearing, and all written comments, data and other information EPA receives, will be maintained by EPA and be available to the public at the EPA Region 7 Office, as described above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the Public Hearing, and after consideration of all written and oral comments and data and the requirements of the CWA and applicable regulations, the EPA Regional Administrator’s designee will reaffirm the original objection, modify the terms of the objection, or withdraw the objection, pursuant to 40 CFR Section 123.44(g). EPA will notify KDHE, the permit applicant, and all persons providing written or oral comments (if a mailing or email address has been provided) of its determination. If EPA either reaffirms the original objection or modifies the terms of the objection, KDHE must, within 30 days of receipt of EPA’s determination, submit to EPA a revised permit which meets the terms of the remaining objection, or exclusive authority to issue the permit passes to EPA for one permit term. If EPA’s objection is withdrawn following the hearing, KDHE may proceed with the permit issuance process for the permit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DISABILITY REASONABLE ACCOMMODATION NOTICE&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you need a reasonable accommodation for a disability, please contact Jonathan Cooper at 913-551-7287 or toll-free at 1-800-223-0425. Please provide one-week advance notice prior to the relevant public hearing date for special requests not related to ongoing programs and services.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Fri, 30 Dec 2016 20:31:06 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>mkessler</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">168061 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Region 7 States Air Quality Monitoring Plans - Kansas</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/ks/region-7-states-air-quality-monitoring-plans-kansas</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;Iowa, Kansas, Missouri, and Nebraska; Annual Monitoring Network Plans, Five-Year Monitoring Network Assessments, and approval documentation. Each year, states are required to submit an annual monitoring network plan to EPA. The network plans provide for the creation and maintenance of monitoring stations, in accordance with EPA monitoring requirements specified in 40 CFR (Code of Federal Regulations) Part 58.  For Five Year Monitoring Network Assessments, as stated at 40 CFR (Code of Federal Regulations) Part 58, each state is required to perform and submit to EPA an assessment of its air quality monitoring network every five years. At a minimum, this “five-year assessment” is meant to determine: if the existing network meets the monitoring objectives defined in Appendix D of 40 CFR Part 58; whether new sites are needed; whether existing sites are no longer needed and can be terminated; and whether new technologies are appropriate for incorporation into the ambient air monitoring network. For PM2.5 (particulate &amp;lt; 2.5 micrometers), the assessment also must identify needed changes to population-oriented sites. The first five-year assessment was due to EPA by July 1, 2010, and each assessment thereafter will be due in five-year increments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-342065&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-12/documents/ks_5yearnetworkassessment2015.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=4229569&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Kansas Department of Health and Environment 2015 Five-Year Ambient Monitoring Network Assessment dated October 16, 2015 (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(44 pp, 4 MB)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-342067&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-12/documents/ks_2015_2016_network_plan.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=4392239&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Kansas Department of Health and Environment 2015-2016 Ambient Air Monitoring Network Plan  (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(38 pp, 4 MB)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-342069&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-12/documents/ks_5yrand2015_approvalletter_12_11_15.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=633484&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Letter to Kansas dated December 11, 2015; Approval of 2015-2016 Ambient Air Monitoring Network Plan and Five-Year Network Assessment (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(1 pg, 633 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 29 Dec 2016 13:40:52 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>mpropst</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">167953 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Haag Oil Company, LLC - Clean Water Act Public Notice</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/ks/haag-oil-company-llc-clean-water-act-public-notice</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;UNITED STATES ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION AGENCY&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In accordance with Section 311(b)(6)(c) of the Clean Water Act (“CWA”), 33 U.S.C. § 1321(b)(6)(C), and 40 C.F.R. § 22.45 of the Consolidated Rules of Practice Governing the Administrative Assessment of Civil Penalties, Issuance of Compliance or Corrective Action Orders, and the Revocation, Termination or Suspension of Permits (“Consolidated Rules”), the Environmental Protection Agency (“EPA”) is providing notice of a proposed Administrative Penalty Assessment against Haag Oil Company, LLC, for alleged violations at the facility located at or near 326 Southeast 15th Street, Topeka, KS 66607.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under Section 311(b)(6)(B)(ii) of the Clean Water Act, 33 U.S.C. § 1321(b)(6)(B)(ii), the EPA is authorized to issue orders assessing civil penalties for various violations of the Clean Water Act.  The EPA may issue such orders after filing a Complaint commencing either a Class I or Class II penalty proceeding.  The EPA provides notice of the proposed assessment of a Class II civil penalty pursuant to 311(b)(6)(B)(ii) of the Clean Water Act, 33 U.S.C. § 1321(b)(6)(B)(ii).  Class II proceedings are conducted under EPA’s Consolidated Rules, 40 C.F.R. Part 22.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this case, the EPA alleges that Respondent discharged 2,400 gallons of oil on or about January 2, 2014, from Respondent’s facility in Topeka, Kansas into Shunganunga Creek, waters of the United States, in violation of Section 311(b) of the Clean Water Act, 33 U.S.C. § 1321(b).  In addition, Respondent failed to properly develop and implement an SPCC plan, in violation of the regulations found at 40 C.F.R. Part 112, issued pursuant to Section 311(j)(1)(C) of the Clean Water Act, 33 U.S.C. § 1321(j)(1)(C).  Respondent has reached agreement with EPA on the terms of a proposed Consent Agreement/Final Order which would resolve this matter.  Under the proposed Consent Agreement/Final Order, Respondent will pay a civil penalty of $31,134 and complete a Supplemental Environmental Project consisting of the installation of secondary containment to a capacity far exceeding what is required by law, at a cost of no less than $26,356.  Final approval of the proposed Consent Agreement/Final Order is subject to the requirements of 40 C.F.R. § 22.45.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The EPA will receive written comments on the proposed Administrative Penalty Assessment for a period of thirty (30) days from the date of publication of this notice.  The procedures by which the public may submit written comments on a proposed Class II order or participate in a Class II proceeding, and the procedures by which a respondent may request a hearing, are set forth in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gpo.gov/fdsys/pkg/CFR-2003-title40-vol1/pdf/CFR-2003-title40-vol1.pdf&quot;&gt;Consolidated Rules&lt;/a&gt;.  Persons wishing to receive a copy of EPA’s Consolidated Rules, review the Consent Agreement/Final Order, comment upon the proposed penalty assessment, or otherwise participate in the proceeding should contact Kathy Robinson, Regional Hearing Clerk, U.S. Environmental Protection Agency, Region 7, 11201 Renner Boulevard, Lenexa, Kansas 66219.  Please reference Docket No. CWA-07-2015-0107.  In order to provide opportunity for public comment, EPA will issue no final order assessing a penalty in this proceeding prior to forty (40) days from the date of this notice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
			&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=&quot;vertical-align:top; width:50%&quot;&gt;12/19/16&lt;br /&gt;
				Date&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td style=&quot;vertical-align:top; width:50%&quot;&gt;/s/&lt;br /&gt;
				John Smith&lt;br /&gt;
				Director, Air and Waste Management Division&lt;br /&gt;
				U.S. Environmental Protection Agency&lt;br /&gt;
				Region 7&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;box multi related-info right&quot;&gt;
	&lt;h2 class=&quot;pane-title&quot;&gt;How to Comment&lt;/h2&gt;

	&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Comments due date&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
			1/28/2017&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;div&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How to comment&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
			Persons wishing to obtain additional information on the proceeding, receive a copy of EPA’s Consolidated Rules, review the prorposed Consent Agreement/Final Order, comment upon the proposed penalty assessment, or otherwise participate in the proceeding should contact Kathy Robinson, Regional Hearing Clerk, U.S. Environmental Protection Agency, Region 7, 11201 Renner Boulevard, Lenexa, Kansas, 66219.  Please reference Docket No. CWA-07-2015-0107.&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Summary&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Environmental Protection Agency (“EPA”) is providing notice of a proposed Administrative Penalty Assessment against Haag Oil Company, LLC, for alleged violations at the facility located at or near 326 Southeast 15th Street, Topeka, KS 66607.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;​&lt;strong&gt;Program/Statute:&lt;/strong&gt;  Clean Water Act (CWA)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Applicant/Respondent(s):&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Haag Oil Company, LLC&lt;br /&gt;
	Topeka, Kansas&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Proposed action:&lt;/strong&gt; Public Notice of Clean Water Act Adminstrative Penalty Settlement&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Docket ID: &lt;/strong&gt;CWA-07-2015-0107&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-342063&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-12/documents/haag-oil-cafo.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=2004699&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Haag Oil Company, LLC proposed Consent Agreement Final Order (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(19 pp, 2 MB)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 29 Dec 2016 13:16:07 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>mpropst</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">167951 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Public Hearing on Douglas L. Smith Middle Basin WWTP Objection</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/ks/public-hearing-douglas-l-smith-middle-basin-wwtp-objection</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;The U.S. Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) Region 7 will hold a Public Hearing February 2 to allow interested persons to submit oral or written comments regarding EPA’s specific objections the Kansas Department of Health and Environment (KDHE) draft National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System (NPDES) permit for the Johnson County Wastewater Treatment Plant (WWTP), Douglas L. Smith Middle Basin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Nov. 2, 2009, EPA issued a specific objection on the Douglas L. Smith permit. EPA’s objection was based on several substantive issues. Following EPA’s objection, KDHE and Johnson County worked together to address the issues raised in the objection. KDHE has written a draft permit for the Douglas L. Smith Middle Basin facility that it believes addresses EPA’s objection.  EPA will consider the revised draft permit and any other information submitted during the hearing process to determine whether the issues raised in the objection have been adequately resolved. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-341917&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-12/documents/douglas-smith-2009-draft-permit-fact-sheet.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=1120728&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;2009 Draft Douglas L. Smith NPDES Permit and Fact Sheet (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(8 pp, 1 MB)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-341919&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-12/documents/douglas-smith-2009-objection.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=599497&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;EPA Objection to Draft Douglas L. Smith Permit (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(2 pp, 599 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-341923&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-12/documents/douglas-smith-2010-kdhe-request-public-hearing.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=289757&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;KDHE Request for a Public Hearing (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(1 pg, 290 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-341927&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-12/documents/douglas-smith-2016-permit-fact-sheet.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=2233506&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;2016 Draft Douglas L. Smith NPDES Permit and Fact Sheet (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(8 pp, 2 MB)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 28 Dec 2016 16:53:34 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>mkessler</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">167893 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Occidental Chemical Corporation, Wichita, Kansas - Information Sheet, December 2016</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/ks/occidental-chemical-corporation-wichita-kansas-information-sheet-december-2016</link>
    <description>&lt;h2 class=&quot;highlighted&quot;&gt;EPA Proposes Approval of No Migration Petition Modification Request&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;INTRODUCTION&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The U.S. Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) Region 7 is proposing the approval of a request by the Occidental Chemical Corporation (Occidental) to modify their existing &lt;strong&gt;No Migration Petition&lt;/strong&gt; (petition), which allows for the disposal of certain restricted hazardous wastes into injection wells located at the company’s facilities at 6200 South Ridge Road, Wichita, Kansas (see 40 CFR Section 148.20). If approved, the modification would allow the use of &lt;strong&gt;Well #11&lt;/strong&gt; as a hazardous waste injection well. EPA’s proposed approval of this request is now subject to a public comment period (see 40 CFR Section 124.10).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Occidental currently operates a chemical manufacturing and processing facility at the Wichita location. Since 1957, Occidental and the previous owner of the facility, Vulcan Chemicals, have used a system of deep underground wells to safely inject and dispose of certain types of hazardous and non-hazardous liquid wastes from their manufacturing operations. Changes to the federal Resource Conservation and Recovery Act (RCRA), which went into effect in 1988, prohibited the injection of hazardous waste unless it had been approved by EPA. The original EPA approval for the existing wells at the facility was granted on Aug. 7, 1990. This approval was renewed by EPA in 2007.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In March 2012, Occidental completed the construction of Well #11 at the facility. This well was drilled and constructed in accordance with a permit issued by the Kansas Department of Health and Environment (KDHE) for non-hazardous waste injection. Occidental’s petition modification request to EPA would allow the use of Well #11 as a hazardous waste injection well that would serve as a replacement for Well #4 (which was plugged in 2008) at the facility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The approval of Occidental’s petition modification request for Well #11 would not increase the volume of fluids that would be allowed to be injected at the facility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;EPA REVIEW OF PETITION REQUEST&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;RCRA and the Underground Injection Control (UIC) program prohibit the injection of hazardous waste, unless a petitioner demonstrates to EPA that there will be no migration of hazardous constituents from the injection zone for as long as the waste remains hazardous (see 40 CFR Section 268.6). These demonstrations are made through the submission of what is known as a No Migration Petition to EPA for review.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CONCLUSION OF EPA REVIEW&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA has concluded that the application and supplemental materials submitted for Occidental’s petition modification request demonstrate that Well #11’s operations, geologic siting, and waste stream characteristics would be in compliance with the requirements of RCRA and the existing petition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following a detailed and thorough review, EPA is proposing that Occidental has sufficiently demonstrated there will be no migration of hazardous constituents from the injection zone for as long as the waste remains hazardous, which is defined as 10,000 years [see 40 CFR Section 148.20(a)].&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PROPOSED APPROVAL OF WASTES&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA’s proposed approval of wastes that could be injected into wells at the facility is limited to a list of 57 specific hazardous wastes. The list includes volatile organic compounds, semi-volatile organic compounds, and inorganic compounds. To review EPA’s &lt;strong&gt;Fact Sheet&lt;/strong&gt; for its proposed petition modification decision, which includes a full listing of the wastes that would be approved for injection disposal, go to &lt;a href=&quot;/ks/occidental-chemical-corporation-well-no-11-proposed-no-migration-fact-sheet&quot;&gt;EPA&#039;s website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, requests for copies of the Fact Sheet, petition modification request, and compact disc copies of the &lt;strong&gt;Administrative Record&lt;/strong&gt; can be made to David Garrett, whose contact information is listed below. Physical copies of the Administrative Record are available for public review at the following locations:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;
				&lt;h2&gt;Information Repositories&lt;/h2&gt;
			&lt;/th&gt;
			&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Haysville Community Library&lt;br /&gt;
				210 Hays Ave.&lt;br /&gt;
				Haysville, KS 67060&lt;br /&gt;
				Mon-Thu: 9 am - 8 pm&lt;br /&gt;
				Fri-Sun: 10 am - 5 pm&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;EPA Region 7 Records Center&lt;br /&gt;
				11201 Renner Blvd.&lt;br /&gt;
				Lenexa, KS 66219&lt;br /&gt;
				Mon-Fri: 8 am - 5 pm&lt;br /&gt;
				 &lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;p&gt;All data submitted by the applicant and all documents used by EPA in making the proposed decision are available as part of the Administrative Record.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PUBLIC COMMENT PERIOD&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA’s proposed approval of Occidental’s petition modification request is subject to a public comment period. &lt;strong&gt;The period begins Dec. 12, 2016, and ends Jan. 25, 2017.&lt;/strong&gt; During this period, all written comments on the proposed approval should be submitted to David Garrett at EPA Region 7, using the contact information found at the end of this page. All persons who wish to comment on, or raise any objection to, the petition modification request or EPA’s proposed decision must do so by the close of the comment period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PUBLIC AVAILABILITY SESSION AND PUBLIC HEARING&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The public is invited to a Public Availability Session, where EPA will provide information and answer questions about the petition modification request, in conjunction with a Public Hearing to receive public comments (see 40 CFR Section 124.12). This combined event will be held:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wednesday, Jan. 11, 2017&lt;br /&gt;
	Public Availability Session: 5:00 to 6:30 p.m.&lt;br /&gt;
	Public Hearing: 7:00 to 8:30 p.m.&lt;br /&gt;
	The Haysville Learning Center, USD 261&lt;br /&gt;
	150 Stewart Ave. &lt;br /&gt;
	Haysville, KS 67060&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;INFORMATION AND COMMENTS&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have questions, need additional information about the Public Availability Session or Public Hearing, or wish to submit comments about EPA’s proposed approval of the petition modification request, please contact:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David Garrett, Environmental Scientist&lt;br /&gt;
	EPA Region 7 (WWPD/DRWM)&lt;br /&gt;
	11201 Renner Blvd.&lt;br /&gt;
	Lenexa, KS 66219&lt;br /&gt;
	Email: &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:garrett.david@epa.gov&quot;&gt;garrett.david@epa.gov&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	Phone: 913-551-7159&lt;br /&gt;
	Toll-free: 1-800-223-0425&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Mon, 12 Dec 2016 22:03:48 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>mkessler</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">166981 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Occidental Chemical Corporation, Wichita, Sedgwick County, Kansas – Public Notice</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/ks/occidental-chemical-corporation-wichita-sedgwick-county-kansas-public-notice</link>
    <description>&lt;h2 class=&quot;highlighted&quot;&gt;EPA Region 7 Announces Public Comment Period and Public Hearing for Proposed Modification of Hazardous Waste Injection Well No Migration Petition&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The U.S. Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) Region 7 proposes to approve a modification to the existing exemption from the land disposal restrictions of the Hazardous and Solid Waste Amendments to the Resource Conservation and Recovery Act (42 U.S.C. Section 6901, et seq; 40 CFR 148) to allow for the use of &lt;strong&gt;Well #11&lt;/strong&gt; for the injection of hazardous waste at the Occidental Chemical Corporation, located at 6200 South Ridge Road, Wichita, Kansas 67215. If approved, Well #11 would be a replacement for Well #4, which had been included in the existing No Migration Petition but was plugged and abandoned in 2008. The approval of Occidental’s petition modification request for Well #11 would not increase the volume of fluids that would be allowed to be injected at the facility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the public comment period described below, EPA has scheduled a &lt;strong&gt;Public Availability Session&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Public Hearing&lt;/strong&gt; that will be held:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wednesday, Jan. 11, 2017&lt;br /&gt;
	Public Availability Session: 5:00 to 6:30 p.m.&lt;br /&gt;
	Public Hearing: 7:00 to 8:30 p.m.&lt;br /&gt;
	The Haysville Learning Center, USD 261&lt;br /&gt;
	150 Stewart Ave. &lt;br /&gt;
	Haysville, KS 67060&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Public Availability Session&lt;/strong&gt; will be structured as an open house, and participants can arrive any time between 5:00 p.m. and 6:30 p.m. EPA representatives will be available to answer questions and provide information about the proposed approval of the No Migration Petition Modification request. A formal &lt;strong&gt;Public Hearing&lt;/strong&gt; will be held from 7:00 to 8:30 p.m., and participants will be given the opportunity to provide oral and written comments on EPA’s proposed approval of the No Migration Petition Modification request (see 40 CFR Section 124.12).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;For reasonable accommodation, contact Jonathan Cooper at 1-800-223-0425 or &lt;/em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;mailto:cooper.jonathan@epa.gov&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;cooper.jonathan@epa.gov&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PUBLIC COMMENT PERIOD:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA encourages public participation and will not make a final decision until thoroughly reviewing all comments received from the public. &lt;strong&gt;The public comment period will begin Dec. 12, 2016, and end Jan. 25, 2017.&lt;/strong&gt; All persons who wish to comment on, or raise any objection to, any condition of EPA’s proposed decision or Occidental’s application must do so by the close of the comment period. A &lt;strong&gt;Fact Sheet&lt;/strong&gt;, which provides the rationale for the proposed decision, is available &lt;a href=&quot;/ks/occidental-chemical-corporation-well-no-11-proposed-no-migration-fact-sheet&quot;&gt;online&lt;/a&gt;. In addition, the &lt;strong&gt;Administrative Record&lt;/strong&gt; (which contains all data submitted by the applicant) is available for public review at the following locations during the comment period:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;
				&lt;h2&gt;Information Repositories&lt;/h2&gt;
			&lt;/th&gt;
			&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Haysville Community Library&lt;br /&gt;
				210 Hays Ave.&lt;br /&gt;
				Haysville, KS 67060&lt;br /&gt;
				Mon-Thu: 9 am - 8 pm&lt;br /&gt;
				Fri-Sun: 10 am - 5 pm&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;EPA Region 7 Records Center&lt;br /&gt;
				11201 Renner Blvd.&lt;br /&gt;
				Lenexa, KS 66219&lt;br /&gt;
				Mon-Fri: 8 am - 5 pm&lt;br /&gt;
				 &lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;p&gt;Comments or requests for information must be submitted no later than &lt;strong&gt;Jan. 25, 2017&lt;/strong&gt;, to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David Garrett, Environmental Scientist&lt;br /&gt;
	EPA Region 7 (WWPD/DRWM)&lt;br /&gt;
	11201 Renner Blvd.&lt;br /&gt;
	Lenexa, KS 66219&lt;br /&gt;
	Email: &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:garrett.david@epa.gov&quot;&gt;garrett.david@epa.gov&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	Phone: 913-551-7159&lt;br /&gt;
	Toll-free: 1-800-223-0425&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Mon, 12 Dec 2016 20:49:36 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>mkessler</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">166965 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Occidental Chemical Corporation Well No. 11 Proposed No Migration Fact Sheet</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/ks/occidental-chemical-corporation-well-no-11-proposed-no-migration-fact-sheet</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this fact sheet is to briefly describe the principal facts and the considerations that went into preparing the proposed petition modification. To meet these objectives, this fact sheet contains background information on the petition process, a description of the facility, a brief description of the petition conditions and the reasons for these petition conditions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The U.S. Environmental Protection Agency proposes to approve a modification to the existing exemption from the land disposal restrictions of the Hazardous and Solid Waste Amendments to the Resource Conservation and Recovery Act (42 U.S.C. § 6901, et seq; 40 CFR 148) to allow for the use of Well #11 for the injection of hazardous waste at the Occidental Chemical Corporation located at 6200 South Ridge Road, Wichita, Kansas 67215. If approved, Well #11 would be a replacement for Well #4 which had been included in the existing No Migration Petition but was plugged and abandoned in 2008.  The approval of Occidental’s petition modification request for Well #11 would not increase the volume of fluids that would be allowed to be injected at the facility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-337011&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-12/documents/occidental-chemical-well-no-11-proposed-no-migration-petition-modification-fact-sheet.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=105482&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Occidental Chemical Corporation Well No. 11 Proposed No Migration Fact Sheet (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(16 pp, 105 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 07 Dec 2016 15:22:03 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>mpropst</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">166567 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>U.S. Army Combined Arms Center and Fort Leavenworth, Fort Leavenworth, Kansas - Fact Sheet, December 2016</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/ks/us-army-combined-arms-center-and-fort-leavenworth-fort-leavenworth-kansas-fact-sheet-december</link>
    <description>&lt;h2 class=&quot;highlighted&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Comment Period for Proposed Final Corrective Measures&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;INTRODUCTION&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA Region 7 invites the public to review and comment on the proposed corrective measures for Solid Waste Management Units (SWMUs) FTL-19, FTL-38, FTL-48, FTL-72 and FTL-75 at Fort Leavenworth (FTL). The 30-day public comment period runs from &lt;strong&gt;Dec. 1 through Dec. 30, 2016&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The public is encouraged to review EPA’s Statements of Basis and investigation reports regarding the SWMUs. This information is contained in the Administrative Record and is available during normal business hours at the following locations:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;
				&lt;h2&gt;Information Repositories&lt;/h2&gt;
			&lt;/th&gt;
			&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Leavenworth Public Library&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
				417 Spruce St.&lt;br /&gt;
				Leavenworth, KS 66048&lt;br /&gt;
				913-682-5666&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;EPA Region 7 Records Center&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
				11201 Renner Blvd.&lt;br /&gt;
				Lenexa, KS 66219&lt;br /&gt;
				1-800-223-0425&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;p&gt;Written comments on the proposed cleanup plan should be mailed or emailed no later than &lt;strong&gt;Dec. 30, 2016, &lt;/strong&gt;and should be sent to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bruce Morrison&lt;br /&gt;
	EPA Region 7 (AWMD/WRAP)&lt;br /&gt;
	11201 Renner Blvd.&lt;br /&gt;
	Lenexa, KS 66219&lt;br /&gt;
	Email: &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:morrison.bruce@epa.gov&quot;&gt;morrison.bruce@epa.gov&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fort Leavenworth is an active U.S. Army installation where officers are trained for staff work. Also, Fort Leavenworth provides long-term confinement for military prisoners in the United States Disciplinary Barracks (USDB). Other significant activities include coordination of combined arms collective training and the National Simulation Center. The Fort has been active since 1827.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The purpose of the Statements of Basis is to summarize the risk posed by hazardous constituents at SWMUs and proposed final corrective measures to address the risk. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;THE CONTAMINATION&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SWMU FTL-19, USDB Farm Sewage Lagoons:&lt;/strong&gt; FTL-19 consisted of two livestock sewage lagoons that were operational from 1980 to 2008. Both lagoons have been backfilled with clean soil. Hexavalent chromium was identified as a contaminant of concern in subsurface soil.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SWMU FTL-38, Wash Rack at Building 305:&lt;/strong&gt; FTL-38 was an outdoor wash station used for cleaning vehicles and equipment. Arsenic, manganese, and hexavalent chromium were identified as contaminants of potential concern.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SWMU FTL-48, Building 138 Sewage Treatment System: &lt;/strong&gt;FTL-48 was a 5,000 gallon-per-day sewage treatment package plant that served to treat domestic wastewater generated at Building 138. Arsenic, barium, and hexavalent chromium were identified as contaminants of potential concern.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SWMU FTL-72, Quarry Creek Drum Site:&lt;/strong&gt; FTL-72 is a solid waste management unit comprised primarily of a historical waste disposal and dump site that covers approximately three acres. Arsenic, lead, benzo(a)pyrene, dichlorodiphenyltrichloroethane (DDT), dichlorodiphenyldichloroethane (DDD), and dichlorodiphenyldichloroethylene (DDE) were identified as contaminants of potential concern.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;FTL-75, Iowa Avenue Sanitary Landfill:&lt;/strong&gt; FTL-75 is presumed to be a landfill that received sanitary waste from the late 1940s to the early 1970s. Arsenic and hexavalent chromium were identified as contaminants of potential concern.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PROPOSED FINAL REMEDY&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Groundwater monitoring, landfill cap inspection and maintenance, and land use controls are proposed for FTL-72. Land use controls are proposed for FTL-19 and FTL-75. No response actions or land use restrictions are being proposed for FTL-38 and FTL-48, due to low levels of contamination that do not pose an unacceptable risk to human health or the environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PERMIT MODIFICATION&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA is also proposing to modify the RCRA Part II Permit to incorporate the selection of the proposed remedies and the corrective measures previously selected for four additional SWMUs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;FOR MORE INFORMATION&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA encourages the public to review the Administrative Record and comment on the proposed final remedies. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Guidelines for Commenting:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Explain your views.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Tell us if you support or disagree with the recommendation. Please be specific.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Provide alternatives if you disagree.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;A formal public hearing has not been scheduled, but will be held if there is sufficient public interest. Requests for a public hearing must be made in writing to the EPA contact at the address listed on Page 1, and must state the nature of issues to be raised at the hearing. EPA will evaluate any request and hold a formal hearing if it finds that a hearing will contribute to the decision-making process by clarifying significant issues affecting the cleanup remedy. Comments or requests should be submitted by &lt;strong&gt;Dec. 30, 2016&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA will make the remedy final only after the public comment period ends and all comments are reviewed. EPA may modify the proposed remedy or choose another one, based on any new information and comments from the public.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have questions or want to receive a copy of the administrative record or further information, please contact:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Brendan Corazzin&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	Community Engagement Specialist&lt;br /&gt;
	EPA Region 7&lt;br /&gt;
	11201 Renner Boulevard&lt;br /&gt;
	Lenexa, KS 66219&lt;br /&gt;
	Phone: 1-800-223-0425&lt;br /&gt;
	Email: &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:corazzin.brendan@epa.gov&quot;&gt;corazzin.brendan@epa.gov&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


</description>
     <pubDate>Fri, 02 Dec 2016 21:40:39 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>mkessler</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">166353 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  </channel>
</rss>

<!-- Page cached by Boost @ 2017-01-25 18:34:40, expires @ 2017-01-26 06:34:40, lifetime 12 hours -->