<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?><rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.epa.gov/feed/133725/rss.xml" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/" xmlns:og="http://ogp.me/ns#" xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#" xmlns:sioc="http://rdfs.org/sioc/ns#" xmlns:sioct="http://rdfs.org/sioc/types#" xmlns:skos="http://www.w3.org/2004/02/skos/core#" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#">
  <channel>
    <title>Climate Change Science   </title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/feed/133725/rss.xml</link>
    <description>Updated Climate Change Science    content from the US Environmental Protection Agency</description>
    <language>en</language>
     <atom:link href="https://www.epa.gov/feed/133725/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      <item>
    <title>Climate Change Impacts and Risk Analysis (CIRA)</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/climate-change-science/climate-change-impacts-and-risk-analysis-cira</link>
    <description>&lt;div class=&quot;box multi related-info right&quot;&gt;
	&lt;h2 class=&quot;pane-title&quot;&gt;Related Links&lt;/h2&gt;

	&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/cira/frequent-questions-about-cira&quot;&gt;Frequent questions on CIRA&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/cira/forms/contact-us-about-cira-report&quot;&gt;Contact us about CIRA&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://epa.gov/climatechange&quot;&gt;Climate Change home&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/climatechange/what-you-can-do-about-climate-change&quot;&gt;What you can do about climate change&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Climate Change Impacts and Risk Analysis (CIRA) project quantifies the physical effects and economic damages under multiple climate change scenarios. The goal of this work is to estimate to what degree climate change impacts and damages to multiple U.S. sectors (e.g., human health, infrastructure, and water resources) may be avoided or reduced in a future under different levels of future global emissions. CIRA advances the estimation of climate change damages by bridging the gap between climate modeling and economic effects, presenting both physical and monetized damages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The peer-reviewed CIRA reports and analyses demonstrate that global action on climate change will significantly benefit Americans by saving lives and avoiding costly damages across the U.S. economy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/cira&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Climate Change in the United States: Benefits of Global Action&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2015 EPA report estimates the physical and monetary benefits to the U.S. of reducing global greenhouse gas emissions in six broad sectors: health, infrastructure, electricity, water resources, agriculture and forestry, and ecosystems.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Avoiding and Reducing Long-term Risks of Climate Change: A Technical Report for the Fourth National Climate Assessment&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This forthcoming Technical Report, currently in peer review,  summarizes and communicates the results of the second phase of modeling under the CIRA project, and is intended to inform the fourth &lt;a href=&quot;http://nca2014.globalchange.gov/&quot;&gt;National Climate Assessment&lt;/a&gt; (NCA4) of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.globalchange.gov/&quot;&gt;U.S. Global Change Research Program&lt;/a&gt; (USGCRP).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 28 Dec 2016 15:04:58 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>ideluca</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">167875 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Methane and Black Carbon Impacts on the Arctic: Communicating the Science</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/climate-change-science/methane-and-black-carbon-impacts-arctic-communicating-science</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;This document describes the scientific understanding of the impacts of methane and black carbon emissions on the Arctic climate. This information is provided to help facilitate communication of the evolving science, evaluate mitigation strategies, and inform decision-making.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-319395&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-09/documents/arctic-methane-blackcarbon_communicating-the-science.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=7342589&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Methane and Black Carbon Impacts on the Arctic: Communicating the Science (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(19 pp, 7 MB)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2016 20:10:32 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>tnayem</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">161453 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Understanding the Link Between Climate Change and Extreme Weather</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/climate-change-science/understanding-link-between-climate-change-and-extreme-weather</link>
    <description>&lt;h3&gt;On This Page:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#changes&quot;&gt;Changes in Extreme Weather and Climate Events&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#events&quot;&gt;Trends in Specific Extreme Weather Events&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#adaptation&quot;&gt;Adaptation: Reducing the Threat of Climate Change and Preparing for Impacts&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;changes&quot; name=&quot;changes&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Changes in Extreme Weather and Climate Events&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;box multi related-info right&quot;&gt;
	&lt;h2 class=&quot;pane-title&quot;&gt;What is extreme weather?&lt;/h2&gt;

	&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;Extreme weather and climate events are events that:
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;typically don&#039;t happen very frequently, such as droughts or floods that have historically occurred on average only once in 100 years.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;vary from &quot;the norm&quot; in severity or duration, like heat waves.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;have severe impacts, like hurricanes.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scientists study many aspects of change in extreme weather and climate events. These include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Frequency:&lt;/strong&gt; Are events occurring more often than they did in the past?&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Intensity:&lt;/strong&gt; Are events getting more severe, with the potential for more damaging effects?&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Duration:&lt;/strong&gt; Are events lasting longer than &quot;the norm&quot;?&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Timing:&lt;/strong&gt; Are events occurring earlier or later in the season or the year than they used to?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Extreme weather is typically rare. But climate change is increasing the odds of more extreme weather events taking place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row cols-2&quot;&gt;
	&lt;div class=&quot;col size-2of3&quot;&gt;
		&lt;div class=&quot;box multi highlight&quot;&gt;
			&lt;h2 class=&quot;pane-title&quot;&gt;Climate Change and Extreme Weather&lt;/h2&gt;

			&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-gif view-mode-medium&quot; style=&quot;width:448px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;An image of a bell curve showing how incidence of extreme weather changes as average temperature increases. Extreme hot weather becomes more common while extreme cold weather becomes less common.&quot; height=&quot;252&quot; width=&quot;448&quot; class=&quot;media-element file-medium&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/medium/public/2016-09/bell-graph_0.gif&quot; title=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt; Watch the &lt;span id=&quot;file-301393&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-x-shockwave-flash&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/sites/production/files/2016-07/bell_curve.swf&quot; type=&quot;application/x-shockwave-flash; length=342354&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Extreme Weather Bell Curve Animation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(1 pg, 342 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
 to learn how this shift is happening. &lt;span&gt;(requires Flash) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;Establishing the most likely causes behind an extreme weather event can be challenging, since these events are due to combinations of multiple factors, including natural variability. Nevertheless, scientists have been able to draw a connection between some types of extreme climate patterns—an even some individual events—and climate change. A good way to think about this connection is to focus on whether an extreme weather event was made &lt;em&gt;more likely&lt;/em&gt; by climate change.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;

	&lt;div class=&quot;col size-1of3&quot;&gt;
		&lt;div class=&quot;box multi related-info&quot;&gt;
			&lt;h2 class=&quot;pane-title&quot;&gt;Key Points&lt;/h2&gt;

			&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
				&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Extreme weather events are becoming more frequent and/or severe around the world. This is consistent with what we expect with a warming planet.&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;Increasingly frequent and/or severe weather events have serious consequences for society and ecosystems.&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;Between 2011 and 2013, the United States experienced 32 weather events that each caused at least one billion dollars in damages.&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;Changes in some weather events are more closely linked to climate change than others.&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;Understanding the links between climate change and extreme events can help us plan for the future.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;box multi related-info right&quot;&gt;
	&lt;h2 class=&quot;pane-title&quot;&gt;Related Links&lt;/h2&gt;

	&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;EPA: &lt;a href=&quot;/climatechange/extreme-heat-guidebook&quot;&gt;Extreme Heat: What You Can Do to Prepare&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;EPA: &lt;a href=&quot;/naturaldisasters&quot;&gt;Natural Disasters&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Online course: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.udemy.com/extreme-weather-101/&quot;&gt;Extreme Weather 101&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Blog: &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.epa.gov/blog/2015/07/heat-waves/&quot;&gt;Heat Waves&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Blog: &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.epa.gov/blog/2013/11/when-it-rains-it-pours/&quot;&gt;When It Rains, It Pours: Extreme Precipitation and Drought&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Blog: &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.epa.gov/blog/2013/11/resiliency-in-the-face-of-stronger-storms/&quot;&gt;Resiliency in the Face of Stronger Storms&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There have been changes in some types of extreme weather events in the United States over the last several decades, including more intense and frequent heat waves, less frequent and intense cold waves, and regional changes in floods, droughts, and wildfires.&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#references&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; This rise in extreme weather events fits a pattern you can expect with a warming planet. Scientists project that climate change will make some of these extreme weather events more likely to occur and/or more likely to be severe.&lt;a id=&quot;events&quot; name=&quot;events&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Trends in Specific Extreme Weather Events&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Learn more by clicking on each tab below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;tabs&quot;&gt;
	&lt;ul class=&quot;tabs&quot; id=&quot;tabsnav&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;menu-internal&quot; href=&quot;#heatwaves&quot;&gt;Heatwaves&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;menu-internal&quot; href=&quot;#droughts&quot;&gt;Droughts&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;menu-internal&quot; href=&quot;#wildfires&quot;&gt;Wildfires&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;menu-internal&quot; href=&quot;#rainfall&quot;&gt;Extreme Rainfall&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
		 
		&lt;li&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;menu-internal&quot; href=&quot;#precipitation&quot;&gt;Winter Precipitation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;menu-internal&quot; href=&quot;#hurricanes&quot;&gt;Hurricanes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;menu-internal&quot; href=&quot;#tornadoes&quot;&gt;Tornadoes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;menu-internal&quot; href=&quot;#floods&quot;&gt;Floods&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;div id=&quot;heatwaves&quot;&gt;
		&lt;h3&gt;Heat Waves&lt;/h3&gt;

		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why does it matter?&lt;/strong&gt; Heat waves can have serious health consequences, particularly for older adults, young children, the poor, and people with certain pre-existing health conditions, like asthma or heart disease.&lt;sup&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#references&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Excessive heat can also kill or injure crops and livestock, and it can lead to power outages as heavy demand for air conditioning strains the power grid.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How does it relate to climate change?&lt;/strong&gt; Even a small rise in average temperature brought on by climate change can boost the odds of extreme heat and heat waves.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What&#039;s happening?&lt;/strong&gt; Climate change has increased the likelihood of more frequent and more severe heat waves. Heat waves have generally become more frequent and intense across the United States in recent decades, particularly in the western United States (including Alaska).&lt;sup&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#references&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The impacts of heat waves are greatest in the Northeast and Midwest,&lt;sup&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#references&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and in urban areas, where the urban heat island effect increases vulnerability to heat-related health impacts.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What&#039;s ahead?&lt;/strong&gt; Heat waves are expected to become more frequent, longer, and more intense in the years ahead.&lt;sup&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#references&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The number of extremely hot days is projected increase throughout the United States.&lt;sup&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#references&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How sure is the science?&lt;/strong&gt; Scientists are highly confident&lt;sup&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#references&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; that heat waves and other extreme heat events have and will continue to become more frequent and intense due to climate change.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

	&lt;div id=&quot;droughts&quot;&gt;
		&lt;h3&gt;Droughts&lt;/h3&gt;

		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why does it matter?&lt;/strong&gt; Droughts can mean crop and livestock failures for farmers, which in turn can cause higher food prices and possibly even food shortages. Droughts can also stress water supplies and contribute to wildfires.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How does it relate to climate change?&lt;/strong&gt; As temperatures rise because of climate change, more water evaporates from land and water bodies. Along with changes in precipitation patterns, this can contribute to unusual dryness in some areas.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What&#039;s happening?&lt;/strong&gt; In recent decades, some regions have experienced more intense and longer droughts, while other regions have seen less frequent, less intense, or shorter droughts.&lt;sup&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#references&quot;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; There has been no general trend in the overall extent of drought across the contiguous United States since 1900.&lt;sup&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#references&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; However, large portions of the Southwest have experienced drought conditions since weekly Drought Monitor records began in 2000.&lt;sup&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#references&quot;&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Droughts are expected to be a normal condition for the southern and central United States in the next century.&lt;sup&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#references&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What&#039;s ahead? &lt;/strong&gt; Summer droughts are expected to intensify almost everywhere in the continental United States due to longer periods of dry weather and more extreme heat. A number of studies project that widespread drought will become more common over much of the southern and central United States, with amplified drought severity. A reduction in soil moisture, which exacerbates heat waves, is projected for much of the western and central United States.&lt;sup&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#references&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How sure is the science?&lt;/strong&gt; Scientists are highly confident&lt;sup&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#references&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; that droughts have become more frequent and intense in some regions of the United States, and that climate change increases the likelihood of these severe droughts in the future, particularly in the Southwest. Factors such as changes in a region&#039;s land use or high draws on water supplies can also play a role, especially at the local level.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

	&lt;div id=&quot;wildfires&quot;&gt;
		&lt;h3&gt;Wildfires&lt;/h3&gt;

		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why does it matter?&lt;/strong&gt; Wildfires and their associated air pollution can cause deaths, injuries, and eye, respiratory, and cardiovascular illnesses. Large wildfires can disrupt or displace communities and have significant economic costs related to fire suppression, property damage, and losses in recreation, tourism, forestry, and related industries, They can also threaten wildlife and degrade local ecosystems.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How does it relate to climate change?&lt;/strong&gt; Climate change can contribute to dry conditions through higher temperatures, increased rates of evaporation, and earlier spring snowmelt (resulting in longer dry seasons), which all increase the risk of wildfires.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What&#039;s happening?&lt;/strong&gt; In recent decades, the extent of wildfires appears to have increased, particularly in the western United States.&lt;sup&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#references&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#references&quot;&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Increased warming, drought, and insect outbreaks, all caused by or linked to climate change, have increased wildfires and impacts to people and ecosystems in the Southwest.&lt;sup&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#references&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What&#039;s ahead?&lt;/strong&gt; There is very high confidence&lt;sup&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#references&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; that under projected climate change, forests and communities in the western United States will be increasingly affected by more frequent, larger, and more intense wildfires.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How sure is the science?&lt;/strong&gt; Scientists are highly confident&lt;sup&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#references&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; that wildfires have increased in size in the western United States and very highly confident&lt;sup&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#references&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; that dry conditions associated with climate change increase the likelihood of large wildfires in the future. Other factors, such as land management, land use changes, and impacts of pests, can also play a role in forest vulnerability.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

	&lt;div id=&quot;rainfall&quot;&gt;
		&lt;h3&gt;Extreme Rainfall&lt;/h3&gt;

		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why does it matter?&lt;/strong&gt; Extreme rainfall events can damage crops, erode soil, and increase flooding. In addition, runoff from precipitation can degrade or contaminate water quality as pollutants deposited on land wash into water bodies used by people for drinking, irrigation, and other activities.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How does it relate to climate change?&lt;/strong&gt; Warmer temperatures cause more water to evaporate into the air. This moisture-laden air can produce more intense precipitation in the form of extreme rainfall events and storms.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What&#039;s happening?&lt;/strong&gt; In recent years, a larger percentage of precipitation has come in the form of intense single-day events.&lt;sup&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#references&quot;&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The amount of rain falling on the heaviest rain days has also increased over the past few decades.&lt;sup&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#references&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What&#039;s ahead?&lt;/strong&gt; It is likely that the frequency and intensity of extreme precipitation events will increase over most of the United States and many other areas of the globe.&lt;sup&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#references&quot;&gt;[5]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; A trend towards increase heavy precipitation will continue to occur, even in areas where total precipitation is projected to decrease.&lt;sup&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#references&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How sure is the science?&lt;/strong&gt; Scientists are highly confident&lt;sup&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#references&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; that across most of the United States, the heaviest rainfall events have become more intense and frequent, especially in the Midwest and Northeast, and that the frequency and intensity of extreme rainfall events will further increase in the future for most areas in the United States. Other factors, such as weather systems and ocean cycles like El Niño, can also play a role.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

	&lt;div id=&quot;precipitation&quot;&gt;
		&lt;h3&gt;Extreme Winter Precipitation&lt;/h3&gt;

		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why does it matter?&lt;/strong&gt; Heavy winter storms can disrupt transportation, the flow of goods, and emergency and medical services. A buildup of snow can collapse roofs, knock down trees and power lines, and cause flooding when it melts.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How does it relate to climate change?&lt;/strong&gt; Warmer temperatures cause more water to evaporate into the air. If the temperature is still below freezing, this moisture-laden air can produce more intense precipitation in the form of unusually heavy snow, sleet, and freezing rain events, even in years when total snowfall is lower than average.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What&#039;s happening?&lt;/strong&gt; Winter storms have increased in frequency and intensity since the 1950s, and their tracks have shifted northward over the United States.&lt;sup&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#references&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What&#039;s ahead?&lt;/strong&gt; It is likely that the frequency and intensity of extreme winter precipitation events will increase in some areas of the United States, particularly in the northern states.&lt;sup&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#references&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How sure is the science?&lt;/strong&gt; Scientists have medium confidence&lt;sup&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#references&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; that winter storms have increased slightly in frequency and intensity.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

	&lt;div id=&quot;hurricanes&quot;&gt;
		&lt;h3&gt;Hurricanes&lt;/h3&gt;

		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why does it matter?&lt;/strong&gt; Powerful hurricanes that make landfall can cause significant numbers of deaths and injuries, and disrupt or displace communities. When combined with coastal waters made higher by sea level rise, strong winds can create damaging storm surges. Hurricanes are also among the most costly extreme weather events, with severe storms causing billions of dollars in economic losses.&lt;sup&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#references&quot;&gt;[6]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#references&quot;&gt;[7]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Even hurricanes that don&#039;t make landfall can influence waves, currents, and storm tides, which can result in property damage, flooding, and coastal erosion.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How does it relate to climate change?&lt;/strong&gt; Increases in hurricane activity are linked to warming ocean temperatures because hurricanes draw more energy from warmer water. But the link between ocean temperature and hurricanes is complex, and other factors can also play a role in the formation and intensity of these storms.&lt;sup&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#references&quot;&gt;[8]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What&#039;s happening?&lt;/strong&gt; There has been an increase in the intensity, frequency, and duration of hurricanes and in the number of strong (Category 4 and 5) hurricanes in the North Atlantic Ocean since the early 1980s.&lt;sup&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#references&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; However, changes in observation methods over time make it difficult to know for certain whether tropical storm activity has shown a long-term increase.&lt;sup&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#references&quot;&gt;[8]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What&#039;s ahead?&lt;/strong&gt; The intensity of the strongest hurricanes is projected to continue to increase as the oceans continue to warm, bringing stronger winds and heavier rains. Whether changes in hurricane frequency or landfall will occur is less certain.&lt;sup&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#references&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How sure is the science?&lt;/strong&gt; Scientists have medium confidence&lt;sup&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#references&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; that hurricane intensity and associated heavy rainfall will continue to increase under a changing climate, but significant uncertainties remain.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

	&lt;div id=&quot;tornadoes&quot;&gt;
		&lt;h3&gt;Tornadoes&lt;/h3&gt;

		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why does it matter?&lt;/strong&gt; Strong tornadoes can cause deaths and injuries, disrupt or displace communities, and inflict severe damage to crops, trees, buildings, and infrastructure.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How does it relate to climate change?&lt;/strong&gt; A warming climate can lead to stronger and more frequent thunderstorms, and these storms can spur tornadoes.&lt;sup&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#references&quot;&gt;[8]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; But scientists do not yet fully understand all of the ways in which tornadoes may be linked to climate change.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What&#039;s happening?&lt;/strong&gt; Although the number of tornado reports has increased with better observation practices, there has been little change in the frequency of the strongest tornadoes over the past 55 years in the United States.&lt;sup&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#references&quot;&gt;[9]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What&#039;s ahead?&lt;/strong&gt; With a warming climate, the thunderstorms and weather conditions that give rise to tornadoes could increase in some areas. But challenges in observing and modeling these events result in many uncertainties about how the frequency and intensity of tornadoes will change.&lt;sup&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#references&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#references&quot;&gt;[10]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How sure is the science?&lt;/strong&gt; Scientists have low confidence&lt;sup&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#references&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; in projections of trends in severe storms, including the intensity and frequency of tornadoes, hail, and damaging thunderstorm winds. This is in part due to a lack of long-term and the fact that such small and often remote storms are difficult to monitor and model.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

	&lt;div id=&quot;floods&quot;&gt;
		&lt;h3&gt;Floods&lt;/h3&gt;

		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why does it matter?&lt;/strong&gt; Flooding can cause disease, deaths, and injuries; damage property and critical infrastructure such as sewer systems and wastewater treatment facilities; and disrupt or displace communities.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How does it relate to climate change?&lt;/strong&gt; Heavy rainfall events, more intense storms, and changes in the timing of snowmelt can lead to more frequent or intense flooding in some areas.&lt;sup&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#references&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What&#039;s happening?&lt;/strong&gt; Many regions of the United States are experiencing significant changes in the magnitude of river flooding. When averaged over the entire nation, however, the increases and decreases cancel each other out and show no national level trend. For instance, there has been an increase in flooding events in the Midwest, Great Plains, and Northeast in the last several decades, where the largest increases in heavy rain amounts have occurred. But flooding has decreased in the Southwest.&lt;sup&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#references&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What&#039;s ahead?&lt;/strong&gt; Heavy rainfall events and more intense storms in some regions could lead to more frequent or intense flooding in many United States regions, even in areas where total precipitation is projected to decline.&lt;sup&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#references&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; There is medium confidence&lt;sup&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#references&quot;&gt;[10]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; that projected increases in heavy rainfall would contribute to increases in local flooding in some regions.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How sure is the science?&lt;/strong&gt; The link between floods and climate change is a relatively new area of research, and many other factors, like land use and management practices, can trigger these events or influence how damaging they become. Scientists have high confidence&lt;sup&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#references&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; that there have been regional trends in floods. However, scientists have low confidence&lt;sup&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#references&quot;&gt;[10]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#references&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; in projections of future changes in flood frequency and intensity, because the causes of regional changes are complex.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;adaptation&quot;&gt;Adaptation: Reducing the Threat of Climate Change and Preparing for Impacts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Extreme weather and climate events pose a serious threat to the health and welfare of American families and businesses. For instance, between 2011 and 2013, the United States experienced 32 weather events that each caused at least one billion dollars in damages.&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#references&quot;&gt;[7]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; 2012 ranks as 2nd costliest year on record, with more than $110 billion in damages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg center view-mode-full caption&quot; style=&quot;width:597px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Map showing billion dollar weather/climate disasters in the United States from 1980 to 2012, from a minimum of 1 (Hawaii) to a maximum of 54 (Texas).&quot; height=&quot;530&quot; width=&quot;597&quot; class=&quot;center media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2016-09/billion-dollar-weather.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;figcaption&quot;&gt;This map summarizes the number of times each state has been affected by weather and climate events over the past 30 years that have resulted in more than a billion dollars in damages. The Southeast has been affected by more billion-dollar disasters than any other region. The primary disaster type for coastal states such as Florida is hurricanes, while interior and northern states in the region also experience sizeable numbers of tornadoes and winter storms. For a list of events and the affected states,&lt;br /&gt;
see: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ncdc.noaa.gov/billions/events&quot;&gt;http://www.ncdc.noaa.gov/billions/events&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Source:&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.globalchange.gov/browse/multimedia/billion-dollar-weatherclimate-disasters&quot;&gt;USGCRP (2014) &lt;em&gt;Billion Dollar Weather/Climate Disasters&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA is taking a number of common-sense actions to &lt;a href=&quot;/climatechange/what-epa-doing-about-climate-change&quot;&gt;reduce greenhouse gas emissions&lt;/a&gt; and help cities and towns build more resilient communities to prepare for the impacts of a changing climate, including the weather extremes described above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information about climate adaptation and things you can do to prepare for changes in extreme weather events, see &lt;a href=&quot;/climatechange/adapting-climate-change&quot;&gt;Climate Change Adaptation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information on how you can reduce greenhouse gas emissions at home, on the road, and in your workplace, see &lt;a href=&quot;/climatechange/what-you-can-do-about-climate-change&quot;&gt;What You Can Do&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;references&quot; name=&quot;references&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;References&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;[1] USGCRP (2014). Melillo, Jerry M., Terese (T.C.) Richmond, and Gary W. Yohe, Eds. &lt;a href=&quot;http://nca2014.globalchange.gov/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Climate Change Impacts in the United States: The Third National Climate Assessment&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. U.S. Global Change Research Program, 841 pp. &lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;[2] US EPA (2006). &lt;a href=&quot;/heat-islands/excessive-heat-events-guidebook&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Excessive Heat Events Guidebook&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;small&gt;.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;[3] CCSP (2008). &lt;a href=&quot;http://downloads.globalchange.gov/sap/sap3-3/sap3-3-final-all.pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Weather and climate extremes in a changing climate&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt; Synthesis and Assessment Product 3.3&lt;/small&gt;&lt;small&gt;.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;[4] US EPA (2014). &lt;a href=&quot;/climate-indicators&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Climate Change Indicators in the United States&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;[5] AMS (2013). Kunkel, K.E., T.R. Karl, H. Brooks, J. Kossin, J. Lawrimore, D. Arndt, L. Bosart, D. Changnon, S.L. Cutter, N. Doesken, K. Emanuel, P.Ya. Groisman, R.W. Katz, T. Knutson, J. O&#039;Brien, C. J. Paciorek, T. Peterson, K. Redmond, D. Robinson, J. Trapp, R. Vose, S. Weaver, M. Wehner, K. Wolter, and D. Wuebbles. 2013. &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://journals.ametsoc.org/doi/pdf/10.1175/BAMS-D-11-00262.1&quot;&gt;Monitoring and understanding changes in extreme storm statistics: State of knowledge&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. Bulletin of the American Meteorological Society 94:499-514.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;[6] NOAA (2013). Smith, A.B., and R.W. Katz. 2013. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.isse.ucar.edu/staff/katz/docs/pdf/nhaz2013.pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;U.S. billion-dollar weather and climate disasters: Data sources, trends, accuracy and biases&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Natural Hazards 67:387-410.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;[7] NOAA (2013). &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ncdc.noaa.gov/billions&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Billion-Dollar Weather and Climate Disasters&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, National Climatic Data Center.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;[8] IPCC (2013). &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ipcc.ch/report/ar5/wg1/&quot;&gt;Climate Change 2013: The Physical Science Basis&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/em&gt;Contribution of Working Group I to the Fifth Assessment Report of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change [Stocker, T.F., D. Qin, G.-K. Plattner, M. Tignor, S.K. Allen, J. Boschung, A. Nauels, Y. Xia, V. Bex and P.M. Midgley (eds.)]. Cambridge University Press, Cambridge, United Kingdom and New York, NY, USA, 1535 p.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;[9] NOAA (2013). &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ncdc.noaa.gov/climate-information/extreme-events/us-tornado-climatology/trends&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Historical records and trends&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, National Climatic Data Center.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;[10] IPCC (2012). &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ipcc-wg2.gov/SREX/images/uploads/SREX-All_FINAL.pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Managing the risks of extreme events and disasters to advance climate change adaptation&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;small&gt; Cambridge, UK: Cambridge University Press.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Fri, 15 Jul 2016 19:43:00 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>tnayem</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">155079 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Future of Climate Change</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/climate-change-science/future-climate-change</link>
    <description>&lt;h3&gt;On This Page&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Greenhouse gas&quot;&gt;Increasing greenhouse gas concentrations will have many effects&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Temperature&quot;&gt;Future temperature changes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Ice&quot;&gt;Future ice, snowpack, and permafrost&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Sea level&quot;&gt;Future sea level change&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Precipitation&quot;&gt;Future precipitation and storm events&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Acidification&quot;&gt;Future ocean acidification&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;Greenhouse gas&quot; id=&quot;Greenhouse gas&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Increasing greenhouse gas concentrations will have many effects&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;box multi related-info right&quot;&gt;
	&lt;h2 class=&quot;pane-title&quot;&gt;Key Points&lt;/h2&gt;

	&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Continued emissions of greenhouse gases will lead to further climate changes. Future changes are expected to include a warmer atmosphere, a warmer and more acidic ocean, higher sea levels, and larger changes in precipitation patterns.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;The extent of future climate change depends on what we do now to reduce greenhouse gas emissions. The more we emit, the larger future changes will be.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
	 

	&lt;h2 class=&quot;pane-title&quot;&gt;Related Links&lt;/h2&gt;

	&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://nca2014.globalchange.gov/&quot;&gt;U.S. National Climate Assessment, 2014&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://globalchange.gov/publications/reports/scientific-assessments/us-impacts/full-report&quot;&gt;USGCRP &lt;em&gt;Global Climate Change Impacts in the United States&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ipcc.ch/publications_and_data/publications_and_data_reports.shtml&quot;&gt;IPCC Fifth Assessment Report&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/em&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://nas-sites.org/americasclimatechoices/sample-page/panel-reports/&quot;&gt;NRC America&#039;s Climate Choices Reports&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/em&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/epahome/exitepa.htm&quot; title=&quot;&amp;quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&amp;quot; &quot;&gt;IPCC &lt;em&gt;Managing the Risks of Extreme Events and Disasters to Advance Climate Change Adaptation&lt;/em&gt;, Summary for Policy Makers&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(20 pp, 11.8 M, &lt;a href=&quot;/home/pdf-files&quot;&gt;About PDF&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nap.edu/catalog.php?record_id=12877#toc&quot;&gt;NRC &lt;em&gt;Climate Stabilization Targets&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Greenhouse gas concentrations in the atmosphere will continue to increase unless the billions of tons of our annual emissions decrease substantially. Increased concentrations are expected to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Increase Earth&#039;s average &lt;a href=&quot;#Temperature&quot;&gt;temperature&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Influence the patterns and amounts of &lt;a href=&quot;#Precipitation&quot;&gt;precipitation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Reduce &lt;a href=&quot;#Ice&quot;&gt;ice&lt;/a&gt; and snow cover, as well as permafrost&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Raise &lt;a href=&quot;#Sea level&quot;&gt;sea level&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Increase the &lt;a href=&quot;#Acidification&quot;&gt;acidity&lt;/a&gt; of the oceans&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Increase the frequency, intensity, and/or duration of extreme events&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Shift &lt;a href=&quot;/climate-impacts/climate-impacts-ecosystems&quot;&gt;ecosystem characteristics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Increase threats to &lt;a href=&quot;/climate-impacts/climate-impacts-human-health&quot;&gt;human health&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;These changes will &lt;a href=&quot;/climate-impacts&quot;&gt;impact&lt;/a&gt; our food supply, water resources, infrastructure, ecosystems, and even our own health.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;em&gt;Future changes will depend on many factors&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nap.edu/catalog.php?record_id=12877#toc&quot;&gt;NRC &lt;em&gt;Climate Stabilization Targets&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/a&gt;increase in greenhouse gas concentrations&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Natural influences on climate (e.g., from volcanic activity and changes in the sun&#039;s intensity) and natural processes within the climate system (e.g., changes in ocean circulation patterns)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Scientists use computer models of the climate system to better understand these issues and project future climate changes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;em&gt;Past and present-day greenhouse gas emissions will affect climate far into the future&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many greenhouse gases stay in the atmosphere for long periods of time. As a result, even if emissions stopped increasing, atmospheric greenhouse gas concentrations would continue to increase and remain elevated for hundreds of years. Moreover, if we stabilized concentrations and the composition of today&#039;s atmosphere remained steady (which would require a dramatic reduction in current greenhouse gas emissions), surface air temperatures would continue to warm. This is because the oceans, which store heat, take many decades to fully respond to higher greenhouse gas concentrations. The ocean&#039;s response to higher greenhouse gas concentrations and higher temperatures will continue to impact climate over the next several decades to hundreds of years.&lt;a href=&quot;#ref2&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[2]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To learn more about greenhouse gases, please visit the &lt;a href=&quot;/ghgemissions&quot;&gt;Greenhouse Gas Emissions page&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&quot;/climate-change-science/causes-climate-change&quot;&gt;Greenhouse Effect section&lt;/a&gt; of the Causes of Climate Change page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because it is difficult to project far-off future emissions and other human factors that influence climate, scientists use a range of scenarios using various assumptions about future economic, social, technological, and environmental conditions.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg center view-mode-medium caption&quot; style=&quot;width:448px;&quot;&gt;&lt;a
    href=&quot;/sites/production/files/2016-07/scenarioco2.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Graph displaying projected GHG concentrations for four different emissions scenarios: highest (RCP 8.5), higher (RCP 6.0), lower (RCP 4.5), and lowest (RCP 2.6). By 2100, their CO2 equivalents in ppm approximate 1350, 850, 650, and 450, respectively.&quot; height=&quot;298&quot; width=&quot;448&quot; class=&quot;center media-element file-medium center&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/medium/public/2016-07/scenarioco2.jpg&quot; title=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;figcaption&quot;&gt;This figure shows projected greenhouse gas concentrations for four different emissions pathways. The top pathway assumes that greenhouse gas emissions will continue to rise throughout the current century. The bottom pathway assumes that emissions reach a peak between 2010 and 2020, declining thereafter.&lt;br /&gt;
Source: Graph created from data in the Representative Concentration Pathways Database (Version 2.0.5)&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.iiasa.ac.at/web-apps/tnt/RcpDb&quot;&gt;http://www.iiasa.ac.at/web-apps/tnt/RcpDb&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Click the image to view a larger version.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;Temperature&quot; name=&quot;Temperature&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Future temperature changes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have already observed global &lt;a href=&quot;/climate-indicators/climate-change-indicators-us-and-global-temperature&quot;&gt;warming&lt;/a&gt; over the last several decades. Future temperatures are expected to change further. Climate models project the following key temperature-related changes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;em&gt;Key global projections&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Increases in average global temperatures are expected to be within the range of 0.5°F to 8.6°F by 2100, with a likely increase of at least 2.7°F for all scenarios except the one representing the most aggressive mitigation of greenhouse gas emissions.&lt;a href=&quot;#ref2&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[2]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Except under the most aggressive mitigation scenario studied, global average temperature is expected to warm at least twice as much in the next 100 years as it has during the last 100 years.&lt;a href=&quot;#ref2&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[2]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Ground-level air temperatures are expected to continue to warm more rapidly over land than oceans.&lt;a href=&quot;#ref2&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[2]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Some parts of the world are projected to see larger temperature increases than the global average.&lt;a href=&quot;#ref2&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[2]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;row cols-2&quot;&gt;
	&lt;div class=&quot;col&quot;&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg view-mode-medium caption&quot; style=&quot;width:448px;&quot;&gt;&lt;a
    href=&quot;/sites/production/files/2016-07/scenarioglobaltemp.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;A series of global maps showing different emissions scenarios and different time series: 2011 to 2030; 2046 to 2065; and 2080 to 2099. The maps show increasing temperature with time, and the increases are more extreme for the highest emission scenario.&quot; height=&quot;365&quot; width=&quot;448&quot; class=&quot;media-element file-medium&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/medium/public/2016-07/scenarioglobaltemp.jpg&quot; title=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;figcaption&quot;&gt;Projected changes in global average temperatures under four emissions pathways (rows) for three different time periods (columns). Changes in temperatures are relative to 1986-2005 averages. The pathways come from the IPCC Fifth Assessment Report: RCP2.6 is a very low emissions pathway, RCP4.5 is a medium emissions pathway, RCP6.0 is a medium-high emissions pathway, and RCP8.5 is the high emissions pathway (emissions are assumed to continue increasing throughout the century). Source:&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ipcc.ch/report/ar5/wg1/&quot;&gt;IPCC, 2013&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&amp;#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Click the image to view a larger version.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

	&lt;div class=&quot;col&quot;&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg view-mode-medium caption&quot; style=&quot;width:448px;&quot;&gt;&lt;a
    href=&quot;/sites/production/files/2016-07/scenariotempgraph_0.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Line graph showing temperature change from 1900-2008 and projected temperature change for 2000-2100 under three emissions scenarios. With lower emissions, temperatures are projected to increase about 4°F. Higher emissions will result in 7-8°F increases.&quot; height=&quot;384&quot; width=&quot;448&quot; class=&quot;media-element file-medium&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/medium/public/2016-07/scenariotempgraph_0.jpg&quot; title=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;figcaption&quot;&gt;Observed and projected changes in global average temperature under four emissions pathways. The vertical bars at right show likely ranges in temperature by the end of the century, while the lines show projections averaged across a range of climate models. Changes are relative to the 1986-2005 average. Source:&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ipcc.ch/report/ar5/wg1/&quot;&gt;IPCC, 2013&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&amp;#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;, FAQ 12.1, Figure 1.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Click the image to view a larger version.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;em&gt;Key U.S. projections&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;By 2100, the average U.S. temperature is projected to increase by about 3°F to 12°F, depending on emissions scenario and climate model.&lt;a href=&quot;#ref1&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[1]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;An increase in average temperatures worldwide implies more frequent and intense extreme heat events, or heat waves. The number of days with high temperatures above 90°F is expected to increase throughout the United States, especially toward the end of the century.&lt;a href=&quot;#ref1&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[1]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Climate models project that if global emissions of greenhouse gases continue to grow, summertime temperatures in the United States that ranked among the hottest 5% in 1950-1979 will occur at least 70% of the time by 2035-2064.&lt;a href=&quot;#ref1&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[1]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg center view-mode-medium caption&quot; style=&quot;width:448px;&quot;&gt;&lt;a
    href=&quot;/sites/production/files/2016-07/scenarioustemp-large.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Four maps showing projected US temperatures under two emissions scenarios. Both show mid-century increases of 3°F in the continental US and 5-6°F in northern Alaska. By end of century, lower emissions increase 4-6°F while higher emissions increase 7-10°F.&quot; height=&quot;534&quot; width=&quot;448&quot; class=&quot;center media-element file-medium center&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/medium/public/2016-07/scenarioustemp-large.jpg&quot; title=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;figcaption&quot;&gt;Projected temperature change for mid-century (left) and end-of-century (right) in the United States under higher (top) and lower (bottom) emissions scenarios. The brackets on the thermometers represent the likely range of model projections, though lower or higher outcomes are possible. Source:&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://nca2009.globalchange.gov/&quot;&gt;USGCRP (2009)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;Precipitation&quot; name=&quot;Precipitation&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Future precipitation and storm events&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patterns of precipitation and storm events, including both rain and snowfall are also likely to change. However, some of these changes are &lt;a class=&quot;colorbox-inline&quot; href=&quot;#confidence&quot;&gt;less certain&lt;/a&gt; than the changes associated with temperature. Projections show that future precipitation and storm changes will vary by season and region. Some regions may have less precipitation, some may have more precipitation, and some may have little or no change. The amount of rain falling in heavy precipitation events is likely to increase in most regions, while storm tracks are projected to shift poleward.&lt;a href=&quot;#ref2&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[2]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Climate models project the following precipitation and storm changes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-png center view-mode-full caption&quot; style=&quot;width:928px;&quot;&gt;&lt;a
    href=&quot;/sites/production/files/2016-07/globalprecipmap-large.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Two maps displaying change in average precipitation (1986-2005 to 2081-2100). The high emissions scenario generally shows increases in precipitation.&quot; height=&quot;326&quot; width=&quot;928&quot; class=&quot;center media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2016-07/globalprecipmap-large.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;figcaption&quot;&gt;Projected changes in global annual mean precipitation for a low emissions scenario (left) and high emissions scenario (right). Blue and green areas are projected to experience increases in precipitation by the end of the century, while yellow and brown areas are projected to experience decreases.&lt;br /&gt;
Source:&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ipcc.ch/publications_and_data/ar4/wg1/en/faq-11-1-figure-1.html&quot;&gt;IPCC, 2013&amp;nbsp;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&amp;#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Click the image to view a larger version.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;em&gt;Key global projections&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Global average annual precipitation through the end of the century is expected to increase, although changes in the amount and intensity of precipitation will vary significantly by region.&lt;a href=&quot;#ref2&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[2]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;The intensity of precipitation events will likely increase on average. This will be particularly pronounced in tropical and high-latitude regions, which are also expected to experience overall increases in precipitation.&lt;a href=&quot;#ref2&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[2]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;The strength of the winds associated with tropical storms is likely to increase. The amount of precipitation falling in tropical storms is also likely to increase.&lt;a href=&quot;#ref2&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[2]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Annual average precipitation is projected to increase in some areas and decrease in others. The figure to the right shows projected regional differences in precipitation under two emission scenarios.&lt;a href=&quot;#ref2&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[2]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3&gt;&lt;em&gt;Key U.S. projections&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Northern areas are projected to become wetter, especially in the winter and spring. Southern areas, especially the Southwest, are projected to become drier.&lt;a href=&quot;#ref1&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[1]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Heavy precipitation events will likely be more frequent, even in areas where total precipitation is projected to decrease. Heavy downpours that currently occur about once every 20 years are projected to occur between twice and five times as frequently by 2100, depending on location.&lt;a href=&quot;#ref1&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[1]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;The proportion of precipitation falling as rain rather than snow is expected to increase, except in far northern areas.&lt;a href=&quot;#ref1&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[1]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;The intensity of Atlantic hurricanes is likely to increase as the ocean warms. Climate models project an increase in the number of the strongest (Category 4 and 5) hurricanes, as well as greater rainfall rates in hurricanes.&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#ref1&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/sup&gt;There is less confidence in projections of the frequency of hurricanes.&lt;a href=&quot;#ref1&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[1]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Cold-season storm tracks are expected to continue to shift northward. The strongest cold-season storms are projected to become stronger and more frequent.&lt;a href=&quot;#ref1&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[1]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-png center view-mode-full caption&quot; style=&quot;width:522px;&quot;&gt;&lt;a
    href=&quot;/sites/production/files/2016-07/usprecipmaps-large.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Series of four maps displaying seasonal precipitation change under a higher emissions scenario. Generally, Canada and the northern half of the US see increases of upto 30%, while Mexico and the southern US see decreases of up to 30%.&quot; height=&quot;650&quot; width=&quot;522&quot; class=&quot;center media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2016-07/usprecipmaps-large.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;figcaption&quot;&gt;The maps show projected future changes in precipitation for the end of this century, compared with 1970-1999, under a higher emissions scenario. For example, in winter and spring, climate models agree that northern areas in the United States are likely to get wetter and southern areas drier. There is less confidence in exactly where the transition between wetter and drier areas will occur. Confidence in the projected changes is highest in the areas marked with diagonal lines. The changes in white areas are not projected to be larger than what would be expected from natural variability. Source:&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;http://nca2014.globalchange.gov/&quot;&gt;U.S. National Climate Assessment&lt;/a&gt;, 2014.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Click the image to view a larger version.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;Ice&quot; name=&quot;Ice&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Future ice, snowpack, and permafrost&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arctic sea ice is already declining.&lt;a href=&quot;#ref2&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[2]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; The area of snow cover in the Northern Hemisphere has decreased since about 1970.&lt;a href=&quot;#ref2&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[2]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Permafrost temperatures in Alaska and much of the Arctic &lt;a href=&quot;#ref2&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[2]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; have increased over the last century.&lt;a href=&quot;#ref1&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[1]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; To learn more about recent changes in snow and ice, visit the &lt;a href=&quot;/climate-indicators/snow-ice&quot;&gt;Snow and Ice page&lt;/a&gt; of the Indicators section.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the next century, it is expected that sea ice will continue to decline, glaciers will continue to shrink, snow cover will continue to decrease, and permafrost will continue to thaw. Potential changes to ice, snow, and permafrost are described below.&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg right view-mode-medium caption&quot; style=&quot;width:448px;&quot;&gt;&lt;a
    href=&quot;/sites/production/files/2016-07/seaiceloss.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Series of global maps displaying Arctic and Antarctic sea ice levels in February and September under three time ranges: 1986-2005 avg, 2081-2100 avg based on RCP4.5, and 2081-2100 avg based on RCP8.5. The latter scenario shows greater declines in sea ice.&quot; height=&quot;497&quot; width=&quot;448&quot; class=&quot;right media-element file-medium right&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/medium/public/2016-07/seaiceloss.jpg&quot; title=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;figcaption&quot;&gt;These maps show projected losses of sea ice in the Arctic and Antarctica. The maps in a) show the average ice concentration (the relative area covered by sea ice) from 1986-2005. The maps in b) and c) show climate model simulations of sea ice thickness in February and September near the end of the 21st century under low (b) and high (c) emission scenarios. In the Arctic, February is projected to have less ice (more blue); September is projected to be nearly ice-free (almost all blue). The projected changes in Antarctic sea ice are more subtle. Source:&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ipcc.ch/report/ar5/wg1/&quot;&gt;IPCC&lt;/a&gt;, 2013&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Click the image to view a larger version.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;em&gt;Key global projections&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;For every 2°F of warming, models project about a 15% decrease in the extent of annually averaged Arctic sea ice and a 25% decrease in the area covered by Arctic sea ice at the end of summer (September).&lt;a href=&quot;#ref3&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[3]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Note that this decrease does not contribute to sea level rise.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;The coastal sections of the Greenland and Antarctic ice sheets are expected to continue to melt or slide into the ocean. If the rate of this ice melting increases in the 21st century, the ice sheets could add significantly to global sea level rise.&lt;a href=&quot;#ref3&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[3]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Glaciers are expected to continue to decrease in size. The rate of melting is expected to continue to increase, which will contribute to sea level rise.&lt;a href=&quot;#ref3&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[3]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3&gt;&lt;em&gt;Key U.S. projections&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Northern Hemisphere snow cover is expected to decrease by approximately 15% by 2100.&lt;a href=&quot;#ref3&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[3]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Models project the snow season will continue to shorten, with snow accumulation beginning later and melting starting earlier. Snowpack is expected to decrease in many regions.&lt;a href=&quot;#ref3&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[3]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Permafrost is expected to continue to thaw in northern latitudes, damaging buildings, infrastructure, and ecosystems in &lt;a href=&quot;/climate-impacts/climate-impacts-alaska&quot;&gt;Alaska&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;a href=&quot;#ref3&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[3]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;Sea level&quot; id=&quot;Sea level&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Future sea level change&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg left view-mode-full caption&quot; style=&quot;width:250px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Photograph of river running through glacier.&quot; height=&quot;208&quot; width=&quot;250&quot; class=&quot;left media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2016-07/greenlandmeltwater.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;figcaption&quot;&gt;Meltwater flowing from the Greenland ice sheet Source:&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;http://climate.nasa.gov/evidence/&quot;&gt;NASA&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;Warming temperatures contribute to sea level rise by: expanding ocean water; melting mountain glaciers and ice caps; and causing portions of the Greenland and Antarctic ice sheets to melt or flow into the ocean.&lt;a href=&quot;#ref3&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[3]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since 1870, global sea level has risen by about 7.5 inches.&lt;a href=&quot;#ref2&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[2]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Estimates of future sea level rise vary for different regions, but global sea level for the next century is expected to rise at a greater rate than during the past 50 years.&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#ref2&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/sup&gt;Studies project global sea level to rise by another 1 to 4 feet by 2100, with an uncertainty range of 0.66 to 6.6 feet.&lt;a href=&quot;#ref1&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[1]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The contribution of thermal expansion, ice caps, and small glaciers to sea level rise is relatively well studied, but the impacts of climate change on ice sheets in Greenland and Antarctica are less understood and represent an active area of research. Changes in ice sheets are currently expected to account for 1.2 to 8 inches of sea level rise by the end of this century.&lt;a href=&quot;#ref3&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[3]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg right view-mode-full caption&quot; style=&quot;width:448px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Graph displaying past and projected changes in global sea level. Proxy records from 1800-1875 show -0.5ft; tide gauge data increase from -0.5ft in 1875 to 0.2 in 1980, satellite data show an increase to 0.3ft in 2005, and projections range 1-4ft by 2100.&quot; height=&quot;332&quot; width=&quot;448&quot; class=&quot;right media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2016-09/scenarioslrgraph.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;figcaption&quot;&gt;Past and projected sea level rise from 1800 to 2100. The orange line at right shows the currently projected range of sea level rise of 1 to 4 feet by 2100; the wider range (0.66 feet to 6.6 feet) reflects uncertainty about how glaciers and ice sheets will react to climate change. Source:&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;http://nca2014.globalchange.gov/&quot;&gt;NCA&lt;/a&gt;, 2014.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Click the image to view a larger version.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;Regional and local factors will influence future relative sea level rise for specific coastlines around the world. For example, relative sea level rise depends on land elevation changes that occur as a result of subsidence (sinking) or uplift (rising). Assuming that these historical geological forces continue, a 2-foot rise in global sea level by 2100 would result in the following relative sea level rise:&lt;a href=&quot;#ref4&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[4]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;2.3 feet at New York City&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;2.9 feet at Hampton Roads, Virginia&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;3.5 feet at Galveston, Texas&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;1 foot at Neah Bay in Washington state&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Relative sea level rise also depends on local changes in currents, winds, salinity, and water temperatures, as well as proximity to thinning ice sheets.&lt;a href=&quot;#ref2&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[2]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;Acidification&quot; name=&quot;Acidification&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Future ocean acidification&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ocean acidification adversely affects many marine species, including plankton, mollusks, shellfish, and corals. As ocean acidification increases, the availability of calcium carbonate will decline. Calcium carbonate is a key building block for the shells and skeletons of many marine organisms. If atmospheric CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; concentrations double, coral calcification rates are projected to decline by more than 30%. If CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; concentrations continue to rise at their current rate, the combination of climate warming and ocean acidification could slow coral growth by nearly 50% by 2050.&lt;a href=&quot;#ref5&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[5]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg center view-mode-full caption&quot; style=&quot;width:576px;&quot;&gt;&lt;a
    href=&quot;/sites/production/files/2016-07/calciumcarbonatemap-large_0.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;2 figures: 1st, graph showing declines in surface pH in the Arctic, S.Ocean, &amp;amp; Tropics from 8.1-8.2 in 1900 to 7.5-7.8 under RCP8.5 and 8.0-8.1 under RCP2.6 in 2100 . Then, a map shows change in surface pH in the 2090s. Most of the planet declines 0.3-0.5&quot; height=&quot;550&quot; width=&quot;576&quot; class=&quot;center media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2016-07/calciumcarbonatemap-large_0.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;figcaption&quot;&gt;Oceans become more acidic as carbon dioxide (CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;) emissions in the atmosphere dissolve in the ocean. This change is measured on the pH scale, with lower values being more acidic. The pH level of the oceans has decreased by approximately 0.1 pH units since pre-industrial times, which is equivalent to an approximately 30% increase in&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www3.epa.gov/climatechange/science/indicators/oceans/acidity.html&quot;&gt;acidity&lt;/a&gt;. As shown in the graph and map above, the pH level of the oceans is projected to decrease even more by the end of the century as CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;&amp;nbsp;concentrations are expected to increase for the foreseeable future.&lt;a href=&quot;#ref1&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[1]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#ref2&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/sup&gt;Source:&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ipcc.ch/report/ar5/wg1/&quot;&gt;IPCC&lt;/a&gt;, 2013, Chapter 6.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Click the image to view a larger version.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h3&gt;References&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;ref1&quot; name=&quot;ref1&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;[1] USGCRP (2014) Melillo, Jerry M., Terese (T.C.) Richmond, and Gary W. Yohe, Eds., 2014: &lt;a href=&quot;http://nca2014.globalchange.gov/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Climate Change Impacts in the United States: The Third National Climate Assessment&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. U.S. Global Change Research Program.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;ref2&quot; name=&quot;ref2&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;[2] IPCC (2013). &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ipcc.ch/report/ar5/wg1/&quot;&gt;Climate Change 2013: The Physical Science Basis&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/em&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;.  Contribution of Working Group I to the Fifth Assessment Report of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change [Stocker, T.F., D. Qin, G.-K. Plattner, M. Tignor, S.K. Allen, J. Boschung, A. Nauels, Y. Xia, V. Bex and P.M. Midgley (eds.)]. Cambridge University Press, Cambridge, United Kingdom and New York, NY, USA.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;ref3&quot; name=&quot;ref3&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;[3] NRC (2011). &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://nas-sites.org/americasclimatechoices/other-reports-on-climate-change/2011-2/climate-stabilization-targets/&quot;&gt;Climate Stabilization Targets: Emissions, Concentrations, and Impacts over Decades to Millennia&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/em&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;. National Research Council. The National Academies Press, Washington, DC, USA.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;ref4&quot; name=&quot;ref4&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;[4] USGCRP (2009). &lt;a href=&quot;http://globalchange.gov/what-we-do/assessment/previous-assessments/global-climate-change-impacts-in-the-us-2009&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Global Climate Change Impacts in the United States&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Thomas R. Karl, Jerry M. Melillo, and Thomas C. Peterson (eds.). United States Global Change Research Program. Cambridge University Press, New York, NY, USA.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;ref5&quot; name=&quot;ref5&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;[5] IPCC (2014). &lt;a href=&quot;http://ipcc-wg2.gov/AR5/&quot;&gt;Climate Change 2014: Impacts, Adaptation, and Vulnerability&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;hidden-content&quot;&gt;
	&lt;div class=&quot;colorbox-hidden&quot; id=&quot;confidence&quot;&gt;
		&lt;h3 id=&quot;dialog-title&quot;&gt;Confidence&lt;/h3&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;Scientists have varying degrees of confidence in the assessment and projection of climate change impacts.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Scientists are confident that humans are contributing significantly to observed warming&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;Measurements collected by scientists are sufficiently accurate to describe large-scale changes in climate that have occurred, including changes in temperature over the last century. Although it is difficult to say exactly how much warming was caused by humans, many lines of evidence support the conclusion that human activities have caused most observed warming over at least the last several decades.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Climate models simulate future climate change with varying degrees of confidence&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;Scientists know a great deal about future climate change. For example, there is high confidence that global temperatures will continue to rise and that climate change will significantly affect human and natural systems. However, there are several aspects of climate change that remain more uncertain. These uncertainties stem primarily from (1) uncertainties about future human actions, especially those that affect the sources and sinks of greenhouse gases, and (2) uncertainties about how the climate system will respond to these actions. In turn, a lower degree of confidence in the response of the climate system stems from both the limitations of climate models and the complexity of the climate system.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Confidence varies by geographic scale&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;Global climate models generally provide consistent and reliable simulations of climate variables only at large continental to global scales. This is because the variability of the climate increases at smaller geographic and shorter temporal scales. Additionally, the grid cells of the models are usually more than 60 miles (100 km) wide, which is larger than important features that matter for local climate like mountains and land cover. Global models and regional techniques are starting to provide useful information about climate changes on local to regional scales. While some of these projections are very well understood, others are more speculative. Generally, confidence decreases as one moves from larger scales to smaller scales. Regional climate modeling is an active area of research to improve our ability to project future changes at smaller spatial scales.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Confidence varies by climate variable&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;Scientists are more confident in estimates of some climate variables than others. For example, changes in precipitation are more difficult to project than changes in temperature. To accurately estimate precipitation changes, models must correctly project a number of underlying processes, like evaporation, that occur on relatively small spatial scales. Moreover, precipitation is strongly influenced by mountainous terrain and other local or regional geographic features, which are not always well represented in current models. Despite the complexities, some projections and conclusions, particularly at the continental to global scales, can be made.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 14 Jul 2016 17:04:15 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>tnayem</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">154837 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Causes of Climate Change</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/climate-change-science/causes-climate-change</link>
    <description>&lt;h3&gt;On This Page:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Balancing&quot;&gt;Earth’s temperature is a balancing act&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Greenhouse&quot;&gt;The greenhouse effect causes the atmosphere to retain heat&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Sun&quot;&gt;Changes in the sun’s energy affect how much energy reaches Earth’s system&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Reflectivity&quot;&gt;Changes in reflectivity affect how much energy enters Earth’s system&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;Balancing&quot; name=&quot;Balancing&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Earth&#039;s temperature is a balancing act&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-png right view-mode-medium caption&quot; style=&quot;width:448px;&quot;&gt;&lt;a
    href=&quot;/sites/production/files/2016-07/models-observed-human-natural.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Graph displaying that models accounting solely for natural factors understate current climate trends by ~1 degree F, compared to models that include human factors, which accurately predict observed temperatures.&quot; height=&quot;295&quot; width=&quot;448&quot; class=&quot;right media-element file-medium right&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/medium/public/2016-07/models-observed-human-natural.png&quot; title=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;figcaption&quot;&gt;Models that account only for the effects of natural processes are not able to explain the warming observed over the past century. Models that also account for the greenhouse gases emitted by humans are able to explain this warming.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Click the image to view a larger version.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;Earth&#039;s temperature depends on the balance between energy entering and leaving the planet’s system. When incoming energy from the sun is absorbed by the Earth system, Earth warms. When the sun’s energy is reflected back into space, Earth avoids warming. When absorbed energy is released back into space, Earth cools. Many factors, both natural and human, can cause changes in Earth’s energy balance, including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Variations in &lt;a href=&quot;#Sun&quot;&gt;the sun&#039;s energy&lt;/a&gt; reaching Earth&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Changes in the &lt;a href=&quot;#Reflectivity&quot;&gt;reflectivity&lt;/a&gt; of Earth’s atmosphere and surface&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Changes in the &lt;a href=&quot;#Greenhouse&quot;&gt;greenhouse effect&lt;/a&gt;, which affects the amount of heat retained by Earth’s atmosphere&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;These factors have caused Earth’s climate to change many times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scientists have pieced together a record of Earth’s climate, dating back hundreds of thousands of years (and, in some cases, millions or hundreds of millions of years), by analyzing a number of indirect measures of climate such as ice cores, tree rings, glacier lengths, pollen remains, and ocean sediments, and by studying changes in Earth’s orbit around the sun.&lt;a href=&quot;#ref2&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[2]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This record shows that the climate system varies naturally over a wide range of time scales. In general, climate changes prior to the Industrial Revolution in the 1700s can be explained by natural causes, such as changes in solar energy, volcanic eruptions, and natural changes in greenhouse gas (GHG) concentrations.&lt;a href=&quot;#ref2&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[2]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recent climate changes, however, cannot be explained by natural causes alone. Research indicates that natural causes do not explain most observed warming, especially warming since the mid-20&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; century. Rather, it is extremely likely that human activities have been the dominant cause of that warming.&lt;a href=&quot;#ref2&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[2]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;Greenhouse&quot; name=&quot;Greenhouse&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;box multi related-info right&quot;&gt;
	&lt;h2 class=&quot;pane-title&quot;&gt;Radiative Forcing&lt;/h2&gt;

	&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;Radiative forcing is a measure of the influence of a particular factor (e.g. GHGs, aerosols, or land use changes) on the net change in Earth’s energy balance. On average, a positive radiative forcing tends to warm the surface of the planet, while a negative forcing tends to cool the surface.&lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;p&gt;GHGs have a positive forcing because they absorb energy radiating from Earth’s surface, rather than allowing it to be directly transmitted into space. This warms the atmosphere like a blanket. Aerosols, or small particles, can have a positive or negative radiative forcing, depending on how they absorb and emit heat or reflect light. For example, black carbon aerosols have a positive forcing since they absorb sunlight. Sulfate aerosols have a negative forcing since they reflect sunlight back into space.&lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;p&gt;NOAA’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.esrl.noaa.gov/gmd/aggi/&quot;&gt;Annual GHG Index&lt;/a&gt;, which tracks changes in radiative forcing from GHGs over time, shows that such forcing from human-added GHGs has increased 27.5 percent between 1990 and 2009. Increases in CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; in the atmosphere are responsible for 80% of the increase. The contribution to radiative forcing by CH&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; and CFCs has been nearly constant or declining, respectively, in recent years.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The greenhouse effect causes the atmosphere to retain heat&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When sunlight reaches Earth’s surface, it can either be reflected back into space or absorbed by Earth. Once absorbed, the planet releases some of the energy back into the atmosphere as heat (also called infrared radiation). Greenhouse gases like water vapor (H&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O), carbon dioxide (CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;), and methane (CH&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;) absorb energy, slowing or preventing the loss of heat to space. In this way, GHGs act like a blanket, making Earth warmer than it would otherwise be. This process is commonly known as the “greenhouse effect.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;The role of the greenhouse effect in the past&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the last several hundred thousand years, CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; levels varied in tandem with the glacial cycles. During warm &quot;interglacial&quot; periods, CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; levels were higher. During cool &quot;glacial&quot; periods, CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; levels were lower.&lt;a href=&quot;#ref2&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[2]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; The heating or cooling of Earth’s surface and oceans can cause changes in the natural sources and sinks of these gases, and thus change greenhouse gas concentrations in the atmosphere.&lt;a href=&quot;#ref2&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[2]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; These changing concentrations are thought to have acted as a positive feedback, amplifying the temperature changes caused by long-term shifts in Earth’s orbit.&lt;a href=&quot;#ref2&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[2]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg view-mode-medium caption&quot; style=&quot;width:475px;&quot;&gt;&lt;a
    href=&quot;/sites/production/files/2016-07/co2temp800kyrs-large.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Graph showing correlating increases and decreases in CO2 and temperature over 800,000 years.&quot; title=&quot;Graph showing correlating increases and decreases in CO2 and temperature over 800,000 years.&quot; height=&quot;374&quot; width=&quot;448&quot; class=&quot;media-element file-medium&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/medium/public/2016-07/co2temp800kyrs-large.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;figcaption&quot;&gt;Estimates of the Earth&amp;rsquo;s changing CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; concentration (top) and Antarctic temperature (bottom), based on analysis of ice core data extending back 800,000 years. Until the past century, natural factors caused atmospheric CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; concentrations to vary within a range of about 180 to 300 parts per million by volume (ppmv). Warmer periods coincide with periods of relatively high CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; concentrations. Note: The past century&amp;rsquo;s temperature changes and rapid CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; rise (to 400 ppmv in 2015) are not shown here. Increases over the past half century are shown in the &lt;a href=&quot;/climate-change-science/causes-climate-change#Recent&quot;&gt;Recent Role&lt;/a&gt; section.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Click the image to view a larger version.&lt;br /&gt;
Source: Based on data appearing in &lt;a href=&quot;http://nas-sites.org/americasclimatechoices/sample-page/panel-reports/87-2/&quot;&gt;NRC (2010)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;div class=&quot;box multi related-info&quot;&gt;
	&lt;h2 class=&quot;pane-title&quot;&gt;Feedbacks Can Amplify or Reduce Changes&lt;/h2&gt;

	&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;Climate feedbacks amplify or reduce direct warming and cooling effects. They do not change the planet’s temperature directly. Feedbacks that amplify changes are called positive feedbacks. Feedbacks that counteract changes are called negative feedbacks. Feedbacks are associated with changes in surface reflectivity, clouds, water vapor, and the carbon cycle.&lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;p&gt;Water vapor appears to cause the most important positive feedback. As Earth warms, the rate of evaporation and the ability of air to hold water vapor both rise, increasing the amount of water vapor in the air. Because water vapor is a greenhouse gas, this leads to further warming.&lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;p&gt;The melting of Arctic sea ice is another example of a positive climate feedback. As temperatures rise, sea ice retreats. The loss of ice exposes the underlying sea surface, which is darker and absorbs more sunlight than ice, increasing the total amount of warming.&lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;p&gt;Some types of clouds cause a negative feedback. Warming temperatures can increase the amount or reflectivity of these clouds, reflecting more sunlight back into space, cooling the surface of the planet. Other types of clouds, however, contribute a positive feedback.&lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;p&gt;There are also several positive feedbacks that increase GHG concentrations. For example, as temperatures warm:&lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Natural processes that are affected by warming, such as permafrost thawing, tend to release more CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;li&gt;The ocean releases CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; into the atmosphere and absorbs atmospheric CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; at a slower rate.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;li&gt;Several types of land surfaces may release more methane (CH&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;These changes lead to higher concentrations of atmospheric GHGs and contribute to increased warming.&lt;a id=&quot;Recent&quot; name=&quot;Recent&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg right view-mode-medium caption&quot; style=&quot;width:448px;&quot;&gt;&lt;a
    href=&quot;/sites/production/files/2016-07/ghgconc2000-large.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Graph showing increase in 3 GHGs (CO2, CH4, &amp;amp; N2O). From 0 to ~1800, concentrations of each were in the following ranges: CO2: 280ppm, CH4: 720ppb, N2O: 270ppb. A sharp increase begins in 1900. By 2000, CO2 approaches 400ppm, CH4 2000ppb, and N2O 320ppb.&quot; height=&quot;319&quot; width=&quot;448&quot; class=&quot;right media-element file-medium right&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/medium/public/2016-07/ghgconc2000-large.jpg&quot; title=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;figcaption&quot;&gt;This graph shows the increase in greenhouse gas (GHG) concentrations in the atmosphere over the last 2,000 years. Increases in concentrations of these gases since 1750 are due to human activities in the industrial era. Concentration units are parts per million (ppm) or parts per billion (ppb), indicating the number of molecules of the greenhouse gas per million or billion molecules of air.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Click the image to view a larger version.&lt;br /&gt;
Source:&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;http://nca2014.globalchange.gov/&quot;&gt;U.S. National Climate Assessment (2014)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;The recent role of the greenhouse effect&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the Industrial Revolution began around 1750, human activities have contributed substantially to climate change by adding CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; and other heat-trapping gases to the atmosphere. These &lt;a href=&quot;/ghgemissions&quot;&gt;greenhouse gas emissions&lt;/a&gt; have increased the greenhouse effect and caused Earth’s surface temperature to rise. The primary human activity affecting the amount and rate of climate change is greenhouse gas emissions from the burning of fossil fuels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;The main greenhouse gases&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most important GHGs directly emitted by humans include carbon dioxide (CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;), methane (CH&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;), nitrous oxide (N&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O), and several others. The sources and recent trends of these gases are detailed below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;&lt;em&gt;Carbon dioxide &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Carbon dioxide is the primary greenhouse gas that is contributing to recent climate change. CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; is absorbed and emitted naturally as part of the carbon cycle, through plant and animal respiration, volcanic eruptions, and ocean-atmosphere exchange. Human activities, such as the burning of fossil fuels and changes in land use, release large amounts of CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;, causing concentrations in the atmosphere to rise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Atmospheric CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; concentrations have increased by more than 40% since pre-industrial times, from approximately 280 parts per million by volume (ppmv) in the 18th century to over 400 ppmv in 2015. The monthly average concentration at Mauna Loa now exceeds 400 ppmv for the first time in human history. The current CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; level is higher than it has been in at least 800,000 years.&lt;a href=&quot;#ref2&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[2]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some volcanic eruptions released large quantities of CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; in the distant past. However, the &lt;a href=&quot;http://volcanoes.usgs.gov/hazards/gas/index.php&quot;&gt;U.S. Geological Survey (USGS)&lt;/a&gt; reports that human activities now emit more than 135 times as much CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; as volcanoes each year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Human activities currently release over 30 billion tons of CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; into the atmosphere every year.&lt;a href=&quot;#ref2&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[2]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; The resultant build-up of CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; in the atmosphere is like a tub filling with water, where more water flows from the faucet than the drain can take away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row cols-2&quot;&gt;
	&lt;div class=&quot;col&quot;&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-png center view-mode-medium caption&quot; style=&quot;width:448px;&quot;&gt;&lt;a
    href=&quot;/sites/production/files/2016-07/keelingcurve-large.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Graph showing increasing Atmospheric CO2 at Mauna Loa Observatory from the 1950&amp;#039;s to 2010.&quot; height=&quot;344&quot; width=&quot;448&quot; class=&quot;center media-element file-medium center&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/medium/public/2016-07/keelingcurve-large.png&quot; title=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;figcaption&quot;&gt;Atmospheric carbon dioxide concentration has risen from pre-industrial levels of 280 parts per million by volume (ppmv) to over 401 ppmv in 2016. Since 1959 alone (shown here), concentrations have risen by more than 85 ppmv. The yearly rise and fall in the chart reflects the growth and decay or northern hemisphere vegetation.&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Click the image to view a larger version.&lt;br /&gt;
Source:&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;https://scripps.ucsd.edu/programs/keelingcurve/&quot;&gt;NOAA&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

	&lt;div class=&quot;col&quot;&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg center view-mode-medium caption&quot; style=&quot;width:411px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Image showing a bathtub. Sources of carbon are the faucet, while sinks of carbon are the drain.&quot; height=&quot;294&quot; width=&quot;411&quot; class=&quot;center media-element file-medium center&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/medium/public/2016-07/carbonbathtub.jpg&quot; title=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;figcaption&quot;&gt;If the amount of water flowing into a bathrub is greater than the amount of water leaving through the drain, the water level will rise. CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;&amp;nbsp;emissions are like the flow of water into the world&amp;#39;s carbon bathtub. &amp;quot;Sources&amp;quot; of CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; emissions such as fossil fuel burning, cement manufacture, and land use are like the bathtub&amp;#39;s faucet. &amp;quot;Sinks&amp;quot; of CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; in the ocean and on land (such as plants) that take up CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; are like the drain. Today, human activities have turned up the flow from the CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; &amp;quot;faucet,&amp;quot; which is much larger than the &amp;quot;drain&amp;quot; can cope with, and the level of CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; in the atmosphere (like the level of water in a bathtub) is rising.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information on the human and natural sources and sinks of CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; emissions, and actions that can reduce emissions, see the &lt;a href=&quot;/ghgemissions/overview-greenhouse-gases#carbon-dioxide&quot;&gt;Carbon Dioxide page&lt;/a&gt; in the &lt;a href=&quot;/ghgemissions&quot;&gt;Greenhouse Gas Emissions&lt;/a&gt; website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;&lt;em&gt;Methane &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Methane is produced through both natural and human activities. For example, natural wetlands, agricultural activities, and fossil fuel extraction and transport all emit CH&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Methane is more abundant in Earth’s atmosphere now than at any time in at least the past 800,000 years.&lt;a href=&quot;#ref2&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[2]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Due to human activities, CH&lt;sub&gt;4 &lt;/sub&gt;concentrations increased sharply during most of the 20th century and are now more than two-and-a-half times pre-industrial levels. In recent decades, the rate of increase has slowed considerably.&lt;a href=&quot;#ref2&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[2]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information on CH&lt;sub&gt;4&lt;/sub&gt; emissions and sources, and actions that can reduce emissions, see EPA’s &lt;a href=&quot;/ghgemissions/overview-greenhouse-gases#methane&quot;&gt;Methane page&lt;/a&gt; in the &lt;a href=&quot;/ghgemissions&quot;&gt;Greenhouse Gas Emissions&lt;/a&gt; website. For information on how methane is impacting the Arctic, see the EPA report &lt;a href=&quot;/climate-change-science/methane-and-black-carbon-impacts-arctic-communicating-science&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Methane and Black Carbon Impacts on the Arctic&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nitrous oxide &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nitrous oxide is produced through natural and human activities, mainly through agricultural activities and natural biological processes. Fuel burning and some other processes also create N&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O. Concentrations of N&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O have risen approximately 20% since the start of the Industrial Revolution, with a relatively rapid increase toward the end of the 20th century.&lt;a href=&quot;#ref2&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[2]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, N&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O concentrations have increased more rapidly during the past century than at any time in the past 22,000 years.&lt;a href=&quot;#ref2&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[2]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; For more information on N&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;O emissions and sources, and actions that can reduce emissions, see EPA’s &lt;a href=&quot;/ghgemissions/overview-greenhouse-gases#nitrous-oxide&quot;&gt;Nitrous Oxide page&lt;/a&gt; in the &lt;a href=&quot;/ghgemissions&quot;&gt;Greenhouse Gas Emissions&lt;/a&gt; website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Other greenhouse gases&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;roomy&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;Water vapor is the most abundant greenhouse gas and also the most important in terms of its contribution to the natural greenhouse effect, despite having a short atmospheric lifetime. Some human activities can influence local water vapor levels. However, on a global scale, the concentration of water vapor is controlled by temperature, which influences overall rates of evaporation and precipitation.&lt;a href=&quot;#ref2&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[2]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Therefore, the global concentration of water vapor is not substantially affected by direct human emissions.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Tropospheric &lt;a href=&quot;/ozone&quot;&gt;ozone (O&lt;sub&gt;3&lt;/sub&gt;)&lt;/a&gt;, which also has a short atmospheric lifetime, is a potent greenhouse gas. Chemical reactions create ozone from emissions of nitrogen oxides and volatile organic compounds from automobiles, power plants, and other industrial and commercial sources in the presence of sunlight. In addition to trapping heat, ground-level ozone is a pollutant that can cause respiratory health problems and damage crops and ecosystems.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Chlorofluorocarbons (CFCs), hydrochlorofluorocarbons (HCFCs), hydrofluorocarbons (HFCs), perfluorocarbons (PFCs), and sulfur hexafluoride (SF&lt;sub&gt;6&lt;/sub&gt;), together called &lt;a href=&quot;/ghgemissions/overview-greenhouse-gases#f-gases&quot;&gt;F-gases&lt;/a&gt;, are often used in coolants, foaming agents, fire extinguishers, solvents, pesticides, and aerosol propellants. Unlike water vapor and ozone, these F-gases have a long atmospheric lifetime, and some of these emissions will affect the climate for many decades or centuries.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;For more information on greenhouse gas emissions, see the &lt;a href=&quot;/ghgemissions&quot;&gt;Greenhouse Gas Emissions&lt;/a&gt; website, including an expanded discussion of &lt;a href=&quot;/ghgemissions/understanding-global-warming-potentials&quot;&gt;global warming potentials&lt;/a&gt; and how they are used to measure the relative strengths of greenhouse gases. To learn more about actions that can reduce these emissions, see &lt;a href=&quot;/climatechange/what-you-can-do-about-climate-change&quot;&gt;What You Can Do&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Other climate forcers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Particles and aerosols in the atmosphere can also affect climate. Human activities such as burning fossil fuels and biomass contribute to emissions of these substances, although some aerosols also come from natural sources such as volcanoes and marine plankton.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;roomy&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/blackcarbon&quot;&gt;Black carbon (BC)&lt;/a&gt; is a solid particle or aerosol, not a gas, but it also contributes to warming of the atmosphere. Unlike GHGs, BC can directly absorb incoming and reflected sunlight in addition to absorbing infrared radiation. BC can also be deposited on snow and ice, darkening the surface and thereby increasing the snow&#039;s absorption of sunlight and accelerating melt. For information on how BC is impacting the Arctic, see EPA assessment &lt;a href=&quot;/climate-change-science/methane-and-black-carbon-impacts-arctic-communicating-science&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Methane and Black Carbon Impacts on the Arctic&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Sulfates, organic carbon, and other aerosols can cause cooling by reflecting sunlight.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Warming and cooling aerosols can interact with clouds, changing a number of cloud attributes such as their formation, dissipation, reflectivity, and precipitation rates. Clouds can contribute both to cooling, by reflecting sunlight, and warming, by trapping outgoing heat.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;For more information on greenhouse gas emissions, see the &lt;a href=&quot;/ghgemissions&quot;&gt;Greenhouse Gas Emissions&lt;/a&gt; website. To learn more about actions that can reduce these emissions, see &lt;a href=&quot;/climatechange/what-epa-doing-about-climate-change&quot;&gt;What EPA is Doing&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;/climatechange/what-you-can-do-about-climate-change&quot;&gt;What You Can Do&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;a id=&quot;Sun&quot; name=&quot;Sun&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Changes in the sun’s energy affect how much energy reaches Earth’s system&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-png right view-mode-medium caption&quot; style=&quot;width:448px;&quot;&gt;&lt;a
    href=&quot;/sites/production/files/2016-07/sunsenergytemp-large.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Graph comparing solar irradiance and difference in global surface temperature. Solar irradiance has been regularly cycling, while global surface temperatures have been steadily increasing.&quot; height=&quot;501&quot; width=&quot;448&quot; class=&quot;right media-element file-medium right&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/medium/public/2016-07/sunsenergytemp-large.png&quot; title=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;figcaption&quot;&gt;The sun&amp;rsquo;s energy received at the top of Earth&amp;rsquo;s atmosphere has been measured by satellites since 1978. It has followed its natural 11-year cycle of small ups and downs, but with no net increase (bottom). Over the same period, global temperature has risen markedly (top).&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Click the image to view a larger version.&lt;br /&gt;
Source:&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;http://downloads.globalchange.gov/usimpacts/pdfs/climate-impacts-report.pdf&quot;&gt;USGCRP (2009)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;Climate is influenced by natural changes that affect how much solar energy reaches Earth. These changes include changes within the sun and changes in Earth’s orbit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Changes occurring in the sun itself can affect the intensity of the sunlight that reaches Earth’s surface. The intensity of the sunlight can cause either warming (during periods of stronger solar intensity) or cooling (during periods of weaker solar intensity). The sun follows a natural 11-year cycle of small ups and downs in intensity, but the effect on Earth’s climate is small.&lt;a href=&quot;#ref1&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[1]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Changes in the shape of Earth’s orbit as well as the tilt and position of Earth’s axis can also affect the amount of sunlight reaching Earth’s surface.&lt;a href=&quot;#ref1&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[1]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#ref2&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[2]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;The role of the sun’s energy in the past&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Changes in the sun’s intensity have influenced Earth’s climate in the past. For example, the so-called “Little Ice Age” between the 17th and 19th centuries may have been partially caused by a low solar activity phase from 1645 to 1715, which coincided with cooler temperatures. The “Little Ice Age” refers to a slight cooling of North America, Europe, and probably other areas around the globe.&lt;a href=&quot;#ref2&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[2]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Changes in Earth’s orbit have had a big impact on climate over tens to hundreds of thousands of years. In fact, the amount of summer sunshine on the Northern Hemisphere, which is affected by changes in the planet’s orbit, appears to drive the advance and retreat of ice sheets. These changes appear to be the primary cause of past &lt;a class=&quot;colorbox-inline&quot; href=&quot;#cycle&quot;&gt;cycles&lt;/a&gt; of ice ages, in which Earth has experienced long periods of cold temperatures (ice ages), as well as shorter interglacial periods (periods between ice ages) of relatively warmer temperatures.&lt;a href=&quot;#ref1&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[1]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#ref2&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[2]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;box multi highlight right&quot;&gt;
	&lt;h2 class=&quot;pane-title&quot;&gt;Rates of Climate Change Have Varied Over Time&lt;/h2&gt;

	&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;colorbox-inline&quot; href=&quot;#cycle&quot;&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg center view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:350px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Image of a glacier calving. Click to learn about how rates of climate change have varied over time.&quot; height=&quot;234&quot; width=&quot;350&quot; class=&quot;center media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2016-07/glacier.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;Click to learn&lt;/a&gt; about how rates of climate change have varied over time.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;The recent role of the sun’s energy&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Changes in solar energy continue to affect climate. However, over the last 11-year solar cycle, solar output has been lower than it has been since the mid-20&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; century, and therefore does not explain the recent warming of the earth.&lt;a href=&quot;#ref2&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[2]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Similarly, changes in the shape of Earth’s orbit as well as the tilt and position of Earth’s axis affect temperature on very long timescales (tens to hundreds of thousands of years), and therefore cannot explain the recent warming.&lt;a id=&quot;Reflectivity&quot; name=&quot;Reflectivity&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Changes in reflectivity affect how much energy enters Earth’s system&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When sunlight reaches Earth, it can be reflected or absorbed. The amount that is reflected or absorbed depends on Earth’s surface and atmosphere. Light-colored objects and surfaces, like snow and clouds, tend to reflect most sunlight, while darker objects and surfaces, like the ocean, forests, or soil, tend to absorb more sunlight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The term albedo refers to the amount of solar radiation reflected from an object or surface, often expressed as a percentage. Earth as a whole has an albedo of about 30%, meaning that 70% of the sunlight that reaches the planet is absorbed.&lt;a href=&quot;#ref3&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[3]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Absorbed sunlight warms Earth’s land, water, and atmosphere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reflectivity is also affected by aerosols. Aerosols are small particles or liquid droplets in the atmosphere that can absorb or reflect sunlight. Unlike greenhouse gases, the climate effects of aerosols vary depending on what they are made of and where they are emitted. Those aerosols that reflect sunlight, such as particles from volcanic eruptions or sulfur emissions from burning coal, have a cooling effect. Those that absorb sunlight, such as black carbon (a part of soot), have a warming effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;The role of reflectivity in the past&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Natural changes in reflectivity, like the melting of sea ice, have contributed to climate change in the past, often acting as feedbacks to other processes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Volcanoes have played a noticeable role in climate. Volcanic particles that reach the upper atmosphere can reflect enough sunlight back to space to cool the surface of the planet by a few tenths of a degree for several years.&lt;a href=&quot;#ref2&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[2]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; These particles are an example of cooling aerosols. Volcanic particles from a single eruption do not produce long-term change because they remain in the atmosphere for a much shorter time than GHGs.&lt;a href=&quot;#ref2&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[2]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;The recent role of reflectivity&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Human changes in land use and land cover have changed Earth’s reflectivity. Processes such as deforestation, reforestation, desertification, and urbanization often contribute to changes in climate in the places they occur. These effects may be significant regionally, but are smaller when averaged over the entire globe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, human activities have generally increased the number of aerosol particles in the atmosphere. Overall, human-generated aerosols have a net cooling effect offsetting about one-third of the total warming effect associated with human greenhouse gas emissions. Reductions in overall aerosol emissions can therefore lead to more warming. However, targeted reductions in black carbon emissions can reduce warming.&lt;a href=&quot;#ref1&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[1]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h3&gt;References:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;ref1&quot; name=&quot;ref1&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;[1] USGCRP (2014). &lt;a href=&quot;http://nca2014.globalchange.gov/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Climate Change Impacts in the United States: The Third National Climate Assessment&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. [Melillo, Jerry M., Terese (T.C.) Richmond, and Gary W. Yohe, Eds.] U.S. Global Change Research Program.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;ref2&quot; name=&quot;ref2&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;[2] IPCC (2013). &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ipcc.ch/report/ar5/wg1/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Climate Change 2013: The Physical Science Basis&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Contribution of Working Group I to the Fifth Assessment Report of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change&lt;/em&gt; [Stocker, T.F., D. Qin, G.-K. Plattner, M. Tignor, S.K. Allen, J. Boschung, A. Nauels, Y. Xia, V. Bex and P.M. Midgley (eds.)]. Cambridge University Press, Cambridge, United Kingdom and New York, NY, USA.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;ref3&quot; name=&quot;ref3&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;[3] NRC (2010). &lt;a href=&quot;http://nas-sites.org/americasclimatechoices/sample-page/panel-reports/87-2/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Advancing the Science of Climate Changes&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/a&gt;. National Research Council. The National Academies Press, Washington, DC, USA.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;hidden-content&quot;&gt;
	&lt;div class=&quot;colorbox-hidden&quot; id=&quot;cycle&quot;&gt;
		&lt;h3 id=&quot;dialog-title&quot;&gt;Rates of climate change have varied over time&lt;/h3&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;Studies of Earth’s past climate suggest periods of relative stability as well as periods of rapid change.&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Periods of relative stability &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
			Interglacial climate periods such as the present tend to be more stable than cooler, glacial climates. For example, Earth’s climate during the current interglacial period is more stable than the most recent glacial period. The glacial period was characterized by widespread, large, and abrupt climate changes. In contrast, the previous interglacial period was similarly stable.&lt;a href=&quot;#ref1&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[1]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;div&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg center view-mode-full caption&quot; style=&quot;width:350px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Image of a glacier calving.&quot; height=&quot;234&quot; width=&quot;350&quot; class=&quot;center media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2016-07/glacier_0.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;figcaption&quot;&gt;This image shows a glacier calving, when a mass of ice suddenly releases and breaks away. Source:&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fs.usda.gov/wps/portal/fsinternet/!ut/p/c4/04_SB8K8xLLM9MSSzPy8xBz9CP0os3gDfxMDT8MwRydLA1cj72BTQxNjAwjQL8h2VAQA9Dlhuw!!/?ttype=photogallery&amp;amp;pnavid=null&amp;amp;counter=null.0&amp;amp;actid=&amp;amp;recid=&amp;amp;ss=111004&amp;amp;cid=2787&amp;amp;navid=100000000000000&amp;amp;navtype=BROWSEBYSUBJECT&amp;amp;pname=Forest%20Service%20-%20Childs%20Glacier%20calving%20an%20iceberg&quot;&gt;USDA&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Periods of abrupt climate change &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
			Abrupt climate change refers to sudden (on the order of decades), large changes in some major component of the climate system, with rapid, widespread effects. Abrupt or rapid climate changes tend to frequently accompany transitions between glacial and interglacial periods (and vice versa).&lt;a href=&quot;#ref2&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[2]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; For example, a significant part of the Northern Hemisphere, particularly around Greenland, may have experienced very rapid warming of 14°F-28°F over several decades during and after the most recent ice age.&lt;a href=&quot;#ref2&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[2]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;Abrupt climate changes occur when a threshold or ‘tipping point’ in the climate system is crossed, causing large changes or impacts to the climate. Scientific data show that abrupt changes in climate at the regional scale have occurred throughout history and are characteristic of Earth’s climate system. Warming from greenhouse gas emissions, as well as other human changes to the Earth system may increase the possibility of large and abrupt regional or global climatic events.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 13 Jul 2016 18:46:07 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>tnayem</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">154765 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Overview of Climate Change Science</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/climate-change-science/overview-climate-change-science</link>
    <description>&lt;h3&gt;On This Page:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Overview&quot;&gt;Overview&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Climate change&quot;&gt;Earth&#039;s climate is changing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Natural causes&quot;&gt;Natural causes alone cannot explain recent changes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Human causes&quot;&gt;Human causes can explain these changes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Emissions&quot;&gt;The extent of future climate change depends on us&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Impacts&quot;&gt;Climate change impacts our health, environment, and economy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;Overview&quot; name=&quot;Overview&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Overview&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earth&#039;s climate is changing. Multiple lines of evidence show changes in our weather, oceans, ecosystems, and more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Natural &lt;a href=&quot;/climate-change-science/causes-climate-change&quot;&gt;causes&lt;/a&gt; alone cannot explain all of these changes. Human activities are contributing to climate change, primarily by releasing billions of tons of carbon dioxide (CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;) and other heat-trapping gases, known as greenhouse gases, into the atmosphere every year.&lt;a href=&quot;#ref1&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[1]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Climate changes will continue into the &lt;a href=&quot;/climate-change-science/future-climate-change&quot;&gt;future&lt;/a&gt;. The more greenhouse gases we emit, the larger future climate changes will be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;box multi&quot;&gt;
	&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
		&lt;div class=&quot;row cols-3&quot;&gt;
			&lt;div class=&quot;col&quot;&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg center view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:235px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Photo of cars on a highway&quot; height=&quot;225&quot; width=&quot;235&quot; class=&quot;center media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2016-06/cars-on-highway.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

			&lt;div class=&quot;col&quot;&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg center view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:235px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Photograph of clear-cut forest with standing trees in the distance.&quot; height=&quot;225&quot; width=&quot;235&quot; class=&quot;center media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2016-06/deforestation.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

			&lt;div class=&quot;col&quot;&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg center view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:235px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Photograph of smokestacks and power lines.&quot; height=&quot;225&quot; width=&quot;235&quot; class=&quot;center media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2016-06/3_us-ghg.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;Human activities, like driving, manufacturing, electricity generation, and the clearing of forests contribute to greenhouse gas emissions and warm the planet.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Changes in the climate system affect our health, environment, and economy. We can prepare for some of the &lt;a href=&quot;/climate-impacts&quot;&gt;impacts&lt;/a&gt; of climate change to reduce their effects on our well-being.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;Climate change&quot; id=&quot;Climate change&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Earth&#039;s climate is changing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;box multi related-info right&quot;&gt;
	&lt;h2 class=&quot;pane-title&quot;&gt;Related Links&lt;/h2&gt;

	&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;USGCRP: &lt;a href=&quot;http://nca2014.globalchange.gov/&quot;&gt;National Climate Assessment, 2014&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;USGCRP: &lt;a href=&quot;http://globalchange.gov/publications/reports/scientific-assessments/us-impacts/full-report&quot;&gt;Global Climate Change Impacts in the United States&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;NRC: &lt;a href=&quot;http://nas-sites.org/americasclimatechoices/sample-page/panel-reports/&quot;&gt;America&#039;s Climate Choices Reports&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;IPCC: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ipcc.ch/publications_and_data/publications_and_data_reports.shtml&quot;&gt;Fifth Assessment Report&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;IPCC: &lt;a href=&quot;http://ipcc.ch/pdf/special-reports/srex/SREX_FD_SPM_final.pdf&quot;&gt;Managing the Risks of Extreme Events and Disasters to Advance Climate Change Adaptation&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The global average temperature has increased by more than 1.5°F since the late 1800s.&lt;a href=&quot;#ref2&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[2]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Some regions of the world have warmed by more than twice this amount. The buildup of greenhouse gases in our atmosphere and the warming of the planet are responsible for other changes, such as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Changing &lt;a href=&quot;/climate-indicators/weather-climate&quot;&gt;temperature and precipitation patterns&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#ref1&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[1]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#ref2&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[2]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Increases in &lt;a href=&quot;/climate-indicators/oceans&quot;&gt;ocean temperatures, sea level, and acidity&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Melting of &lt;a href=&quot;/climate-indicators/snow-ice&quot;&gt;glaciers and sea ice&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#ref1&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[1]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Changes in the frequency, intensity, and duration of &lt;a href=&quot;/climate-change-science/understanding-link-between-climate-change-and-extreme-weather&quot;&gt;extreme weather events&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Shifts in &lt;a href=&quot;/climate-indicators/ecosystems&quot;&gt;ecosystem characteristics&lt;/a&gt;, like the length of the growing season, timing of flower blooms, and migration of birds&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Increasing effects on &lt;a href=&quot;/climate-indicators/health-society&quot;&gt;human health and well-being&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Learn more about the &lt;a href=&quot;/climate-indicators&quot;&gt;indicators of climate change&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg center view-mode-full caption&quot; style=&quot;width:928px;&quot;&gt;&lt;a
    href=&quot;/sites/production/files/2016-07/globaltempmaps-large.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Temperatures across the world in the 1880s (left) and the 1980s (right).&quot; height=&quot;258&quot; width=&quot;928&quot; class=&quot;center media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2016-07/globaltempmaps-large.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;figcaption&quot;&gt;These maps show temperatures across the world in the 1880s (left) and the 1980s (right). Blue colors represent cooler temperatures compared with the average temperatures from 1951 to 1980, and red colors represent warmer temperatures compared to this average. The map on the left shows that it was colder in the 1880s in most places. The map on the right shows it was warmer in the 1980s in most places. Earth&amp;#39;s average surface temperature has increased by more than 1.5&amp;deg;F since the 1880s. Two-thirds of the warming has occurred since 1975, at a rate of roughly 0.3&amp;deg;F &lt;span&gt;&amp;ndash;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;0.4&amp;deg;F per decade.&amp;nbsp;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

Click the image to view a larger version.&amp;nbsp;Source:&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;http://climate.nasa.gov/vital-signs/global-temperature/&quot;&gt;NASA&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;row cols-2&quot;&gt;
	&lt;div class=&quot;col&quot;&gt;
		&lt;div class=&quot;box multi highlight&quot;&gt;
			&lt;h2 class=&quot;pane-title&quot;&gt;Climate Change v. Global Warming&lt;/h2&gt;

			&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
				&lt;div&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;colorbox-inline&quot; href=&quot;#colorbox-hidden&quot;&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg center view-mode-medium&quot; style=&quot;width:448px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Photo of a city skyline on hot day&quot; title=&quot;City skyline on hot day&quot; height=&quot;299&quot; width=&quot;448&quot; class=&quot;center media-element file-medium center&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/medium/public/2016-08/climate_v_global_warming.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

				&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;Click on the image for a pop-up on the difference between climate change and global warming.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;

	&lt;div class=&quot;col&quot;&gt;
		&lt;div class=&quot;box multi highlight&quot;&gt;
			&lt;h2 class=&quot;pane-title&quot;&gt;Weather v. Climate&lt;/h2&gt;

			&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
				&lt;div&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;colorbox-inline&quot; href=&quot;#colorbox-hidden2&quot;&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg center view-mode-medium&quot; style=&quot;width:448px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Photo of rain falling in puddle&quot; title=&quot;Rain falling in puddle&quot; height=&quot;299&quot; width=&quot;448&quot; class=&quot;center media-element file-medium center&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/medium/public/2016-08/weather_v_climate.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

				&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;Click on the image to open a pop-up that explains the differences between weather and climate.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;Natural causes&quot; id=&quot;Natural causes&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Natural causes alone cannot explain recent changes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Natural processes such as changes in the sun&#039;s energy, shifts in ocean currents, and others affect Earth&#039;s climate. However, they do not explain the warming that we have observed over the last half-century.&lt;a href=&quot;#ref1&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[1]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;Human causes&quot; id=&quot;Human causes&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Human causes can explain these changes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-png right view-mode-medium caption&quot; style=&quot;width:448px;&quot;&gt;&lt;a
    href=&quot;/sites/production/files/2016-07/models-observed-human-natural.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Graph displaying that models accounting solely for natural factors understate current climate trends by ~1 degree F, compared to models that include human factors, which accurately predict observed temperatures.&quot; height=&quot;295&quot; width=&quot;448&quot; class=&quot;right media-element file-medium right&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/medium/public/2016-07/models-observed-human-natural.png&quot; title=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;figcaption&quot;&gt;Models that account only for the effects of natural processes are not able to explain the warming observed over the past century. Models that also account for the greenhouse gases emitted by humans are able to explain this warming.&lt;br /&gt;
	Source:&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;http://nca2014.globalchange.gov/&quot;&gt;U.S. National Climate Assessment (2014)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

Click the image to view a larger version.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;Most of the warming of the past half century has been caused by human emissions of &lt;a href=&quot;/ghgemissions&quot;&gt;greenhouse gases&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;a href=&quot;#ref1&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[1]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Greenhouse gases come from a variety of human activities, including: burning fossil fuels for heat and energy, clearing forests, fertilizing crops, storing waste in landfills, raising livestock, and producing some kinds of industrial products.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Greenhouse gas emissions are not the only way that people can change the climate. Activities such as agriculture or road construction can change the reflectivity of Earth&#039;s surface, leading to local warming or cooling. This effect is observed in urban centers, which are often &lt;a href=&quot;/heat-islands&quot;&gt;warmer&lt;/a&gt; than surrounding, less populated areas. Emissions of small particles, known as aerosols, into the air can also lead to reflection or absorption of the sun&#039;s energy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/climate-change-science/causes-climate-change&quot;&gt;Learn more&lt;/a&gt; about past and present climate trends and their causes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg right view-mode-medium caption&quot; style=&quot;width:448px;&quot;&gt;&lt;a
    href=&quot;/sites/production/files/2016-07/ghgconc2000-large.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Graph showing increase in 3 GHGs (CO2, CH4, &amp;amp; N2O). From 0 to ~1800, concentrations of each were in the following ranges: CO2: 280ppm, CH4: 720ppb, N2O: 270ppb. A sharp increase begins in 1900. By 2000, CO2 approaches 400ppm, CH4 2000ppb, and N2O 320ppb.&quot; height=&quot;319&quot; width=&quot;448&quot; class=&quot;right media-element file-medium right&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/medium/public/2016-07/ghgconc2000-large.jpg&quot; title=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;figcaption&quot;&gt;This graph shows the increase in greenhouse gas (GHG) concentrations in the atmosphere over the last 2,000 years. Increases in concentrations of these gases since 1750 are due to human activities in the industrial era. Concentration units are parts per million (ppm) or parts per billion (ppb), indicating the number of molecules of the greenhouse gas per million or billion molecules of air.&lt;br /&gt;
	Source:&amp;nbsp;&lt;a href=&quot;http://downloads.globalchange.gov/usimpacts/pdfs/climate-impacts-report.pdf&quot;&gt;USGCRP 2009&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

Click the image to view a larger version.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;Emissions&quot; name=&quot;Emissions&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The extent of future climate change depends on us&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The extent of the change will depend on how much, and how quickly, we can reduce greenhouse gas emissions. During the 21&lt;sup&gt;st&lt;/sup&gt; century, global warming is projected to continue and climate changes are likely to intensify. Scientists have used climate models to project different aspects of future climate, including temperature, precipitation, snow and ice, ocean level, and ocean acidity. Depending on future emissions of greenhouse gases and how the climate responds, average global temperatures are projected to increase worldwide by 0.5°F to 8.6°F by 2100, with a likely increase of at least 2.0°F for all scenarios except the one representing the most aggressive mitigation of greenhouse gas emissions.&lt;a href=&quot;#ref2&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[2]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;/climate-change-science/future-climate-change&quot;&gt;Learn more&lt;/a&gt; about the projections of future climate change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;Impacts&quot; name=&quot;Impacts&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Climate change impacts our health, environment, and economy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Climate change affects our environment and natural resources, and impacts our way of life in many ways. For example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Warmer temperatures increase the frequency, intensity, and duration of heat waves, which can pose &lt;a href=&quot;/climate-impacts/climate-impacts-human-health&quot;&gt;health risks&lt;/a&gt;, particularly for young children and the elderly.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Climate change can also impact human health by worsening air and water quality, increasing the spread of certain diseases, and altering the frequency or intensity of extreme weather events.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Rising sea levels threaten &lt;a href=&quot;/climate-impacts/climate-impacts-coastal-areas&quot;&gt;coastal communities&lt;/a&gt; and ecosystems.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Changes in the patterns and amount of rainfall, as well as changes in the timing and amount of stream flow, can affect &lt;a href=&quot;/climate-impacts/climate-impacts-water-resources&quot;&gt;water supplies and water quality&lt;/a&gt; and the production of &lt;a href=&quot;/climate-impacts/climate-impacts-energy&quot;&gt;hydroelectricity&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/climate-impacts/climate-impacts-ecosystems&quot;&gt;Changing ecosystems&lt;/a&gt; influence geographic ranges of many plant and animal species and the timing of their lifecycle events, such as migration and reproduction.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Increases in the frequency and intensity of extreme weather events, such as heat waves, droughts, and floods, can increase losses to property, cause costly disruptions to &lt;a href=&quot;/climate-impacts/climate-impacts-society&quot;&gt;society&lt;/a&gt;, and reduce the availability and affordability of insurance.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;We can prepare for some of the likely climate change impacts to reduce their effect on ecosystems and human well-being. Making such preparations is known as adaptation. Examples of adaptation include strengthening water conservation programs, upgrading stormwater systems, developing early warning systems for extreme heat events, and preparing for stronger storms through better emergency preparation and response strategies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Learn more about how &lt;a href=&quot;/climate-impacts&quot;&gt;climate change impacts&lt;/a&gt; are expected to affect different U.S. &lt;a href=&quot;/climate-impacts/climate-change-impacts-region&quot;&gt;regions&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;/climate-impacts/climate-change-impacts-sector&quot;&gt;sectors&lt;/a&gt; and how we can prepare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h3&gt;References&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;ref1&quot; name=&quot;ref1&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;1. USGCRP (2014). Melillo, Jerry M., Terese (T.C.) Richmond, and Gary W. Yohe, Eds. &lt;a href=&quot;http://nca2014.globalchange.gov/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Climate Change Impacts in the United States: The Third National Climate Assessment&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt; U.S. Global Change Research Program.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;ref2&quot; name=&quot;ref2&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;2. IPCC (2013). &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ipcc.ch/report/ar5/wg1/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Climate Change 2013: The Physical Science Basis&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/small&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;em&gt;Contribution of Working Groups I, II and III to the Fourth Fifth Assessment Report of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change&lt;/em&gt; [Stocker, T.F., D. Qin, G.-K. Plattner, M. Tignor, S.K. Allen, J. Boschung, A. Nauels, Y. Xia, V. Bex and P.M. Midgley (eds.)]. Cambridge University Press, Cambridge, United Kingdom and New York, NY, USA.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;hidden-content&quot;&gt;
	&lt;div class=&quot;colorbox-hidden&quot; id=&quot;colorbox-hidden&quot;&gt;
		&lt;h3 id=&quot;dialog-title&quot;&gt;Climate Change vs. Global Warming&lt;/h3&gt;

		&lt;div&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;The term &lt;strong&gt;climate change&lt;/strong&gt; is sometimes used interchangeably with the term &lt;strong&gt;global warming&lt;/strong&gt;. However, the terms do not refer entirely to the same thing.&lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Global warming&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; refers to the recent and ongoing rise in global average temperature near Earth&#039;s surface. It is caused mostly by increasing concentrations of greenhouse gases in the atmosphere. Global warming is causing climate patterns to change. However, global warming itself represents only one aspect of climate change.&lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Climate change&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; refers to any significant change in the measures of climate lasting for an extended period of time. In other words, climate change includes major changes in temperature, precipitation, or wind patterns, among others, that occur over several decades or longer. Climate change can occur at the global, continental, regional, and local levels. Climate change may refer to natural changes in climate, or changes caused by human activities.&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;hidden-content2&quot;&gt;
	&lt;div class=&quot;colorbox-hidden&quot; id=&quot;colorbox-hidden2&quot;&gt;
		&lt;h3 id=&quot;dialog-title&quot;&gt;Weather vs. Climate&lt;/h3&gt;

		&lt;div&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;The difference between weather and climate is primarily a matter of time and geography. Weather refers to the conditions of the atmosphere over a short period of time, such as hours or days, and typically for a local area. Climate refers to the behavior of the atmosphere over a longer period of time, and usually for a large area.&lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;p&gt;Familiar examples of weather characteristics include the daily temperature, humidity, or the amount of precipitation produced by a storm. Weather also includes severe weather conditions such as hurricanes, tornadoes, and blizzards. Because of the dynamic nature of the atmosphere, it is not possible to predict weather conditions in a specific location months or years in advance.&lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;p&gt;Climate is typically defined based on 30-year averages of weather. Climate represents our expectations for the weather. For example, climate tells us how warm we expect a typical summer to be, how much rainfall would correspond to a wetter-than-average spring, or how frequently we expect a snowy winter to occur. Scientists can compare recent and long-term observations of the climate to detect the influence of greenhouse gases on climate conditions.&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jun 2016 19:40:50 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>tnayem</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">152481 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Contact Us About  Climate Change Science</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/climate-change-science/forms/contact-us-about-climate-change-science</link>
    <description>&lt;div class=&quot;box right&quot;&gt;
	&lt;div class=&quot;slat-image&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/enforcement/report-environmental-violations&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Report an environmental violation&quot; src=&quot;/sites/all/themes/epa/img/badge.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

	&lt;div class=&quot;slat-content&quot;&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/enforcement/report-environmental-violations&quot;&gt;Report a Violation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;Report possible violations of environmental laws and regulations.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please use the form below to send us comments or questions. Be sure to include your e-mail address if you’d like a response.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mailing Address:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	OAR/OAP/CCD&lt;br /&gt;
	U.S. Environmental Protection Agency&lt;br /&gt;
	1200 Pennsylvania Ave NW&lt;br /&gt;
	Mail Code 6202A&lt;br /&gt;
	Washington, DC 20460&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Mon, 01 Feb 2016 20:18:21 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>tnayem</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">133727 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  </channel>
</rss>

<!-- Page cached by Boost @ 2017-01-25 05:03:33, expires @ 2017-01-25 17:03:33, lifetime 12 hours -->