<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?><rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.epa.gov/feed/803/rss.xml" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/" xmlns:og="http://ogp.me/ns#" xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#" xmlns:sioc="http://rdfs.org/sioc/ns#" xmlns:sioct="http://rdfs.org/sioc/types#" xmlns:skos="http://www.w3.org/2004/02/skos/core#" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#">
  <channel>
    <title>Border 2020</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/feed/803/rss.xml</link>
    <description>Updated Border 2020 content from the US Environmental Protection Agency</description>
    <language>en</language>
     <atom:link href="https://www.epa.gov/feed/803/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      <item>
    <title>Border 2020 Environmental Education Taskforce (Feb 2017)</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/border2020/border-2020-environmental-education-taskforce-feb-2017</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Border 2020 Environmental Education Taskforce Public Meeting (El Paso-Cuidad Juá&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;rez-Dona Ana)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;em&gt;Texas-New Mexico-Chihuahua Regional Workgroup&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Date: &lt;/strong&gt;February 1st, 2017&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Time:&lt;/strong&gt; 4 to 6:30 pm&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Place:&lt;/strong&gt; Holiday Inn- Downtown El Paso&lt;br /&gt;
	409 E. Missouri Ave., El Paso, Texas&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Free admission&lt;br /&gt;
	Simultaneous translation available&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AGENDA:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1)    Welcome &lt;br /&gt;
	2)    Issues in Paso del Norte region&lt;br /&gt;
	•    Resilience &amp;amp; Sustainability Efforts in the area &lt;br /&gt;
	•    Results of 2nd Environmental Conference, COLECH &lt;br /&gt;
	•    El Paso Resilience Program - “Our Common Home Public Forum”&lt;br /&gt;
	•    Action Plan 2015-2016 Outcomes &lt;br /&gt;
	3)    Public Comments for future actions&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Frontera 2020 Grupo de Trabajo de Educación Ambiental Junta Pública (El Paso-Ciudad Juárez-Dona Ana)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;em&gt;Grupo Regional de Trabajo Texas-New Mexico-Chihuahua&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fecha: 1º de febrero, 2017&lt;br /&gt;
	Hora: 4 a 6:30 pm&lt;br /&gt;
	Lugar: Holiday Inn Hotel- Centro de El Paso&lt;br /&gt;
	409 E. Missouri Ave., El Paso, Texas &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Admisión gratuita&lt;br /&gt;
	Traducción simultánea disponible&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AGENDA&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1)    Bienvenida&lt;br /&gt;
	2)    Asuntos en la región Paso del Norte&lt;br /&gt;
	•    Programas de Resiliencia y Sustentabilidad en esta área&lt;br /&gt;
	•    Resultados de 2ª Conferencia Ambiental-COLECH&lt;br /&gt;
	•    Oficina de Resiliencia de El Paso - “Foro Público Nuestra Casa Común”&lt;br /&gt;
	•    Resultados del Plan de Acción 2015-2016 &lt;br /&gt;
	3)    Comentarios del público para acciones futuras&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-348353&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2017-01/documents/env_educ_tf_agenda_feb_1_use.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=515959&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Env Education &amp;amp; Health Feb 2017 Agenda (English &amp;amp; Spanish) (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(1 pg, 516 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jan 2017 19:54:58 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>msisnero</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">169849 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Joint Advisory Committee (JAC): 68th Meeting </title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/border2020/joint-advisory-committee-jac-68th-meeting</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Joint Advisory Committee (JAC) for the Improvement of Air Quality in the&lt;br /&gt;
	Ciudad Juárez, Chihuahua / El Paso, Texas / Doña Ana County, New México Air Basin&lt;br /&gt;
	68th Ordinary Meeting&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Day:Thursday, January 19, 2017&lt;br /&gt;
	Time: 11:00 AM—3:00 PM&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Location: &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	Texas Commission on Environmental Quality&lt;br /&gt;
	401 E. Franklin Avenue&lt;br /&gt;
	Conference Room 570&lt;br /&gt;
	El Paso, Texas, 79901&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Alternative Location:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	Ciudad Juárez City Hall &lt;br /&gt;
	Avenida Francisco Villa # 950 NTE. &lt;br /&gt;
	Third Floor, Zona Centro, C.P. 32000 &lt;br /&gt;
	Ciudad Juárez, Chihuahua &lt;/p&gt;



&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-346263&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2017-01/documents/68th_jac_agenda_bilingual_final_011217.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=212756&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;JAC January 2017 Agenda (English &amp;amp; Spanish) (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(2 pp, 213 K, 
  January 2017)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Fri, 13 Jan 2017 22:51:55 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>msisnero</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">169155 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Situación de la Región Fronteriza 2016 Reporte Intermedio (Diciembre 2016)</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/border2020/situacion-de-la-region-fronteriza-2016-reporte-intermedio-diciembre-2016</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/border2020/state-border-region-2016-interim-report-december-2016&quot;&gt;&lt;span lang=&quot;ES-MX&quot; xml:lang=&quot;ES-MX&quot;&gt;Versión Ingles&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;highlighted&quot;&gt;GENERALIDADES DEL REPORTE:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;El reporte sobre la Situación de la Región Fronteriza 2010 brinda información sobre la situación y las tendencias de la calidad ambiental y la salud ambiental en la región fronteriza de México y los Estados Unidos. Describe los avances logrados en el Programa Ambiental México-Estados Unidos: Frontera 2020.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	Esta obra se ha construido con base en el reporte de la Situación de la Región Fronteriza 2005 y su edición 2010. En ella se actualizan los indicadores clave reportados en 2010 y se agregan nuevos indicadores que reflejan los nuevos enfoques y actividades del Programa 2020. Al igual que en los reportes previos, éste se ha estructurado considerando los objetivos del Programa Frontera 2020, incluyendo capítulos sobre aire, agua, suelo, preparación y respuesta a emergencias ambientales y aplicación y cumplimiento de la ley.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	Los indicadores se presentan con información breve sobre la fuente de los datos. Los datos originales completos, así como los detalles de las fuentes para los indicadores están disponibles en el documento complementario Situación de la Región Fronteriza 2016 Reporte Intermedio: Metadatos y tablas de datos de los Indicadores.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Frontera 2020&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	Frontera 2020 es un programa de cooperación de ocho años entre los Estados Unidos y México. Fue iniciado en el 2013 como sucesor del Programa Frontera 2012. La Misión de Frontera 2020 es “proteger la salud pública y ambiental en la región fronteriza México-Estados Unidos, en congruencia con los principios del desarrollo sustentable.” A través del programa Frontera 2020, los organismos e instituciones federales, estatales, tribales y locales trabajan de manera conjunta para generar acciones prioritarias y sostenidas que consideran las necesidades de las comunidades fronterizas. Las acciones implementadas bajo el programa Frontera 2020 se rigen por una serie de objetivos y metas orientados a resultados. Los objetivos y metas del programa Frontera 2020 fueron actualizados al final del periodo del Programa 2012 para reflejar las nuevas necesidades y oportunidades en la región.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	El programa Frontera 2020 es la iniciativa de cooperación bilateral más reciente implementada bajo el Acuerdo de La Paz de 1983. Este programa parte de los esfuerzos realizados previamente, en particular, el programa Frontera XXI, que representó el primer esfuerzo binacional para desarrollar indicadores ambientales para la región fronteriza.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;&lt;caption&gt;Frontera 2020: Objectivos&lt;/caption&gt;
	&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;1: Reducir la contaminación del aire.&lt;br /&gt;
				2: Mejorar el acceso a agua limpia y segura.&lt;br /&gt;
				3: Promover el manejo integral de materiales y sitios limpios.&lt;br /&gt;
				4: Mejorar la preparación conjunta de respuesta ambiental.&lt;br /&gt;
				5: Fortalecer el cumplimiento de la ley y la promoción de una gestión ambiental.&lt;br /&gt;
				Cada objetivo del Programa Frontera 2020 está acompañado por objetivos específicos y sub-objetivos relacionados con problemáticas ambientales particulares de la región fronteriza.&lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;¿Cómo se desarrollaron los indicadores del reporte?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	El punto de partida para los indicadores incluidos en este reporte fue el reporte de la Situación de la Región Fronteriza 2010. Un principio guía clave considerado desde el reporte 2010 fue que los indicadores deberían ser tan relevantes como fuera posible para poder trabajar en alcanzar los objetivos y las metas del Programa Frontera 2020. Los grupos de trabajo de Frontera 2020 identificaron cuáles indicadores serían los más importantes para actualizar para el reporte de 2016 y cuáles indicadores deberían ser añadidos. A su vez, dichos grupos también aportaron nuevos datos. Como en el caso del Reporte 2010, el proceso de desarrollo de los indicadores se enfocó en identificar datos binacionales comparables y específicos para la región fronteriza (definida como una franja de 100 kilómetros al norte y al sur de la frontera internacional). En muchos casos, las fuentes de datos y las políticas fueron lo suficientemente diferentes entre los Estados Unidos y México para ameritar que se reportaran indicadores diferentes pero relacionados para ambos países. Cuando éstos existían, a menudo se reportaron a nivel municipal o de condado, o aun a nivel de los estados fronterizos de Estados Unidos y México, por lo que se requirió agregar los datos o interpretarlos para describir la región fronteriza.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;¿Qué indicadores se incluyen y cómo se describen?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	El primer capítulo del reporte se enfoca en información general acerca de la región fronteriza. Brinda el contexto para muchos de los retos ambientales y de salud pública en la región. Los cinco capítulos que le siguen presentan indicadores relacionados con objetivos y metas específicos del programa Frontera 2020.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	La gráfica de la siguiente página ilustra la manera en la que los indicadores se presentan en el reporte. Cada indicador está acompañado de una referencia al tipo de indicador (por ejemplo, presión, necesidad, producto o resultado como se describe en el recuadro de arriba en esta página). Para cada indicador, el reporte incluye una tabla o gráfica que complementa al texto. El reporte identifica la meta y sub-meta más relevante del programa Frontera 2020 para cada grupo de indicadores. Además, la descripción de cada indicador aborda las preguntas:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;¿Por qué es importante el indicador?&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;¿Qué muestra el indicador?&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;¿Qué factores afectan a este indicador y qué puede hacerse en el futuro?&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;¿Qué consideraciones técnicas son importantes para comprender este indicador y sus limitaciones?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Esperamos que este reporte resulte informativo y útil, e invite a brindar comentarios sobre futuros indicadores para medir la calidad y salud ambientales en la región fronteriza.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;&lt;caption&gt;Tipos de indicadores&lt;/caption&gt;
	&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;Presión: describen las actividades humanas que imponen estrés sobre el ambiente.&lt;br /&gt;
				Necesidad: comunican nuestra comprensión de la magnitud o tipo de necesidad de una respuesta programática.&lt;br /&gt;
				Producto: miden actividades, productos o servicios resultantes de un proyecto o programa.&lt;br /&gt;
				Resultado: miden los cambios en la situación del ambiente o los efectos de condiciones ambientales sobre la salud humana y/o ecológica.&lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-345221&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2017-01/documents/situacion_de_la_region_fronteriza_2016_122216.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=2838603&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Situacion de la region fronteriza 2016 (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(44 pp, 3 MB, 
  December 2016)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-345223&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2017-01/documents/situacion_de_la_region_fronteriza_2016_metadatos_01102017.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=1084567&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;situacion de la region fronteriza 2016 metadatos y tablas (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(22 pp, 1 MB, 
  December 2016)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jan 2017 22:58:58 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>msisnero</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">168845 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>State of the Border Region 2016- Interim Report (December 2016)</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/border2020/state-border-region-2016-interim-report-december-2016</link>
    <description>&lt;p class=&quot;highlighted&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/border2020/situacion-de-la-region-fronteriza-2016-reporte-intermedio-diciembre-2016&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Version Español&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 class=&quot;highlighted&quot;&gt;Report Overview:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The State of the Border Region 2016 Interim Report provides information on the status and trends of environmental quality in the U.S.-Mexico border region. In doing so, it also illustrates progress made under the U.S.-Mexico Border 2020 program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This report builds on the flagship 2005 State of the Border Region report and the 2010 State of the Border Region report. It refreshes and updates key indicators from 2010 and adds new indicators to reflect new areas of Border 2020 focus and activity. As with previous reports, this report is structured around the goals of Border 2020 with chapters on air, water, land, environmental readiness and response, and enforcement and compliance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indicators are presented with brief data source information below each indicator. Complete underlying data and details on indicator data sources are available in a companion document, State of the Border Region 2016 Interim Update: Indicator Metadata and Data Tables.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Border 2020&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	Border 2020 is an eight-year cooperative program between the United States and Mexico. It was initiated in 2013 as a successor to Border 2012. Border 2020’s mission is to “protect the environment and public health in the U.S.-Mexico border region, consistent with the principles of sustainable development.” Through Border 2020, federal, state, tribal, and local institutions and agencies collaboratively work to produce prioritized and sustained actions that consider the needs of border communities. The actions implemented under Border 2020 are guided by a series of results-oriented goals and objectives. Border 2020&#039;s goals and objectives were updated at the end of the Border 2012 period to reflect new needs and opportunities in the region.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Border 2020 is the latest cooperative initiative implemented under the 1983 La Paz Agreement. It builds on the previous efforts, particularly Border XXI, which marked the first binational effort to develop environmental indicators for the border region.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;&lt;caption&gt;Border 2020 Goals&lt;/caption&gt;
	&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;Goal 1: Reduce Air Pollution&lt;br /&gt;
					Goal 2: Improve Access to Clean and Safe Water&lt;br /&gt;
					Goal 3: Promote Materials Management, Waste Management, and Clean Sites&lt;br /&gt;
					Goal 4: Enhance Joint Preparedness for Environmental Response&lt;br /&gt;
					Goal 5: Enhance Compliance Assurance and Environmental Stewardship&lt;br /&gt;
					Each of the Border 2020 goals is accompanied by specific objectives and sub-objectives related to specific border environment issues.&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How Were Indicators Developed for This Report?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	The starting point for indicators included in this report was the 2010 State of the Border Region report. A key guiding principle carried forward from the 2010 report is that indicators should be as relevant as possible to the work of achieving Border 2020 goals and objectives. Border 2020 working groups identified which indicators were most important to update for 2016 and what new indicators should be introduced. Working groups also provided new annual data. In some cases, they updated data originally reported in 2010 where data sources improved or were more complete. As with the 2010 report, the indicator development process focused on identifying comparable binational data specific to the border region (defined as 100 kilometers north and south of the international border). In many cases, data sources and policies differed enough between the U.S. and Mexico that separate but related indicators needed to be reported for both countries. Data specific to the border region were not always available. If they were available, they often were reported at the municipal or county-level or even at the level of U.S. and Mexico border states, requiring data aggregation or interpretation in order to describe the border region.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What Indicators Are Included and How Are They Described?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	The first chapter of the report focuses on general information about the border region. It provides the context for many of the current environmental and health challenges in the region. The five chapters that follow present indicators related to specific Border 2020 program goals and objectives.&lt;br /&gt;
	The graphic on the next page illustrates how indicators are presented in the report. Indicators are grouped according to questions. Each indicator is accompanied by a reference to the indicator type (i.e., pressure, need, output, or outcome as described in the call-out box on this page). For each indicator, the report includes a chart or table to accompany the indicator text. The report identifies the most relevant Border 2020 objective or sub-objective for each group of indicators. Additionally, each indicator description addresses the questions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Why is this indicator important?&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;What is this indicator showing?&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;What influences this indicator and what can be done in the future?&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;What technical considerations are important for understanding this indicator and its limitations?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;We hope that you find this report informative and useful, and we invite your feedback on future indicators to help measure environmental quality and environmental health in the border region.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;&lt;caption&gt;Types of Indicators&lt;/caption&gt;
	&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;Pressure: Indicators that describe human activities that place stresses on the environment.&lt;br /&gt;
				Need: Indicators that inform our understanding of the magnitude or type of need for a programmatic response.&lt;br /&gt;
				Output: Indicators that measure activities, products, or services resulting from a project or program.&lt;br /&gt;
				Outcome: Indicators that measure changes in the state of the environment or the effects of environmental conditions on human and/or ecological health.&lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-345217&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2017-01/documents/state_of_the_border_region_2016_122216.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=2933676&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;State of the Border Region 2016 Interim Report (December 2016) (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(41 pp, 3 MB, 
  December 2016)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-345219&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2017-01/documents/state_of_the_border_region_2016_metadata_01062017.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=965588&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;State of the Border Region 2016 Metadata and Data Tables (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(22 pp, 966 K, 
  December 2016)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jan 2017 22:45:45 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>msisnero</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">168843 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>U.S. EPA - BHC Collaborative Agreement Accomplishments Report (2015-2016)</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/border2020/us-epa-bhc-collaborative-agreement-accomplishments-report-2015-2016</link>
    <description>&lt;h3 class=&quot;highlighted&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	This report summarizes the efforts completed under a 2015-2016 collaborative agreement between the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency (U.S. EPA), U.S.-Mexico Border 2020 Program and the U.S. Section of the U.S.-Mexico Border Health Commission (BHC), U.S. Department of Health and Human Services. The work accomplished under this agreement from September 2015 to September 2016 include the following highlights:&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Providing medical information and advice on environmental conditions that influence children’s health along the border through the Pediatric Environmental Health Speciality Units.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt; Conducting 6 promotores training courses over the past year in 6 cities along the Border covering a range of topics including asthma, pesticides, lead, water, and climate change. Two Children’s Environmental Health Symposia addressed vector-borne disease including Rocky Mountain spotted fever and Zika.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Leveraging binational expertise through active support and participation of EPA’s Task Forces in meetings, sharing and reporting out on meeting discussion with stakeholders.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Compiling environmental health data in a 2015-2016 report for the Arizona-Sonora border region.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-345197&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2017-01/documents/final_epa-bhc_accomplishments_report_jan_2017.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=662203&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;EPA-BHC Accomplishment Report (2015-2016) (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(8 pp, 662 K, 
  January 2017)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;field field-name-field-document-description field-type-text field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    EPA-BHC Accomplishment Report (2015-2016)  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jan 2017 22:15:20 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>msisnero</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">168839 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Reporte de Logros (Otoño 2016) Programa Frontera 2020</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/border2020/reporte-de-logros-otono-2016-programa-frontera-2020</link>
    <description>&lt;p class=&quot;highlighted&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/border2020/border-2020-highlights-report-autumn-2016&quot;&gt;&lt;span lang=&quot;ES-MX&quot; xml:lang=&quot;ES-MX&quot;&gt;Versión Ingles&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 class=&quot;highlighted&quot;&gt;MENSAJE DE LOS COORDINADORES NACIONALES&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;El Programa Frontera 2020 ha consolidado una fuerte alianza entre nuestras naciones y refuerza, hoy más que nunca, el mensaje de que la cooperación es la mejor forma de alcanzar soluciones inte-grales a los retos ambientales y de salud pública que enfrentamos en la actualidad a nivel local, re-gional y global. El modelo de cooperación impulsado en el marco de este Programa ha sido y es fundamental para asegurar que las comunidades fronterizas se desarrollen de manera sustentable y en armonía con el medio ambiente.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	Durante las casi tres décadas de colaboración entre nuestros países, hemos alcanzado beneficios que han permitido mejorar la calidad de vida de las comunidades en ambos lados de la frontera, así como la conservación de nuestro medio ambiente común. Por ejemplo, hemos colaborado con la Sección Estadounidense de la Comisión de Salud Fronteriza en la identificación y atención conjun-ta de las prioridades ambientales y de salud pública de la región fronteriza. Hemos trabajado en alianza para mejorar la salud infantil y promover la educación sobre salud ambiental atendiendo a las poblaciones más vulnerables.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	El presente informe contiene algunos de los principales logros y esfuerzos de los últimos dos años. Nos complace informar que durante estos dos años de trabajos, se han concluido 35 proyectos que permiten mejorar las condiciones que enfrentan las comunidades fronterizas y otros 11 se encuen-tran en fase de implementación. Estos proyectos atendieron retos relacionados con agua potable, calidad del aire, manejo apropiado de residuos sólidos, respuesta a emergencias ambientales y ges-tión ambiental.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	Ahora que nos encontramos a la mitad del periodo de implementación del Programa, nosotros, como Coordinadores Nacionales, refrendamos nuestro apoyo a los socios colaboradores de Go-bierno en todos sus niveles, incluyendo a los pueblos indígenas mexicanos y a los gobiernos tribales en los estados fronterizos de Estados Unidos. Agradecemos el apoyo y compromiso de todas las personas, comunidades, organizaciones e instituciones involucradas en las numerosas actividades del Programa y cuya participación es fundamental para mejorar las condiciones ambientales y de salud pública de la región fronteriza. Reconocemos y celebramos su entrega y compromiso; el es-fuerzo de cada una de las personas involucradas en este Programa es esencial para el cumplimiento exitoso de sus ambiciosas metas y objetivos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	Los invitamos a hacer un balance de nuestros recientes logros y a renovar, junto con nosotros, nuestra dedicación y compromiso a la búsqueda de soluciones binacionales integrales a los retos ambientales y de salud pública que persisten en la región fronteriza. Trabajando juntos podemos administrar de manera eficaz y eficiente nuestros recursos compartidos para atender estos retos .&lt;br /&gt;
	Muchas gracias!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	               Enrique Lendo                                                                     Jane Nishida&lt;br /&gt;
	               Coordinadora Nacional                                                   Coordinadora Nacional&lt;br /&gt;
	               México                                                                                     Estados Unidos de América&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-345111&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2017-01/documents/reporte_resultados_f2020_2016_hq.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=11113077&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Reporte de Logros del Programa Frontera 2020 (atono 2016) (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(30 pp, 11 MB, 
  Autumn 2016)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;field field-name-field-document-description field-type-text field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    2016 Accomplishment Report  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jan 2017 21:19:05 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>msisnero</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">168823 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Border 2020 Highlights Report (Autumn 2016)</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/border2020/border-2020-highlights-report-autumn-2016</link>
    <description>&lt;p class=&quot;highlighted&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/border2020/reporte-de-logros-otono-2016-programa-frontera-2020&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Version Españ&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ol&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 class=&quot;highlighted&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;MESSAGE FROM THE NATIONAL COORDINATORS:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Border 2020 Program has established a strong alliance between our two countries and re-inforces, more than ever, the message that cooperation is the best way to achieve integral solu-tions to environmental and public health challenges that we face today at the local, regional and global levels. The cooperation model promoted in the framework of this Program has been, and is fundamental to ensuring that border communities are developed sustainably and in har-mony with the environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	During nearly three decades of collaboration between our two countries, we have achieved benefits that improve the quality of life of communities on both sides of the border, and the preservation of our common environment. For example, we have collaborated with the Border Health Commission to identify and address joint environmental and public health priorities and concerns in the border region. We have worked together to improve children’s health and pro-mote environmental health education and outreach to vulnerable populations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	This report contains some highlights of the achievements and efforts of the Border 2020 Pro-gram during the last two years. We are pleased that during the last two years of work, thirty-five projects have been concluded to improve conditions facing border communities and eleven are in the implementation phase. These projects have addressed challenges of clean water, air quali-ty, proper management of solid waste, environmental emergency response and environmental stewardship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	Now that we are halfway through the implementation period of the Program, we, as National Coordinators, reiterate our support to partners from government at all levels, including tribal governments in the border states of the United States and the Mexican indigenous communi-ties. We also appreciate the support and commitment of all individuals, communities, organiza-tions and institutions involved in the many activities of the Program and whose participation is critical to improve environmental and public health conditions in the border region. We recog-nize and celebrate all these efforts; the dedication and commitment of every person involved in this Program has been essential to the successful completion of its ambitious goals and objec-tives.&lt;br /&gt;
	We invite you to take stock of our recent achievements and renew, with us, your continued support and commitment for comprehensive binational solutions to address the public health and environ-mental challenges that persist in the border region. Working together we can manage our shared resources effectively and efficiently to meet these challenges.&lt;br /&gt;
	Thank you very much!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;highlighted&quot;&gt;                Jane Nishida                                                                            Enrique Lendo&lt;br /&gt;
	                National Coordinator                                                           National Coordinator&lt;br /&gt;
	                United States of America                                                    México&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-345053&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2017-01/documents/b2020_highlights_report_2016_hq.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=11012222&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Border 2020 Highlights Report (Autumn 2016) (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(30 pp, 11 MB, 
  Autumn 2016)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;field field-name-field-document-description field-type-text field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    Border 2020 Highlights Report (Autumn 2016)  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jan 2017 20:50:34 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>msisnero</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">168813 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Gulf Task Force Meeting (December 2016)</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/border2020/gulf-task-force-meeting-december-2016</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;As part of the U.S.-Mexico Border 2020 Program, and on behalf of the Co-leaders of the Gulf Task Force and federal and state partners in the United States and Mexico, you are cordially invited to a meeting of the task force on &lt;strong&gt;Friday, December 9, 2016.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Event:&lt;/strong&gt;   Meeting of the Gulf Task Force &lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Date:&lt;/strong&gt;   Friday, December 9, 2016&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Location:&lt;/strong&gt; City of Harlingen- City Hall&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Address:&lt;/strong&gt;   118 E Tyler Ave, Harlingen, TX 78550&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Time:&lt;/strong&gt;        1:30 pm-5:00 pm&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Map Link&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/maps/place/118+E+Tyler+Ave,+Harlingen,+TX+78550/@26.1892892,-97.6970584,17z/data=!3m1!4b1!4m5!3m4!1s0x866f8221d00df3cf:0x6b5d7ab92ac955f1!8m2!3d26.1892892!4d-97.6948697&quot;&gt;https://www.google.com/maps/place/118+E+Tyler+Ave,+Harlingen,+TX+78550/@26.1892892,-97.6970584,17z/data=!3m1!4b1!4m5!3m4!1s0x866f8221d00df3cf:0x6b5d7ab92ac955f1!8m2!3d26.1892892!4d-97.6948697&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The objectives of the meeting are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Discuss new environmental priorities and projects&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Share information on projects funded by the Border 2020 Program&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Work in the two year (2017- 2018) action plan&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;To learn more about the Border 2020 Four-State Regional Workgroup: &lt;a href=&quot;/border2020&quot;&gt;http://www2.epa.gov/border2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Como parte del Programa Ambiental Frontera 2020 de los Estados Unidos y México, a nombre de los Co-líderes del Equipo de Trabajo Golfo así como los representantes a nivel federal y estatal en los Estados Unidos y México, se les invita cordialmente a asistir a la reunión del equipo de trabajo que se va a realizar el proximo &lt;strong&gt;viernes de 9 diciembre del 2016.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Evento:&lt;/strong&gt; Reunión del Equipo de Trabajo Golfo&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fecha:&lt;/strong&gt;  Viernes 9 de diciembre del 2016&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sitio:  &lt;/strong&gt;City of Harlingen- City Hall (Presidencia Municipal de la Ciudad de Harlingen)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ubicacion:&lt;/strong&gt; 118 E Tyler Ave, Harlingen, TX 78550&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hora:&lt;/strong&gt; 1:30 pm – 5:00 pm&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mapa:&lt;/strong&gt;   &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/maps/place/118+E+Tyler+Ave,+Harlingen,+TX+78550/@26.1892892,-97.6970584,17z/data=!3m1!4b1!4m5!3m4!1s0x866f8221d00df3cf:0x6b5d7ab92ac955f1!8m2!3d26.1892892!4d-97.6948697&quot;&gt;https://www.google.com/maps/place/118+E+Tyler+Ave,+Harlingen,+TX+78550/@26.1892892,-97.6970584,17z/data=!3m1!4b1!4m5!3m4!1s0x866f8221d00df3cf:0x6b5d7ab92ac955f1!8m2!3d26.1892892!4d-97.6948697&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Los objetivos de la reunión son:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Hablar sobre las nuevas prioridades y proyectos ambientales&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Compartir informacion sobre los proyectos subsidiados por el Programa Frontera 2020&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Trabajar en el nuevo plan de trabajo de dos años (2017-2018)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Para aprendar mas sobre el Grupo Regional de los Cuatro Estados del Programa Frontera 2020: &lt;a href=&quot;/border2020&quot;&gt;http://www2.epa.gov/border2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-336005&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-12/documents/agenda_b2020_gulf_tf_meeting_english_and_spanish_120916.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=132477&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Agenda Gulf Task Force December 2016 (English &amp;amp; Spanish) (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(2 pp, 132 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 01 Dec 2016 21:48:08 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>msisnero</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">166265 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Falcon Task Force Meeting (December 2016)</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/border2020/falcon-task-force-meeting-december-2016</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;The Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) and the Texas Commission on Environmental Quality would like to cordially invite you to a meeting of the Border 2020 &lt;strong&gt;Falcon Task Force on Wednesday, December 7, 2016 in Laredo, Texas&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Event:&lt;/strong&gt;  Meeting of the Falcon Task Force &lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Date:&lt;/strong&gt;   Wednesday, December 7, 2016&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Location:&lt;/strong&gt; City of Laredo Public Works Service Center&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Address:&lt;/strong&gt; 5512 Thomas Avenue, Laredo, TX 78041&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Time:&lt;/strong&gt;      1:30 pm-5:00 pm&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The objectives of the meeting are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Discuss new environmental priorities and projects&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Share information on projects funded by the Border 2020 Program&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Work on the two year (2017- 2018) action plan.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;You can also join us through the web conferencing service &lt;em&gt;Go to Meeting&lt;/em&gt;. Here are the instructions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;JOIN the Meeting via Go to Meeting:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;Please join my meeting from your computer, tablet or smartphone.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://global.gotomeeting.com/join/577337197&quot;&gt;https://global.gotomeeting.com/join/577337197&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li value=&quot;2&quot;&gt;Join the conference call.&lt;br /&gt;
		U.S. Phone Number:  (915)257-8916   Code 7064&lt;br /&gt;
		Mexican Phone Number:  01 (656 )688-4607   Code 7064    &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;First GoToMeeting? Try a test session: &lt;a href=&quot;http://help.citrix.com/getready&quot;&gt;http://help.citrix.com/getready&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To learn more about the Border 2020 Four-State Regional Workgroup please visit: &lt;a href=&quot;/border2020&quot;&gt;http://www2.epa.gov/border2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;p&gt;La Agencia de Protección al Medio Ambiente (EPA) y la Comisión de Calidad Ambiental de Texas (TCEQ) les invita cordialmente a asistir a la reunión Frontera 2020 del Equipo de Trabajo Falcón que se va a realizar el miércoles 7 de diciembre del 2016 en Laredo, TX.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Evento:&lt;/strong&gt; Reunión del Equipo de Trabajo Falcón&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fecha:&lt;/strong&gt;  miércoles 7 de diciembre del 2016&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sitio:  &lt;/strong&gt;Laredo Public Works Service Center&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ubicacion:&lt;/strong&gt; 5512 Thomas Avenue, Laredo, TX 78041&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hora:&lt;/strong&gt; 1:30 pm – 5:00 pm&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Los objetivos de la reunión son:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Dialogar sobre las nuevas prioridades y proyectos ambientales&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Compartir informacion sobre los proyectos subsidiados por el Programa Frontera 2020&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Trabajar en el nuevo plan de trabajo de dos años (2017-2018)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;Favor de unirse a mi reunión desde tu computadora, tablet o telefóno móvil por&lt;strong&gt; GO to Meeting&lt;/strong&gt; .&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://global.gotomeeting.com/join/577337197&quot;&gt;https://global.gotomeeting.com/join/577337197&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li value=&quot;2&quot;&gt;Unirse a la conferencia telefónica.&lt;br /&gt;
		Línea Americana  (915)257-8916   Clave NIP 7064&lt;br /&gt;
		Línea Mexicana   01 (656 )688-4607   Clave NIP 7064     &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pare aprendar mas sobre el Grupo Regional de los Cuatro Estados del Programa Frontera 2020: &lt;a href=&quot;/border2020&quot;&gt;http://www2.epa.gov/border2020&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-336003&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-12/documents/draft_agenda_b2020_falcon_tf_meeting_120716.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=67929&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Agenda Falcon TF December 7 2016 (English &amp;amp; Spanish) (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(2 pp, 68 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 01 Dec 2016 21:41:01 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>msisnero</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">166263 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  </channel>
</rss>

<!-- Page cached by Boost @ 2017-01-26 05:27:17, expires @ 2017-01-26 17:27:17, lifetime 12 hours -->