<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?><rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.epa.gov/feed/41895/rss.xml" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/" xmlns:og="http://ogp.me/ns#" xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#" xmlns:sioc="http://rdfs.org/sioc/ns#" xmlns:sioct="http://rdfs.org/sioc/types#" xmlns:skos="http://www.w3.org/2004/02/skos/core#" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#">
  <channel>
    <title>Rodenticides</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/feed/41895/rss.xml</link>
    <description>Updated Rodenticides content from the US Environmental Protection Agency</description>
    <language>en</language>
     <atom:link href="https://www.epa.gov/feed/41895/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      <item>
    <title>Canceling Some d-CON Mouse and Rat Control Products</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/rodenticides/canceling-some-d-con-mouse-and-rat-control-products</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;EPA has reached agreement with Reckitt Benckiser, the manufacturer, to cancel 12 d-CON rat and mouse poison products, listed in the table below, which will help prevent risks to children, pets and wildlife. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;On this page:&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#basic info&quot;&gt;Basic information on the cancellation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#12 products&quot;&gt;12 d-CON products being canceled and phased out&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#additional details&quot;&gt;Additional details about implementing the cancellation&lt;em&gt;​&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;basic info&quot; id=&quot;basic info&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Basic Information on the Cancellation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;box multi related-info right&quot;&gt;
	&lt;h2 class=&quot;pane-title&quot;&gt;Types of Rodenticides&lt;/h2&gt;

	&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;There are three types of rodenticide products.&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First-generation anticoagulants&lt;/strong&gt; usually require multiple feedings by rodents to deliver a lethal dose. Death generally occurs within 5-7 days. Anticoagulants interfere with blood clotting, and death can result from excessive bleeding.&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Second-generation anticoagulants&lt;/strong&gt; are more toxic and persistent than first-generation anticoagulants. Rodents can consume a lethal dose of second-generation anticoagulants in one night of feeding but can consume more because death usually occurs 5-7 days after a lethal dose is consumed. Risk to predators and scavengers is higher because the amount of poison rodents consume over several days is greater, and second-generation anticoagulants persist in rodent carcasses much longer than first-generation anticoagulants. Brodifacoum, bromadiolone, difenacoum, and difethialone are second-generation anticoagulants.&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Non-anticoagulants &lt;/strong&gt;are toxic in other ways, such as affecting the nerves or other body organs.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 12 d-CON products being canceled do not meet EPA’s current safety standards. All 12 of the products are sold without a protective bait station. Bait stations are required for consumer products to protect children and pets from contact with bait pellets. Also, 8 of the 12 products contain second generation anticoagulants pesticides that pose unacceptable risks to non-target wildlife.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on the agreement, Reckitt began phase out production of the 12 d-CON rat and mouse poison products in June 2014. Production of these products stopped on December 31, 2014. Distribution to retailers ended March 31, 2015. The timeline is likely to be considerably faster than would be achieved by the required administrative process. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mouse and rat poison products meeting our safety criteria are now widely available, effective, and affordable, and pose significantly less risk to people, pets, and wildlife such as mountain lions, eagles and foxes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/rodenticides/choosing-bait-station-product-household-use&quot;&gt;Learn more about bait stations for household use&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More information about safety measures and risk concerns for rodent control products is available in the &lt;a href=&quot;/rodenticides/rodent-control-pesticide-safety-review&quot;&gt;Risk Mitigation Decision for Ten Rodenticides&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;12 products&quot; id=&quot;12 products&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;12 d-CON Products Being Canceled and Phased Out&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;table summary=&quot;12 D-CON Products Being Canceled&quot;&gt;&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Product Name &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
			&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;EPA Registration No.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;d-CON Concentrate Kills Rats &amp;amp; Mice&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;3282-3&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;d-CON Ready Mixed Kills Rats &amp;amp; Mice&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;3282-4&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;d-CON Mouse Prufe Kills Mice&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;3282-9&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;d-CON Pellets Kills Rats &amp;amp; Mice&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;3282-15&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;d-CON Mouse Prufe II&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;3282-65&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;d-CON Pellets Generation II&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;3282-66&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;d-CON Bait Pellets II&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;3282-74&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;d-CON Ready Mixed Generation II&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;3282-81&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;d-CON Mouse-Prufe III&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;3282-85&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;d-CON Bait Pellets III&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;3282-86&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;d-CON II Ready Mix Baitbits III&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;3282-87&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;d-CON Bait Packs III&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;3282-88&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;additional details&quot; id=&quot;additional details&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Additional Details about Implementing the Cancellation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;How does Reckitt’s decision to cancel these products affect the ongoing cancellation proceeding? &lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The EPA had previously made the determination that 12 products produced by Reckitt did not comply with current safety standards and issued a Notice of Intent to Cancel these products in February 2013. Reckitt exercised its right to contest the cancellation through an administrative hearing process. Reckitt’s decision to voluntarily cancel the 12 d-CON products will make the ongoing cancellation proceeding moot. In addition to Reckitt’s decision to voluntarily cancel the 12 d-CON products, Reckitt will no longer pursue its legal challenge of the Agency’s denials of applications for registration of two other d-CON products.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;What are the terms of the agreement reached between Reckitt and EPA?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The major provisions of the agreement reached between Reckitt and EPA include the following:&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Reckitt began phase out production of the 12 d-CON rat and mouse poison products in June 2014, stopped all production by December 31, 2014.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Reckitt ceased distribution of existing stocks of these products by March 31, 2015.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;During the phase-out period, Reckitt will not stockpile or increase production of the 12 d-CON rat and mouse poison products.  Reckitt will only produce quantities of these products to satisfy previously existing contracts and agreements.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Retailers will be permitted keep the products on the shelves until stocks are depleted, and end users will be permitted to use them until exhausted.  EPA anticipates that the majority will be sold and used within 3 months or less, though small quantities may persist for a year or so.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Are these the only rat and mouse poisons that do not comply with EPA’s 2008 standards?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, the products subject to this action are the only currently registered rat and mouse poison products that do not meet the standards EPA announced in 2008. With this action, as of January 1, 2015, all registered consumer use rat and mouse poisons conform to EPA’s 2008 Risk Mitigation Decision. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;How long will these products remain on the shelves and available to consumers? &lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In most stores, these types of products sell in three months or less. However, some of these products could remain on the shelves of smaller stores for as long as a year or more. The timeline is likely to be considerably faster than would be achieved by the required administrative process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The state of California has his issued a rule prohibiting sale of several of these d-CON products in California except to certified applicators beginning July 1, 2014.  For more information please visit the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cdpr.ca.gov/docs/legbills/rulepkgs/13-002/13-002.htm&quot;&gt;California Department of Pesticide Regulation website&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Can consumers continue to use the product after March 2015?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will continue to be legal for consumers to use the 12 d-CON mouse and rat poison products, provided they follow all label directions and precautions.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;What advice does EPA have to consumers regarding disposal of any unwanted or unused products?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consumers who wish to dispose of any of the d-CON mouse and rat poison products listed above should contact their state or local waste disposal program or service for information on proper disposal in their community. These pesticides are harmful to the wildlife, so consumers who have opened containers should not discard them outdoors or dispose of them in sinks or toilets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consumers can contact their local government for recommendations on how to dispose of unwanted or unused pesticide products.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Disposal Contacts&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;To identify a local solid waste agency, consumers may look in the government section of the phone book under categories such as solid waste, public works or garbage, trash or refuse collection.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;To identify your state pesticide disposal program coordinator, see &lt;a href=&quot;/pesticide-worker-safety/pesticide-disposal-contacts-states&quot;&gt;Pesticide Disposal Contacts in States&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;To identify your state solid or hazardous waste agency, see &lt;a href=&quot;/learn-issues/learn-about-waste&quot;&gt;Learn about Waste&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;For information on pesticide storage and disposal, see &lt;a href=&quot;/pesticide-worker-safety/containers-containment-storage-and-disposal-pesticides&quot;&gt;Containers, Containment, Storage and Disposal of Pesticides&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Contact Earth 911 at 1-800-Cleanup (253-2687) or &lt;a href=&quot;http://earth911.com&quot;&gt;http://www.earth911.com&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt; to obtain community disposal information. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 04 Mar 2014 14:58:06 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>morganic</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">46475 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Restrictions on Rodenticide Products</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/rodenticides/restrictions-rodenticide-products</link>
    <description>&lt;div class=&quot;box multi related-info right&quot;&gt;
	&lt;h2 class=&quot;pane-title&quot;&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;types&quot; name=&quot;types&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Types of Rodenticides&lt;/h2&gt;

	&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;Most of the rodenticides used today are anticoagulant compounds that interfere with blood clotting and cause death from excessive bleeding. Deaths typically occur between four days and two weeks after rodents begin to feed on the bait. &lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;first&quot; name=&quot;first&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;First-generation anticoagulants&lt;/strong&gt; include the anticoagulants that were developed as rodenticides before 1970. These compounds are much more toxic when feeding occurs on several successive days rather than on one day only. Chlorpophacinone, diphacinone and warfarin are first-generation anticoagulants that are registered to control rats and mice in the United States.&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;second&quot; name=&quot;second&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Second-generation anticoagulants&lt;/strong&gt; were developed beginning in the 1970s to control rodents that are resistant to first-generation anticoagulants. Second-generation anticoagulants also are more likely than first-generation anticoagulants to be able to kill after a single night&#039;s feeding. These compounds kill over a similar course of time but tend to remain in animal tissues longer than do first-generation ones. These properties mean that second-generation products pose greater risks to nontarget species that might feed on bait only once or that might feed upon animals that have eaten the bait. Due to these risks, second-generation anticoagulant rodenticides no longer are registered for use in products geared toward consumers and are registered only for the commercial pest control and structural pest control markets. Second-generation anticoagulants registered in the United States include &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;brodifacoum, bromadiolone, difenacoum, and difethialone.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;non&quot; name=&quot;non&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Other rodenticides&lt;/strong&gt; that currently are registered to control mice include bromethalin, cholecalciferol and zinc phosphide. These compounds are not anticoagulants. Each is toxic in other ways.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Rodenticide Products for &quot;Consumer&quot; Use&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rodenticide products currently available on the consumer market are ready-to-use bait stations that contain and/or are packaged with a rodenticide bait that is in block or paste form. Pelleted baits no longer are permitted to be used in rodenticide products targeted for consumer markets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bait components of the ready-to-use bait station products currently registered for the consumer market to control mice and/or rats contain one of the following rodenticides:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Bromethalin.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Chlorophacinone.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Diphacinone. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;If bait stations are of a refillable design, up to one pound of bait to be used to fill or refill the bait station may be included with the bait station in the retail package. Ready-to-use bait stations that are not refillable must be properly disposed after the bait in them has been consumed or contaminated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ready-to-use bait station products are labeled for use:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;indoors; or&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;indoors and outdoors within 50 feet of buildings. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Where a specific product is authorized for use depends upon whether the bait station component of the product has been shown to be resistant to tampering by young children and by dogs as well as whether the unit has been found to be weather-resistant. Read the labels of these products before purchasing any of them to make sure that the product obtained is labeled for use in the place(s) that you intend to apply it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Rodenticide Products for Structural Professional and Agricultural Use Products&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These products include rodenticide baits registered for use by professional applicators to control rats and/or mice in or near (within 100 feet of) buildings and other structures or for use in and near agricultural buildings and man-made agricultural structures. They may contain any one of the active ingredients mentioned under &lt;a href=&quot;#types&quot;&gt;Types of Rodenticides&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Products geared to these categories of users are not to be sold in “consumer” stores, including drug stores, grocery stores, hardware stores, club stores, and similar retail outlets.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Products containing second-generation anticoagulants must be sold in containers holding at least 16 pounds of bait if they are labeled for use by professional applicators and at least eight pounds of bait if labeled for use in or near agricultural structures.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Professional- and agricultural-use products containing first-generation anticoagulants, bromethalin, cholecalciferol, or zinc phosphide must be sold in containers that hold at least four pounds of bait.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The bait products marketed to these categories of users may be in block, paste or pelleted form. These products are not packaged in or with bait stations. However, the labels for these products require use of tamper-resistant bait stations:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;If bait is to be placed in any indoor or outdoor location to which children under six years-of-age, pets or nontarget wildlife have access. &lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;For all applications made outdoors and above ground. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Bait stations suitable for using these bait products in such areas are commercially available. Baiting of burrows outdoors is permitted only for pelleted baits that are placed at least six inches down active rat burrows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;For More Information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.regulations.gov/#!documentDetail;D=EPA-HQ-OPP-2006-0955-0764&quot;&gt;2008 safety review and risk mitigation decision for rodenticides&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/rodenticides/canceling-some-d-con-mouse-and-rat-control-products&quot;&gt;Canceling Some d-CON Rat and Mouse Control Products&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 04 Mar 2014 14:39:42 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>morganic</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">46473 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Rodent Control Pesticide Safety Review</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/rodenticides/rodent-control-pesticide-safety-review</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;EPA completed a safety review in 2008 of rat and mouse poison products. Based on that review, EPA tightened safety standards to reduce risks to humans, pets, and non-target wildlife. Most companies have ensured that products are in compliance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/rodenticides/canceling-some-d-con-mouse-and-rat-control-products&quot;&gt;Read about cancellation of products that do not meet the stricter standards&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;box multi related-info right&quot;&gt;
	&lt;h2 class=&quot;pane-title&quot;&gt;Differences Among the Rodenticides&lt;/h2&gt;

	&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;The ten rodenticide active ingredients covered by this action can be divided into three categories:&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;span&gt;First-generation anticoagulants: warfarin, chlorophacinone, and diphacinone.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;span&gt;Second-generation anticoagulants: brodifacoum, bromadiolone, difenacoum, and difethialone.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;span&gt;Non-anticoagulants: bromethalin, cholecalciferol and zinc phosphide.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;All the anticoagulants interfere with blood clotting, and death can result from excessive bleeding.&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;The second-generation anticoagulants are especially hazardous for several reasons. They are highly toxic, and they persist a long time in body tissues. The second-generation anticoagulants are designed to be toxic in a single feeding, but since time-to-death is several days, rodents can feed multiple times before death, leading to carcasses containing residues that may be many times the lethal dose. Predators or scavengers that feed on those poisoned rodents may consume enough to suffer harm.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;The non-anticoagulants have differing ways of affecting pests:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Bromethalin is a nerve toxicant that causes respiratory distress. &lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Cholecalciferol is vitamin D3, which in small dosages is needed for good health in most mammals, but in massive doses is toxic, especially to rodents. &lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Zinc phosphide causes liberation of toxic phosphine gas in the stomach.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To minimize the possibility of children and pets being exposed to mouse and rat poisons, we require consumer products:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Be sold with bait stations that securely contain the poison.
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;More protective bait stations that offer resistant to tampering by children, pets, and/or to weathering are available and required for applications made around children, pets, or outdoors.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Contain the block or paste poison bait (loose bait forms are no longer permitted).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rodenticide manufacturers may no longer sell consumer products:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;With more than one pound of poison.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Containing four pesticides that pose the greatest risk to non-target wildlife (called second generation anticoagulants – brodifacoum, bromadiolone, difenacoum, and difethialone).
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Baits containing these poisons may still be used in homes by pest control professionals.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Non-target wildlife and pets can be poisoned if they eat rodent baits, as can predators or scavengers that consume rodents that have eaten certain poisons. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;span&gt;For More Information&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.regulations.gov/#!documentDetail;D=EPA-HQ-OPP-2006-0955-0764&quot;&gt;2008 safety review and risk mitigation decision for rodenticides&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/rodenticides/restrictions-rodenticide-products&quot;&gt;Rodenticide product restrictions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 04 Mar 2014 14:16:31 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>morganic</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">46471 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Which Governmental Agencies are Involved in Rat and Mouse Control?</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/rodenticides/which-governmental-agencies-are-involved-rat-and-mouse-control</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;In addition to its regulatory role, EPA works with the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) and various other state and local agencies and institutions to provide to the public information and tools for controlling rodents and the risks they may pose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CDC protects public health and works closely with state and local health departments to provide the public with information.  They are a rich source for information regarding &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cdc.gov/rodents/&quot;&gt;rodent management&lt;/a&gt;. CDC also has a fact sheet for &lt;a href=&quot;http://emergency.cdc.gov/disasters/rodents.asp&quot;&gt;rodent control in disaster settings&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While pest management begins with individuals, effective control is often community- or locally-based. Each state and locality has a unique system for pest management, including the prevention and treatment of rodents. To see what your state is doing to treat and prevent rodents, visit &lt;a href=&quot;http://npic.orst.edu/mlr.html&quot;&gt;your state’s Department of Health website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2013 11:32:46 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>morganic</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">42053 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>In Case of Pesticide Emergency</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/rodenticides/case-pesticide-emergency</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;If someone has swallowed or inhaled a pesticide or gotten it in the eye or on the skin:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Call 911 if the person is unconscious, having trouble breathing, or having convulsions.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Check the label for directions on how to give first aid.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Call the Poison Control Center at 1-800-222-1222 for help with first aid information.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://npic.orst.edu/ingred/index.html&quot;&gt;National Pesticide Information Center (NPIC)&lt;/a&gt; (1-800-858-7378) also can provide information about pesticide products and their toxicity.&lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;EPA&#039;s publication, &lt;a href=&quot;/pesticide-worker-safety/recognition-and-management-pesticide-poisonings&quot;&gt;Recognition and Management of Pesticide Poisoning&lt;/a&gt; provides information about symptoms caused by poisoning with specific pesticides and treatment information.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Also, have available the EPA registration number of the product involved.  This number can be found on the product label. &lt;span&gt;See more about the &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/pesticide-labels&quot;&gt;contents of a pesticide product label&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2013 11:28:33 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cgesalma</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">42051 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Tips for Hiring a Rodent Control Professional</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/rodenticides/tips-hiring-rodent-control-professional</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;If you have a rat or mouse infestation problem and are uncomfortable dealing with it by yourself, you may wish to hire a rodent control professional.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Choose a pest control company carefully.  Ask to see the company’s license.  If you have concerns, call your &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.npic.orst.edu/mlr.html&quot;&gt;state pesticide regulatory agency&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;EPA’s &lt;a href=&quot;/safepestcontrol/citizens-guide-pest-control-and-pesticide-safety&quot;&gt;Citizen’s Guide to Pest Control and Pesticide Safety&lt;/a&gt; offers tips on how to choose a pest control company. &lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;For additional assistance and tips on locating and hiring a pest control professional in your area, contact:
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://npic.orst.edu/&quot;&gt;The National Pesticide Information Center (NPIC)&lt;/a&gt;: Call 1-800-858-7378, send an e-mail to &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:npic@ace.orst.edu&quot;&gt;npic@ace.orst.edu&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.pestworld.org&quot;&gt;The National Pest Management Association (NPMA)&lt;/a&gt;: Call (703) 352-6762, send an e-mail to &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:info@pestworld.org?subject=Information%20Request%20from%20Pestworld.org&quot;&gt;info@pestworld.org&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2013 20:29:27 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cgesalma</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">41999 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Choosing a Bait Station Product for Household Use</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/rodenticides/choosing-bait-station-product-household-use</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://espanol.epa.gov/control-de-plagas/elegir-una-estacion-de-cebo-para-uso-domestico&quot;&gt;Información relacionada disponible en español&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More than a dozen ready-to-use bait station products are registered for use to control house mice. Some of those products also are registered to control rats. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A ready-to-use bait station is one that is sold with a rodenticide bait packaged in or with it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Some ready-to-use bait stations cannot readily be opened and, therefore, are non-refillable. Those products are to be discarded, as directed by labeling, after their bait contents have been consumed or contaminated. &lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Other ready-to-use bait stations are designed to be opened by users and refilled after the baits originally placed in them have been consumed or contaminated. These refillable bait stations are sold with additional bait to be used as refills.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;When used as directed, ready-to-use bait stations reduce access to bait by young children, pets, and nontarget wildlife while allowing the targeted rodents to enter and feed from them. These products come in several forms:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Ready-to-use bait stations (Tier 1) that have been shown to be resistant to tampering efforts by young children and by dogs and are considered to be weather-resistant may be used indoors and outdoors, within 50 feet of buildings. &lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Tier 2 ready-to-use bait stations have been shown to be resistant to tampering by young children and by dogs but cannot be used outdoors because they are not considered to be weather-resistant bait stations. &lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Tier 3 ready-to-use bait stations have been shown to be resistant to tampering by young children and can be used indoors in area to which pets have no access. &lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Tier 4 ready-to-use bait stations either have not been shown to be tamper-resistant or have not been tested in that regard. Therefore, Tier 4 stations may only be used indoors in areas to which young children and pets have no access, including residences where no young children or pets live or visit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;Always read and follow the directions on the label to reduce accidental exposure to the poison. You can find the labels for these products in our &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://iaspub.epa.gov/apex/pesticides/f?p=PPLS:1&quot;&gt;Pesticide Product Label System (PPLS)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt;. This resource can help you if the packaging for the product you have has been damaged and you can&#039;t read all the directions or if you hear about a product, and you want to find out more about it. You can search by product name, EPA registration number, or company name.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2013 20:13:51 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>dcoleman</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">41989 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Safely Use Rodent Bait Products</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/rodenticides/safely-use-rodent-bait-products</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://espanol.epa.gov/control-de-plagas/utilice-en-forma-segura-los-productos-con-cebo-para-roedores&quot;&gt;Información relacionada disponible en español&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rat and mouse poison products, if misused, can potentially harm you, your children, or your pets.  &lt;strong&gt;Always&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;/safepestcontrol/why-read-labels&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;read the product label&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;and follow all directions when using pesticides&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Remember!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Always store pesticides away from the reach of children and pets&lt;/strong&gt;, such as in a locked utility cabinet or garden shed.  &lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Place traps or baits only in locations where children and pets cannot access them.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Never store pesticides next to food, including pet food.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Read and follow the instructions on the pesticide label.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;To prevent accidental poisoning of wildlife and pets that might eat a dead animal, promptly remove and dispose of carcasses of dead rodents. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rodenticide products marketed to consumers include ready-to-use bait stations that are labeled according to the extent of protection they provide to young children and to dogs and whether or not they are weather-resistant. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rodenticide (rodent poison) products sold at consumer outlets are ready-to-use bait stations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;These products contain bait in the form of a block or a paste. &lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;The bait must be secured within the bait station that comes in the retail package. 
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;If the bait station is refillable, up to one pound of bait to be used to fill and refill the bait station may be packaged with the station. &lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;The baits used in these products must use one of the following rodenticide compounds as active ingredient:
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;bromethalin,&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;chlorophacinone,&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;cholecalciferol,&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;diphacinone,&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;warfarin, or&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;zinc phosphide. &lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;The baits used in these products may not contain a second-generation anticoagulant rodenticide (e.g., brodifacoum, bromadiolone, difenacoum, or difethialone).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;Learn how &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/rodenticides/rodent-control-pesticide-safety-review&quot;&gt;EPA regulates the safety of rat and mouse poison products&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2013 20:05:52 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>dcoleman</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">41985 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Options for Dealing With Rodent Infestations</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/rodenticides/options-dealing-rodent-infestations</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://espanol.epa.gov/control-de-plagas/opciones-para-tratar-las-infestaciones-por-roedores&quot;&gt;Información relacionada disponible en español&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have options for ridding your property of a rat or mouse infestation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/rodenticides/identify-and-prevent-rodent-infestations&quot;&gt;Identify and prevent rodent infestations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; -- it is always a good idea to try these simple methods first.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lethal traps&lt;/strong&gt; - such as snap traps, are designed to trap and kill rodents.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Live traps&lt;/strong&gt; - such as cage-type traps, capture rodents alive and unharmed, but the rodents must then be released or killed. Rodents released outside may find their way back into the house unless you have sealed the entry points into the house.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Poison baits (rodenticides) in tamper-resistant bait stations &lt;/strong&gt;combine a poison with edible material that is appealing to rodents. Protect children, pets, and wildlife by only using tamper-resistant bait stations, and follow all label directions and precautions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Always place traps and baits in places where children and pets cannot reach them.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/rodenticides/safely-use-rodent-bait-products&quot;&gt;Safely Use Rodent Poison Products&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/rodenticides/choosing-bait-station-product-household-use&quot;&gt;Choosing a Bait Station for Household Use&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2013 19:59:35 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>dcoleman</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">41983 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  </channel>
</rss>

<!-- Page cached by Boost @ 2017-01-26 04:11:57, expires @ 2017-01-26 16:11:57, lifetime 12 hours -->