<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?><rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.epa.gov/feed/61891/rss.xml" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/" xmlns:og="http://ogp.me/ns#" xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#" xmlns:sioc="http://rdfs.org/sioc/ns#" xmlns:sioct="http://rdfs.org/sioc/types#" xmlns:skos="http://www.w3.org/2004/02/skos/core#" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#">
  <channel>
    <title>EPA in Missouri</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/feed/61891/rss.xml</link>
    <description>Updated EPA in Missouri content from the US Environmental Protection Agency</description>
    <language>en</language>
     <atom:link href="https://www.epa.gov/feed/61891/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      <item>
    <title>Univar, Inc. Facility, Springfield, Missouri – Public Notice</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/mo/univar-inc-facility-springfield-missouri-public-notice</link>
    <description>&lt;h2 class=&quot;highlighted&quot;&gt;EPA Legal Notice - Proposed Determination of Corrective Action Complete Without Controls&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The U.S. Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) Region 7 invites the public to comment on its proposed determination of Corrective Action Complete Without Controls under the Resource Conservation and Recovery Act (RCRA), as amended, for the Univar, Inc. facility located in Springfield, Missouri, MOR000504795.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Corrective Action Complete Without Controls means that the facility owner/operator has satisfied RCRA corrective action obligations. Based on information currently available, EPA has developed Proposed Agency Decision Memoranda (Memoranda) with an Administrative Record, which includes all documents supporting the proposed decision of Corrective Action Complete Without Controls. EPA is not aware of any environmental releases of hazardous constituents at the facility at levels that present a potential threat to human health or the environment. EPA will make a final decision after considering all comments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The aforementioned Univar, Inc. facility was located at 220 South Barnes Avenue in Springfield, and was permitted as a storage facility between 1984 and 1994. During this time, the hazardous waste storage area went unused as incoming wastes were accumulated on the transports. A RCRA Facility Assessment Report was completed by the Missouri Department of Natural Resources on Aug. 18, 1993, and the facility underwent closure under a plan approved in 1995.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA encourages the public to review the Administrative Record at the EPA Region 7 Records Center or at The Library Center, 4653 S. Campbell Ave., Springfield, Mo., 65810.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Persons wishing to comment on EPA’s proposed decision summarized in the Memoranda must submit comments to EPA within the 30-day comment period &lt;strong&gt;ending Feb. 8, 2017&lt;/strong&gt;. All comments must be submitted in writing via mail or email to the EPA Project Manager listed below. A public meeting is not scheduled at this time; however, a meeting may be requested in writing. The request must include a statement of issues related to the proposed decision and findings in the Memoranda. EPA will evaluate the request to determine its applicability to the proposed decision and whether a public meeting is appropriate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA will consider all comments before making a final decision. If the decision is substantially unchanged from the one summarized in the Memoranda, EPA will issue a final decision and inform all persons who submitted written comments or requested notice of EPA’s final decision. If the final decision is significantly different from the one proposed, EPA will issue a public notice explaining the new proposed decision and will reopen the comment period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Memoranda are available on &lt;a href=&quot;/mo/proposed-agency-decision-memoranda-univar-inc&quot;&gt;EPA’s website&lt;/a&gt;. For additional information, please contact Sean Clary, EPA Project Manager, Waste Remediation and Permitting Branch, U.S. EPA Region 7, 11201 Renner Boulevard, Lenexa, Kan. 66219; Phone: 913-551-7908; Email: &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:clary.sean@epa.gov&quot;&gt;clary.sean@epa.gov&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;


</description>
     <pubDate>Mon, 09 Jan 2017 20:27:25 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>mkessler</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">168579 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Proposed Agency Decision Memoranda for Univar, Inc.</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/mo/proposed-agency-decision-memoranda-univar-inc</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;These memoranda document EPA’s proposed determination of Corrective Action Complete without Controls under the Resource Conservation and Recovery Act, as amended, for the Univar, Inc. Facility located in Springfield, Missouri.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-342885&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2017-01/documents/univarmemo.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=338658&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Proposed Agency Decision Memorandum for Univar, Inc. (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(2 pp, 339 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-342887&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2017-01/documents/mor000504795_univar_supp_memo.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=345473&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Supplemental Memo for CA999; Univar, Inc. (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(2 pp, 345 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jan 2017 16:51:57 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>mpropst</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">168181 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Region 7 States Air Quality Monitoring Plans - Missouri</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/mo/region-7-states-air-quality-monitoring-plans-missouri</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;Iowa, Kansas, Missouri, and Nebraska; Annual Monitoring Network Plans, Five-Year Monitoring Network Assessments, and approval documentation. Each year, states are required to submit an annual monitoring network plan to EPA. The network plans provide for the creation and maintenance of monitoring stations, in accordance with EPA monitoring requirements specified in 40 CFR (Code of Federal Regulations) Part 58.  For Five Year Monitoring Network Assessments, as stated at 40 CFR (Code of Federal Regulations) Part 58, each state is required to perform and submit to EPA an assessment of its air quality monitoring network every five years. At a minimum, this “five-year assessment” is meant to determine: if the existing network meets the monitoring objectives defined in Appendix D of 40 CFR Part 58; whether new sites are needed; whether existing sites are no longer needed and can be terminated; and whether new technologies are appropriate for incorporation into the ambient air monitoring network. For PM2.5 (particulate &amp;lt; 2.5 micrometers), the assessment also must identify needed changes to population-oriented sites. The first five-year assessment was due to EPA by July 1, 2010, and each assessment thereafter will be due in five-year increments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-349059&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2017-01/documents/mo-2016monitoringnetworkplan-appendix1-5.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=5755878&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Missouri Department of Natural Resources 2016 Ambient Monitoring Network Plan; Through Appendix 5)  (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(184 pp, 6 MB)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-349061&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2017-01/documents/mo-2016monitoringnetworkplan-appendix6.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=5687819&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Missouri Department of Natural Resources 2016 Ambient Air Monitoring Network Plan Appendix 6 (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(99 pp, 6 MB)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-349063&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2017-01/documents/mo-2016monitoringnetworkplan-appendix7.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=4313402&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Missouri Department of Natural Resources 2016 Ambient Air Monitoring Network Plan Appendix 7 (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(68 pp, 4 MB)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-349065&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2017-01/documents/mo-2016monitoringnetworkplan-approvalletter.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=277802&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Letter to Missouri; Approval of 2016 Ambient Air Monitoring Network Plan (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(2 pp, 278 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-342077&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-12/documents/mo_5yearnetworkassessment2015.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=8930128&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Missouri Department of Natural Resources 2015 Five-Year Ambient Monitoring Network Assessment (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(208 pp, 9 MB)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-342079&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-12/documents/mo_network_plan_7_27_15.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=11700851&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Missouri Department of Natural Resources 2015 Ambient Air Monitoring Network Plan (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(198 pp, 12 MB)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-342081&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-12/documents/mo_5yrand2015approvalletter_01_25_16.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=797392&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Letter to Missouri; Approval of 2015 Ambient Air Monitoring Network Plan and Five-Year Network Assessment (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(2 pp, 797 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 29 Dec 2016 13:52:32 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>mpropst</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">167957 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Spanish Village Subdivision, Bridgeton, Missouri - Fact Sheet, December 2016</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/mo/spanish-village-subdivision-bridgeton-missouri-fact-sheet-december-2016</link>
    <description>&lt;h2 class=&quot;highlighted&quot;&gt;EPA Conducting Sampling&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In November 2016, a lawsuit was filed on behalf of a family residing in the Spanish Village neighborhood of Bridgeton, Mo. The lawsuit alleged that radioactive contamination consistent with uranium processing waste was present in the home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Out of an abundance of caution, EPA is conducting a focused investigation in response to concerns raised by residents of Spanish Village. EPA plans to sample two to three homes during this focused investigation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SAMPLING PLAN AND METHODS&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA personnel and contractors under EPA oversight will perform exterior and interior screening and sampling at a limited number of residential properties in Spanish Village. The Quality Assurance Project Plan for this investigation is available &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.epaosc.org/bridgetondust&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;online&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the exterior portion of the screening, radiation detectors will be used to survey the soil outside the home. The radiation survey will detect gamma radiation and be used to identify locations to collect soil samples from the surface of the property.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the sampling locations identified by the radiation survey, soil samples will be collected from areas with the greatest potential for contamination or exposure, including play areas, vegetable gardens and at other exterior features such as downspouts. If non-native soils are present on the surface or subsurface of the property, a sample will be collected to analyze those soils as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA will also conduct interior radiation surveys, and swipe and dust sampling. Handheld instruments that can detect alpha, beta, and gamma radiation will be used to determine optimum locations for dust sampling and surface swipe sampling of floors, walls, and furniture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Swipe samples will also be collected from surfaces in rooms where people spend the greatest amount of time, such as a bedroom or living room. Swipe samples will be collected from entrances, where there is a higher potential for materials from the outdoors to be tracked indoors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The swipe samples will be screened by EPA using appropriate field equipment. The swipe samples exhibiting higher results from the screening will be selected for additional testing and analysis at a laboratory.  The certified laboratory will test for the presence of various radionuclides, including radium and thorium.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the survey, EPA will inform the homeowner of the general results. A final report with certified laboratory results of the analysis of soil and interior surface and dust samples will be available to the homeowner in approximately 60 days following the sampling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NEXT STEPS&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The data collected during this screening will help EPA determine if elevated levels of radionuclides are present beyond what is naturally occurring, and if further investigation and response by EPA may be warranted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;EQUIPMENT USED&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA and contractors under EPA oversight will use the following equipment during the investigation. Additional equipment that may be used is outlined in the Quality Assurance Project Plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-png view-mode-teaser caption&quot; style=&quot;width:160px;&quot;&gt;&lt;a
    href=&quot;/sites/production/files/2016-12/ludlum_model_44-9.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;image of Ludlum Model 44-9 sampling equipment&quot; height=&quot;257&quot; width=&quot;160&quot; class=&quot;media-element file-teaser&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/small/public/2016-12/ludlum_model_44-9.png&quot; title=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;figcaption&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;LUDLUM MODEL 44-9: This detector is sensitive to alpha, beta, and gamma radiation.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-png view-mode-teaser caption&quot; style=&quot;width:160px;&quot;&gt;&lt;a
    href=&quot;/sites/production/files/2016-12/ludlum_model_43-90.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;image of Ludlum Model 43-90 sampling equipment&quot; height=&quot;133&quot; width=&quot;160&quot; class=&quot;media-element file-teaser&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/small/public/2016-12/ludlum_model_43-90.png&quot; title=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;figcaption&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;LUDLUM MODEL 43-90:&amp;nbsp;This detector is sensitive to alpha radiation.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-png view-mode-teaser&quot; style=&quot;width:160px;&quot;&gt;&lt;a
    href=&quot;/sites/production/files/2016-12/ludlum_model_3030.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;image of Ludlum Model 3030 sampling equipment&quot; height=&quot;194&quot; width=&quot;160&quot; class=&quot;media-element file-teaser&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/small/public/2016-12/ludlum_model_3030.png&quot; title=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-png view-mode-teaser caption&quot; style=&quot;width:160px;&quot;&gt;&lt;a
    href=&quot;/sites/production/files/2016-12/ludlum_model_3030p.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;image of Ludlum Model 3030P sampling equipment&quot; height=&quot;147&quot; width=&quot;160&quot; class=&quot;media-element file-teaser&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/small/public/2016-12/ludlum_model_3030p.png&quot; title=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;figcaption&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;LUDLUM MODEL 3030 and MODEL 3030P:&amp;nbsp;The Model 3030 and Model 3030P will be used to test swipe samples for alpha and beta radiation.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-png view-mode-teaser caption&quot; style=&quot;width:160px;&quot;&gt;&lt;a
    href=&quot;/sites/production/files/2016-12/rad7_radon_detector.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;image of Rad7 Radon detector&quot; height=&quot;167&quot; width=&quot;160&quot; class=&quot;media-element file-teaser&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/small/public/2016-12/rad7_radon_detector.png&quot; title=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;figcaption&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;RAD7 RADON DETECTOR: The Rad7 is an electronic radon detector with real-time monitoring and spectral analysis.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;QUESTIONS?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have questions, please contact:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ben Washburn&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	Community Involvement Coordinator&lt;br /&gt;
	Phone: 913-551-7364&lt;br /&gt;
	Toll-free: 1-800-223-0425&lt;br /&gt;
	Email: &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:washburn.ben@epa.gov&quot;&gt;washburn.ben@epa.gov&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 27 Dec 2016 17:12:07 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>mkessler</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">167837 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Southwest Jefferson County Mining Superfund Site, OU-4 - Big River and Floodplain, Jefferson County, Missouri - Fact Sheet, December 2016</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/mo/southwest-jefferson-county-mining-superfund-site-ou-4-big-river-and-floodplain-jefferson-county</link>
    <description>&lt;h2 class=&quot;highlighted&quot;&gt;EPA Region 7 to Host Public Availability Session&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The U.S Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) Region 7 will host a Public Availability Session to discuss and answer questions about the ongoing Remedial Investigation and Feasibility Study (RI/FS) for the Southwest Jefferson County Mining National Priorities List (NPL) Superfund Site, Operable Unit 4 (OU-4), Big River and Floodplain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The session will be held:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tuesday, Dec. 13, 2016&lt;br /&gt;
	6:00 to 8:00 p.m.&lt;br /&gt;
	Hillsboro Community Civic Club&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jefferson County Fairgrounds&lt;br /&gt;
	10349 Business 21&lt;/strong&gt;

	&lt;div&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hillsboro, MO 63050&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;For reasonable accommodations at this Public Availability Session,&lt;/strong&gt; please contact Jonathan Cooper toll-free at 1-800-223-0425 or at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:cooper.jonathan@epa.gov&quot;&gt;cooper.jonathan@epa.gov&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;INTRODUCTION&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Southwest Jefferson County Mining National Priorities List (NPL) Superfund Site includes all of Jefferson County, Missouri, excluding the Herculaneum Site. Jefferson County is located on the northern portion of an area known as the Old Lead Belt where mining began in the early 1700s. Mine waste has contaminated soil, sediment, surface water and groundwater at the site with heavy metals, primarily lead. Mine waste has also been transported by the Big River and manually relocated to other areas throughout the county. In residential properties, this material has been used as topsoil, fill material, and aggregate for roads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA and Missouri state agencies have been addressing lead-contaminated soils in Jefferson County for more than a decade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;WHAT ARE THE OPERABLE UNITS?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Southwest Jefferson County Mining Site is separated into eight Operable Units (OUs). OU-1, OU-2, and OU-3 include the residential properties. OU-4 includes the Big River and floodplain, OU-5 includes groundwater, OU-6 is the Valles Mines area, OU-7 is the rail lines, and OU-8 consists of the mine waste areas. EPA works on the various operable units on a priority basis, based on the potential for human health and environmental risks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;WHAT IS THE CURRENT SITE STATUS?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As of August 2015, in support of OU-1 through OU-3, EPA has collected soil samples from 2,902 residential properties within site boundaries and has cleaned up (remediated) 551 of these properties. The remedial action phase is the actual construction or implementation of a Superfund site cleanup that follows the remedial design. The cleanup (remediation) consists of excavating and removing contaminated soil and gravel from affected properties, and replacing the excavated material with clean fill and vegetative cover, including sod and hydro-seed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sampling and cleanup (remediation) work is ongoing and is expected to continue until the remedial action objectives are met. Reports for these actions can be found at the site repositories listed at the end of this document.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA Region 7 staff and contractors have continued to collect soil and groundwater samples from residential properties. If your property has not been sampled, and you would like to have your soil and/or groundwater analyzed, please contact EPA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA is currently conducting Remedial Investigation activities at OU-4 and OU-8. Additionally, EPA has completed a dam stabilization project at the Rockford Beach Park, and is conducting a pilot project along the Big River at Brynes Mill City Park, including removal of contaminated soil and replacement with clean material. EPA is also planning a pilot project near the Mammoth River access point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;WHAT&#039;S BEING DONE TO PROTECT HUMAN HEALTH AND THE ENVIRONMENT?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the remediation of lead contaminated soils, EPA is also working with the Missouri Department of Natural Resources and the Missouri Department of Health and Senior Services to increase public awareness to protect residents from exposure to heavy metals, and is collaborating with the community to safeguard future residential development and protect remediated residential properties from lead recontamination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Health and fish advisory signs are being placed along access points to the Big River where elevated levels of lead in the sediment have been detected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;REMEDIAL INVESTIGATION AND FEASIBILITY STUDY (RI/FS) FOR OU-4&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA is currently conducting a Remedial Investigation (RI) at OU-4 that includes the Big River and floodplain to determine the full extent of mining-related metals contamination and to evaluate human health and ecological risk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Upon completion of the RI, EPA plans to initiate a Feasibility Study (FS) to evaluate remediation alternatives. Upon completion of the FS, a Proposed Plan will be presented to the public describing the evaluated alternatives and the proposed remedy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA is committed to promoting communication between citizens and the agency. EPA will continue to engage the public in various activities designed to inform and involve community members throughout the decision-making process. Prior to any site cleanup decisions, EPA will present findings of the investigation to the community and solicit public comments about the next steps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a part of this process, EPA will provide recommendations for cleanup to include costs, and will work to identify potentially responsible parties (PRPs) responsible for the contamination. PRPs could be required to conduct or pay for the cleanup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ADMINISTRATIVE RECORD (AR)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The AR file includes EPA decision documents about the response actions at the site. It is available for review during normal business hours at the following locations:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th colspan=&quot;2&quot; scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;
				&lt;h2&gt;Site Information Repositories&lt;/h2&gt;
			&lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;EPA Region 7 Records Center&lt;br /&gt;
				11201 Renner Blvd.&lt;br /&gt;
				Lenexa, KS 66219&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;De Soto Public Library&lt;br /&gt;
				712 S. Main St. &lt;br /&gt;
				De Soto, MO 63020&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SITE PROFILE WEB PAGE&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The AR is also available through an online repository at &lt;a href=&quot;/superfund/southwestjeffersoncountymining&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;www.epa.gov/superfund/southwestjeffersoncountymining&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ADDITIONAL INFORMATION&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Questions and requests for information about the site can be directed to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Elizabeth Kramer&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;Community Engagement Specialist&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;EPA Region 7&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;11201 Renner Boulevard&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;Lenexa, KS 66219&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;913-551-7186 or toll-free at 1-800-223-0425&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;Email: &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:kramer.elizabeth@epa.gov&quot;&gt;kramer.elizabeth@epa.gov&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Preston Law&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	Remedial Project Manager&lt;br /&gt;
	EPA Region 7&lt;br /&gt;
	913-551-7097 or toll-free at 1-800-223-0425&lt;br /&gt;
	Email: &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:law.preston@epa.gov&quot;&gt;law.preston@epa.gov&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;​&lt;strong&gt;Greg Bach&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	Remedial Project Manager&lt;br /&gt;
	EPA Region 7&lt;br /&gt;
	913-551-7291 or toll-free at 1-800-223-0425&lt;br /&gt;
	Email: &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:bach.greg@epa.gov&quot;&gt;bach.greg@epa.gov&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ADDITION INFORMATION ABOUT LEAD&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Visit &lt;a href=&quot;/lead&quot;&gt;EPA’s lead website&lt;/a&gt; and the Agency for Toxic Substances &amp;amp; Disease Registry’s&lt;strong&gt; ToxFAQs™ &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.atsdr.cdc.gov/toxfaqs/tfacts13.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Fact Sheet&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 06 Dec 2016 19:21:33 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>mkessler</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">166519 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Sporlan Valve Plant 1 Superfund Site</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/mo/sporlan-valve-plant-1-superfund-site</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SITE BACKGROUND&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Sporlan Valve Plant 1 Superfund Site was first developed as a refrigeration valve manufacturing facility in 1939. Continuous additions were constructed until 1968 when the final addition was added, bringing the total area of the factory to 80,000 square feet. In 2011, the brick building and concrete slab were demolished and the site was cleared. Over the course of the facility’s history, a release of trichloroethylene (TCE) to the ground occurred. Environmental assessments conducted between 2003 and 2006 at the site concluded that soil and groundwater beneath the site had been impacted by this chemical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In October 2004, Parker Hannifin purchased the Sporlan Valve Company via an asset sale, which excluded the real property associated with the site. SV Land, LLC, purchased the real property associated with the site in December 2004.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SITE LOCATION&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The site is located at 611 E. 7th Street, Washington, Franklin County, Missouri, 63090. The site is centrally located within the city of Washington and is approximately a half mile from the Missouri River.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CONTAMINANTS OF CONCERN&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The primary contaminant of concern is trichloroethylene, an industrial solvent more commonly known as TCE. TCE poses a potential human health hazard to the central nervous system, kidney, liver, immune system, male reproductive system, and developing fetus. TCE is characterized by EPA as “carcinogenic in humans” by all routes of exposure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TCE associated with the site has been detected in shallow monitoring wells and nearby residential homes. Existing monitoring well data indicates TCE contaminated groundwater is traveling away from the release point(s) in shallow groundwater, primarily towards the south and southeast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other contaminants of concern at this site include benzene, vinyl chloride and 1,1-DCE.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PROPOSED ACTION DESCRIPTION&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-png right view-mode-medium caption&quot; style=&quot;width:448px;&quot;&gt;&lt;a
    href=&quot;/sites/production/files/2016-07/sporlan_valve_pub_mtg_fs.vapor_intrusion_figure.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Figure showing vapor intrusion into a home&quot; height=&quot;547&quot; width=&quot;448&quot; class=&quot;right media-element file-medium right&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/medium/public/2016-07/sporlan_valve_pub_mtg_fs.vapor_intrusion_figure.png&quot; title=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;figcaption&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;FIGURE SHOWING VAPOR INSTRUSION INTO A HOME&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;Due to the presence of TCE in shallow groundwater under residential properties in the area, there exists the potential for TCE vapor intrusion into homes. Because of this, EPA is proposing a series of actions at the site. These actions will include sampling for TCE in homes, and installation of vapor mitigation systems in homes determined to be impacted, or at risk of being impacted, by TCE vapors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vapor intrusion is a way that volatile chemicals in soil and groundwater can enter and accumulate inside buildings. Volatile chemicals are a class of chemicals that tend to evaporate easily into the air. Normally, if these chemicals evaporate into outdoor air, they dissipate and do not pose health risks. Vapor mitigation systems that remove these vapors from home interiors can be a reliable and effective way to keep such vapors from accumulating, so that they do not pose health risks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA Region 7 has issued a Unilateral Administrative Order to SV Land, LLC, which purchased the former manufacturing property in 2004, requiring the company to design, install, and confirm the effectiveness of vapor mitigation systems at affected homes in the area. Owners of potentially affected properties have been contacted by EPA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ADDITIONAL INFORMATION&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA has established an Administrative Record for the Sporlan Valve Plant 1 Superfund Site. The Administrative Record file is the official site file and is available &lt;a href=&quot;https://semspub.epa.gov/src/collection/07/AR64582&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;online&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have questions or need additional information, please contact:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tamara Freeman&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;Community Engagement Specialist&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;EPA Region 7&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;11201 Renner Boulevard&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;Lenexa, KS 66219&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;Toll-free: 1-800-223-0425&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;Email: &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:freeman.tamara@epa.gov&quot;&gt;freeman.tamara@epa.gov&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 20 Oct 2016 19:07:15 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>mkessler</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">163189 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Pools Prairie Superfund Site, Manufacturing Plant Area (MPA) - OU4, Neosho, Newton County, Missouri - Fact Sheet, October 2016</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/mo/pools-prairie-superfund-site-manufacturing-plant-area-mpa-ou4-neosho-newton-county-missouri-fact</link>
    <description>&lt;h2 class=&quot;highlighted&quot;&gt;EPA Provides Update on Removal Activity&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;INTRODUCTION&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In response to public requests, EPA Region 7 has compiled this fact sheet to provide updated information on recent and continuing removal activity at the Pools Prairie Superfund Site’s Operable Unit 4 (OU4), Neosho, Mo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This Superfund site was discovered in July 1994 as a result of investigation into a citizen&#039;s complaint about gasoline contamination in a well located west of Highway 71 on Quince Road, southwest of the Neosho city limits. Numerous studies conducted since 1994 have indicated the presence of thousands of pounds of solvent-related compounds in multiple areas of the site. Causes of the contamination (primarily trichloroethylene or TCE) have included placement of waste solvent into unlined lagoons, leaks of solvent from manmade structures, and use of the solvent for weed control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the source areas that contributed to the contamination was the Manufacturing Plant Area (MPA), otherwise known as Operable Unit 4 (OU4). The area was used for various activities associated with the testing, manufacturing, overhauling, and storage of rocket engines, jet engines, and associated components.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CLEANUP OBJECTIVES AND METHODS&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;There are four distinct areas of concern at the MPA:&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;Former TCE Storage Area&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Former Railroad Spur Area&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Chemical Storage Area&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Former Surface Impoundment Area&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;EPA&#039;s short-term and long-term objectives at the Pools Prairie Site include restoring groundwater to beneficial use, if possible, and preventing any further human exposure to contaminants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-png left view-mode-full caption&quot; style=&quot;width:500px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;image of excavation at Pools Prairie Superfund Site&quot; height=&quot;375&quot; width=&quot;500&quot; class=&quot;left media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2016-10/pools_prairie_fact_sheet1.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;figcaption&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;An excavation is conducted at the MPA former chemical storage area, which is being backfilled with remediated soil from the landfarm. (U.S. EPA photo by Todd Campbell)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;These objectives are being met at the MPA by removing the source(s) of the contamination via excavation and landfarming of contaminated soils, and installing two different treatment technologies: a soil vapor extraction system (SVE), and a biovent system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;SVE&lt;/strong&gt; applies a vacuum to soil via a series of pipes buried in the ground. This vacuum pulls air through the soil, which then allows underground solvents to be removed from the subsurface.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;biovent system&lt;/strong&gt; pulls ambient air from the atmosphere and forces it underground via a series of pipes, wells and a large air compressor. This air is then used by aerobic microorganisms living in the soil, which allows them to flourish and subsequently use the trapped solvents as a source of food, effectively reducing the concentration of subsurface soil contaminants with minimal disturbance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Landfarming&lt;/strong&gt; is a treatment technique that involves bringing contaminated soils or material to the surface, or into treatment cells, where it is frequently turned, or tilled, to allow aeration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ONGOING WORK&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The source removal action to address source area contaminants at the MPA began in spring 2015 using a combination of the three different processes to achieve cleanup goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-png right view-mode-medium caption&quot; style=&quot;width:448px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;image of SVE piping assembly at Pools Prairie Superfund Site&quot; height=&quot;336&quot; width=&quot;448&quot; class=&quot;right media-element file-medium right&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/medium/public/2016-10/pools_prairie_fact_sheet2.png&quot; title=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;figcaption&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A contractor for the Potentially Responsible Party assembles horizontal SVE piping in the upper residuum of the soils near the MPA. (U.S. EPA photo by Todd Campbell)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;To date, approximately 7,500 cubic yards of contaminated soil has been excavated and landfarmed, where it was processed until the solvent concentrations in the soil were low enough to allow the material to be placed back into the excavated area. The SVE and biovent systems were constructed during summer 2015 and placed into service during fall 2015. Both systems are currently undergoing regular monitoring and management to maximize efficiency and to ensure that the site cleanup goals are met in a timely fashion. This removal action is anticipated for completion in 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ADDITIONAL INFORMATION&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Site documents are available for the public to review at the following locations:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;strong&gt;EPA Region 7 Records Center&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;11201 Renner Boulevard&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;Lenexa, KS 66219&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Neosho City Hall&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;203 E. Main&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;Neosho, MO 64850&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have questions or need additional information, please contact:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Brendan Corazzin&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;Community Engagement Specialist&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;Enforcement Coordination Office&lt;br /&gt;
	EPA Region 7&lt;br /&gt;
	11201 Renner Boulevard&lt;br /&gt;
	Lenexa, KS 66219&lt;br /&gt;
	Phone: 1-800-223-0425&lt;br /&gt;
	Email: &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:corazzin.brendan@epa.gov&quot;&gt;corazzin.brendan@epa.gov&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 11 Oct 2016 20:08:40 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>mkessler</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">162439 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Former Toastmaster Superfund Site, Macon, Macon County, Missouri - Fact Sheet, October 2016</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/mo/former-toastmaster-superfund-site-macon-macon-county-missouri-fact-sheet-october-2016</link>
    <description>&lt;h2 class=&quot;highlighted&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;EPA Provides Site Update&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;INTRODUCTION&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The U.S. Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) Region 7 has reached a settlement with Compton’s LLC and Spectrum Brands Inc., the current and previous owners of the Former Toastmaster Facility in Macon, Mo. This settlement requires investigations and response actions to address contamination associated with the release of trichloroethene (TCE). This settlement is in the form of an Administrative Settlement Agreement and Order on Consent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TCE is used in industrial solvents and degreasers, and household products such as correction fluids, paints, paint removers, adhesives, rug and metal cleaners, and spot removers. It is a manufactured substance and does not occur naturally in the environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Single (acute) or short-term exposure to TCE can potentially affect a developing fetus. High acute concentrations of TCE vapors can irritate the respiratory system and skin, and induce central nervous system effects such as light-headedness, drowsiness, and headaches. Repeated (chronic) or prolonged exposure to TCE has been associated with effects in the liver, kidneys, immune system, and central nervous system. EPA also has concerns for effects in a developing fetus from chronic exposure. TCE is carcinogenic to humans by all routes of exposure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Former Toastmaster Facility is located at 704 South Missouri Street, in Macon, Mo. From the mid-1950s to 2001, the facility manufactured small appliances. Since 2001, the facility has been used as retail and warehouse space. During an environmental investigation conducted in 1991, TCE was discovered to have been released from an above-ground storage tank on the facility. Further investigation found that TCE vapors were present in both the indoor air and sub-slab air of the facility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In July 2014, the Missouri Department of Natural Resources conducted indoor air and sub-slab soil gas sampling in homes in the immediate vicinity of the facility to determine whether the contaminants from the facility were impacting nearby residences. The results of this sampling documented elevated indoor and/or sub-slab levels of TCE in two of the nearby residences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In October 2014, EPA conducted a fund-lead removal action and installed sub-slab vapor mitigation devices in the two residences that had elevated levels of TCE.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CURRENT ACTIVITIES&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA is currently overseeing investigation actions that will include the collection of sub-slab soil gas data at the Former Toastmaster Facility to aid in the design of a sub-slab vapor system. This investigation will also include collection of exterior soil gas data near selected residences on the north side of Kohl Street to determine if these homes may be at risk from vapor intrusion and/or require supplemental sampling activities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NEXT STEPS&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA will review the data collected during the most recent sampling activity to determine whether more sampling will be needed both on- and off-site. Additionally, any residences that are discovered to contain vapors above health-based screening levels will be eligible to have a vapor mitigation system installed in the structure, in order to eliminate direct exposure to TCE vapors. EPA is also in the process of negotiating with the current responsible parties to address the main source of the contamination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ADDITIONAL INFORMATION&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA has established an Administrative Record file for the Former Toastmaster Superfund Site. The Administrative Record file is available &lt;a href=&quot;https://semspub.epa.gov/src/collection/07/AR64034&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;online&lt;/a&gt;.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have questions, please contact:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Brendan Corazzin&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	Enforcement Coordination Office&lt;br /&gt;
	EPA Region 7&lt;br /&gt;
	11201 Renner Boulevard&lt;br /&gt;
	Lenexa, KS 66219&lt;br /&gt;
	Phone: 1-800-223-0425&lt;br /&gt;
	Email: &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:corazzin.brendan@epa.gov&quot;&gt;corazzin.brendan@epa.gov&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Fri, 07 Oct 2016 21:54:31 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>mkessler</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">162319 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Washington County Lead District - Potosi, Old Mines, and Richwoods Superfund Sites, Washington County, Missouri - Fact Sheet, September 2016</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/mo/washington-county-lead-district-potosi-old-mines-and-richwoods-superfund-sites-washington-county</link>
    <description>&lt;h2 class=&quot;highlighted&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;EPA Conducting Remedial Investigation/Feasibility Study and&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Remedial Action&lt;/strong&gt;: Operable Units 1, 2, 3 and 4&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;INTRODUCTION&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-png right view-mode-medium caption&quot; style=&quot;width:448px;&quot;&gt;&lt;a
    href=&quot;/sites/production/files/2016-09/washington-co-fact-sheet2-fig-1-map.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Washington County Superfund Site site map 2&quot; height=&quot;584&quot; width=&quot;448&quot; class=&quot;right media-element file-medium right&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/medium/public/2016-09/washington-co-fact-sheet2-fig-1-map.png&quot; title=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;figcaption&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;FIGURE 1&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;On March 19, 2008, the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) added the Washington County Lead District (WCLD) - Potosi, Old Mines, and Richwoods Superfund Sites to the National Priorities List (NPL). The NPL is a list of the nation’s hazardous waste sites with the highest priority for cleanup. These sites are eligible for extensive, long-term response action money, as authorized by Congress under the Superfund program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The WCLD - Potosi, Old Mines, and Richwoods sites are actually three of four Superfund sites located in Washington County, Mo. (see Figure 1 at right. The fourth site, Furnace Creek, is being addressed as a separate investigation and is not included as part of this fact sheet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Remedial Action for residential yard cleanups (Operable Unit 1 or OU1) began in 2016 for all three sites addressed here. Residential yard cleanups are set to continue through the end of 2018. EPA is currently conducting the Remedial Investigation/Feasibility Study (RI/FS) for groundwater (OU2), mine waste (OU3), and surface water/sediment (OU4) at these three sites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Washington County is part of Missouri’s Old Lead Belt, where lead and barite mining, milling and smelting occurred over the span of three centuries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Potosi, Old Mines, and Richwoods Superfund sites encompass approximately 180 square miles in northeast Washington County. Historical mining operations at these sites were similar, with remnants of past mining operations such as strip mines, mineshafts, mine dumps, tailings areas, tailings ponds, and associated dams present throughout.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These mining activities have contributed to elevated levels of lead in soil, groundwater, surface water and sediment. Some residents have also unknowingly purchased lead-contaminated gravel for use in landscaping and construction of driveways, parking areas, and playgrounds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PREVIOUS SITE ACTIONS&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA and Missouri state agencies have been addressing lead-contaminated soils in Washington County for more than a decade, providing information, soil assessments, and removal actions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the past several years, EPA has conducted residential yard cleanups (time-critical removal actions) at properties with the highest levels of lead contamination – prioritizing properties with children present – due to a potentially greater health risk. Reports for these actions can be found at the site repositories listed at the end of this document.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the initial cleanup (removal actions), EPA collected soil samples from more than 3,408 residential properties within site boundaries. More than 1,481 of those properties had lead contamination greater than the levels of concern. EPA cleaned up residential soil at more than 355 properties in the three WCLD sites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the removal actions, EPA collected water samples from more than 1,866 drinking water wells within site boundaries. Of the drinking water wells tested, 315 were confirmed to have lead levels in the groundwater that exceeded the agency’s health-based level of concern. EPA has continued to address contamination in private drinking water supply wells by providing filtration or alternate sources of drinking water to owners of properties where lead or cadmium has been identified above health-based levels of concern. Removal actions are scheduled to be complete in September 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the Potosi, Old Mines, and Richwoods sites, the RI/FS reports for residential yards (OU1) were issued in February and July 2010, respectively. After completion of the RI/FSs, EPA submitted proposed plans to the public for review, presented agency findings in a public forum, provided an opportunity for the public to submit comments, and compiled responses to comments into the three Records of Decision (RODs). The RODs for residential yards for all three sites were final on Sept. 29, 2011. The RODs identified the cleanup objectives that were used to evaluate how properties would be addressed. The selected remedy is soil excavation and disposal, health education, and institutional controls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Remedial Action for Operable Unit 1&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Remedial Action phase is the actual construction or implementation of a Superfund site cleanup that follows the remedial design. The cleanup consists of excavating and removing contaminated soil and gravel from affected properties, and replacing the excavated material with clean fill and vegetative cover, including sod and hydro-seed. The Remedial Action is scheduled to begin in September 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SOIL &amp;amp; GROUNDWATER SAMPLING&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA Region 7 staff and contractors have continued to collect soil and groundwater samples from residential properties located within the Potosi, Old Mines, and Richwoods sites. If your property has not been sampled, and you would like to have your soil and groundwater analyzed, please contact EPA. Or, if you have questions about prior testing and/or need information about how to change private drinking water well filters, please contact EPA (see Additional Information section below).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CONTAMINANT OF CONCERN&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lead is a toxic metal that is harmful if inhaled or swallowed. Children are more sensitive to lead than adults and can develop lifelong learning disabilities and behavioral problems from lead exposure. Children can get lead into their bodies by putting their hands or toys in their mouths after touching contaminated soil. Pregnant women and nursing mothers should also avoid exposure to lead. Lead poisoning can cause negative health effects in infants and young children, including, but not limited to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Slowed physical growth&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Hearing problems&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Nervous system damage&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Learning disabilities&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Hyperactivity and other behavioral problems&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Decreased intelligence&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Lead exposure and its effects can be reduced by the following actions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Wash hands after playing outside and before meals.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Clean floors, window frames, window sills, and other surfaces weekly. Use a mop or sponge with warm water and general all-purpose cleaner.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Thoroughly rinse sponges and mop heads often during cleaning of dirty or dusty areas, and again afterward.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Keep play areas clean. Wash bottles, pacifiers, toys and stuffed animals regularly.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Clean or remove shoes before entering your home to avoid tracking in lead from soil.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Make sure children avoid fatty (or high fat) foods and eat nutritious meals high in iron and calcium. Children with good diets absorb less lead.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Children 6 years old and younger are most at risk from the hazards of lead poisoning. It is important that children in this age range be tested every year, because lead-poisoned children typically do not look or act sick. The only way to know if your child has an elevated blood-lead level is to have his or her blood tested. EPA encourages parents to have their children tested for lead exposure. You can call your local health department or physician to get your child tested. For additional information about lead, please see the EPA contacts under the Additional Information section below. You may also contact the Agency for Toxic Substances &amp;amp; Disease Registry (ATSDR). For more information, visit an &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.atsdr.cdc.gov/toxfaqs/tf.asp?id=93&amp;amp;tid=22&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;online fact sheet&lt;/a&gt; about lead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;COMMUNITY INVOLVEMENT&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA is committed to providing opportunities for communication between citizens and the agency. Active public involvement is crucial to the success of any public project. EPA will continue to engage the public in various activities designed to inform and involve community members throughout the decision-making process. Prior to any future site cleanup decisions, EPA will continue to present findings of the investigation to the community and solicit public comments about the next steps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ADMINISTRATIVE RECORD&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Administrative Record file serves as the official record for the sites and contains all site documents. It is available for review during normal business hours at:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Washington County Public Library&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;235 East High Street&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;Potosi, MO 64664&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;strong&gt;EPA Region 7 Records Center&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;11201 Renner Boulevard&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;Lenexa, KS 66219&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SITE PROFILE WEB PAGE&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;To view EPA site profile pages for the WCLD sites, visit the Missouri Cleanups page at &lt;a href=&quot;/mo/missouri-cleanups&quot;&gt;www.epa.gov/mo/missouri-cleanups&lt;/a&gt;, click on “Search for Superfund Site Where You live,” and search for Washington County.&lt;/p&gt;

	&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ADDITIONAL INFORMATION&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

	&lt;p&gt;If you have questions about this fact sheet or need additional information, please contact:&lt;/p&gt;

	&lt;div&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Elizabeth Kramer&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

	&lt;div&gt;Community Engagement Specialist&lt;/div&gt;

	&lt;div&gt;Enforcement Coordination Office&lt;/div&gt;

	&lt;div&gt;EPA Region 7&lt;/div&gt;

	&lt;div&gt;11201 Renner Boulevard&lt;/div&gt;

	&lt;div&gt;Lenexa, KS 66219&lt;/div&gt;

	&lt;div&gt;Phone: 913-551-7186&lt;/div&gt;

	&lt;div&gt;Toll-free: 1-800-223-0425&lt;/div&gt;

	&lt;div&gt;Email: &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:kramer.elizabeth@epa.gov&quot;&gt;kramer.elizabeth@epa.gov&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

	&lt;div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;

	&lt;div&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Steve Kemp&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

	&lt;div&gt;Remedial Project Manager&lt;/div&gt;

	&lt;div&gt;Superfund Division&lt;/div&gt;

	&lt;div&gt;EPA Region 7&lt;/div&gt;

	&lt;div&gt;11201 Renner Boulevard&lt;/div&gt;

	&lt;div&gt;Lenexa, KS 66219&lt;/div&gt;

	&lt;div&gt;Phone: 913-551-7194&lt;/div&gt;

	&lt;div&gt;Toll-free: 1-800-223-0425&lt;/div&gt;

	&lt;div&gt;Email: &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:kemp.steve@epa.gov&quot;&gt;kemp.steve@epa.gov&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Fri, 16 Sep 2016 20:09:18 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>mkessler</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">160449 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  </channel>
</rss>

<!-- Page cached by Boost @ 2017-01-25 16:26:35, expires @ 2017-01-26 04:26:35, lifetime 12 hours -->