<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?><rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.epa.gov/feed/58493/rss.xml" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/" xmlns:og="http://ogp.me/ns#" xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#" xmlns:sioc="http://rdfs.org/sioc/ns#" xmlns:sioct="http://rdfs.org/sioc/types#" xmlns:skos="http://www.w3.org/2004/02/skos/core#" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#">
  <channel>
    <title>Reducing Pesticide Drift</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/feed/58493/rss.xml</link>
    <description>Updated Reducing Pesticide Drift content from the US Environmental Protection Agency</description>
    <language>en</language>
     <atom:link href="https://www.epa.gov/feed/58493/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      <item>
    <title>Drift Reduction Technology Logos</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/reducing-pesticide-drift/drift-reduction-technology-logos</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;See larger image of the logos here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-291857&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-06/documents/drift_reduction_logos.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=369496&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Drift Reduction Logos (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(3 pp, 369 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jun 2016 15:27:34 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>dcoleman</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">151693 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Environmental Technology Verification: Pesticide Spray Drift Reduction Technologies for Row and Field Crops</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/reducing-pesticide-drift/environmental-technology-verification-pesticide-spray-drift-reduction</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Evaluation of the Verification Protocol for Low and High Speed Wind Tunnel Testing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Environmental Technology Verification (ETV) Program, established by the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency (EPA), is designed to accelerate the development and commercialization of new or improved technologies through third-party verification and reporting of performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The goal of the ETV Program is to verify the performance of commercially ready environmental technologies through the evaluation of objective and quality-assured data in order to provide potential purchasers and permitters an independent, credible assessment of the technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA established a Drift Reduction Technology (DRT) project under EPA’s Environmental and Sustainable Technology (ESTE) program, which itself is part of the ETV Program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This report describes the evaluation of the draft protocol for pesticide spray DRTs verification at low and high speeds. All testing was performed in accordance with approved test/quality assurance plans that implement the requirements of the generic verification protocol at the test laboratory.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-278319&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-04/documents/final-drt-gvp-eval_rpt-20120508x.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=605679&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Environmental Technology Verification Pesticide Spray Drift Reduction Technologies for Row and Field Crops, Evaluation of the Verification Protocol for Low and High Speed Wind Tunnel Testing  (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(34 pp, 606 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 21 Apr 2016 12:09:59 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>morganic</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">147249 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Verification Testing of Air Pollution Control Technology Quality Management Plan Revision 2.3</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/reducing-pesticide-drift/verification-testing-air-pollution-control-technology-quality-management</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;The Air Pollution Control Technology Verification Center (APCT Center) was established in 1995 as part of the EPA’s Environmental Technology Verification (ETV) Program to accelerate the development and commercialization of improved environmental technologies through third-party verification testing and reporting on the tested technologies’ performance. The APCT Center verifies the environmental performance of commercial-ready technologies in collaboration with qualified testing organizations (TOs). This document is the basis for Quality Assurance for the APCT Center. It describes the policies, organizational structure, responsibilities, procedures, and quality systems that will be followed under this cooperative agreement to meet the requirements of American National Standards Institute/American Society for Quality Standard E4-1994, Specifications and Guidelines for Quality Systems for Environmental Data Collection and Environmental Technology Programs (ANSI/ASQC, 1994).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-278313&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-04/documents/p100brw3.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=228062&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Verification Testing of Air Pollution Control Technology Quality Management Plan Revision 2.3  (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(51 pp, 228 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 21 Apr 2016 12:00:05 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>morganic</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">147247 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Generic Verification Protocol for Testing Pesticide Application Spray Drift Reduction Technologies for Row and Field Crops</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/reducing-pesticide-drift/generic-verification-protocol-testing-pesticide-application-spray-drift</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;This generic verification protocol provides a detailed method for conducting and reporting results from a verification test of pesticide application technologies for their potential reduction of spray drift. This testing approach is used to generate high-quality, peer-reviewed data for drift reduction technologies, including test design and quality assurance aspects. EPA utilizes this test protocol as part of a program to accelerate acceptance and use of improved and cost-effective application technologies which can significantly reduce spray drift and thereby provide benefits to applicators, the public, and the environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read the testing protocol for spray drift reduction technologies:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-295605&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-06/documents/drt-protocol-06-21-2016-v2.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=460290&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;U.S. EPA Generic Verification Protocol for Testing Pesticide Application Spray Drift Reduction Technologies for Row and Field Crops (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(57 pp, 460 K, 
  June 2016)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Mon, 27 Jul 2015 20:13:22 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>ctran</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">100523 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Drift Reduction Technology (DRT) Documents</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/reducing-pesticide-drift/drift-reduction-technology-drt-documents</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;Drift Reduction Technology Field Study and WindTunnel Submission Guides&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-211369&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-10/documents/drt_field_study_submission_guide_corrected_100715.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=149167&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;DRT Field Study Submission Guide  (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(9 pp, 149 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-211371&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-10/documents/drt_wind_tunnel_submission_guide_corrected_100715.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=182160&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;DRT Wind Tunnel Submission Guide  (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(9 pp, 182 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 12 May 2015 18:01:34 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>dcoleman</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">83907 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Drift Reduction Technology Study Format</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/reducing-pesticide-drift/drift-reduction-technology-study-format</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;Study reports related to wind-tunnel and field studies, submitted in support of the DRT program, should be submitted in one cohesive volume that contains the following elements. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additional guidance can be found:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/reducing-pesticide-drift/drift-reduction-technology-drt-documents&quot;&gt;DRT Field Study Submission Guide&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/reducing-pesticide-drift/drift-reduction-technology-drt-documents&quot;&gt;DRT Wind Tunnel Submission Guide&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ol type=&quot;I&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;Title Page
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Title of the submitted study
				&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Title should be self-explanatory with key words&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Author(s) and address of the study report generator&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Name of the performing laboratory&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Report submitter’s affiliation&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;br /&gt;&lt;li&gt;Quality Control Statement and Miscellaneous Requirements
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Signed statement of no data confidentiality claims&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Quality Assurance statement&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Signature page of participants of the study&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;br /&gt;&lt;li&gt;Executive Summary/Abstract
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;State main objectives and describe methods.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Summarize the most important results.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;State major conclusions and significance.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;br /&gt;&lt;li&gt;Introduction
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Provide information regarding specific objectives within a larger theoretical framework.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;br /&gt;&lt;li&gt;Methods and Materials
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Provide descriptions of experimental design, the apparatus, methods of gathering data and type of control (e.g., reference nozzle) used.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Field experiments: provide location, experimental layout, maps, field data and meteorological condition.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;br /&gt;&lt;li&gt;Results and Discussion
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Report must contain summarized data using narrative text and, where appropriate, tables and figures to display summarized data. Interpretation of the data and conclusions about what the data might mean are given in this section.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;br /&gt;&lt;li&gt;Conclusions
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;State what the data mean and, as such, how they relate directly back to the objectives stated in the introduction.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;br /&gt;&lt;li&gt;References
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;List in alphabetical order by author all published information that was referred to anywhere in the submitted report.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;br /&gt;&lt;li&gt;Appendix
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Provide raw data (e.g., Laser diffractogram with replicated measurements)&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Provide calculations (e.g., spreadsheet, statistics etc.).&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;For field experiment:
				&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Provide analytical report of chemical&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;Provide weather data file&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 12 May 2015 16:28:22 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cgesalma</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">83845 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>EPA-Verified and Rated Drift Reduction Technologies</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/reducing-pesticide-drift/epa-verified-and-rated-drift-reduction-technologies</link>
    <description>&lt;h2&gt;Review of Test Reports and Assigning DRT Ratings to Technologies&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div&gt;The EPA reviews drift reduction technology (DRT) test reports submitted to the agency and verifies:&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;roomy&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;whether the test was performed in an appropriate manner, and&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;if the data support a DRT rating.  &lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The drift reduction suggested by the study results will be used to assign the tested DRT a drift reduction rating. The four DRT ratings represented by one, two, three or four stars are awarded for technologies that demonstrate at least 25% reduction in potential spray drift as compared to the test standard nozzle.  The greater the number of stars, the greater the potential reduction of spray drift:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;roomy&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;One star -- 25-50 % reduction&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Two stars -- 51-75 % reduction&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Three stars -- 76-90 % reduction&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Four stars -- More than 90 % reduction&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Verified and Rated DRTs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA-verified drift reduction technologies (DRTs) and their ratings will be added to this page as they become available.  Pesticide applicators will be able to search tables for DRT-rated technology for ground boom and aerial applications by manufacturer and system pressure (psi).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technology manufacturers may use these assigned &lt;span&gt;DRT star ratings in the literature and labeling for their products.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


</description>
     <pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2014 11:15:59 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>dcoleman</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">58761 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>How to Test Pesticide Spray Technologies for Drift Reduction </title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/reducing-pesticide-drift/how-test-pesticide-spray-technologies-drift-reduction</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;Manufacturers interested in participating in the voluntary drift reduction technology (DRT) program can submit data to EPA. We prefer that applicants conduct their studies using EPA&#039;s test method, described below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will evaluate each data submission to verify the technology&#039;s drift reduction potential. If appropriate we will assign a drift-reduction star rating to the specific tested technology, based on the technology’s potential to reduce spray drift.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read more about &lt;a href=&quot;/reducing-pesticide-drift/epa-verified-and-rated-drift-reduction-technologies&quot;&gt;EPA&#039;s review and rating of technologies&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Testing Protocol Available&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With technical input from external experts, we have developed a protocol for testing pesticide application technologies for their potential reduction of spray drift.  DRT verification testing should be performed according to the &lt;a href=&quot;/reducing-pesticide-drift/generic-verification-protocol-testing-pesticide-application-spray-drift&quot;&gt;Generic Verification Protocol for Testing Pesticide Application Spray Drift Reduction Technologies for Row and Field Crops&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;This protocol addresses three testing approaches:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Low speed wind tunnels (to simulate application by ground boom equipment).&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;High speed wind tunnels (to simulate application by aircraft).&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Field testing (groundboom or aerial applications).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;We anticipate that the testing of smaller technologies, such as spray nozzles and combinations of nozzles and drift-reducing adjuvants (an adjuvant is &lt;span&gt;any &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;substance separately added to a pesticide product--typically as part of a spray tank mixture--that &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;will improve the performance of the pesticide product)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;, would be conducted in wind tunnels that measure the amount of the relatively smallest driftable droplets produced by the technology under conditions of the test. Larger technologies, such as shielded sprayers, would be tested in field studies in which the amount of pesticide deposition from spray drift downwind from the edge of the field is measured. Manufacturers may also choose to use field studies for nozzles and adjvant-nozzle combinations.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In both types of studies, measurements of droplets or deposition are compared with those from a standard set of nozzles used in the study. &lt;span&gt;The protocol describes the specific set of nozzles to use for the standard. Using a standard protocol with a standard set of nozzles as a baseline allows EPA to calculate comparison of drift reduction potential for each validated technology and across all validated technologies. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;We can use data from both wind tunnel and field tests in our risk assessments and therefore for risk management decisions for pesticides labeled for use with DRTs.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We limited the protocol to technologies for application to row and field crops because a large majority of agricultural pesticides are applied to these crops by ground boom and aerial equipment. Encouraging the use of DRTs for these uses should have an overall greater benefit to drift reduction. In the future, we may consider expanding this voluntary program to application technologies for orchard and vineyard crops, which require the use of significantly different application equipment (e.g., air blast sprayers).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technology manufacturers should contract with a qualified testing facility capable of performing these tests with the appropriate equipment, methods and quality control standards. Refer to the &lt;a href=&quot;/reducing-pesticide-drift/generic-verification-protocol-testing-pesticide-application-spray-drift&quot;&gt;protocol, section A8, Special Training and Certifications&lt;/a&gt;, for further information. Also, we strongly recommend those who plan to conduct a field study to contact us in advance so we can review the field study protocol, since such studies are complex and expensive.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2014 20:26:45 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>morganic</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">58757 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>About the Drift Reduction Technology Program</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/reducing-pesticide-drift/about-drift-reduction-technology-program</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;EPA&#039;s purpose for the Drift Reduction Technology (DRT) Program is to encourage the manufacture, marketing, and use of spray technologies scientifically verified to significantly reduce pesticide drift. Initially, the focus of the program is on spray technologies used primarily for pesticide applications to row and field crops by ground or aerial application equipment. EPA hopes to expand this program to include technologies for orchard and vineyard crops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To participate, EPA encourages technology manufacturers to test their technologies for drift reduction potential. EPA has provided test methods for manufactures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA will use a rating system to indicate the level of potential drift reduction of tested technologies. Based on review of submitted test results, the agency will assign a DRT rating, using one to four stars, to each technology that meets the minimum standard for drift reduction. Pesticide manufacturers are encouraged to state on their product labels that applicators should use DRT-rated technologies in applying pesticide products. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read more about &lt;a href=&quot;/reducing-pesticide-drift/epa-verified-and-rated-drift-reduction-technologies&quot;&gt;DRT review and rating.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technologies include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;roomy&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;nozzles,&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;spray shields and&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;drift-reducing adjuvant chemicals. (An adjuvant is any substance added separately to a pesticide product, typically as part of a spray tank mixture, that will improve the performance of the pesticide product.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Read more about &lt;a href=&quot;/reducing-pesticide-drift/how-test-pesticide-spray-technologies-drift-reduction&quot;&gt;testing of drift reduction technologies&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How to submit a study for review &lt;a href=&quot;/reducing-pesticide-drift/drift-reduction-technology-study-format&quot;&gt;formatting a scientific study&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Directions for &lt;a href=&quot;/pesticide-registration/pesticide-registration-manual-chapter-21-directions-submitting-applications&quot;&gt;submitting studies&lt;/a&gt; to EPA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Benefits of Using Drift Reduction Technology&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using DRT-verified pesticide spray technology can benefit pesticide applicators, the environment and people by:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;roomy&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;reducing loss of pesticide from the application site,&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;keeping more of the applied pesticide on the crop, improving pest control,&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;reducing pesticide exposures to people, wildlife, and the environment, and&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;reducing risks of damage and liabilities from off-target deposition of drift.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The use of DRTs should result in significantly less pesticide from spray applications drifting and being deposited in areas not targeted by those applications, compared to spray technologies that do not meet the minimum DRT standard. EPA may place fewer use restrictions on pesticide products that must be used in conjunction with DRTs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Availability and Adoption of DRTs &lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over time, the successful adoption of the DRT program will move the agricultural sector toward the widespread use of low-drift technologies. A robust adoption of this voluntary testing program by equipment and pesticide manufacturers and the widespread use of these technologies by pesticide applicators will provide a standardized, verified system for reducing pesticide drift. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drift-reduction ratings could appear on technology and pesticide labels as early as  spring of 2017. Look for information about use of DRT in the directions for use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;View &lt;a href=&quot;/reducing-pesticide-drift/epa-verified-and-rated-drift-reduction-technologies&quot;&gt;EPA-Verified and Rated Drift Reduction Technologies&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;For More Information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Documents describing the DRT program, including test methods or protocols, the Information Collection Request and our guidance to industry for participating in the program are available in the docket &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.regulations.gov/#!docketDetail;D=EPA-HQ-OPP-2012-0631&quot;&gt;(EPA-HQ-OPP-2012-0631&lt;/a&gt;) at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.regulations.gov&quot;&gt;www.regulations.gov&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read the Federal Register notice: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.federalregister.gov/documents/2014/10/15/2014-24525/agricultural-pesticide-spray-drift-reduction-technologies-voluntary-program&quot;&gt;Agricultural Pesticide Spray Drift Reduction Voluntary Program&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For questions on the Drift Reduction Technology Program, contact &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:overstreet.anne@epa.gov&quot;&gt;Anne Overstreet&lt;/a&gt; (overstreet.anne@epa.gov) at (703) 308-8068 or &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:overstreet.anne@epa.gov&quot;&gt;Tracy Lantz&lt;/a&gt; (lantz.tracy@epa.gov) at&lt;br /&gt;
	(703) 308-6415.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


</description>
     <pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2014 20:16:22 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>dcoleman</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">58755 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  </channel>
</rss>

<!-- Page cached by Boost @ 2017-01-26 03:58:00, expires @ 2017-01-26 15:58:00, lifetime 12 hours -->