<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?><rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.epa.gov/feed/28519/rss.xml" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/" xmlns:og="http://ogp.me/ns#" xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#" xmlns:sioc="http://rdfs.org/sioc/ns#" xmlns:sioct="http://rdfs.org/sioc/types#" xmlns:skos="http://www.w3.org/2004/02/skos/core#" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#">
  <channel>
    <title>Reduce, Reuse, Recycle</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/feed/28519/rss.xml</link>
    <description>Updated Reduce, Reuse, Recycle content from the US Environmental Protection Agency</description>
    <language>en</language>
     <atom:link href="https://www.epa.gov/feed/28519/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      <item>
    <title>How to Create and Maintain an Indoor Worm Composting Bin</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/recycle/how-create-and-maintain-indoor-worm-composting-bin</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg right view-mode-medium&quot; style=&quot;width:448px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;This is a picture of a large blue plastic bin used for worm composting&quot; height=&quot;251&quot; width=&quot;448&quot; class=&quot;right media-element file-medium right&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/medium/public/2016-05/binpic_0.jpg&quot; title=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;A worm composting bin, known as a vermicomposter, can be fairly inexpensive and easy to maintain. There are several ways to vermicompost. Below are instructions on how to build one kind of worm composting bin designed to be used inside. It is also possible to purchase worm composting bins. You will want to put your bin in an indoor space as you do not want the worms to freeze in the winter or get too warm in the summer. Additionally, you may want to put the bin in a basement or other out-of-the-way space since you will be producing compost and worm “tea” in the composter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On this page:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#need&quot;&gt;What You Need&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#prepare&quot;&gt;Preparing the Bins&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#paper&quot;&gt;Preparing the Paper, Soil, Water Medium and Adding the Worms&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#feed&quot;&gt;Feeding the Worms&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#maintain&quot;&gt;Maintaining the Bin&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;need&quot; name=&quot;need&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What You Need&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, buy, borrow or repurpose the following items that you will need to start worm composting:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. Two plastic bins &lt;/strong&gt;– one must be taller and rest inside the other, shorter bin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;div class=&quot;box multi related-info right&quot;&gt;
			&lt;h2 class=&quot;pane-title&quot;&gt;Why holes?&lt;/h2&gt;

			&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;Holes near the top of the tub allow air in for the worms to breathe. Holes near the bottom of the tub are to allow excess liquid to drain out of the box so the worms don’t drown. You can manage the liquid manually, but it is hard to get it just right, so holes make the bin easier to maintain. Both sets of holes are covered with a fine vinyl screen so the worms don’t escape.&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
		The shorter, bottom bin does not need a top. A bin made of rubber or plastic and that is approximately 15 inches deep, 25 inches wide and 5 inches high works great. The extra length allows you to scoop out the extra liquid or “worm tea” for use elsewhere (e.g., in the garden, for plants, shrubs, etc.).&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;The top tub should have a top to keep the worms from finding their way outside the box. It also needs to be somewhat flexible so you can drill holes into it. An 18 gallon tub that is roughly 15 inches deep, 20 inches wide and 15 inches tall works well.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;A drill &lt;/strong&gt;– A drill with a one inch diameter and a one-eighth inch diameter drill bit is needed to drill the holes mentioned above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. Screening material &lt;/strong&gt;– The type used for window screens is fine – just be sure NOT to use metal which will rust over time when exposed to the moisture in the bin. You only need about four 4 inch by 4 inch scraps of screen. Why use screening? If you don’t cover the holes, the worms may escape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg right view-mode-medium&quot; style=&quot;width:448px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;this is a picture of a pile of shredded paper to be used for worm composting&quot; height=&quot;252&quot; width=&quot;448&quot; class=&quot;right media-element file-medium right&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/medium/public/2016-05/shreddedpaper.jpg&quot; title=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. Waterproof glue&lt;/strong&gt; – To keep the screens in place, even after they get wet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5. Shredded paper&lt;/strong&gt; – Enough to fill your bin three inches deep and extra to add each time you feed the worms once a week. Almost any kind of paper works, but avoid heavy, shiny paper and colored paper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;6. &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A little bit of dirt&lt;/strong&gt; – A pound will be enough. Just make sure it does not have harmful chemicals in it. If all goes well, the worms will be producing their own dirt (compost) soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;7. A little bit of water&lt;/strong&gt; – Some water is needed to moisten the paper and dirt to create a comfortable medium for the worms to thrive. Soak the paper and then drain it before using.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg right view-mode-medium&quot; style=&quot;width:448px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;This is a picture looking down into a worm composting bin at the worms and dirt&quot; height=&quot;252&quot; width=&quot;448&quot; class=&quot;right media-element file-medium right&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/medium/public/2016-05/wormpic.jpg&quot; title=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;8. Worms &lt;/strong&gt;– A pound of red wrigglers are recommended because they consume waste quickly, but earthworms also work. Red wrigglers are available online, from your U.S. Department of Agriculture (USDA) extension office or from another worm bin owner. Be careful of worms that are invasive species, such as the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nps.gov/grsm/learn/nature/dff-earthworms10.htm&quot;&gt;Asian Jumping Worm&lt;/a&gt;, which can be sold as the Alabama Jumper or Georgia Jumper. Worm bins produce more worms as well as great compost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;9. A trowel&lt;/strong&gt; – Needed to move the compost as needed in the bin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;10. Food scraps container&lt;/strong&gt; – Use a small container with a tightly fitting top to collect vegetable and fruit scraps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why not just put the food straight into the worm bin? Worms do best left alone, so it is best to feed them only once a week. Use the food scraps container to collect scraps for a week and then feed the worms weekly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;prepare&quot; name=&quot;prepare&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Preparing the Bins&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below are the steps to take to prepare the bins:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Drill a 1-inch hole about two inches from the top of the taller bin on one side. Drill another hole on the opposite side. Drill four 1/8-inch holes near the bottom near the corners of the bin.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Cover each of the holes with vinyl screening and glue the screening in place with the waterproof glue. Be sure the glue is completely dry before continuing to the next step.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Place the tall bin inside the short bin. Do NOT drill any holes in the short bin.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;paper&quot; name=&quot;paper&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Preparing the Paper, Soil, Water Medium and Adding the Worms&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Combine shredded paper, soil and just enough water to dampen everything. Put the mixture into the tall bin and fill the bin about three inches deep. Add your worms to the mixture and let them get used to it for a day before feeding them. Make sure the mixture is very moist, but not forming puddles of water.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;feed&quot; name=&quot;feed&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Feeding the Worms&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg right view-mode-medium&quot; style=&quot;width:448px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;this is a picture of a clear plastic container holding food waste that will be put in a worm composting bin&quot; height=&quot;252&quot; width=&quot;448&quot; class=&quot;right media-element file-medium right&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/medium/public/2016-05/containeroffoodtocompost.jpg&quot; title=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;Collect food scraps, such as vegetables and fruit scraps, bread, tea bags, coffee grounds, and cereal in your food scrap container as you prepare and clean up after meals. Do not include any animal by-products (fat, bone, dairy, meat, waste). Also, it may take the worms longer to process woody or dry items like stems or the outer layer of onions. Worms will eat paper as long as it is thin or cut into small pieces, but they will not eat plastic or fabric tea bags, coffee filters or the labels placed on produce by grocery stores. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.compostsantacruzcounty.org/Home_Composting/Worm_Composting/worm_feeding.htm&quot;&gt;Learn more about what to and what not to feed your worms&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once a week, do the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Take the scraps to the worm bin.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Gently use a trowel to create a hole to put the scraps into.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Throw in a small handful of shredded paper.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Add all the food scraps on top of the paper.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Cover ALL of the food scraps with dirt and moist paper. Exposed food attracts fruit flies, but covered food scraps don’t. Add dirt and moist paper to the bin until the worms have made enough compost to use to cover the food scraps.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Notice what the worms are eating and what they are not. Remove any scraps that your worms have not eaten for a while as they may not like that type of food (e.g., some worms will not tackle a whole potato or citrus rind, but may eat them if they are cut up).&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Put the lid back on the worm bin.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Wash out the food scraps container for the coming week.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;maintain&quot; name=&quot;maintain&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Maintaining the Bin&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg right view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:928px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;This is a picture of a large blue plastic bin used for worm composting and a trowel next to it.&quot; height=&quot;522&quot; width=&quot;928&quot; class=&quot;right media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2016-05/binandtrowel.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;Once every few months, scoop the liquid out of the lower container and use it as fertilizer outside on soil near plants, or water it down to use on indoor plants. When the worm bin is full (i.e., when the compost reaches the bottom of the top holes you drilled), do the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Feed the worms on one side of the bin for a couple of weeks in order to draw the worms to that side.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Once all the worms are on one side, harvest the compost on the other side and use it in pots, your garden, or sprinkle it across your yard. You can also scoop compost and worms onto a newspaper and sort them out, but this is a bit messier. Be sure to harvest compost at the end of the week, before you feed the worms again.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;If there are too many worms in the worm bin, share extras with friends and family or release some with the dirt in your yard.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 05 May 2016 01:38:11 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>esundin</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">148689 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Managing, Reusing, and Recycling Used Oil</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/recycle/managing-reusing-and-recycling-used-oil</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;Used oil is exactly what its name implies: any petroleum-based or synthetic oil that has been used. Oil keeps our cars, lawnmowers, and many other machines running smoothly. However, during normal use, impurities such as dirt, metal scrapings, water, or chemicals, can get mixed in with the oil, so that in time, the oil no longer performs well. Eventually, this used oil must be replaced with virgin or re-refined oil to do the job correctly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On this page:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#01&quot;&gt;Basic Information on Handling Used Oil at Home&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#02&quot;&gt;The Benefits of Reusing and Recycling Used Oil&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#03&quot;&gt;How it Works: Recycling Used Oil and Oil Filters&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; Information on this page is meant for consumers. For information on managing used oil at your place of business, &lt;a href=&quot;/hw/managing-used-oil-answers-frequent-questions-businesses&quot;&gt;read through our frequent questions for small businesses&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;01&quot; id=&quot;01&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Basic Information on Handling Used Oil at Home&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are one of the many people who change their own motor oil, you too need to know how to properly manage the used oil. After all, used oil from one oil change can contaminate one million gallons of fresh water — a years’ supply for 50 people! When handling used oil, be sure to take these key points into consideration:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Used motor oil is insoluble, persistent, and can contain toxic chemicals and heavy metals.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;It’s slow to degrade.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;It sticks to everything from beach sand to bird feathers.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;It’s a major source of oil contamination of waterways and can result in pollution of drinking water sources.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Are you a “Do-It Yourselfer” —do you change the oil in your car at home? On average, about four million people reuse motor oil as a lubricant for other equipment or take it to a recycling facility. If you plan to recycle your used oil, take care not to spill any when you collect it and place it in a leak-proof can or container.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check with local automobile maintenance facilities, waste collectors, and government waste officials to see when and where you can drop off your used oil for recycling. Don’t forget to drain and recycle used oil filters as well—usually you can drop off the filters at the same collection centers where you deposit used oil.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;02&quot; name=&quot;02&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The Benefits of Reusing and Recycling Used Oil&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recycling and reusing used motor oil is preferable to disposal and can provide great environmental benefits. Recycled used motor oil can be re-refined into new oil, processed into fuel oils, and used as raw materials for the petroleum industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;box multi related-info right&quot;&gt;
	&lt;h2 class=&quot;pane-title&quot;&gt;Looking for a Place to Recycle your Used Oil?&lt;/h2&gt;

	&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;Use the below resources to find recycling locations near you:&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.recycleoil.org/&quot;&gt;American Petroleum Institute Used Motor Oil Collection and Recycling Site&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://ccar-greenlink.org/&quot;&gt;Compliance Assistance Center for Auto Repair&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ecarcenter.org/&quot;&gt;Environmental Compliance for Auto Recyclers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://search.earth911.com/?what=used+motor+oil&quot;&gt;Earth 911 Recycling Search Tool&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	Used oils such as engine lubrication oil, hydraulic fluids, and gear oils used in cars, bikes, or lawnmowers can pollute the environment if they are not recycled or disposed of properly. Used oil must be managed properly by local waste management authorities or automotive repair shops to prevent contaminating the environment. Used oil filters pose similar waste concerns. If properly drained, they can be safely recycled or disposed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the many reasons to reuse and recycle used oil include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Recycling used oil keeps it from polluting soil and water.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Motor oil does not wear out—it just gets dirty—so recycling it saves a valuable resource.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Less energy is required to produce a gallon of re-refined base stock than a base stock from crude oil.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;One gallon of used motor oil provides the same 2.5 quarts of lubricating oil as 42 gallons of crude oil.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;03&quot; name=&quot;03&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;How it Works: Recycling Used Oil and Oil Filters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Used oil can be re-refined into lubricants, processed into fuel oils, and used as raw materials for the refining and petrochemical industries. Additionally, used oil filters contain reusable scrap metal, which steel producers can reuse as scrap feed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, how is used oil recycled? Note that the most preferred option, re-refined oil—must meet the same stringent refining, compounding, and performance standards as virgin oil for use in automotive, heavy-duty diesel, and other internal combustion engines, and hydraulic fluids and gear oils. Extensive laboratory testing and field studies conclude that re-refined oil is equivalent to virgin oil—it passes all prescribed tests and, in some situations, even outperforms virgin oil.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same consumers and businesses that use regular oil also can use re-refined oil, since re-refining simply re-processes used oil into new, high-quality lubricating oil. Any vehicle maintenance facilities, automobile owners, and other machinery maintenance operations that use oil also can use re-refined oil. In some cases, fleet maintenance facilities that use large volumes of oil arrange to reuse the same oil that they send to be re-refined—a true closed recycling loop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 12 Jan 2016 20:28:54 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>esundin</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">131741 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>America Recycles Day 2016</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/recycle/america-recycles-day-2016</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg center view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:676px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;America Recycles Day 2015&quot; title=&quot;America Recycles Day 2015&quot; height=&quot;210&quot; width=&quot;676&quot; class=&quot;center media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2015-11/ard_banner.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;This America Recycles Day, November 15, EPA highlights that effective sustainable recycling programs are initiated by the leadership of communities and businesses across America. The Agency encourages the public to work with their local leaders and businesses to develop innovative recycling opportunities that promote economic growth and minimize environmental impacts. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;Currently about &lt;a href=&quot;/smm/advancing-sustainable-materials-management-facts-and-figures&quot;&gt;34.6 percent of what Americans throw away is recycled&lt;/a&gt;, reducing 186 million tons of carbon dioxide equivalent emissions annually. EPA asks every American to be a part of the effort to increase sustainable materials management across the country. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On this page: &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;Benefits of recycling&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#WYCD&quot;&gt;What you can do to reduce waste&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#jobs&quot;&gt;Reycling saves resources and creates green jobs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#bin&quot;&gt;Bin there, do that&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#energy&quot;&gt;Save energy by recycling &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;benefits&quot; name=&quot;benefits&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Benefits of Recycling&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg right view-mode-teaser&quot; style=&quot;width:160px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Woman recycling plastic in blue bin&quot; title=&quot;Woman recycling plastic in blue bin&quot; height=&quot;240&quot; width=&quot;160&quot; class=&quot;right media-element file-teaser right&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/small/public/2015-11/sustainability_recycling_epa.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Reduces the amount of waste sent to landfills and incinerators&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Conserves natural resources such as timber, water, and minerals&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Prevents pollution by reducing the need to collect new raw materials&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Saves energy&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Reduces greenhouse gas emissions that contribute to global climate change&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Helps sustain the environment for future generations&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Helps create new well-paying jobs in the recycling and manufacturing industries in the United States&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;WYCD&quot; name=&quot;WYCD&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;What You Can Do To Reduce Waste                                       &lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find out what you can do to help make a difference in our environment every day. Whether you&#039;re at home, on the go, in the office, or at school, there are many opportunities to go green by Reducing, Reusing, and Recycling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/recycle/reducing-waste-what-you-can-do#Tips for Home&quot;&gt;At home&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/recycle/reducing-waste-what-you-can-do#Tips for Students and Schools&quot;&gt;At school&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/recycle/reducing-waste-what-you-can-do#Tips for Work&quot;&gt;At work&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/recycle/reducing-waste-what-you-can-do#Tips for Communities&quot;&gt;In your community&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;jobs&quot; name=&quot;jobs&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Recycling Saves Resources and Creates Green Jobs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To celebrate America Recycles Day, EPA released significant findings on the economic benefits of the recycling industry with an update to the national Recycling Economic Information (REI) Study. This study analyzes the numbers of jobs, wages and tax revenues attributed to recycling. The study found that in a single year, recycling and reuse activities in the United States accounted for:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;757,000 jobs&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;$36,6 billion in wages; and&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;$6.7 billion in tax revenues.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;This equates to 1.57 jobs for every 1,000 tons of materials recycled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information, &lt;a href=&quot;/smm/recycling-economic-information-rei-report&quot;&gt;check out the full report&lt;/a&gt;, view the Agency&#039;s press release, or read Assisstant Adminstrator Mathy Stanislaus&#039; blog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;bin&quot; name=&quot;bin&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Bin There, Do That&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-gif left view-mode-medium&quot; style=&quot;width:160px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Meme telling you to stop and think before you trash it. &quot; title=&quot;Meme telling you to stop and think before you trash it. &quot; height=&quot;155&quot; width=&quot;160&quot; class=&quot;left media-element file-teaser file-medium left&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/medium/public/2015-12/atarithis.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How often do you ask yourself what&#039;s safe to put in your in recycling bin? &lt;span&gt;Next time you go to throw something away, get creative and think &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;of ways to reduce waste in the first place! There are many small habit changes that can motivate you to reduce, reuse and recycle more.&lt;/span&gt; Learn some do&#039;s and don&#039;ts and other helpful tips, as well as why &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.epa.gov/blog/2015/12/the-bags-dont-get-binned/&quot;&gt;The Bags Don&#039;t Get Binned&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;energy&quot; name=&quot;energy&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Save Energy By Recycling &lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recycling everyday objects, such as paper, bottles and magazines saves energy. The materials that you recycle are used to create the products you buy. This means less virgin material needs to be mined or harvested, processed, manufactured and transported - all of which consume energy. The iWARM tool is based on EPA&#039;s &lt;a href=&quot;/warm&quot;&gt;Waste Reduction Model (WARM)&lt;/a&gt; for solid waste planners and organizations. iWARM can be used to calculate how much energy organizations can save and how much greenhouse gases they can avoid by recycling versus landfilling their waste. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe id=&quot;iwarm&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot; src=&quot;//www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/widgets/iwarm-tall.html&quot; width=&quot;355&quot; height=&quot;385&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Fri, 13 Nov 2015 20:28:02 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>esundin</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">126011 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Donating Food</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/recycle/donating-food</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;By redirecting unspoiled food from landfill to our neighbors in need, individuals can support their local communities and reduce environmental impact. Non-perishable and unspoiled perishable food can be donated. Donated food can also include leftovers from events and surplus food inventory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On this page:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Wheretodonate&quot;&gt;Where to Donate Food&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#ideasforincreasing&quot;&gt;Ideas for Increasing Food Donations in Your Community&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#resources&quot;&gt;Food Donation Resources&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;Wheretodonate&quot; name=&quot;Wheretodonate&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Where to Donate&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg right view-mode-medium&quot; style=&quot;width:448px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;father and daughter donating food &quot; title=&quot;father and daughter donating food &quot; height=&quot;299&quot; width=&quot;448&quot; class=&quot;right media-element file-medium right&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/medium/public/2015-11/donationpicgirlandman_2.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Food Pantries
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Food pantries, food banks and food rescue programs are available across the country to collect food and redistribute it to those in need.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Food Banks
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Food banks are community-based, professional organizations that collect food from a variety of sources and save the food in warehouses. The food bank then distributes the food to hungry families and individuals through a variety of emergency food assistance agencies, such as soup kitchens, youth or senior centers, shelters and pantries. Most food banks tend to collect less perishable foods such as canned goods because they can be stored for a longer time.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Food Rescue Programs
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Food rescue programs take excess perishable and prepared food and distribute it to agencies and charities that serve hungry people such as soup kitchens, youth or senior centers, shelters and pantries. Many of these agencies visit the food bank each week to select fresh produce and packaged products for their meal programs or food pantries. Many also take direct donations from stores, restaurants, cafeterias, and individuals with surplus food to share. Remember to contact your local food pantry, food bank or food rescue operation to find out what items they accept. Also, food banks will often pick up donations free of charge.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;ideaforincreasing&quot; name=&quot;ideaforincreasing&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Ideas for Increasing Food Donations in Your Community&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Leverage your existing relationships with food banks and kitchens to donate food after events.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Enlist groups that meet within your facilities to assist in collection or distribution of donated food.&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg right view-mode-medium&quot; style=&quot;width:448px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;little girl and woman at food donation drive&quot; title=&quot;little girl and woman at food donation drive&quot; height=&quot;299&quot; width=&quot;448&quot; class=&quot;right media-element file-medium right&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/medium/public/2015-11/manpic.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Reach out to your local grocers, restaurants, venues and/or schools to suggest that they could donate wholesome food that will be wasted.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Create a schedule for pick-up of donated food on a weekly, biweekly or monthly basis.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Use donated food to feed the hungry or elderly of your community or for events held at your facility.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Create a schedule of deliveries to shelters and food banks for donated food that cannot be used in your facility.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;resources&quot; name=&quot;resources&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Food Donation Resources&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;disclaimer&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Disclaimer:&lt;/strong&gt; These sites are listed for informational purposes only. US EPA does not endorse any of these entities nor their services. &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:orcrweb@epa.gov&quot;&gt;Contact Us&lt;/a&gt; to suggest any additional links. The following links exit the site&lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://feedingamerica.org/get-involved/corporate-opportunities/become-a-partner/become-a-product-partner/protecting-our-food-partners.aspx&quot;&gt;Federal Bill Emerson Good Samaritan Act of 1996&lt;/a&gt; encourages individuals or businesses to donate food to nonprofits by minimizing liability.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://feedingamerica.org/foodbank-results.aspx&quot;&gt;Feeding America Food Bank Locator&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.foodrescue.net/our-story.html&quot;&gt;Food Rescue&lt;/a&gt; volunteer to collect unused food from restaurants and grocers to supply local food banks.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.foodtodonate.com/Fdcmain/FoodSafety.aspx&quot;&gt;Food Donation Connection&lt;/a&gt;provides useful information on food safety. FDC assists food service companies with putting their surplus food to good use.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jun 2015 18:03:47 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>esundin</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">91633 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>The Secret Life of a Smart Phone</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/recycle/secret-life-smart-phone</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg right view-mode-teaser&quot; style=&quot;width:160px;&quot;&gt;&lt;a
    href=&quot;/sites/production/files/2015-06/smartphone_infographic_700.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Infographic explaining the lifecycle and recycling of smart phones.&quot; title=&quot;The Secret Life of a Smart Phone&quot; height=&quot;625&quot; width=&quot;160&quot; class=&quot;right media-element file-teaser right&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/small/public/2015-06/smartphone_infographic_700.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Did you know that smart phones have a significant impact on the environment?&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Understanding the life cycle of a smart phone can help you make environmentally smart choices about your phone—and what to do with it when you want a new one.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Click the image to the right to view a larger size or download a PDF of the infographic below.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-139463&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-06/documents/smart_phone_infographic_v4.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=6583339&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;The Secret Life of a Smart Phone (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(1 pg, 7 MB)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jun 2015 15:40:15 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>tbuhrman</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">87361 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Reducing Waste: What You Can Do </title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/recycle/reducing-waste-what-you-can-do</link>
    <description>&lt;div class=&quot;box multi related-info right&quot;&gt;
	&lt;h2 class=&quot;pane-title&quot;&gt;Related Resources&lt;/h2&gt;

	&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/recycle/how-do-i-recycle-common-recyclables&quot;&gt;How do I recycle my?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/recycle/composting-home&quot;&gt;Composting at Home&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/hw/household-hazardous-waste-hhw&quot;&gt;Household Hazardous Waste&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;box multi related-info right clear-right&quot;&gt;
	&lt;h2 class=&quot;pane-title&quot;&gt;Green Ideas on Pinterest&lt;/h2&gt;

	&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
		&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type:disc&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pinterest.com/epagov/green-your-dorm-or-your-home/&quot;&gt;Greening Your Dorm Room&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pinterest.com/epagov/greening-your-holidays/&quot;&gt;Greening Your Holidays&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find out what you can do to help make a difference in our environment every day. Whether you&#039;re at home, on the go, in the office, or at school, there are many opportunities to go green by Reducing, Reusing, and Recycling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On this page:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Tips for Home&quot;&gt;Tips for Home&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Tips for Students and Schools&quot;&gt;Tips for Students and Schools &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Tips for Work&quot;&gt;Tips for Work&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Tips for Communities&quot;&gt;Tips for Communities&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Tips for Travel&quot;&gt;Tips for Travel&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Tips for the Holidays&quot;&gt;Tips for Holidays and Events&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
		&lt;div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;

		&lt;div&gt;
			&lt;div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;

			&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;Tips for Home&quot; id=&quot;Tips for Home&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Tips for Home&lt;/h2&gt;

			&lt;p&gt;The best place to start making a difference is right in your own home. Learn how you can reduce, reuse, and recycle materials to decrease household waste. The tips below will help you get started.&lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;ul class=&quot;accordion&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#pane-1&quot; title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot;&gt;Lawn and Garden&lt;/a&gt;

					&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;pane-1&quot;&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/recycle/composting-home&quot;&gt;Learn to compost at home&lt;/a&gt;. Use food scraps, yard trimmings, and other organic wastes to create a compost pile. Adding the compost you make to soil increases water retention, decreases erosion, and keeps organic materials out of landfills. &lt;/li&gt;
							&lt;li&gt;Raise the cutting height of your lawnmower during hot summer months to keep grass roots shaded and cooler, reducing weed growth, browning, and the need for watering.&lt;/li&gt;
							&lt;li&gt;If you need large lawn and garden equipment such as tillers and chainsaws, you can reduce waste (and save money) by setting up a sharing program with your neighbors.&lt;/li&gt;
							&lt;li&gt;When you mow, “grasscycle” by leaving grass clippings on your lawn instead of bagging then. The clippings will return nutrients to the soil instead of taking up space in landfills.&lt;/li&gt;
							&lt;li&gt;Donate healthy plants that you want to replace to community gardens, parks and schools.&lt;/li&gt;
							&lt;li&gt;If you have a wood burning fireplace, save your ashes instead of throwing them away. Once cooled, wood ashes can be mixed into your compost heap and provide nutrients to your garden.&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
				&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#pane-2&quot; title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot;&gt;Home Improvement&lt;/a&gt;
					&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;pane-2&quot;&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Use insulation made from recycled paper, glass, and other recovered materials.&lt;/li&gt;
							&lt;li&gt;Clean and properly store tools, toys and outdoor furniture to protect them from damage and keep them out of landfills.&lt;/li&gt;
							&lt;li&gt;Turn off or unplug lights during the day. Doing so will save energy and help your lights last longer.&lt;/li&gt;
							&lt;li&gt;Storms can cause power outages. Prevent waste by keeping rechargeable batteries for your flashlights. If you do use disposable batteries, reduce hazardous waste by buying ones with low mercury content.&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
				&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#pane-3&quot; title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot;&gt;Moving &amp;amp; Cleaning&lt;/a&gt;
					&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;pane-3&quot;&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Have a yard sale to find homes for clothes, toys, appliances, and books that you no longer need.&lt;/li&gt;
							&lt;li&gt;When moving, use old newspapers to wrap fragile materials.&lt;/li&gt;
							&lt;li&gt;Use moving boxes with the highest content of recycled paper and bubble wrap containing recycled plastic. Be sure to recycle packaging materials after your move. Many organizations, such as U-Haul, have places where you can drop of unused boxes for others to reuse.&lt;/li&gt;
							&lt;li&gt;Be sure to properly dispose of any non-recyclable items that you won’t be taking with you. Look for household hazardous waste collection days in your community to properly dispose of cleaners, paints, automotive supplies and other hazardous items.&lt;/li&gt;
							&lt;li&gt;For cleaning chores, buy reusable mops, rags and sponges. When using cleaning products, use only the amount you need and follow the bottle’s directions for use and disposal.&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
				&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;Tips for Students and Schools&quot; id=&quot;Tips for Students and Schools&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Tips for Students and Schools&lt;/h2&gt;

			&lt;p&gt;Students, parents, and teachers can all make a difference in reducing waste at school. By practicing the &quot;3 R&#039;s&quot; of waste reduction—reduce, reuse, and recycle—we can all do our part.&lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;ul class=&quot;accordion&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#b_pane-1&quot; title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot;&gt;Green School Supplies&lt;/a&gt;

					&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;b_pane-1&quot;&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/recycle/think-green-you-shop-full-infographic-image-jpg&quot;&gt;Think green before you shop&lt;/a&gt;. Before starting the new school year, look through last year’s materials. Many items can be reused or recycled.&lt;/li&gt;
							&lt;li&gt;Purchase and use school supplies made from recycled products, such as pencils made from old blue jeans and binders made from old shipping boxes.&lt;/li&gt;
							&lt;li&gt;Keep waste out of landfills by using school supplies wrapped in minimal packaging, and buying in bulk when possible.&lt;/li&gt;
							&lt;li&gt;Save packaging, colored paper, egg cartons and other items for arts and crafts projects. Look for other ways that you can reduce the amount of packing that you throw away.&lt;/li&gt;
							&lt;li&gt;Maintain new school supplies. Keep track of pens and pencils. Make an effort to put your things in a safe place every day. This will not only reduce waste, but save you money in the long run.&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
				&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#b_pane-2&quot; title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot;&gt;In the Cafeteria&lt;/a&gt;
					&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;b_pane-2&quot;&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;
								&lt;p&gt;If you bring your lunch to school, package it in reusable containers instead of disposable ones. Carry food in reusable plastic or cloth bags, and bring drinks in a thermos instead of disposable bottles or cartons. Read EPA&#039;s &lt;a href=&quot;/students/pack-waste-free-lunch&quot;&gt;Pack a Waste Free Lunch&lt;/a&gt; guide for more tips.&lt;/p&gt;
							&lt;/li&gt;
							&lt;li&gt;
								&lt;p&gt;When buying lunch, grab only what you need. Too often extra ketchup packets and napkins go to waste.&lt;/p&gt;
							&lt;/li&gt;
							&lt;li&gt;
								&lt;p&gt;Remember to recycle your cans and bottles after you finish eating.&lt;/p&gt;
							&lt;/li&gt;
							&lt;li&gt;
								&lt;p&gt;Work with your teachers to set up a composting program at school.&lt;/p&gt;
							&lt;/li&gt;
							&lt;li&gt;
								&lt;p&gt;Make posters that remind students what can be composted or recycled.&lt;/p&gt;
							&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
				&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;Tips for Work&quot; id=&quot;Tips for Work&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Tips for Work&lt;/h2&gt;

			&lt;p&gt;Engage and motivate your coworkers to buy green products and help reduce waste. Learn more about how your office can go green.&lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;ul class=&quot;accordion&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#c_pane-1&quot; title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot;&gt;In the Office&lt;/a&gt;

					&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;c_pane-1&quot;&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Instead of printing hard copies of your documents, save them to your hard drive or email them to yourself to save paper.&lt;/li&gt;
							&lt;li&gt;Make your printer environmentally friendly. Change your printer settings to make double-sided pages. Use small point fonts when possible and use the “fast draft&quot; setting when possible to save ink.&lt;/li&gt;
							&lt;li&gt;Pay your bills via e-billing programs when possible to save paper.&lt;/li&gt;
							&lt;li&gt;Use paperclips (over staples) when possible.&lt;/li&gt;
							&lt;li&gt;Reuse envelopes with metal clasps and reuse file folders by sticking a new label over the previous one.&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
				&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#c_pane-2&quot; title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot;&gt;Green Purchasing at Work&lt;/a&gt;
					&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;c_pane-2&quot;&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Purchase recycled paper and keep a recycling bin nearby your desk.&lt;/li&gt;
							&lt;li&gt;For information on how to buy more recycled-content products for your office, see &lt;a href=&quot;/smm/comprehensive-procurement-guideline-cpg-program&quot;&gt;EPA’s Comprehensive Procurement Guidelines&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
							&lt;li&gt;Buy energy efficient items with the ENERGY STAR ® logo or items that are &lt;a href=&quot;/smm-electronics/assessment-tools-electronics-stewardship#03&quot;&gt;EPEAT registered&lt;/a&gt; for the office.&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
				&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;Tips for Communities&quot; id=&quot;Tips for Communities&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Tips for Communities&lt;/h2&gt;

			&lt;p&gt;Citizens in every community can do many activities to work together and reduce waste. Each of us can make a difference by reducing, reusing, and recycling materials throughout our communities-and encouraging our neighbors to do the same.&lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;ul class=&quot;accordion&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#d_pane-1&quot; title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot;&gt;eCycling&lt;/a&gt;

					&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;d_pane-1&quot;&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Donate your old computers and tablets to a school. Many schools will be able to make good use of your old machine.&lt;/li&gt;
							&lt;li&gt;Before replacing a computer that no longer fits your needs, consider enhancing the computer’s capacity by upgrading the hard drive or memory. This can save you money too.&lt;/li&gt;
							&lt;li&gt;Donating used (but still operating) electronics for reuse extends the lives of valuable products and keeps them out of the waste stream for a longer period of time. &lt;a href=&quot;/recycle/electronics-donation-and-recycling#where&quot;&gt;Learn where to donate your TVs, computers&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
							&lt;li&gt;Be smart with your smart phone! It contains precious raw materials. Learn how to keep your information and our environment safe when donating your old device. &lt;a href=&quot;/recycle/secret-life-smart-phone&quot;&gt;Check out our guide&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
				&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#d_pane-2&quot; title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot;&gt;Starting Community Projects&lt;/a&gt;
					&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;d_pane-2&quot;&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;On Earth Day, April 22, show your commitment to a clean environment by volunteering for a cleanup effort in your community.&lt;/li&gt;
							&lt;li&gt;Organize a recycling drive in your neighborhood or at school. Collect bottles, glass, plastic, newspapers or books and take them to your local recycling center or a charity in need.&lt;/li&gt;
							&lt;li&gt;Create a community drop-off site for old computers at a neighborhood school.&lt;/li&gt;
							&lt;li&gt;Set up a composting program for your neighborhood or school. It only takes a small amount of land space to collect organic waste into a compost pile. The compost can be bagged and sold for community and school funds.&lt;/li&gt;
							&lt;li&gt;Hold a “donation picnic” at your local park or rec center. Participants can eat, talk and bring their old toys, clothes, books, furniture and other items for charitable organizations.&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
				&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;Tips for Travel&quot; id=&quot;Tips for Travel&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Tips for Travel&lt;/h2&gt;

			&lt;p&gt;Travelers create a lot of waste, even with the best intentions. Whether you are traveling for business or pleasure, you can do a few simple things that will reduce your waste, conserve resources, and minimize the overall environmental impact of your visit.&lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;ul class=&quot;accordion&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#e_pane-1&quot; title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot;&gt;Trips and Vacations&lt;/a&gt;

					&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;e_pane-1&quot;&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;When visiting beaches and parks, be sure to take back everything you bring in, so that you can leave places unlettered and undisturbed.&lt;/li&gt;
							&lt;li&gt;To pass the time on long drives or rainy vacation days, bring scrap paper for drawing and games.&lt;/li&gt;
							&lt;li&gt;Hot summer days make you thirsty. Be sure to recycle your used drink containers. Consider putting a filter on your water tap and refilling bottles with the filtered water. Instead of buying many small drink bottles, buy drink mixes in bulk and fill your reusable bottles.&lt;/li&gt;
							&lt;li&gt;Share the ride and the road. Public transportation and carpooling reduce pollution.&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
				&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#e_pane-2&quot; title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot;&gt;Car Maintenance&lt;/a&gt;
					&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;e_pane-2&quot;&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;If you change your own motor oil, collect and store used oil in a sturdy plastic container and &lt;a href=&quot;http://search.earth911.com/&quot;&gt;take it to a recycling center&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;Dumping oil down storm drains or on the ground can contaminate groundwater.&lt;/li&gt;
							&lt;li&gt;Purchase extended life anti-freeze for your car. When it’s time to change it out, take your used anti-freeze to a recycling center. Call 1-800-CLEANUP or visit &lt;a href=&quot;http://search.earth911.com/&quot;&gt;Earth 911&#039;s website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;to find the recycling center nearest to you.&lt;/li&gt;
							&lt;li&gt;Take used or damaged car batteries to auto stores that stock or repair lead-acid batteries for safe disposal. The batteries contain toxic amounts of lead and acid, and should not be thrown out with your regular trash.&lt;/li&gt;
							&lt;li&gt;Return used car tires to retailers or wholesalers that recycle or retread them. Tires are banned from most landfills, and illegally dumped tires become breeding grounds for mosquitoes and other pests.&lt;/li&gt;
							&lt;li&gt;Make sure your car has a clean air filter—a dirty air filter can increase your car’s fuel consumption by as much as 10 percent.&lt;br /&gt;
								Instead of sending your car to a low-value car to a landfill, offer it to a local charity. The gift will be tax-deductible.&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
				&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;Tips for the Holidays&quot; id=&quot;Tips for the Holidays&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Tips for the Holidays&lt;/h2&gt;

			&lt;p&gt;Holidays are the best time to connect with family and friends, but parties and gift giving often creates extra waste. Learn what you can do to keep you holidays as green as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;ul class=&quot;accordion&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#f_pane-1&quot; title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot;&gt;Giving Gifts&lt;/a&gt;

					&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;f_pane-1&quot;&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/recycle/think-green-you-shop&quot;&gt;Think green before you shop&lt;/a&gt; the holiday sales. Bring your own reusable cloth bag for carrying your purchases, and try to buy items with minimal packaging and/or made with recycled content.&lt;/li&gt;
							&lt;li&gt;Wrap gifts in recycled or reused wrapping paper. Also remember to save or recycle your used wrapping paper. Give gifts that don&#039;t require much packaging, such as concert tickets or gift certificates.&lt;/li&gt;
							&lt;li&gt;Send recycled-content greeting cards and remember to recycle any paper cards you receive. You can also try sending electronic greeting cards to reduce paper waste.&lt;/li&gt;
							&lt;li&gt;Bake cookies or other goodies and package them in reusable and/or recyclable containers as gifts. Homemade goodies show how much you care and help you avoid packaging waste.&lt;/li&gt;
							&lt;li&gt;When gifting flowers, consider buying long-lasting silk flowers, potted plants, or live bushes, shrubs, or trees that can be planted in the spring as gifts.&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
				&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#f_pane-2&quot; title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot;&gt;Green Parties and Events&lt;/a&gt;
					&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;f_pane-2&quot;&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;If you host a party, set the table with cloth napkins and reusable dishes, glasses, and silverware. Also save and reuse party hats, decorations, and favors.&lt;/li&gt;
							&lt;li&gt;Be sure your guest know where to properly dispose of and recycle their wastes at your party.&lt;/li&gt;
							&lt;li&gt;After holiday festivities, put leftovers in recyclable containers, and share them with family, friends, or others. Donate untouched leftovers from parties to a local food bank or homeless shelter.&lt;/li&gt;
							&lt;li&gt;After parties, fill your dishwasher up completely before running it. You will run fewer cycles, which saves energy.&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
				&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 13 May 2015 20:47:23 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>esundin</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">84161 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Electronics Donation and Recycling</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/recycle/electronics-donation-and-recycling</link>
    <description>&lt;div class=&quot;box multi related-info right&quot;&gt;
	&lt;h2 class=&quot;pane-title&quot;&gt;Additional Recycling and Donation Resources&lt;/h2&gt;

	&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.call2recycle.org/locator/&quot;&gt;Call2Recycle&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://search.earth911.com/&quot;&gt;Earth911&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ecyclingcentral.com/&quot;&gt;Electronic Industries Alliance&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cta.tech/Consumer-Resources/Greener-Gadgets.aspx/&quot;&gt;GreenerGadgets&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;Electronics donation and recycling is a great way to help conserve resources and natural materials. It is important to make sure you are donating and/or recycling electronics safely and correctly.&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On this page:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#why&quot;&gt;Why Recycle Electronic Products&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#donate&quot;&gt;Before Donating or Recycling Your Used Electronics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#where&quot;&gt;Where to Donate or Recycle&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;why&quot;&gt;Why Recycle Electronic Products&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;box multi related-info right&quot;&gt;
	&lt;h2 class=&quot;pane-title&quot;&gt;Related Information&lt;/h2&gt;

	&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;Check out our &lt;a href=&quot;/recycle/secret-life-smart-phone&quot;&gt;Secret Life of a Smart Phone infographic.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Electronic products are made from valuable resources and materials, including metals, plastics, and glass, all of which require energy to mine and manufacture. Donating or recycling consumer electronics conserves our natural resources and avoids air and water pollution, as well as greenhouse gas emissions that are caused by manufacturing virgin materials.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;For example:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Recycling one million laptops saves the energy equivalent to the electricity used by more than 3,500 US homes in a year.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;For every million cell phones we recycle, 35 thousand pounds of copper, 772 pounds of silver, 75 pounds of gold and 33 pounds of palladium can be recovered.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;donate&quot;&gt;Before Donating or Recycling Your Used Electronics&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;For your computer or laptop, consider upgrading the hardware or software instead of buying a brand new product.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Delete all personal information from your electronics.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Remove any batteries from your electronics, they may need to be recycled separately.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Check for &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ecyclingcentral.com/&quot;&gt;recycling facilities&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt; in your state  or community. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;where&quot;&gt;Where to Donate or Recycle&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Manufacturers and retailers offer several options to donate or recycle electronics. Search below to find programs developed by Sustainable Materials Management (SMM) Electronics Challenge participants. If you are an original equipment manufacturer or retailer, learn how to join the SMM Electronics Challenge. Participation in the SMM Electronics Challenge is voluntary. EPA does not endorse any of the participants or their products and services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/smm-electronics/sustainable-materials-management-smm-electronics-challenge&quot;&gt;Sustainable Materials Management (SMM) Electronics Challenge&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Search by Electronic Device or Company&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;disclaimer&quot;&gt;The following links exit the site &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;table id=&quot;datatable&quot;&gt;&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th&gt;Electronic Device&lt;/th&gt;
			&lt;th&gt;Company Name&lt;/th&gt;
			&lt;th&gt;Company Logo&lt;/th&gt;
			&lt;th&gt;Additional Information&lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Television&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-gif inline view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:46px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Television&quot; title=&quot;Television&quot; height=&quot;46&quot; width=&quot;46&quot; class=&quot;inline media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2015-06/icon_tv.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bestbuy.com/site/Global-Promotions/Recycling-Electronics/pcmcat149900050025.c?id=pcmcat149900050025&quot;&gt;Best Buy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bestbuy.com/site/Global-Promotions/Recycling-Electronics/pcmcat149900050025.c?id=pcmcat149900050025&quot;&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-gif inline view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:70px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Best Buy&quot; title=&quot;Best Buy&quot; height=&quot;48&quot; width=&quot;70&quot; class=&quot;media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2015-06/bestbuy.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;Offers in-store, event, online, and haul away recycling options&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;PC&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-gif inline view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:55px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;personal computer&quot; title=&quot;personal computer&quot; height=&quot;46&quot; width=&quot;55&quot; class=&quot;inline media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2015-06/icon_pc.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bestbuy.com/site/Global-Promotions/Recycling-Electronics/pcmcat149900050025.c?id=pcmcat149900050025&quot;&gt;Best Buy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bestbuy.com/site/Global-Promotions/Recycling-Electronics/pcmcat149900050025.c?id=pcmcat149900050025&quot;&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-gif inline view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:70px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Best Buy&quot; title=&quot;Best Buy&quot; height=&quot;48&quot; width=&quot;70&quot; class=&quot;media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2015-06/bestbuy.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Offers in-store, event, and online recycling options&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Mobile device&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-gif inline view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:32px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;mobile device&quot; title=&quot;mobile device&quot; height=&quot;46&quot; width=&quot;32&quot; class=&quot;inline media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2015-06/icon_mobile.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bestbuy.com/site/Global-Promotions/Recycling-Electronics/pcmcat149900050025.c?id=pcmcat149900050025&quot;&gt;Best Buy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bestbuy.com/site/Global-Promotions/Recycling-Electronics/pcmcat149900050025.c?id=pcmcat149900050025&quot;&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-gif inline view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:70px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Best Buy&quot; title=&quot;Best Buy&quot; height=&quot;48&quot; width=&quot;70&quot; class=&quot;media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2015-06/bestbuy.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Offers in-store, event, and online recycling options&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Television&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-gif inline view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:46px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Television&quot; title=&quot;Television&quot; height=&quot;46&quot; width=&quot;46&quot; class=&quot;inline media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2015-06/icon_tv.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.staples.com/sbd/cre/marketing/sustainability-center/&quot;&gt;Staples&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.staples.com/sbd/cre/marketing/sustainability-center/&quot;&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-gif inline view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:80px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Staples&quot; title=&quot;Staples&quot; height=&quot;32&quot; width=&quot;80&quot; class=&quot;media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2015-06/staples.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;Offers event recycling option&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;PC&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-gif inline view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:55px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;personal computer&quot; title=&quot;personal computer&quot; height=&quot;46&quot; width=&quot;55&quot; class=&quot;inline media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2015-06/icon_pc.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.staples.com/sbd/cre/marketing/sustainability-center/&quot;&gt;Staples&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.staples.com/sbd/cre/marketing/sustainability-center/&quot;&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-gif inline view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:80px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Staples&quot; title=&quot;Staples&quot; height=&quot;32&quot; width=&quot;80&quot; class=&quot;media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2015-06/staples.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;Offers in-store and event recycling options&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Mobile device&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-gif inline view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:32px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;mobile device&quot; title=&quot;mobile device&quot; height=&quot;46&quot; width=&quot;32&quot; class=&quot;inline media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2015-06/icon_mobile.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.staples.com/sbd/cre/marketing/sustainability-center/&quot;&gt;Staples&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.staples.com/sbd/cre/marketing/sustainability-center/&quot;&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-gif inline view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:80px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Staples&quot; title=&quot;Staples&quot; height=&quot;32&quot; width=&quot;80&quot; class=&quot;media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2015-06/staples.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;Offers in-store and event recycling options&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;PC&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-gif inline view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:55px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;personal computer&quot; title=&quot;personal computer&quot; height=&quot;46&quot; width=&quot;55&quot; class=&quot;inline media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2015-06/icon_pc.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dell.com/learn/us/en/uscorp1/dell-environment-recycling?c=us&amp;amp;l=en&amp;amp;s=corp&quot;&gt;Dell&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dell.com/learn/us/en/uscorp1/dell-environment-recycling?c=us&amp;amp;l=en&amp;amp;s=corp&quot;&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-gif inline view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:70px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Dell&quot; title=&quot;Dell&quot; height=&quot;20&quot; width=&quot;70&quot; class=&quot;media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2015-06/dell.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;Offers in-store, permanent drop-off site, mail-in and event recycling options&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Mobile device&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-gif inline view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:32px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;mobile device&quot; title=&quot;mobile device&quot; height=&quot;46&quot; width=&quot;32&quot; class=&quot;inline media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2015-06/icon_mobile.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dell.com/learn/us/en/uscorp1/dell-environment-recycling?c=us&amp;amp;l=en&amp;amp;s=corp&quot;&gt;Dell&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dell.com/learn/us/en/uscorp1/dell-environment-recycling?c=us&amp;amp;l=en&amp;amp;s=corp&quot;&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-gif inline view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:70px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Dell&quot; title=&quot;Dell&quot; height=&quot;20&quot; width=&quot;70&quot; class=&quot;media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2015-06/dell.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;Offers in-store, and event recycling options&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Television&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-gif inline view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:46px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Television&quot; title=&quot;Television&quot; height=&quot;46&quot; width=&quot;46&quot; class=&quot;inline media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2015-06/icon_tv.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lgrecyclingprogram.com/&quot;&gt;LG&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lgrecyclingprogram.com/&quot;&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg inline view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:80px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;LG Electronics&quot; title=&quot;LG Electronics&quot; height=&quot;54&quot; width=&quot;80&quot; class=&quot;inline media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2015-06/life-good-sm.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;Offers permanent drop-off site and event recycling option&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Mobile device&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-gif inline view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:32px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;mobile device&quot; title=&quot;mobile device&quot; height=&quot;46&quot; width=&quot;32&quot; class=&quot;inline media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2015-06/icon_mobile.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lgrecyclingprogram.com/&quot;&gt;LG&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lgrecyclingprogram.com/&quot;&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg inline view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:80px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;LG Electronics&quot; title=&quot;LG Electronics&quot; height=&quot;54&quot; width=&quot;80&quot; class=&quot;inline media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2015-06/life-good-sm.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;Offers mail-in recycling options&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Television&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-gif inline view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:46px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Television&quot; title=&quot;Television&quot; height=&quot;46&quot; width=&quot;46&quot; class=&quot;inline media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2015-06/icon_tv.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.vizio.com/environment&quot;&gt;VIZIO&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-png center view-mode-thumbnail&quot; style=&quot;width:96px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img height=&quot;24&quot; width=&quot;96&quot; class=&quot;center media-element file-thumbnail center&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/thumbnail/public/2016-08/vizio_logo.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;Offers mail-in recycling options and permanent drop-off site in some states&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;PC&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-gif inline view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:55px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;personal computer&quot; title=&quot;personal computer&quot; height=&quot;46&quot; width=&quot;55&quot; class=&quot;inline media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2015-06/icon_pc.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.vizio.com/environment&quot;&gt;VIZIO&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-png center view-mode-thumbnail&quot; style=&quot;width:96px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img height=&quot;24&quot; width=&quot;96&quot; class=&quot;center media-element file-thumbnail center&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/thumbnail/public/2016-08/vizio_logo.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;Offers mail-in recycling options and permanent drop-off site in some states&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Television&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-gif inline view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:46px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Television&quot; title=&quot;Television&quot; height=&quot;46&quot; width=&quot;46&quot; class=&quot;inline media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2015-06/icon_tv.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.samsung.com/us/aboutsamsung/citizenship/usactivities/environmentalinitiatives/recyclingdirect/&quot;&gt;Samsung&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.samsung.com/us/aboutsamsung/citizenship/usactivities/environmentalinitiatives/recyclingdirect/&quot;&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg inline view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:80px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Samsung&quot; title=&quot;Samsung&quot; height=&quot;30&quot; width=&quot;80&quot; class=&quot;center media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2015-06/samsung-logo.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;Offers permanent drop-off site recycling option&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;PC&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-gif inline view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:55px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;personal computer&quot; title=&quot;personal computer&quot; height=&quot;46&quot; width=&quot;55&quot; class=&quot;inline media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2015-06/icon_pc.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.samsung.com/us/aboutsamsung/citizenship/usactivities/environmentalinitiatives/recyclingdirect/&quot;&gt;Samsung&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.samsung.com/us/aboutsamsung/citizenship/usactivities/environmentalinitiatives/recyclingdirect/&quot;&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg inline view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:80px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Samsung&quot; title=&quot;Samsung&quot; height=&quot;30&quot; width=&quot;80&quot; class=&quot;center media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2015-06/samsung-logo.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;Offers permanent drop-off site recycling options&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Mobile device&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-gif inline view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:32px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;mobile device&quot; title=&quot;mobile device&quot; height=&quot;46&quot; width=&quot;32&quot; class=&quot;inline media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2015-06/icon_mobile.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.samsung.com/us/aboutsamsung/citizenship/usactivities/environmentalinitiatives/recyclingdirect/&quot;&gt;Samsung&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.samsung.com/us/aboutsamsung/citizenship/usactivities/environmentalinitiatives/recyclingdirect/&quot;&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg inline view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:80px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Samsung&quot; title=&quot;Samsung&quot; height=&quot;30&quot; width=&quot;80&quot; class=&quot;center media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2015-06/samsung-logo.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;Offers mail-in recycling options&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Television&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-gif inline view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:46px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Television&quot; title=&quot;Television&quot; height=&quot;46&quot; width=&quot;46&quot; class=&quot;inline media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2015-06/icon_tv.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sony.com/ecotrade&quot;&gt;Sony&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sony.com/ecotrade&quot;&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-gif inline view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:80px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Sony&quot; title=&quot;Sony&quot; height=&quot;17&quot; width=&quot;80&quot; class=&quot;inline media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2015-06/sony.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;Offers permanent drop-off site, event, and haul away recycling options&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;PC&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-gif inline view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:55px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;personal computer&quot; title=&quot;personal computer&quot; height=&quot;46&quot; width=&quot;55&quot; class=&quot;inline media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2015-06/icon_pc.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sony.com/ecotrade&quot;&gt;Sony&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sony.com/ecotrade&quot;&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-gif inline view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:80px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Sony&quot; title=&quot;Sony&quot; height=&quot;17&quot; width=&quot;80&quot; class=&quot;inline media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2015-06/sony.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;Offers in-store, permanent drop-off site, and event recycling options&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Mobile device&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-gif inline view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:32px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;mobile device&quot; title=&quot;mobile device&quot; height=&quot;46&quot; width=&quot;32&quot; class=&quot;inline media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2015-06/icon_mobile.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://goodworks.sprint.com/product/&quot;&gt;Sprint&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://goodworks.sprint.com/product/&quot;&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg inline view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:80px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Sprint&quot; title=&quot;Sprint&quot; height=&quot;38&quot; width=&quot;80&quot; class=&quot;inline media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2015-06/sprint.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;Offers in-store, permanent drop-off site and mail-in recycling options&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2014 18:50:16 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>tbuhrman</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">68859 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Think Green Before You Shop Full Infographic Image  (JPG)</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/recycle/think-green-you-shop-full-infographic-image-jpg</link>
    <description>&lt;div class=&quot;figure image mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:700px&quot;&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:700px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img height=&quot;2965&quot; width=&quot;700&quot; alt=&quot;reduce, reuse, recycle infographic large jpg image&quot; title=&quot;reduce, reuse, recycle infographic large jpg image&quot; class=&quot;media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2014-12/ful_infogrphc_700px.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2014 19:10:10 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>eocampo</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">68763 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Think Green Before You Shop</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/recycle/think-green-you-shop</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;01&quot; id=&quot;01&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;figure image mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:750px&quot;&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:750px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Be green! When youre out shopping, carefully choose what you buy and how much of it.&quot; title=&quot;Partial image banner from the infographic Think Before You Shop&quot; height=&quot;1107&quot; width=&quot;750&quot; class=&quot;media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2014-11/infogrphc_1a_1.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;02&quot; id=&quot;02&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;figure image mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:750px&quot;&gt;
	&lt;div class=&quot;figure image mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:750px&quot;&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:750px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Be green! When youre out shopping, carefully choose what you buy and how much of it.&quot; title=&quot;Partial image banner from the infographic Think Green Before You Shop&quot; height=&quot;1242&quot; width=&quot;750&quot; class=&quot;media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2014-11/infogrphc_2a.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

	&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;03&quot; id=&quot;03&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

	&lt;div class=&quot;figure image mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:750px&quot;&gt;
		&lt;div class=&quot;figure image mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:750px&quot;&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:750px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Be green! When youre out shopping, carefully choose what you buy and how much of it.&quot; title=&quot;Partial image banner from the infographic Think Green Before You Shop&quot; height=&quot;1012&quot; width=&quot;750&quot; class=&quot;media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2014-11/infogrphc_3a.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2014 20:14:51 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>eocampo</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">67433 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  </channel>
</rss>

<!-- Page cached by Boost @ 2017-01-26 04:20:18, expires @ 2017-01-26 16:20:18, lifetime 12 hours -->