<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?><rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.epa.gov/feed/128115/rss.xml" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/" xmlns:og="http://ogp.me/ns#" xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#" xmlns:sioc="http://rdfs.org/sioc/ns#" xmlns:sioct="http://rdfs.org/sioc/types#" xmlns:skos="http://www.w3.org/2004/02/skos/core#" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#">
  <channel>
    <title>Acid Rain</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/feed/128115/rss.xml</link>
    <description>Updated Acid Rain content from the US Environmental Protection Agency</description>
    <language>en</language>
     <atom:link href="https://www.epa.gov/feed/128115/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      <item>
    <title>Effects of Acid Rain</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/acidrain/effects-acid-rain</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;On this Page:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#ecosystems&quot;&gt;Effects of Acid Rain on Ecosystems&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#materials&quot;&gt;Effects of Acid Rain on Materials&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#other&quot;&gt;Other Effects of SO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; and NO&lt;sub&gt;X&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#visability&quot;&gt;Visibility&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#health&quot;&gt;Human Health&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;ecosystems&quot; name=&quot;ecosystems&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The Effects of Acid Rain on Ecosystems&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;fish&quot; name=&quot;fish&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-png right view-mode-full caption&quot; style=&quot;width:250px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Graph showing level of acidity that is tolerable to various species of aquatic life&quot; height=&quot;396&quot; width=&quot;250&quot; class=&quot;right media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2016-03/fishkillgraphic2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;figcaption&quot;&gt;This figure illustrates the pH level at which key organisms may be lost as their environment becomes more acidic. Not all fish, shellfish, or the insects that they eat can tolerate the same amount of acid.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An ecosystem is a community of plants, animals and other organisms along with their environment including the air, water and soil. Everything in an ecosystem is connected. If something harms one part of an ecosystem – one species of plant or animal, the soil or the water – it can have an impact on everything else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Effects of Acid Rain on Fish and Wildlife&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ecological effects of acid rain are most clearly seen in aquatic environments, such as streams, lakes, and marshes where it can be harmful to fish and other wildlife. As it flows through the soil, acidic rain water can leach aluminum from soil clay particles and then flow into streams and lakes. The more acid that is introduced to the ecosystem, the more aluminum is released.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some types of plants and animals are able to tolerate acidic waters and moderate amounts of aluminum. Others, however, are acid-sensitive and will be lost as the pH declines. Generally, the young of most species are more sensitive to environmental conditions than adults. At pH 5, most fish eggs cannot hatch. At lower pH levels, some adult fish die. Some acidic lakes have no fish. Even if a species of fish or animal can tolerate moderately acidic water, the animals or plants it eats might not. For example, frogs have a critical pH around 4, but the mayflies they eat are more sensitive and may not survive pH below 5.5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;plants&quot; name=&quot;plants&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Effects of Acid Rain on Plants and Trees&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dead or dying trees are a common sight in areas effected by acid rain. Acid rain leaches aluminum from the soil.  That aluminum may be harmful to plants as well as animals. Acid rain also removes minerals and nutrients from the soil that trees need to grow. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At high elevations, acidic fog and clouds might strip nutrients from trees’ foliage, leaving them with brown or dead leaves and needles. The trees are then less able to absorb sunlight, which makes them weak and less able to withstand freezing temperatures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;buffering&quot; name=&quot;buffering&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Buffering Capacity&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many forests, streams, and lakes that experience acid rain don’t suffer effects because the soil in those areas can &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;buffer&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; the acid rain by neutralizing the acidity in the rainwater flowing through it. This capacity depends on the thickness and composition of the soil and the type of bedrock underneath it. In areas such as mountainous parts of the Northeast United States, the soil is thin and lacks the ability to adequately neutralize the acid in the rain water. As a result, these areas are particularly vulnerable and the acid and aluminum can accumulate in the soil, streams, or lakes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;episodic&quot; name=&quot;episodic&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Episodic Acidification&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Melting snow and heavy rain downpours can result in what is known as episodic acidification. Lakes that do not normally have a high level of acidity may temporarily experience effects of acid rain when the melting snow or downpour brings greater amounts of acidic deposition and the soil can’t buffer it. This short duration of higher acidity (i.e., lower pH) can result in a short-term stress on the ecosystem where a variety of organisms or species may be injured or killed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;nitrogen&quot; name=&quot;nitrogen&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Nitrogen Pollution&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not just the acidity of acid rain that can cause problems. Acid rain also contains nitrogen, and this can have an impact on some ecosystems. For example, nitrogen pollution in our coastal waters is partially responsible for declining fish and shellfish populations in some areas. In addition to agriculture and wastewater, much of the nitrogen produced by human activity that reaches coastal waters comes from the atmosphere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/nutrientpollution&quot;&gt;Learn more about Nitrogen Pollution&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/aboutepa/about-chesapeake-bay-program-office&quot;&gt;EPA&#039;s Chesapeake Bay Program Office&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;materials&quot; name=&quot;materials&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Effects of Acid Rain on Materials&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not all acidic deposition is &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;wet&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. Sometimes dust particles can become acidic as well, and this is called &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;dry deposition&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. When acid rain and dry acidic particles fall to earth, the nitric and sulfuric acid that make the particles acidic can land on statues, buildings, and other manmade structures, and damage their surfaces. The acidic particles corrode metal and cause paint and stone to deteriorate more quickly. They also dirty the surfaces of buildings and other structures such as monuments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consequences of this damage can be costly:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;damaged materials that need to be repaired or replaced,&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;increased maintenance costs, and&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;loss of detail on stone and metal statues, monuments and tombstones.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;other&quot; name=&quot;other&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Other Effects of SO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; and NO&lt;sub&gt;X&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;visability&quot; name=&quot;visability&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Visibility&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the atmosphere, SO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; and NO&lt;sub&gt;X&lt;/sub&gt; gases are transformed into sulfate and nitrate particles, and the NO&lt;sub&gt;X&lt;/sub&gt; can react with other pollutants to form ozone. These particles make the air hazy and difficult to see through. This affects our enjoyment of national parks that we visit for the scenic view such as Shenandoah and the Great Smoky Mountains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/visibility&quot;&gt;Learn more about Visability and Regional Haze&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;health&quot; name=&quot;health&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Human Health&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Walking in acid rain, or even swimming in an acid lake, is no more dangerous to humans than walking or swimming in clean water. However, the pollutants that cause acid rain, and their particulates — SO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; and NO&lt;sub&gt;X,&lt;/sub&gt; sulfate and nitrate particles—do damage human health.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; and NO&lt;sub&gt;X&lt;/sub&gt; react in the atmosphere to form fine sulfate and nitrate particles that people can inhale into their lungs. Many scientific studies have shown a relationship between these particles and heart and lung disorders, such as asthma and bronchitis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Learn more about:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www3.epa.gov/airquality/sulfurdioxide/&quot;&gt;Sulfur Dioxide&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www3.epa.gov/airquality/nitrogenoxides/&quot;&gt;Nitrogen Oxides&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www3.epa.gov/pm/&quot;&gt;Particulate Matter (PM)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/asthma&quot;&gt;Asthma&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;In addition, NO&lt;/span&gt;&lt;sub&gt;X&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;span&gt; emissions also contribute to ground level ozone. Ozone harms human health in a number of ways, including asthma and emphysema.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/ozone-pollution&quot;&gt;Learn more about Ground Level Ozone&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 16 Mar 2016 20:29:47 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cwalke</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">139191 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>What is Acid Rain?</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/acidrain/what-acid-rain</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;Acid rain, or acid deposition, is a broad term that includes any form of precipitation with acidic components, such as sulfuric or nitric acid that fall to the ground from the atmosphere in wet or dry forms.  This can include rain, snow, fog, hail or even dust that is acidic.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;What Causes Acid Rain?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-png right view-mode-media_original&quot; style=&quot;width:450px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;This image illustrates the pathway for acid rain in our environment.&quot; height=&quot;450&quot; width=&quot;450&quot; class=&quot;right media-element file-media-original&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/2016-03/450x375_acidrainpathway_3-28.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;Acid rain results when sulfur dioxide (SO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;) and nitrogen oxides (NO&lt;sub&gt;X&lt;/sub&gt;) are emitted into the atmosphere and transported by wind and air currents.  The SO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; and NO&lt;sub&gt;X&lt;/sub&gt; react with water, oxygen and other chemicals to form sulfuric and nitric acids.  These then mix with water and other materials before falling to the ground.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While a small portion of the SO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; and NO&lt;sub&gt;X&lt;/sub&gt; that cause acid rain is from natural sources such as volcanoes, most of it comes from the burning of fossil fuels.  The major sources of SO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; and NO&lt;sub&gt;X&lt;/sub&gt; in the atmosphere are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Burning of fossil fuels to generate electricity.  Two thirds of SO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; and one fourth of NO&lt;sub&gt;X&lt;/sub&gt; in the atmosphere come from electric power generators.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Vehicles and heavy equipment.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Manufacturing, oil refineries and other industries.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Winds can blow SO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; and NO&lt;sub&gt;X&lt;/sub&gt; over long distances and across borders making acid rain a problem for everyone and not just those who live close to these sources. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Forms of Acid Deposition&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Wet Deposition&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wet deposition is what we most commonly think of as &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;acid rain&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.  The sulfuric and nitric acids formed in the atmosphere fall to the ground mixed with rain, snow, fog, or hail.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Dry Deposition&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Acidic particles and gases can also deposit from the atmosphere in the absence of moisture as &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;dry deposition&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.  The acidic particles and gases may deposit to surfaces (water bodies, vegetation, buildings) quickly or may react during atmospheric transport to form larger particles that can be harmful to human health. When the accumulated acids are washed off a surface by the next rain, this acidic water flows over and through the ground, and can harm plants and wildlife, such as insects and fish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The amount of acidity in the atmosphere that deposits to earth through dry deposition depends on the amount of rainfall an area receives.  For example, in desert areas the ratio of dry to wet deposition is higher than an area that receives several inches of rain each year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Measuring Acid Rain&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-png right view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:500px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;A diagram showing where various substances fall on the pH scale.&quot; title=&quot;A diagram showing where various substances fall on the pH scale.&quot; height=&quot;350&quot; width=&quot;500&quot; class=&quot;center media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2016-03/500x350_phscale_3-2.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;Acidity and alkalinity are measured using a pH scale for which 7.0 is neutral. The lower a substance&#039;s pH (less than 7), the more acidic it is; the higher a substance&#039;s pH (greater than 7), the more alkaline it is. Normal rain has a pH of about 5.6; it is slightly acidic because carbon dioxide (CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;) dissolves into it forming weak carbonic acid.  Acid rain usually has a pH between 4.2 and 4.4.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Policymakers, research scientists, ecologists, and modelers rely on the National Atmospheric Deposition Program’s (NADP) National Trends Network (NTN) for measurements of wet deposition. The NADP/NTN collects acid rain at more than 250 monitoring sites throughout the US, Canada, Alaska, Hawaii and the US Virgin Islands. Unlike wet deposition, dry deposition is difficult and expensive to measure. Dry deposition estimates for nitrogen and sulfur pollutants are provided by the Clean Air Status and Trends Network (CASTNET). Air concentrations are measured by CASTNET at more than 90 locations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When acid deposition is washed into lakes and streams, it can cause some to turn acidic. The Long-Term Monitoring (LTM) Network measures and monitors surface water chemistry at over 280 sites to provide valuable information on aquatic ecosystem health and how water bodies respond to changes in acid-causing emissions and acid deposition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Learn more about:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
	&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/castnet&quot;&gt;Clean Air Status and Trends Network (CASTNET)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://nadp.isws.illinois.edu/&quot;&gt;National Atmospheric Deposition Program (NADP)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/airmarkets/monitoring-surface-water-chemistry&quot;&gt;Long-Term Monitoring (LTM) Network &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 09 Feb 2016 17:10:27 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>mbanta</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">134679 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Contact Us About Acid Rain</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/acidrain/forms/contact-us-about-acid-rain</link>
    <description>&lt;div class=&quot;box right&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;box left&quot; href=&quot;/tips&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Report an environmental violation&quot; src=&quot;/sites/all/themes/epa/img/badge.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

	&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/tips&quot;&gt;Report a Violation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

	&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;Report possible violations of environmental laws and regulations.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Please use the form below to send us comments or questions. Be sure to include your e-mail address if you’d like a response.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Call the Acid Rain Hotline: 202-343-9620&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Regular or certified mail:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;US EPA&lt;br /&gt;
	Clean Air Markets Division&lt;br /&gt;
	1200 Pennsylvania Avenue, NW&lt;br /&gt;
	Mail Code 6204M&lt;br /&gt;
	Washington, DC 20460&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Overnight mail:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;US EPA&lt;br /&gt;
	Clean Air Markets Division (6204M)&lt;br /&gt;
	1201 Constitution Avenue, NW&lt;br /&gt;
	Room 7231B&lt;br /&gt;
	Washington, DC 20004&lt;br /&gt;
	Tel: (202) 343-9790&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 03 Dec 2015 01:17:24 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>mhesslin</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">128119 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  </channel>
</rss>

<!-- Page cached by Boost @ 2017-01-26 04:17:36, expires @ 2017-01-26 16:17:36, lifetime 12 hours -->