<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?><rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.epa.gov/feed/45675/rss.xml" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/" xmlns:og="http://ogp.me/ns#" xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#" xmlns:sioc="http://rdfs.org/sioc/ns#" xmlns:sioct="http://rdfs.org/sioc/types#" xmlns:skos="http://www.w3.org/2004/02/skos/core#" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#">
  <channel>
    <title>Sustainable Marketplace: Greener Products and Services</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/feed/45675/rss.xml</link>
    <description>Updated Sustainable Marketplace: Greener Products and Services content from the US Environmental Protection Agency</description>
    <language>en</language>
     <atom:link href="https://www.epa.gov/feed/45675/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      <item>
    <title>Assessment Summaries of Environmental Performance Standards and Ecolabels for Federal Procurement</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/greenerproducts/assessment-summaries-environmental-performance-standards-and-ecolabels-federal</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;The assessment summaries below provide detailed information regarding the standards and ecolabels in &lt;a href=&quot;/greenerproducts/recommendations-specifications-standards-and-ecolabels-federal-purchasing&quot;&gt;EPA’s Recommendations&lt;/a&gt;. For each standard and ecolabel, these summaries outline:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Whether it aligns with applicable federal programs; and&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;How it addressess the four sections outlined in the Guidelines:
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Section I: Process for Developing Standards;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Section II: Environmental Effectiveness of the Standard;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Section III: Conformity Assessment;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Section IV: Management of Ecolabel Programs.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt; The assessments were based upon &lt;a href=&quot;/greenerproducts/draft-guidelines-product-environmental-performance-standards-and-ecolabels-voluntary&quot;&gt;EPA’s Guidelines for Environmental Performance Standards and Ecolabels&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-341659&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-12/documents/carpet-assessment_summary_0.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=498527&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Carpet Standard/ Ecolabel Assessment Summary (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(3 pp, 499 K, 
  01/03/2017)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-341661&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-12/documents/flooring-assessment_summary_0.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=516816&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Flooring Standard/ Ecolabel Assessment Summary (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(4 pp, 517 K, 
  01/03/2017)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-341665&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-12/documents/interiorlatexpaint-assessment_summary_0.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=490066&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Interior Latex Paint Standard/ Ecolabel Assessment Summary (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(3 pp, 490 K, 
  01/03/2017)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-342745&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2017-01/documents/furniture_assessmentsummary.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=537047&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Furniture Assessment Summary (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(4 pp, 537 K, 
  01/03/2017)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 20 Dec 2016 18:09:32 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>kdonner</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">167565 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Footnotes - Recommendations of Specifications, Standards, and Ecolabels for Federal Purchasing</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/greenerproducts/footnotes-recommendations-specifications-standards-and-ecolabels-federal-purchasing</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;This page contains footnotes for EPA&#039;s &quot;&lt;a href=&quot;/greenerproducts/recommendations-specifications-standards-and-ecolabels-federal-purchasing&quot;&gt;Recommendations of Specifications, Standards, and Ecolabels&lt;/a&gt;&quot; for federal purchasers. The Recommendations provide guidance on the use of private sector environmental performance standards and ecolabels in order assist federal purchasers in identifying and procuring environmentally sustainable products and services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Footnotes:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;1&quot; name=&quot;1&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;vertical-align:baseline&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Recommendation based on EPA’s assessment per the &lt;a href=&quot;/greenerproducts/final-pilot-assessment-guidelines-epas-recommendations-standards-and-ecolabels&quot;&gt;2016 Pilot Guidelines&lt;/a&gt;. For more information on the Pilot and the assessment results, please &lt;a class=&quot;menu-internal&quot; href=&quot;#tab-1&quot;&gt;visit the Background section&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;/greenerproducts/assessment-summaries-environmental-performance-standards-and-ecolabels-federal&quot;&gt;Assessment Summaries for Carpet, Interior Latex Paints, Flooring, and Furniture&lt;/a&gt; are available for more detailed information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;2&quot; name=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;vertical-align:baseline&quot;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Recommendation based on DOE’s Office of Sustainability Support analysis. For further information on this voluntary program, see:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://sftool.gov/greenprocurement/doe&quot;&gt;DOE’s Full Priority Products List&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fedcenter.gov/Documents/index.cfm?id=28226&amp;amp;amp;pge_id=1854&quot;&gt;DOE’s Background and Evaluation Process&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;3&quot; name=&quot;3&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;vertical-align:baseline&quot;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; Recommendation based on GSA’s Public Buildings Service analysis. For further information, see:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gsa.gov/portal/directive/d0/content/664134&quot;&gt;GSA’s Key Sustainable Products&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gsa.gov/portal/getMediaData?mediaId=239595&quot;&gt;GSA’s Background and Evaluation Process&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;*&quot; id=&quot;*&quot;&gt;*&lt;/a&gt; This standard does not meet baseline criteria in Section I of EPA’s Guidelines, which contains the requirements necessary to demonstrate that a standard is a Voluntary Consensus Standard (VCS).  Section 12(d) of The National Technology Transfer and Advancement Act (NTTAA, PL 103-114) calls federal agencies to use Voluntary Consensus Standards (VCS) in lieu of government-unique standards in their procurement and regulatory activities, except where inconsistent with law or otherwise impractical.  Section 5(e) of the Office of Management and Budget Circular A-119 (OMB A-119) further outlines factors that individual agencies should evaluate when determining whether to use standards, on a case by case basis. This includes the extent to which the standards development process reflected the attributes of a VCS body. &lt;a href=&quot;https://standards.gov/icsp/query/members.cfm&quot;&gt;Federal agency representatives can contact their agency’s Standards Executive for assistance in determining whether this standard should be considered for use by the agency&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;**&quot; id=&quot;**&quot;&gt;**&lt;/a&gt; These certification programs do not meet baseline criteria in Section III of EPA’s guidelines, which contains the requirements necessary to demonstrate that a conformity assessment body is competent to assess conformance with the standard and follows general good practice specific to conformity assessment for environmental performance standards. An alternative method to demonstrate that a conformity assessment body is competent to assess conformance to this standard is proof of accreditation by an accreditation body that is a signatory to the International Accreditation Forum Multilateral Recognition Arrangement (IAF MLA) for a scope including ISO/IEC 17065 and this applicable standard.  Guidance on Federal Conformity Assessment (15 CFR Part 287) directs federal agencies to identify appropriate private sector conformity assessment practices and programs (including third-party certification) and consider the results of such practices and/or programs as appropriate in procurement activities.  The Guidance stresses that responsibility for the determination of appropriateness rests with each agency. &lt;a href=&quot;https://standards.gov/icsp/query/members.cfm&quot;&gt;Federal agency representatives can contact their agency’s Standards Executive for assistance in determining whether this standard should be considered for use by the agency&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;††&quot; id=&quot;††&quot;&gt;†&lt;/a&gt; Please note that the following recommendations do not currently consider the standards’/ecolabels’/certifications’ effectiveness in addressing the potential environmental impacts of material harvesting and/or extraction. EPA intends to address that important lifecycle stage of a product in the Recommendations in 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;^&quot; id=&quot;^&quot;&gt;^&lt;/a&gt; EPA did not specifically solicit textile standards/ecolabels for the pilot. There could be others that are interested in being assessed per the Guidelines and considered for EPA’s Recommendations in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 20 Dec 2016 16:03:17 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>kdonner</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">167553 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Draft Options for Panel and Governance Committee Feedback based on EPA’s Pilot Assessment of Standards and Ecolabels for Federal Purchasers</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/greenerproducts/draft-options-panel-and-governance-committee-feedback-based-epas-pilot-assessment</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;This document was used to obtain feedback from the Governance Committee members on several aspects of the pilot program&#039;s measurements, models and potential approaches to evaluating product categories. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-339431&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-12/documents/draft_options_for_gc_and_panel_feedback_10-2016.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=1164691&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;EPP Pilot to Assess Standards and Ecolabels for EPA’s Recommendations to Federal Agencies - Options for Panel and Governance Committee Feedback (DRAFT) (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(42 pp, 1 MB)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Mon, 19 Dec 2016 15:06:43 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>tgelaber</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">167461 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Final PILOT Assessment Guidelines for EPA’s Recommendations of Standards and Ecolabels</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/greenerproducts/final-pilot-assessment-guidelines-epas-recommendations-standards-and-ecolabels</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;This document details the final guidelines used for the pilot assessment in three product categories for EPA&#039;s Recommended Standards and Ecolabels for use by federal agencies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-342153&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-12/documents/guidelines_-_final_pilot_guidelines_-_clean_12-29-2016_1.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=379556&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;EPP Pilot to Assess Standards and Ecolabels for EPA&amp;#039;s Recommendations to Federal Agencies - Final PILOT Assessment Guidelines12-29-2016.pdf (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(23 pp, 380 K, 
  December 2016)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Mon, 19 Dec 2016 14:53:48 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>jlarkin</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">167459 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Charter &amp; Operating Procedures for the Guidelines Pilot Governance Committee</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/greenerproducts/charter-operating-procedures-guidelines-pilot-governance-committee</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;This document outlines the charge given to the governance committee which oversaw the testing of EPA&#039;s guidelines for environmental perfomance standards and ecolabels by separate panels in select pilot areas  It details the bylaws and the procedures by which the governance committee operated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-339407&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-12/documents/testing_epas_draft_guidelines-charter_and_operating_procedures.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=168945&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Testing EPAs Draft Gidelines Charter and Operating Procedures (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(6 pp, 169 K, 
  September 2015)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Mon, 19 Dec 2016 14:42:15 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>tgelaber</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">167455 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Independent Assessment Entity (IAE) Findings and Recommendations Report on Recommended Standards and Ecolabels initial pilot results.</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/greenerproducts/independent-assessment-entity-iae-findings-and-recommendations-report-recommended</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;EPA Guidelines Pilot for Assessing Standards and Ecolabels for Federal Government Procurement: Draft Independent Assessment Entity (IAE) Findings and Recommendations Report completed 13 September 2016&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Industrial Economics, Inc. (IEc), under contract to Resolve and EPA, was commissioned to independently assess the responses provided by volunteer standards, certifiers, and ecolabel programs to meeting EPA’s pilot criteria for federal procurement. The assessment criteria were based on the draft Guidelines for Assessing Environmental Performance Standards and Ecolabels for Federal Procurement, and further developed and refined by the three product category panels (furniture, flooring, and paints &amp;amp; coatings) and Governance Committee, groups facilitated by Resolve in 2015 and 2016. The assessment took place between June and August, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-339261&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-12/documents/iae_findings_and_recommendations_report_09-13-16.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=1360969&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;EPA Guidelines Pilot for Assessing Standards and Ecolabels for Federal Government Procurement (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(51 pp, 1 MB, 
  September 2016)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;field field-name-field-document-description field-type-text field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    This is the description.  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Mon, 19 Dec 2016 13:17:45 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>tgelaber</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">167449 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Department of Interior Focuses on Cleaning Products</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/greenerproducts/department-interior-focuses-cleaning-products</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.doi.gov/&quot;&gt;U.S. Department of the Interior (DOI)&lt;/a&gt; recognizes the importance of a clean working environment that also is healthy and safe. In November 1998, in an effort to procure recycled-content products and to address concerns over the indoor air quality in its Main and South Interior Buildings in downtown Washington, DC, DOI embarked on a quest to initiate a contract for custodial services (e.g., window washing, floor stripping, maintaining restroom supplies) using environmentally preferable cleaning products and supplies. The Department decided to make environmental preferability a significant factor in the selection of the new contractor and included &quot;greening&quot; language in the solicitation. The 5-year, $6.28 million contract (including option years) for cleaning 1.4 million square feet of office space was awarded in August 1999.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Environmentally Preferable Products&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the contract solicitation, DOI established both &quot;mandatory&quot; and &quot;desirable&quot; characteristics for evaluating five categories of cleaning products and recycled-content products such as bathroom tissue and paper towels. Mandatory characteristics were rated on a pass or fail basis. Desirable characteristics were those above and beyond the mandatory requirements and that DOI determined would result in a more environmentally favorable product. In determining which environmental characteristics would be mandatory under the contract, DOI considered those that were relevant locally (e.g., prohibiting the use of products that contain &lt;a href=&quot;http://nepis.epa.gov/Exe/ZyPURL.cgi?Dockey=2000VYFY.TXT&quot;&gt;&quot;Toxics of Concern&quot; to the Chesapeake Bay&lt;/a&gt;) those that would make a significant environmental difference (e.g., preferring restroom paper products with a high percentage of postconsumer recycled content that were not deinked or bleached using elemental chlorine), and those that would be healthier for its employees (e.g., cleaners that minimize irritation to the respiratory system, eyes, and skin).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Cleaning Products&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In designing its solicitation strategy for chemical cleaning products, DOI first counted the number of cleaning products currently being used in the buildings - 19 products in all. The DOI team, which included technical staff, building management personnel, and legal representatives, developed the contract solicitation in part by reviewing environmental attributes used by Santa Monica, California, in its custodial contracts, as well as the &lt;a href=&quot;/nepis.epa.gov/Exe/ZyPURL.cgi?Dockey=20000WW3.TXT&quot;&gt;U.S. General Services Administration&#039;s (GSA&#039;s) cleaning products pilot project&lt;/a&gt; and the Environmental Protection Agency&#039;s (EPA&#039;s) cleaning products wizard. In the solicitation, DOI requested that bidders identify five products by brand name in five representative chemical cleaning product categories that they would use if awarded the contract. These categories included: all-purpose cleaner, general degreaser, general disinfectant, floor stripper, and bathroom cleaner. Bidders were required to include material safety data sheets or other product information to substantiate claims made about the products.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though DOI only evaluated five categories of cleaning products, it required the successful bidder to meet or exceed mandatory criteria for all 19 cleaning products used at DOI. The mandatory characteristics DOI chose included the following restrictions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;No Chesapeake Bay Toxics of Concern or EPA 33/50 Program 17 Target Priority Pollutants.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;No sealed aerosol spray cans.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;No carcinogens.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;No hazardous wastes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;DOI gave more favorable consideration to bidders who included products with the following desirable characteristics:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Minimal skin, eye, and respiratory irritation.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Biodegradability.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Avoidance of undesirable or unnecessary dyes and fragrances.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Recyclable containers and minimization of nonrecyclable waste.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Recycled-Content Products and Other Environmental Attributes&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DOI is fully committed to the goals of the &lt;a href=&quot;/smm/comprehensive-procurement-guideline-cpg-program&quot;&gt;Comprehensive Procurement Guidelines (CPG)&lt;/a&gt;, EPA&#039;s program that designates recycled-content products for purchase by federal agencies and recommends recycled-content levels for those products. To achieve compliance with this program, DOI required bidders to identify specific brands of recycled-content products meeting the CPG recommendations that they proposed to use under the contract for the following product categories:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Bathroom tissue - minimum 100 percent recovered materials and 20 percent postconsumer content.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Toilet seat covers - minimum 100 percent recovered materials and 40 percent postconsumer content.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Paper towels and general purpose industrial wipes - minimum 100 percent recovered materials and 40 percent postconsumer content.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Plastic trash bags - minimum of 25 percent postconsumer content.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;DOI also included desirable characteristics for recycled-content products in its solicitation, which would earn bidders more favorable consideration. These features included the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;No use of deinking solvents containing chlorine or any other chemicals listed in the Toxics Release Inventory in the manufacture of paper products.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;No use of chlorine or chlorine derivatives in bleaching processes for paper products.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Additional recycled-content products (e.g., cleaning supply carts, waste collection carts) and use of higher postconsumer recycled-content percentages than those required for the five product categories.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;In addition to their ability to provide environmentally preferable chemical cleaning products and recycled-content products, bidders were requested to demonstrate their ability to develop and implement strategies to enhance recycling in the building. Bidders were asked to explain how their services would help DOI accomplish the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Efficiently collect and manage recovered materials.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Monitor the volume of waste and recyclables recovered.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Measure the rate of employee participation in the recycling program.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Promote participation and avoid contamination of recovered materials.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Ensure custodial staff participated fully in these efforts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Finally, to help ensure successful implementation of these green efforts, the contract calls for the contractor to have one person identified as the Stewardship Coordinator. This individual will be the point person for all environmental performance issues under the contract and will facilitate a Cleaning Stewardship Committee composed of custodial employees as well as building management and building tenants. The idea of the Stewardship Committee was drawn from the new &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.astm.org/cgi-bin/resolver.cgi?E1971&quot;&gt;ASTM standard E-1971&lt;/a&gt;, &quot;Stewardship in the Cleaning of Commercial and Institutional Buildings.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Cost Considerations&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cost was obviously a consideration as DOI moved forward with this effort. Staff wondered if services they deemed environmentally preferable would cost more. As it turned out, the bid selected as the most environmentally preferable also had the best overall cleaning operations plan. In addition, the same bid had the lowest price of those under consideration. Establishing best value to the government was not difficult under these circumstances. Finally, as an added surprise, the new contract cost projected over the 5-year, full option period will cost significantly less than the previous custodial contract, mainly because the contract is written to be performance-based. For example, instead of vacuuming every day, the contractor will vacuum only when carpets are dirty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Lessons Learned&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DOI was pleased with the solicitation process and would follow a similar procedure for future environmentally preferable purchases. DOI believes that incorporating requirements for environmentally preferable purchasing into service contracts is critical to the realization of the affirmative procurement goals of the &lt;a href=&quot;/rcra&quot;&gt;Resource Conservation and Recovery Act (RCRA)&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/greenerproducts/executive-order-13101-greening-government-through-waste-prevention-recycling-and&quot;&gt;Executive Order (EO) 13101&lt;/a&gt;, and other environmental purchasing mandates, since these types of contracts have a large indirect purchasing component. In fact, DOI staff members are chairing the interagency workgroup charged with creating model language for revising service contracts typically used by government including fleet management services, facility operations and maintenance, cafeteria services, construction, space leases, groundskeeping and landscape services, conference services, and waste disposal. In addition, DOI feels it would be an enormous benefit to integrate environmental attributes into &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gsaadvantage.gov/advantage/main/start_page.do&quot;&gt;GSA Advantage&lt;/a&gt;, so that it would be clear to purchasers what products they should be buying to comply with RCRA or EO 13101.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information on DOI&#039;s custodial services contract, contact Heather Davies of DOI at 202 208-7884 or &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:heather_davies@ios.doi.gov&quot;&gt;heather_davies@ios.doi.gov&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 04 Feb 2016 17:34:23 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>tgelaber</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">134193 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Executive Order 13101—Greening the Government Through Waste Prevention, Recycling, and Federal Acquisition</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/greenerproducts/executive-order-13101-greening-government-through-waste-prevention-recycling-and</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;It is the national policy to prefer pollution prevention, whenever feasible. Pollution that cannot be prevented should be recycled; pollution that cannot be prevented or recycled should be treated in an environmentally safe manner. Disposal should be employed only as a last resort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Agencies shall comply with executive branch policies for the acquisition and use of environmentally preferable products and services and implement cost-effective procurement preference programs favoring the purchase of these products and services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This order creates a Steering Committee, a Federal Environmental Executive (FEE), and a Task Force, and establishes Agency Environmental Executive (AEE) positions within each agency, to be responsible for ensuring 	the implementation of this order. The FEE, AEEs, and members of the Steering Committee and Task Force shall be full-time Federal Government employees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-247039&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-01/documents/13101.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=99460&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Executive Order 13101 (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(11 pp, 99 K, 
  September 16, 1998)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 14 Jan 2016 17:39:43 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>tgelaber</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">131981 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Environmental Labeling Issues, Policies, and Practices Worldwide</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/greenerproducts/environmental-labeling-issues-policies-and-practices-worldwide</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;The report presents a snapshot of the major environmental labeling programs in existence during the research phase for which information was available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-201945&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-09/documents/wwlabel3.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=1492637&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Environmental Labeling Issues, Policies, and Practices Worldwide (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(322 pp, 1 MB, 
  December 1998, 
  EPA 742-R-98-009)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 24 Sep 2015 21:34:29 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cguthrie</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">117157 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  </channel>
</rss>

<!-- Page cached by Boost @ 2017-01-26 04:15:07, expires @ 2017-01-26 16:15:07, lifetime 12 hours -->