<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?><rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.epa.gov/feed/51119/rss.xml" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/" xmlns:og="http://ogp.me/ns#" xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#" xmlns:sioc="http://rdfs.org/sioc/ns#" xmlns:sioct="http://rdfs.org/sioc/types#" xmlns:skos="http://www.w3.org/2004/02/skos/core#" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#">
  <channel>
    <title>Biosolids</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/feed/51119/rss.xml</link>
    <description>Updated Biosolids content from the US Environmental Protection Agency</description>
    <language>en</language>
     <atom:link href="https://www.epa.gov/feed/51119/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      <item>
    <title>Basic Information about Biosolids</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/biosolids/basic-information-about-biosolids</link>
    <description>&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;The term sewage sludge is used in EPA regulations that establish a protective regulatory framework to manage the use and disposal of sewage sludge.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;The terms &lt;em&gt;biosolids&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;sewage sludge &lt;/em&gt;are&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;often used interchangeably.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;When properly treated and processed, sewage sludge becomes biosolids which are nutrient-rich organic materials produced from wastewater treatment facilities.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Biosolids can be recycled and applied as fertilizer to improve and maintain productive soils and stimulate plant growth.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Effective sewage sludge and biosolids management options help ensure that useful materials are recycled on land and harmful materials are not released to water bodies.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 13 Jul 2016 14:59:09 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>rrsteven</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">154727 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Peer Review Standards for the Disposal of Sewage Sludge</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/biosolids/peer-review-standards-disposal-sewage-sludge</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;In 1989 the Cooperative State Research Service Technical Committee W-170, with the assistance of experts from EPA, academia, environmental groups, and units of state and local government agencies, organized a Peer Review Committee which conducted a review of the Environmental Protection Agency 40 CFR Parts 257 and 503 Standards for the Disposal of Sewage Sludge Proposed Rule.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-279387&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-04/documents/40_cfr_part_503_peer_review_1989.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=8273365&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Peer Review Standards for the Disposal of Sewage Sludge Proposed Rule 40 CFR Parts 257 and 503 (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(146 pp, 8 MB, 
  July 24, 1989)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 18:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>rrsteven</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">147087 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>EPA Office of Inspector General</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/biosolids/epa-office-inspector-general</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;The EPA&#039;s Office of Inspector General (OIG) is an independent office within EPA that helps the agency protect the environment in a more efficient and cost effective manner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/office-inspector-general/about-epas-office-inspector-general&quot;&gt;EPA Office of Inspector General&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The OIG evaluated the effectiveness of the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency’s (EPA’s) programs in preventing and addressing contamination of surface water from hazardous chemicals passing through publicly owned treatment works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The OIG made recommendations to the EPA develop a format for sharing annual Toxics Release Inventory data, develop a list of chemicals beyond the priority pollutants list for inclusion in permits, confirm compliance with the hazardous waste notification requirement, and track required submittals of toxicity tests and violations. Final determinations on matters in the report were made by EPA managers in accordance with established audit resolution procedures. All recommendations are resolved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-185969&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-09/documents/more_action_is_needed_to_protect_water_resources_from_unmonitored_hazardous_chemicals_2014.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=1123541&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;More Action is Needed to Protect Water Resources From Unmonitored Hazardous Chemicals (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(31 pp, 1 MB, 
  September 2014, 
  14-P-0363)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 02 Sep 2015 13:45:42 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>rkearney</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">110643 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Uniform Federal Policy for Quality Assurance Project Plans</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/biosolids/uniform-federal-policy-quality-assurance-project-plans</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;The &lt;i&gt;Uniform Federal Policy for Quality Assurance Project Plans &lt;/i&gt;(the UFP-QAPP Manual), prepared by the Intergovernmental Data Quality Task Force (IDQTF), provides instructions for preparing Quality Assurance Project Plans (QAPPs). The UFP-QAPP Manual was developed IDQTF, a joint initiative between the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency (EPA), the Department of Defense (DoD), and the Department of Energy (DOE). The purpose of the Manual is to provide a single national consensus document for consistently and systematically implementing the project-specific QAPP requirements across the Federal agencies involved in the IDQTF (currently EPA, DoD, and DOE). In addition, implementation of the UFP-QAPP Manual will help to ensure the quality, objectivity, utility, and integrity of environmental information that the Federal government disseminates as required by EPA&#039;s Information Quality Guidelines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-164237&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-07/documents/ufp_qapp_v1_0305.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=1881665&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Uniform Federal Policy for Quality Assurance Project Plans (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(177 pp, 2 MB, 
  March 2005, 
  EPA: EPA-505-B-04-9)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-164285&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-07/documents/epa_infoqualityguidelines_0.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=917387&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;EPA Information Quality Guidelines (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(61 pp, 917 K, 
  October 2002, 
  EPA/260R-02-008)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jul 2015 13:33:04 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>rrsteven</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">99661 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Frequent Questions about Biosolids</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/biosolids/frequent-questions-about-biosolids</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;These are answers to some of the more frequently asked questions about sewage sludge and biosolids.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;accordion&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot; class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#pane-1&quot;&gt;1) What are Biosolids?&lt;/a&gt;

		&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;pane-1&quot;&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;They are nutrient-rich organic materials resulting from the treatment of domestic sewage in a treatment facility. When treated and processed, these residuals can be recycled and applied as fertilizer to improve and maintain productive soils and stimulate plant growth.&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot; class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#pane-2&quot;&gt;2) What is the difference between biosolids and sludge?&lt;/a&gt;
		&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;pane-2&quot;&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;Biosolids are treated sewage sludge. Biosolids are carefully treated and monitored and must be used in accordance with regulatory requirements.&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot; class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#pane-3&quot;&gt;3) Why do we have biosolids?&lt;/a&gt;
		&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;pane-3&quot;&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;We have biosolids as a result of the wastewater treatment process. Water treatment technology has made our water safer for recreation and seafood harvesting. Thirty years ago, thousands of American cities dumped their raw sewage directly into the nation&#039;s rivers, lakes, and bays. Through regulation of this dumping, local governments now required to treat wastewater and to make the decision whether to recycle biosolids as fertilizer, incinerate it, or bury it in a landfill.&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot; class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#pane-4&quot;&gt;4) How are biosolids generated and processed?&lt;/a&gt;
		&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;pane-4&quot;&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;Biosolids are created through the treatment of domestic wastewater generated from sewage treatment facilities. The treatment of biosolids can actually begin before the wastewater reaches the sewage treatment plant. In many larger wastewater treatment systems, pre-treatment regulations require that industrial facilities pre-treat their wastewater to remove many hazardous contaminants before it is sent to a wastewater treatment plant. Wastewater treatment facilities monitor incoming wastewater streams to ensure their recyclability and compatibility with the treatment plant process.&lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;p&gt;Once the wastewater reaches the plant, the sewage goes through physical, chemical and biological processes which clean the wastewater and remove the solids. If necessary, the solids are then treated with lime to raise the pH level to eliminate objectionable odors. The wastewater treatment processes sanitize wastewater solids to control pathogens (disease-causing organisms, such as certain bacteria, viruses and parasites) and other organisms capable of transporting disease.&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot; class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#pane-5&quot;&gt;5) How are biosolids used?&lt;/a&gt;
		&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;pane-5&quot;&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;After treatment and processing, biosolids can be recycled and applied as fertilizer to improve and maintain productive soils and stimulate plant growth. The controlled land application of biosolids completes a natural cycle in the environment. By treating sewage sludge, it becomes biosolids which can be used as valuable fertilizer, instead of taking up space in a landfill or other disposal facility.&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot; class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#pane-6&quot;&gt;6) Where are biosolids used?&lt;/a&gt;
		&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;pane-6&quot;&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;Farmers and gardeners have been recycling biosolids for ages. Biosolids recycling is the process of beneficially using treated the treated residuals from wastewater treatment to promote the growth of agricultural crops, fertilize gardens and parks and reclaim mining sites. Land application of biosolids takes place in all 50 states.&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot; class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#pane-7&quot;&gt;7) Why are biosolids used on farms?&lt;/a&gt;
		&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;pane-7&quot;&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;The application of biosolids reduces the need for chemical fertilizers. As more wastewater plants become capable of producing high quality biosolids, there is an even greater opportunity to make use of this valuable resource.&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot; class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#pane-8&quot;&gt;8) What percentage of biosolids are recycled and how many farms use biosolids?&lt;/a&gt;
		&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;pane-8&quot;&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;About 50% of all biosolids are being recycled to land. These biosolids are used on less than one percent of the nation&#039;s agricultural land.&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot; class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#pane-9&quot;&gt;9) Are biosolids safe?&lt;/a&gt;
		&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;pane-9&quot;&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;The National Academy of Sciences has reviewed current practices, public health concerns and regulator standards, and has concluded that &quot;the use of these materials in the production of crops for human consumption when practiced in accordance with existing federal guidelines and regulations, presents negligible risk to the consumer, to crop production and to the environment.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot; class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#pane-10&quot;&gt;10) Do biosolids smell?&lt;/a&gt;
		&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;pane-10&quot;&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;Biosolids may have their own distinctive odor depending on the type of treatment it has been through. Some biosolids may have only a slight musty, ammonia odor. Others have a stronger odor that may be offensive to some people. Much of the odor is caused by compounds containing sulfur and ammonia, both of which are plant nutrients.&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot; class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#pane-11&quot;&gt;11) Are there regulations for the land application of biosolids?&lt;/a&gt;
		&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;pane-11&quot;&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;The federal biosolids rule is contained in 40 CFR Part 503. Biosolids that are to be land applied must meet these strict regulations and quality standards. The Part 503 rule governing the use and disposal of biosolids contain numerical limits, for metals in biosolids, pathogen reduction standards, site restriction, crop harvesting restrictions and monitoring, record keeping and reporting requirements for land applied biosolids as well as similar requirements for biosolids that are surface disposed or incinerated. Most recently, standards have been proposed to include requirements in the Part 503 Rule that limit the concentration of dioxin and dioxin like compounds in biosolids to ensure safe land application.&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot; class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#pane-12&quot;&gt;12) Where can I find out more about the regulations?&lt;/a&gt;
		&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;pane-12&quot;&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;The biosolids rule is described in the EPA publication, A &lt;a href=&quot;/biosolids/plain-english-guide-epa-part-503-biosolids-rule&quot;&gt;Plain English Guide to the EPA Part 503 Biosolids Rule&lt;/a&gt;. This guide states and interprets the Part 503 rule for the general reader. This guide is also available in hard copy. In addition to the Plain English Guide, EPA has prepared &lt;a href=&quot;/biosolids/guide-biosolids-risk-assessment-epa-part-503-rule&quot;&gt;A Guide to the Biosolids Risk Assessments for the EPA Part 503 Rule&lt;/a&gt; which shows the many steps followed to develop the scientifically defensible, safe set of rules (also available from EPA in hard copy.)&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot; class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#pane-13&quot;&gt;13) How are biosolids used for agriculture?&lt;/a&gt;
		&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;pane-13&quot;&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;Biosolids are used to fertilize fields for raising crops. Agricultural use of biosolids, that meet strict quality criteria and application rates, have been shown to produce significant improvements in crop growth and yield. Nutrients found in biosolids, such as nitrogen, phosphorus and potassium and trace elements such as calcium, copper, iron, magnesium, manganese, sulfur and zinc, are necessary for crop production and growth. The use of biosolids reduces the farmer&#039;s production costs and replenishes the organic matter that has been depleted over time. The organic matter improves soil structure by increasing the soil&#039;s ability to absorb and store moisture.&lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;p&gt;The organic nitrogen and phosphorous found in biosolids are used very efficiently by crops because these plant nutrients are released slowly throughout the growing season. This enables the crop to absorb these nutrients as the crop grows. This efficiency lessens the likelihood of groundwater pollution of nitrogen and phosphorous.&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot; class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#pane-14&quot;&gt;14) Can biosolids be used for mine reclamation?&lt;/a&gt;
		&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;pane-14&quot;&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;Biosolids have been used successfully at mine sites to establish sustainable vegetation. Not only does the organic matter, inorganic matrix and nutrients present in the biosolids reduce the bioavailability of toxic substances often found in highly disturbed mine soils, but also regenerate the soil layer. This regeneration is very important for reclaiming abandoned mine sites with little or no topsoil. The biosolids application rate for mine reclamation is generally higher than the agronomic rate which cannot be exceeded for use of agricultural soils.&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot; class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#pane-15&quot;&gt;15) How are biosolids used for forestry?&lt;/a&gt;
		&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;pane-15&quot;&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;Biosolids have been found to promote rapid timber growth, allowing quicker and more efficient harvest of an important natural resource.&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot; class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#pane-16&quot;&gt;16) Can biosolids be used for composting?&lt;/a&gt;
		&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;pane-16&quot;&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;Yes, biosolids may be composted and sold or distributed for use on lawns and home gardens. Most biosolids composts, are highly desirable products that are easy to store, transport and use.&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot; class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#pane-17&quot;&gt;17) Are there rules about where biosolids can be applied?&lt;/a&gt;
		&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;pane-17&quot;&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;To determine whether biosolids can be applied to a particular farm site, an evaluation of the site&#039;s suitability is generally performed by the land applier. The evaluation examines water supplies, soil characteristics, slopes, vegetation, crop needs and the distances to surface and groundwater.&lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;p&gt;There are different rules for different classes of biosolids. Class A biosolids contain no detectible levels of pathogens. Class A biosolids that meet strict vector attraction reduction requirements and low levels metals contents, only have to apply for permits to ensure that these very tough standards have been met. Class B biosolids are treated but still contain detectible levels of pathogens. There are buffer requirements, public access, and crop harvesting restrictions for virtually all forms of Class B biosolids.&lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;p&gt;Nutrient management planning ensures that the appropriate quantity and quality of biosolids are land applied to the farmland. The biosolids application is specifically calculated to match the nutrient uptake requirements of the particular crop. Nutrient management technicians work with the farm community to assure proper land application and nutrient control.&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot; class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#pane-18&quot;&gt;18) Are there buffer requirements or restrictions on public access to sites with biosolids?&lt;/a&gt;
		&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;pane-18&quot;&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;In general, exceptional quality (Class A) biosolids used in small quantities by general public have no buffer requirements, crop type, crop harvesting or site access restrictions. Exceptional Quality biosolids is the name given to treated residuals that contain low levels of metals and do not attract vectors. When used in bulk, Class A biosolids are subject to buffer requirements, but not to crop harvesting restrictions. In general, there are buffer requirements, public access, and crop harvesting restrictions for virtually all forms of Class B biosolids (treated but still containing detectible levels of pathogens).&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot; class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#pane-19&quot;&gt;19) Can anyone apply biosolids to land?&lt;/a&gt;
		&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;pane-19&quot;&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;Anyone who wants to use biosolids for land application must comply with all relevant federal and state regulations. In some cases a permit may be required.&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot; class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#pane-20&quot;&gt;20) What will it mean for a wastewater treatment plant, biosolids manager or land applier to agree to follow an Environmental Management System (EMS) for Biosolids?&lt;/a&gt;
		&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;pane-20&quot;&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;A voluntary EMS is now being developed for biosolids by the National Biosolids Partnership (NBP). The NBP consists of members from the Association of Metropolitan Sewerage Agency, the Water Environment Federation, the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) and other stakeholders including the general public. Those facilities who pledge to follow the EMS are agreeing to follow community-friendly practices in addition to being in compliance with applicable state and Federal regulations. Community friendly practices refer to the control of odor, traffic, noise, and dust as well as the management of nutrients. Those who pledge to follow the EMS will be subjected to audit by impartial independent third parties.&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;For More Information&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Contact &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:stevens.rick@epa.gov&quot;&gt;Rick Stevens&lt;/a&gt; (stevens.rick@epa.gov) at 202-566-1135.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jul 2015 14:04:29 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>rrsteven</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">97249 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Reusing Cleaned Up Superfund Sites: Ecological Use Where Waste is Left on Site</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/biosolids/reusing-cleaned-superfund-sites-ecological-use-where-waste-left-site</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;This report provides technical information useful in planning, designing, and implementing remediation and reuse projects at sites that are to include ecological reuse. It is especially useful for sites where the remedy calls for on-site containment or treatment of contaminants and contaminated materials or post-construction monitoring or treatment. This information may be useful to remediation planners and managers when considering how the remedy and reuse options may affect each other during various stages of EPA’s processes for managing NPL sites and non-time-critical removal actions. The document may also be useful to communities, potentially responsible parties (PRPs), Trustees, and other stakeholders planning for the reuse of Superfund sites in coordinating with the cleanup team during all stages of the cleanup process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-154493&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-07/documents/reusing_cleaned_up_superfund_sites_2006.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=4132345&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Reusing Cleaned up Superfund Sites (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(90 pp, 4 MB, 
  July 2006, 
  OSWER 9202.1-27-D)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jul 2015 18:41:06 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>rrsteven</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">95363 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Biosolids Generation, Use, and Disposal in the United States</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/biosolids/biosolids-generation-use-and-disposal-united-states</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;This report broadens the U.S. Environmental ProtectionAgency’s (EPA) series of solid waste studies by quantifying the amount of biosolids managed by municipal solid waste (MSW) facilities. Biosolids are the byproduct of municipal wastewater treatment and also are known as sewage sludge. This report focuses on biosolids generated by publicly owned treatment works (POTWs) and the subsequent management practices used by POTWs for treating and then recycling or disposing of biosolids.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-154463&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-07/documents/biosolids_generation_use_disposal_in_u.s_1999.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=548581&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Biosolids Generation Use and Disposal in the United States (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(81 pp, 549 K, 
  September 1999, 
  EPA530-R-99-009)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jul 2015 18:19:35 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>rrsteven</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">95355 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>A History of Land Application as a Treatment Alternative</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/biosolids/history-land-application-treatment-alternative</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;This review was conducted to attempt to determine whether the history of land treatment could assist in explaining the reasons behind the apparent reluctance to use this wastewater treatment option, and to provide a basis for judging its future prospects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-154431&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-07/documents/1979_history_of_land_application_as_a_treatment_alternative.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=4865091&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;A History of Land Application as a Treatment Alternative (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(98 pp, 5 MB, 
  April 1979, 
  EPA/439/9-79-012)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jul 2015 17:34:40 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>rrsteven</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">95333 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Use of Composting for Biosolids Management</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/biosolids/use-composting-biosolids-management</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;Composting is one of several methods for treating biosolids to create a marketable end product that is easy to handle, store, and use. The end product is usually a Class A, humus-like material without detectable levels of pathogens that can be applied as a soil conditioner and fertilizer to gardens, food and feed crops, and rangelands. This compost provides large quantities of organic matter and nutrients (such as nitrogen and potassium) to the soil, improves soil texture, and elevates soil cation exchange capacity (an indication of the soil’s ability to hold nutrients), all characteristics of a good organic fertilizer. Biosolids compost is safe to use and generally has a high degree of acceptability by the public. Thus, it competes well with other bulk and bagged products available to homeowners, landscapers, farmers, and ranchers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-153967&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-06/documents/use_of_composting_for_biosolids_management.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=286150&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Use of Composting for Biosolids Management (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(10 pp, 286 K, 
  September , 
  EPA/832-F-02-024)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 30 Jun 2015 18:39:10 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>rrsteven</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">95171 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  </channel>
</rss>

<!-- Page cached by Boost @ 2017-01-26 05:26:44, expires @ 2017-01-26 17:26:44, lifetime 12 hours -->