<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?><rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.epa.gov/feed/40657/rss.xml" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/" xmlns:og="http://ogp.me/ns#" xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#" xmlns:sioc="http://rdfs.org/sioc/ns#" xmlns:sioct="http://rdfs.org/sioc/types#" xmlns:skos="http://www.w3.org/2004/02/skos/core#" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#">
  <channel>
    <title>Water Research</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/feed/40657/rss.xml</link>
    <description>Updated Water Research content from the US Environmental Protection Agency</description>
    <language>en</language>
     <atom:link href="https://www.epa.gov/feed/40657/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      <item>
    <title>Rapid Benefit Indicators (RBI) Approach</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/water-research/rapid-benefit-indicators-rbi-approach</link>
    <description>&lt;h2&gt;Process for Assessing Social Benefits of Ecological Restoration&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-png left view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:928px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;All photos by Rick McKinney. Image 1 is of the Woonasquatucket River, image 2 is a person kayaking down the Woonasquatucket River, image 3 is the Woonasquatucket River. &quot; title=&quot;Rapid Benefit Indicators Approach&quot; height=&quot;206&quot; width=&quot;928&quot; class=&quot;left media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2017-01/rbi_approach.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The RBI approach is an easy-to-use process for assessing restoration sites using non-monetary benefit indicators. It uses readily-available data to estimate and quantify benefits to people around an ecological restoration site. Whether you are a federal, state, or local manager, or a member of an interest group or funding organization, this simple yet powerful site analysis will allow you and your stakeholders to systematically and equitably incorporate social benefits in restoration decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 class=&quot;highlighted&quot;&gt;Application &lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The RBI approach can be used to do the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Prioritize restoration sites and projects&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Screen projects that may require further evaluation&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Justify funding requests&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Assess who may benefit the most from a project&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Evaluate tradeoffs&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Inform people about the benefits of restoration&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Evaluate what a project has accomplished&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Inform further planning&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Inform a structured decision making process or monetary evaluation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 class=&quot;highlighted&quot;&gt;Downloads&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cfpub.epa.gov/si/si_public_record_Report.cfm?dirEntryId=331110&quot;&gt;RBI Approach Tool, Manual, and Forms&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt; This page provides the interactive tool with associated manual, as well as an alternative to the interactive tool, all in one location. Each component can also be accessed individually below:

		&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type:circle&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cfpub.epa.gov/si/si_public_file_download.cfm?p_download_id=529815&quot;&gt;RBI Approach Checklist Tool (interactive Excel® spreadsheet)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt; This tool accompanies the guidebook and provides a way to record information and compare sites using the RBI approach. The spreadsheet-based tool includes prompts to guide you through the assessment process, and automatically summarizes entries. &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://nepis.epa.gov/Exe/ZyPURL.cgi?Dockey=P100PIKB.txt&quot;&gt;(Checklist Tool Quick Start Manual&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cfpub.epa.gov/si/si_public_file_download.cfm?p_download_id=529807&quot;&gt;RBI Approach Fillable Checklist Forms (pdf)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt; This alternative to the interactive Checklist Tool is a fillable, formatted PDF that will work on any operating system. The PDF does not have all the functionality of the spreadsheet and will only allow for the comparison of two sites at a time.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cfpub.epa.gov/si/si_public_record_Report.cfm?dirEntryId=325010&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;RBI Approach Guidebook&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. The guidebook presents the RBI approach using an example application to wetland restoration. In this guide, each step of the RBI approach is introduced by an overview section that summarizes the step and explains how to apply it. Following the full walkthrough of each step, you will find “Step in Action” pages that demonstrate how the step is applied in a real-world scenario, using an example application to freshwater wetland restoration in the Woonasquatucket River Watershed in Rhode Island, USA.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://nepis.epa.gov/Exe/ZyPURL.cgi?Dockey=P100PMSW.txt&quot;&gt;RBI Approach Fact Sheet.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; This one-page document briefly describes the RBI approach and how it might be used.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2 class=&quot;highlighted&quot;&gt;Related Resources&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cfpub.epa.gov/si/si_public_record_Report.cfm?dirEntryId=309610&quot;&gt;Benefit Indicators for Flood Regulation Services of Wetlands: A Modeling Approach&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. This report describes a modeling process, following the RBI approach, used to develop indicators to assess increases in flood protection benefits from wetlands restoration.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://nepis.epa.gov/Exe/ZyNET.exe/P100PP1C.TXT?ZyActionD=ZyDocument&amp;amp;Client=EPA&amp;amp;Index=2011+Thru+2015&amp;amp;Docs=&amp;amp;Query=&amp;amp;Time=&amp;amp;EndTime=&amp;amp;SearchMethod=1&amp;amp;TocRestrict=n&amp;amp;Toc=&amp;amp;TocEntry=&amp;amp;QField=&amp;amp;QFieldYear=&amp;amp;QFieldMonth=&amp;amp;QFieldDay=&amp;amp;IntQFieldOp=0&amp;amp;ExtQFieldOp=0&amp;amp;XmlQuery=&amp;amp;File=D%3A%5Czyfiles%5CIndex%20Data%5C11thru15%5CTxt%5C00000022%5CP100PP1C.txt&amp;amp;User=ANONYMOUS&amp;amp;Password=anonymous&amp;amp;SortMethod=h%7C-&amp;amp;MaximumDocuments=1&amp;amp;FuzzyDegree=0&amp;amp;ImageQuality=r75g8/r75g8/x150y150g16/i425&amp;amp;Display=hpfr&amp;amp;DefSeekPage=x&amp;amp;SearchBack=ZyActionL&amp;amp;Back=ZyActionS&amp;amp;BackDesc=Results%20page&amp;amp;MaximumPages=1&amp;amp;ZyEntry=1&amp;amp;SeekPage=x&amp;amp;ZyPURL&quot;&gt;Barriers, Opportunities, and Strategies for Urban Ecosystem Restoration: Lessons Learned from Restoration Managers in Rhode Island, U.S.A.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; This report presents barriers, opportunities, and strategies for restoration projects and synthesizes lessons learned by restoration managers working in primarily urban settings.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cfpub.epa.gov/si/si_public_record_report.cfm?dirEntryId=307295&amp;amp;simpleSearch=0&amp;amp;showCriteria=2&amp;amp;searchAll=Manager+Perspectives+on+Communication+and+Public+Engagement+in+Ecological+Restoration+&amp;amp;TIMSType=&amp;amp;dateBeginPublishedPresented=11%2F21%2F2014&quot;&gt;Manager Perspectives on Communication and Public Engagement in Ecological Restoration Project Success&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt; This article focuses on the restoration community in Rhode Island to draw connections among communication, community involvement, and ecological restoration project success. Offering real-world examples drawn from interviews with 27 local, state, federal, and nonprofit restoration managers, it synthesizes the mechanisms that managers found effective. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 21 Dec 2016 16:45:05 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>mlatham</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">167655 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Storm Water Management Model Fact Sheet</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/water-research/storm-water-management-model-fact-sheet</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;Science in Action Fact Sheet&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-319489&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-09/documents/swmm_factsheet_final_16sep01-508_compliant.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=665820&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Storm Water Management Model Fact Sheet (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(2 pp, 666 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 29 Sep 2016 12:22:25 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>kmaloney</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">161495 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Watershed Management Optimization Support Tool Fact Sheet</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/water-research/watershed-management-optimization-support-tool-fact-sheet</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;Science in Action Fact Sheet&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-316535&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-09/documents/wmostv2_fact_sheet_508.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=689390&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Watershed Management Optimization Support Tool (WMOST) Fact Sheet (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(2 pp, 689 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 20 Sep 2016 15:14:12 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>kmaloney</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">160699 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Drought Resilience and Water Conservation</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/water-research/drought-resilience-and-water-conservation</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg right view-mode-medium&quot; style=&quot;width:295px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Drought&quot; height=&quot;185&quot; width=&quot;295&quot; class=&quot;right media-element file-medium right&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/medium/public/2015-10/drought295.jpg&quot; title=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;In many areas of the United States, the frequency, intensity, and duration of drought events is increasing. This pattern is expected to continue and shift outside of historical trends, making forecasting our water supply and quality more difficult. EPA is conducting research and working with stakeholders to better understand the impact of drought on water quality and availability, and to provide solutions to help communities become more resilient. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;accordion&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#pane-1&quot; title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot;&gt;Water Efficiency &amp;amp; Aging Infrastructure&lt;/a&gt;

		&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;pane-1&quot;&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;EPA supports innovative plumbing products that help conserve water and energy through its WaterSense program. By purchasing products with a WaterSense label, consumers can save money, while conserving water and energy. EPA also works with the U.S. Department of Housing and Urban Development to incorporate water efficiency into HUD programs. Advances in low-flow plumbing and fixtures for water quantity conservation present new challenges for maintaining water quality in systems designed for higher flows. EPA is funding research to support water conservation and healthy drinking water in distribution and premise plumbing systems (plumbing in homes and other buildings) under lower-flow conditions&lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;p&gt;Aging infrastructure, such as leaky pipes and water mains, is estimated to result in the loss of 2.1 trillion gallons of treated drinking water in the U.S. each year. Replacing our Nation&#039;s failing water infrastructure is expected to cost approximately $500 billion. EPA is helping by providing water loss training workshops to public and tribal water utilities and collaborating with states and tribes to leverage Drinking Water State Revolving Funds--EPA&#039;s largest funding source for drinking water infrastructure--for water loss control auditing.&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#pane-2&quot; title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot;&gt;Aquifer Recharge&lt;/a&gt;
		&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;pane-2&quot;&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;Prolonged drought can deplete groundwater aquifers that many communities rely on for drinking water and irrigation. Through the National Drought Resilience Partnership (NDRP), EPA will work with municipalities and utilities to promote stormwater and rainwater capture to augment water supplies and replenish aquifers. EPA scientists and partners are conducting field studies to explore the influences of innovative green infrastructure practices, such as dry wells and infiltration basins, on water movement into aquifers. They are also evaluating the quality of the recharged water.&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#pane-3&quot; title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot;&gt;Water Reuse&lt;/a&gt;
		&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;pane-3&quot;&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;Water conservation practices promoting water reuse--also known as fit-for-purpose water--for potable (drinking) and nonpotable (not for drinking) water are becoming increasingly important. Such practices are especially critical in parts of the western U.S. where climate change, extreme drought, increased evaporation, and population growth are decreasing water availability. To help states achieve water supply resiliency, EPA is promoting water reuse and the expansion of nontraditional water supplies (for example, impaired, alternative, or reclaimed water) previously not considered for reuse, while continuing to protect human and environmental health. EPA is also working with other federal agencies to address sustainability at the federal level, including water resource management and drought response.&lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;p&gt;To advance innovative water reuse, EPA is assessing approaches for controlling waterborne contaminants associated with built infrastructure; evaluating treatment, monitoring, and risks to human health; advancing water systems that encompass the entire water cycle; developing approaches to evaluate transformative water systems (systems that meet public health and environmental goals while optimizing treatment and maximizing resource recovery and system resiliency); and evaluating rainwater harvesting systems for nonpotable water supplies. EPA has awarded grants to five institutions to better understand potential human and ecological health effects associated with water reuse and conservation practices. Their research will evaluate how reclaimed water applications, such as direct and indirect potable reuse, aquifer recharge, and irrigation, might affect public and ecological health.&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#pane-4&quot; title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot;&gt;Desalination&lt;/a&gt;
		&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;pane-4&quot;&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;Brackish and salt water can augment water supplies in areas impacted by drought. EPA scientists are growing salt-tolerant algae that remove salts from these waters, which could reduce the energy footprint and costs of desalination. The algae could then be harvested and used as raw material for biofeul production. EPA scientists are also identifying, designing, and demonstrating cost-effective options that will enable the recovery of water from compromised sources, with an added goal of managing the brine concentrates produced by desalination systems.&lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;p&gt;EPA has given Small Business Innovation Research awards to companies developing and testing new cost-effective technologies. These include a microdevice to desalinate water off grid, allowing its use where it is needed most, and a system that will enable small water utilities to include lower water quality source water (such as salt water) at their intakes, further reducing the demand on groundwater and surface water.&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#pane-5&quot; title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot;&gt;Response, Recovery, &amp;amp; Restoration&lt;/a&gt;
		&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;pane-5&quot;&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;EPA is participating in partnerships across the Nation and providing research grants, tools, support, and training to help communities become more drought resilient. Through the National Drought Resilience Partnership (NDRP), EPA is collaborating on the development of tools and guides that water and wastewater utilities can use to prepare for, respond to, and recover from droughts. EPA&#039;s Climate Ready Utilities Program is working nationwide while using the &lt;em&gt;Climate Resilience Evaluation and Awareness Tool&lt;/em&gt; to help utilities conduct climate change risk assessment to identify utility-level strategies that will build readiness and resilience. EPA and the Indian Health Service are convening federal and state partners to coordinate information on infrastructure needs and funding, technical assistance, emergency drought relief, and conservation opportunities for tribes.&lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;p&gt;To advance drought-related research even further, EPA has awarded grants to four institutions to investigate how drought and wildfire--and projects for managing wildfires--might impact the quality of surface water and its treatment at drinking water facilities. The research also includes reducing risks associated with preparedness for pre-drought planning and emergency response.&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#pane-6&quot; title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot;&gt;Watershed Sustainability&lt;/a&gt;
		&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;pane-6&quot;&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;EPA is supporting community efforts to identify, and find solutions for, issues related to drought resiliency and watershed sustainability. EPA&#039;s Centers of Excellence for Watershed Management program works with academia across the Southeast to provide products and services for communities to address watershed problems related to water scarcity and drought and issues of climate resilience and water utility infrastructure sustainability. EPA is supporting projects in vineyards and orchards that are implementing management practices to reduce irrigation demand, retain soil moisture, and minimize soil loss. Other actions include working with partners to decrease the impacts of low flows and climate change on wetland projects, and to provide information on changes in water flow due to drought, floods, and other stresses that impact flow regimes and affect aquatic life.&lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;p&gt;EPA researchers are also providing tools and conducting studies to better understand how drought affects watersheds, including evaluating drought-related stream salinization effects on the local extinction of aquatic organisms, quantifying the extent and impact of drought conditions affecting watershed resilience and integrity, and assessing influences of drought and water management on lake level decline and habitat quality.&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/water-research/drought-resilience-and-water-conservation-technical-brief&quot;&gt;Technical Brief: Drought Resilience and Water Conservation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Fri, 15 Jul 2016 13:29:47 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>dholla02</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">155009 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Drought Resilience and Water Conservation Technical Brief</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/water-research/drought-resilience-and-water-conservation-technical-brief</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;Information in the technical brief highlight EPA drought and conservation activities across the nation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-297999&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-06/documents/epa_drought_technical_brief_may_2016.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=357266&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Drought Resilience and Water Conservation Technical Brief (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(10 pp, 357 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jun 2016 16:30:27 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>kmaloney</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">153703 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Final Agenda - 13th Annual U.S. EPA Drinking Water Workshop</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/water-research/final-agenda-13th-annual-us-epa-drinking-water-workshop</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;This agenda is subject to change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-297961&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-06/documents/epa_2016_dw_workshop_draft_agenda_29jun16.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=278597&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Final Agenda -- 13th Annual Drinking Water Workshop (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(3 pp, 279 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jun 2016 15:41:47 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>kmaloney</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">153687 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>VELMA v2.0 Fact Sheet</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/water-research/velma-v20-fact-sheet</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;Science in Action Fact Sheet&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-316629&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-09/documents/508_velma_fact_sheet_revised_6-21-16.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=319281&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;VELMA 2.0 Model Fact Sheet (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(2 pp, 319 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jun 2016 13:18:41 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>kmaloney</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">152349 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Water Research Webinar: Assessment of Major Ion Effects on Aquatic Organisms</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/water-research/water-research-webinar-assessment-major-ion-effects-aquatic-organisms</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;April 27, 2016 Water Research Webinar Flyer&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-277219&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-04/documents/sswr_webinar_april2016.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=369635&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Assessment of Major Ion Effects on Aquatic Organisms (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(1 pg, 370 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Mon, 18 Apr 2016 14:44:46 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>kmaloney</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">146765 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Small Systems Webinar: Disinfection Byproducts (DBPs) Regulatory Issues and Solutions</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/water-research/small-systems-webinar-disinfection-byproducts-dbps-regulatory-issues-and-solutions</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;April 26, 2016 Small Systems Webinar Flyer&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-273439&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-04/documents/epa_smallsystemswebinar_april2016.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=180580&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Disinfection Byproducts (DBPs): Regulatory Issues and Solutions (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(1 pg, 181 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Mon, 04 Apr 2016 16:15:12 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>kmaloney</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">142099 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  </channel>
</rss>

<!-- Page cached by Boost @ 2017-01-25 04:27:43, expires @ 2017-01-25 16:27:43, lifetime 12 hours -->