<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?><rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.epa.gov/feed/9249/rss.xml" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/" xmlns:og="http://ogp.me/ns#" xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#" xmlns:sioc="http://rdfs.org/sioc/ns#" xmlns:sioct="http://rdfs.org/sioc/types#" xmlns:skos="http://www.w3.org/2004/02/skos/core#" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#">
  <channel>
    <title>Ground Water and Drinking Water</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/feed/9249/rss.xml</link>
    <description>Updated Ground Water and Drinking Water content from the US Environmental Protection Agency</description>
    <language>en</language>
     <atom:link href="https://www.epa.gov/feed/9249/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      <item>
    <title>Possible Funding Sources for Managing Cyanobacterial Harmful Algal Blooms and Cyanotoxins in Drinking Water</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/ground-water-and-drinking-water/possible-funding-sources-managing-cyanobacterial-harmful-algal</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;This document provides an explanation of possible funding sources that can be used to manage cyanobacterial harmful algal blooms and cyanotoxins. These sources include the Safe Drinking Water Act and Clean Water Act revolving funds and other possible funding sources to support drinking water systems in managing risks to drinking water from harmful algal blooms and cyanotoxins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-347531&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2017-01/documents/cyanohabs_funding_fact_sheet.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=257180&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;FACT SHEET: Possible Funding Sources for Managing Cyanobacterial Harmful Algal Blooms and Cyanotoxins in Drinking Water (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(7 pp, 257 K, 
  January 2017, 
  EPA-810-F-17-001)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 19 Jan 2017 18:22:22 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cwadling</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">169569 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Water System Partnerships Meeting</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/ground-water-and-drinking-water/water-system-partnerships-meeting</link>
    <description>&lt;h3&gt;Register Online Today&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://epa-watersystemspartnerships.eventbrite.com&quot;&gt;https://epa-watersystemspartnerships.eventbrite.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please join us on &lt;strong&gt;January 31, 2017 &lt;/strong&gt;in Washington, D.C for a daylong meeting focused on water system partnerships, including promoting partnership activities and creating incentives for and reducing challenges to their development. This will be a working meeting with very limited presentations and a high emphasis on discussion and input from the participants. It is part of a collaborative vision to establish a framework to support partnership activities on a national and local level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The working meeting will focus on three key theme areas: incentives and drivers to support water system partnership development, funding and finance options for partnerships, and outreach and education. Participants will actively engage and help drive the short term and long term actions needed for each of these areas. Participants will include federal agencies, state and local government, utilities, associations, private sector and non-profits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information, contact: &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:ogwdwprotectiontraining@epa.gov&quot;&gt;ogwdwprotectiontraining@epa.gov&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-339181&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-12/documents/watersystempartnerships_savethedate_1.31.17.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=161912&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Water System Partnerships Meeting Flyer (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(1 pg, 162 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-347361&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2017-01/documents/january_31_wsp_meeting_agenda.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=1332778&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Water Systems Partnerships Meeting Agenda (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(2 pp, 1 MB)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-347363&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2017-01/documents/january_31_wsp_meeting_background_document.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=225564&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Water Systems Partnerships Meeting Background Document (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(6 pp, 226 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Fri, 16 Dec 2016 20:46:23 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cwadling</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">167433 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Drinking Water Action Plan:  What are they saying?</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/ground-water-and-drinking-water/drinking-water-action-plan-what-are-they-saying</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;&quot;Americans deserve to access their tap water with confidence and to know that their state and federal regulators are vigilant. This plan sets ambitious but necessary priorities.&quot; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;i&gt;- John Linc Stine, Commissioner of the Minnesota Pollution Control Agency and President of the Environmental Council of the States &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&quot;The plan importantly addresses necessary infrastructure investment and accelerates critical reform of the existing lead and copper rule. The plan identifies key areas for a national drinking water conversation, and states look forward to bringing our experience and expertise to the dialogue – particularly as states will be responsible for much of the intensive front-line implementation of the plan.&quot; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;i&gt;- Craig Butler, Director of the Ohio Environmental Protection Agency and ECOS Executive Committee Representative &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&quot;We appreciate the time EPA took to obtain state thoughts on the concepts embedded in the plan. As we move into the next Administration, this Plan provides a clear roadmap to improve a program that is critical to Americans’ everyday life and to thriving economies.&quot; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;i&gt;- Alexandra Dapolito Dunn, Executive Director and General Counsel of the Environmental Council of the States &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&quot;The National Drinking Water Action Plan is a positive step forward to help local governments with affordable, clean, and safe drinking water.&quot; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;i&gt;- Mayor Elizabeth Kautz, Burnsville, MN &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&quot;The Drinking Water Action Plan is essential for clean and safe drinking water, ensuring public health for all of our citizens now and in the future&quot;. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;i&gt;- Dr. Hector Gonzalez, M.D., Director of City of Laredo Public Health &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&quot;It is exciting to be a part of such a collaborative effort to protect America&#039;s water supply. We owe it to our citizens to make sure there is clean and affordable water for everyone in our community. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;i&gt;- Mayor Karen Freeman-Wilson, Gary, Indiana &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&quot;As public officials we have no greater concern than the welfare of our families and communities. Clean and safe drinking water is the lifeblood of all our communities. We must be good stewards of our drinking water and work at all levels of government to ensure that it is protected for now and the years to come.&quot; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;i&gt;- Mayor Bob Dixson, Greensburg, KS and Chairman of the Local Government Advisory Committee &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&quot;The National Drinking Water Action Plan provides a comprehensive strategic framework for the future of one of our nation’s most important resources. While the Action Plan recognizes current and emerging challenges, the plan also highlights opportunities for innovation and collaboration moving forward. The development of the plan included extensive stakeholder involvement and it is clear that local government perspectives are reflected in the report’s challenges and proposed actions. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;i&gt;- Susan Hann, Chairwoman, LGAC’s Protecting America’s Waters Workgroup &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&quot;Drinking water isn’t a talking point, it’s an action item. EPA&#039;s Drinking Water Action plan outlines concrete steps to increase oversight, investment and innovation to meet today’s drinking water challenges.&quot; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;i&gt;- Lynn Thorp, National Campaigns Manager at Clean Water Action &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Mon, 05 Dec 2016 19:52:37 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cwadling</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">166419 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Drinking Water Action Plan</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/ground-water-and-drinking-water/drinking-water-action-plan</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&quot;&lt;em&gt;Ensuring that all Americans have access to safe drinking water is an absolute top priority for EPA&lt;/em&gt;.&quot;&lt;/strong&gt; - EPA Administrator, Gina McCarthy&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;p&gt;EPA&#039;s Drinking Water Action Plan serves as a national call to action, urging all levels of government, utilities, community organizations, and other stakeholders to work together to increase the safety and reliability of drinking water.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Plan is organized around six Priority Areas in which there is significant opportunity for leadership from states and other partners. The Priority Areas include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;table&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/ground-water-and-drinking-water/drinking-water-action-plan-priority-area-1&quot;&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg center view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:325px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Promote Equity and Build Capacity for Drinking Water Infrastructure Financing and Management in Disadvantaged, Small, and Environmental Justice Communities&quot; height=&quot;100&quot; width=&quot;325&quot; class=&quot;center media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2016-11/pa11_0.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/ground-water-and-drinking-water/drinking-water-action-plan-priority-area-2&quot;&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:326px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Advance Next Generation Oversight for the Safe Drinking Water Act &quot; height=&quot;102&quot; width=&quot;326&quot; class=&quot;media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2016-11/pa2_0.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/ground-water-and-drinking-water/drinking-water-action-plan-priority-area-3&quot;&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:325px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Strengthen Source Water Protection and Resilience of Drinking Water Supplies&quot; height=&quot;100&quot; width=&quot;325&quot; class=&quot;media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2016-11/pa3.1.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/ground-water-and-drinking-water/drinking-water-action-plan-priority-area-4&quot;&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:325px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Take Action to Address Unregulated Contaminants &quot; height=&quot;100&quot; width=&quot;325&quot; class=&quot;media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2016-11/paucmr_2.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/ground-water-and-drinking-water/drinking-water-action-plan-priority-area-5&quot;&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:325px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Improve Transparency, Public Education, and Risk Communication on Drinking Water Safety &quot; height=&quot;100&quot; width=&quot;325&quot; class=&quot;media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2016-11/untitled-1.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/ground-water-and-drinking-water/drinking-water-action-plan-priority-area-6&quot;&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:326px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Reduce Lead Risks through the Lead and Copper Rule &quot; height=&quot;102&quot; width=&quot;326&quot; class=&quot;media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2016-11/pa6.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;The plan reflects input from state, tribal, and local government officials; drinking water utilities; community groups; and environmental organizations. While EPA and partners have already begun to take some actions, others will require additional resources and further stakeholder engagement. EPA recognizes that partnership and collaboration across all levels of government, utilities, the private sector, and the public will be essential to the success of the plan.&lt;/p&gt;

	&lt;p&gt;Download the complete &lt;a href=&quot;/sites/production/files/2016-11/documents/508.final_.usepa_.drinking.water_.action.plan_11.30.16.v0.pdf&quot;&gt;Drinking Water Action Plan&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

	

	&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Press Release: &lt;a href=&quot;/newsreleases/epa-outlines-actions-improve-safety-reliability-nations-drinking-water&quot;&gt;EPA Outlines Actions to Improve Safety, Reliability of Nation’s Drinking Water&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

	&lt;p&gt;Interested in reading &quot;&lt;a href=&quot;/ground-water-and-drinking-water/drinking-water-action-plan-what-are-they-saying&quot;&gt;What are they saying about the Drinking Water Action Plan&lt;/a&gt;&quot;?&lt;/p&gt;

	&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Related Information&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

	&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/sites/production/files/2016-10/documents/lgacdrinkingwatertransmittal_letter_final_1.1.pdf&quot;&gt;Letter to EPA from the Local Government Advisory Committee&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/sites/production/files/2016-10/documents/lgac_water_report_-final-draft_3.1.pdf&quot;&gt;Local Government Advisory Committee&#039;s Finding and Recommendations Report&lt;/a&gt; (October 2016)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;disclaimer pdf&quot;&gt;You will need Adobe Reader to view some of the files on this page. See &lt;a href=&quot;/home/pdf-files&quot;&gt;EPA’s About PDF page&lt;/a&gt; to learn more.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 29 Nov 2016 19:11:30 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cwadling</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">165939 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Drinking Water Action Plan: Priority Area 6</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/ground-water-and-drinking-water/drinking-water-action-plan-priority-area-6</link>
    <description>&lt;h2&gt;Reduce Lead Risks through the Lead and Copper Rule&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Goals&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To strengthen implementation of the current Lead and Copper Rule and improve public health protection through updates to the rule.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Challenges&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;While EPA’s Lead and Copper Rule has resulted in substantial reductions of lead and copper in drinking water, it is now 25 years old and both the rule and its implementation are in need of a substantial overhaul.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;The rule is one of the most challenging for primacy agencies and utilities to implement and there is a clear opportunity to improve the public health protections it affords.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Proposed Actions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Continue to engage in enhanced oversight activities.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Provide information to utilities and local communities on best practices, costs, and mechanisms for lead service line replacement.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Enhance training and technical assistance to primacy agencies on Lead and Copper Rule implementation.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Update and improve EPA’s Training, Testing and Telling (3Ts) guide for protection of drinking water in schools.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Develop proposed revisions to the Lead and Copper Rule as outlined in EPA’s Lead and Copper Rule Revisions White Paper.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Continue enhanced engagement with partners and stakeholders on the development of proposed revisions to the Lead and Copper Rule.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Back to &lt;a href=&quot;/ground-water-and-drinking-water/drinking-water-action-plan&quot;&gt;Drinking Water Action Plan&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 29 Nov 2016 18:05:47 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cwadling</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">165927 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Drinking Water Action Plan: Priority Area 5</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/ground-water-and-drinking-water/drinking-water-action-plan-priority-area-5</link>
    <description>&lt;h2&gt;Improve Transparency, Public Education, and Risk Communication on Drinking Water Safety&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Goals&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Provide the public with timely, clear and understandable information about drinking water quality, potential health risks, and the investments and actions needed to reliably deliver safe drinking water.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Challenges&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Safe drinking water is a basic necessity of daily life upon which we rely for our very existence. Yet consumers have relatively little information on drinking water quality or related risks and operational challenges. People need more than just data; they also need better communication about the context and meaning of drinking water information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Proposed Actions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Strengthen existing and new or revised rules, including through updated implementation guidance, to support more robust communication of key information to the public.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Develop indicators of drinking water quality utilizing enhanced water system and primacy agency data on drinking water quality that are communicated to the public through a web portal featuring key indicators and infographics.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Conduct an evaluation of the effectiveness of the required Consumer Confidence Reports.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Invest in strengthening risk communication expertise to better meet the needs of all members of the community.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Back to &lt;a href=&quot;/ground-water-and-drinking-water/drinking-water-action-plan&quot;&gt;Drinking Water Action Plan&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 29 Nov 2016 17:59:57 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cwadling</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">165925 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Drinking Water Action Plan: Priority Area 4</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/ground-water-and-drinking-water/drinking-water-action-plan-priority-area-4</link>
    <description>&lt;h2&gt;Take Action to Address Unregulated Contaminants&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Goals&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To provide the opportunity for creative new approaches to prioritize regulatory actions, better leverage non-regulatory tools, protect sources of drinking water, address drinking water system vulnerabilities and promote affordable treatment technologies that address a range of contaminants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Challenges&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;The past few years have underscored the vulnerability of drinking water systems across the country to localized contamination from unregulated contaminants, ranging from algal toxins related to harmful algal blooms, to industrial chemicals such as perfluorinated compounds (PFCs).&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;EPA, state primacy agencies and utilities must be prepared to address potential contaminants in the context of the time consuming process of the SDWA regulatory approach.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Proposed Actions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Through the National Drinking Water Advisory Council (NDWAC), identify a risk-based prioritization framework for consideration of new contaminants for regulation.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Strengthen the effectiveness of drinking water health advisories through enhanced collaboration and an increased focus on risk management and risk communication approaches.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Develop a guidance framework to help utilities and primacy agency and local regulatory officials in proactively assessing and managing risks to individual systems from unregulated contaminants.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Enhance available tools and information for quantitative assessment of the comparative costs of source water protection and advanced drinking water treatment technologies that can address a broad spectrum of regulated and unregulated contaminants.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Promote the development of low cost and innovative technologies to remove a broad spectrum of contaminants, particularly in small systems.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Back to &lt;a href=&quot;/ground-water-and-drinking-water/drinking-water-action-plan&quot;&gt;Drinking Water Action Plan&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 29 Nov 2016 17:50:08 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cwadling</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">165923 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Drinking Water Action Plan: Priority Area 3</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/ground-water-and-drinking-water/drinking-water-action-plan-priority-area-3</link>
    <description>&lt;h2&gt;Strengthen Source Water Protection and Resilience of Drinking Water Supplies&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Goals&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Energize efforts to protect source water and build resilience to drought and other hazards – by focusing on source water assessments, better leveraging land conservation resources, building collaborative partnerships for watershed protection, developing new tools to assess and manage source water risks, and advancing water efficiency and reclamation efforts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Challenges&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;As a nation we are facing growing threats to drinking water sources. These include surface and ground water contamination from industrial and nonpoint sources, potential impacts to underground sources of drinking water from induced seismicity, as well as growing risks to water availability due to overuse, drought and other extreme weather events. &lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Nutrients and other contaminants from agricultural practices and urban storm water continue to contribute significantly to source water protection challenges.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;The costs of failure to protect source water quality and assure reliable access to water supplies can be substantial.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Proposed Actions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Update and take action on source water assessments. &lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Develop modern online platforms and GIS tools to facilitate public access to watershed data that are critical to source water protection efforts. &lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Undertake source water monitoring pilot projects through technical assistance and funding.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Support source water protection through expanded, watershed-based approaches, including collaborative approaches to source water protection between programs at the federal, state, and local levels.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Work with state Clean Water Act (CWA) and SDWA partners to promote greater integration and leveraging of both the clean water and drinking water programs. &lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Work with key partners to develop a national community resilience initiative to comprehensively address community water resilience challenges (flood, drought, spills, harmful algal blooms, and other hazards). &lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Promote efforts to increase water efficiency and reuse, such as: the release of a summary of best practices in potable reuse in 2017; Cooperative Agreements among public and private sector entities to evaluate and demonstrate advanced treatment technologies; and water efficiency guidelines to help promote water conservation by state and local governments and utilities.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Back to &lt;a href=&quot;/ground-water-and-drinking-water/drinking-water-action-plan&quot;&gt;Drinking Water Action Plan&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 29 Nov 2016 17:45:45 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cwadling</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">165921 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Drinking Water Action Plan: Priority Area 2</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/ground-water-and-drinking-water/drinking-water-action-plan-priority-area-2</link>
    <description>&lt;h2&gt;Advance Next Generation Oversight for the Safe Drinking Water Act&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Goals&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To work together with regulators, utilities and a broad cross section of stakeholders to better leverage the power of information – to ensure timely identification of problems, efficient use of oversight and technical assistance resources, promote quicker mitigation of problems and robust public accountability for utilities and regulators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Challenges&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Safe drinking water requires effective oversight of over 150,000 public water systems across the country – at the level of state and tribal primacy agencies and at the federal level.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;In addition to the challenge of working to ensure simultaneous compliance with over 90 NPDWRs for 150,000 public water systems nationwide, regulators are facing increasing challenges associated with unregulated contaminants, aging infrastructure, and extreme weather impacts with limited and often declining resources, and recent events have eroded public confidence.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Proposed Actions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Develop a national e-reporting rule under SDWA to require water utilities and states to report SDWA compliance data electronically.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Implement the Compliance Monitoring Data Portal (CMDP), a compliance monitoring and analysis tool that facilitates electronic reporting.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Publish regular, triennial on-site reviews of primacy agency drinking water programs.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Develop priority indicators for troubled drinking water systems that can be used to best focus primacy agency and EPA oversight resources and technical assistance on troubled systems.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Collaborate with the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, primacy agencies, and the Association of State and Territorial Health Officials, to support local efforts to integrate public health surveillance data (such as childhood blood lead levels) with community drinking water quality data.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Promote Use of Advanced Monitoring Technology and Citizen Science.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Back to &lt;a href=&quot;/ground-water-and-drinking-water/drinking-water-action-plan&quot;&gt;Drinking Water Action Plan&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 29 Nov 2016 17:40:55 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cwadling</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">165917 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  </channel>
</rss>

<!-- Page cached by Boost @ 2017-01-26 04:19:36, expires @ 2017-01-26 16:19:36, lifetime 12 hours -->