<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?><rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.epa.gov/feed/52453/rss.xml" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/" xmlns:og="http://ogp.me/ns#" xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#" xmlns:sioc="http://rdfs.org/sioc/ns#" xmlns:sioct="http://rdfs.org/sioc/types#" xmlns:skos="http://www.w3.org/2004/02/skos/core#" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#">
  <channel>
    <title>Land Research</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/feed/52453/rss.xml</link>
    <description>Updated Land Research content from the US Environmental Protection Agency</description>
    <language>en</language>
     <atom:link href="https://www.epa.gov/feed/52453/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      <item>
    <title>ProUCL version 5.1.00 Documentation Downloads</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/land-research/proucl-version-5100-documentation-downloads</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;ProUCL 5.1 is a user friendly freeware package providing statistical and graphical tools needed to address statistical issues described in the various EPA guidance documents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-285929&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-05/documents/proucl_v5.1_inst.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=45365&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Instructions (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(2 pp, 45 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-285933&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-05/documents/proucl_5.1_fact_sheet.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=65936&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Fact Sheet (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(1 pg, 66 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-285941&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-05/documents/proucl_5.1_user-guide.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=6714950&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;User Guide (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(272 pp, 7 MB)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-285945&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-05/documents/proucl_5.1_tech-guide.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=6850241&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Technical Guide (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(351 pp, 7 MB)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 18 May 2016 18:27:15 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cbooker</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">149929 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>EPA scientists develop method for assessing bioavailability of arsenic &amp; lead in contaminated soils</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/land-research/epa-scientists-develop-method-assessing-bioavailability-arsenic-lead-contaminated</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;Cleaning up arsenic and lead at &lt;a href=&quot;/superfund/sites/index.htm&quot;&gt;Superfund sites&lt;/a&gt; can be an expensive proposition. Currently, if contaminant levels are high, the top layer of soil is removed and transported to a hazardous materials landfill for treatment to isolate and remove toxic metals. The price tag for such remediation activities can reach into the millions of dollars per acre.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, not all toxic metals present in soil are in a form that can harm humans or animals. Certain forms of arsenic and lead are not fully available, or absorbed by the human body. The amount that is absorbed is referred to as “bioavailable,” meaning it is in a form that can enter the bloodstream and affect human health.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Improved methods are needed to determine bioavailability of metals to protect human health.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA scientists are developing rapid, reliable, inexpensive methods for assessing the bioavailability of arsenic and lead in contaminated soils.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of these new methods involves the use of mice to mimic how the human digestive system absorbs arsenic. Mice are given food and soil containing arsenic, replicating measurements taken at a contaminated site. After a certain amount of time, scientists measure the amount of toxic metals found in the animals’ urine and compare it to the amount that was given in food. The difference between the two is the amount of lead or arsenic the mice have absorbed — in other words, the amount that is bioavailable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA scientists are also working on a chemical extraction laboratory method that mimics the human gastrointestinal system. As part of this effort, they are using advanced instruments to determine the chemical form of arsenic and lead in soil samples and assess whether they are potentially bioavailable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scientists plan to use the mouse method to validate the new lab method. If successful, researchers will be able to determine the bioavailability of these contaminants without having to rely on animals at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The use of bioavailability methods is a much more cost-effective way to obtain accurate data for contaminated sites and could have a big impact on the way Superfund and other contaminated sites are managed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Results from this bioavailability research have already provided information and protocols for assessing Superfund sites. When researchers evaluated arsenic-contaminated soil samples from a site using the newly developed bioavailability methods, they found that only about half the arsenic was bioavailable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this example, only approximately 90 acres of soil needed to be removed, which reduced the price of the cleanup from $24 million to $15 million.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, once the development of the chemical laboratory method is complete, researchers will be able to determine the bioavailability of contaminants without the use of animal studies. The use of site-specific bioavailability information has the potential to allow for customized cleanup levels that could result in millions of dollars in savings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Technical Contact&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;mailto:bradham.karen@epa.gov&quot;&gt;Karen Bradham, Ph.D.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Related Links&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/aboutepa/about-national-exposure-research-laboratory-nerl&quot;&gt;EPA Exposure Research&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/sciencematters/epa-science-matters-newsletter-volume-3-number-1#vol3_1-5&quot;&gt;Science Matters: New Testing Methods for Arsenic and Lead in Soil&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/21749965&quot;&gt;Journal article: Relative bioavailability and bioaccessibility and speciation of arsenic in contaminated soil&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/superfund/superfund-cleanup-process&quot;&gt;Cleaning up the Nation’s hazardous waste sites&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/land-research/superfund-and-technology-liaison-program-fact-sheet&quot;&gt;Fact Sheet: EPA Superfund and Technology Liaison Program&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/superfund/superfund-community-involvement&quot;&gt;Superfund Community Involvement&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/land-research/superfund-and-technology-liaison-program-fact-sheet&quot;&gt;EPA land and waste management research&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/land-research/innovative-ways-testing-contaminated-soil-factsheet&quot;&gt;Fact Sheet: New testing methods for arsenic and lead in soil&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;div&gt;
		&lt;div id=&quot;_com_1&quot;&gt; &lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 12 Apr 2016 14:20:24 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cbooker</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">142673 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Innovative Ways for Testing Contaminated Soil Factsheet</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/land-research/innovative-ways-testing-contaminated-soil-factsheet</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;EPA scientists are developing rapid, reliable, inexpensive methods for assessing the bioavailability of arsenic and lead in contaminated soils.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-274715&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-04/documents/bioavailability_factsheet.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=631591&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Innovative Ways for Testing Contaminated Soil Factsheet (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(2 pp, 632 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 06 Apr 2016 14:27:14 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cbooker</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">142303 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Engineering Technical Support Center (ETSC)</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/land-research/engineering-technical-support-center-etsc</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-png right view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:200px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;ETSC remediatIng contaminatnts using Situ Chemical Oxidation technology from hazardous wasate site&quot; height=&quot;150&quot; width=&quot;200&quot; class=&quot;right media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2015-09/_thumb_59022.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;The Engineering Technical Support Center (ETSC) provides technical support for soil, sediment, groundwater and mining-related contamination.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ETSC is one of EPA’s technical support and resource centers responsible for providing specialized scientific and engineering support to decision-makers in the EPA&#039;s program and ten regional offices. EPA’s regional offices work with states, communities, and local businesses within their area. These decision-makers include remedial project managers, corrective action staff, and on-scene coordinators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;accordion&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#pane-1&quot; title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What We Can Do For You&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

		&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;pane-1&quot;&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;ETSC delivers expertise on the latest methods, approaches, and technologies to characterize, remediate, and manage pollution at contaminated sites. We supply scientific and engineering knowledge and expertise in soil, sediment, and mine waste. ETSC provides site-specific technical assistance at&lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Superfund,&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;li&gt;RCRA,&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;li&gt;brownfields, and&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;li&gt;ecosystem restoration sites.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;ETSC also develops and conducts&lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;treatability studies, modeling support and site-specific document reviews;&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;li&gt;workshops, seminars, and conferences on state-of-the-science issues; and&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;li&gt;publications on remediation and treatment technologies for Superfund, RCRA, brownfields, and other contaminated site issues.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#pane-2&quot; title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Site Specific Assistance&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
		&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;pane-2&quot;&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;In FY14, ETSC responded to approximately 270 technical support requests from over 120 contaminated sites in the U.S., its territories (Puerto Rico) and internationally (Vietnam and Canada). Seventy-five percent of the contaminated site requests were &lt;a href=&quot;/superfund/superfund-national-priorities-list-npl&quot;&gt;Superfund National Priority List (NPL)&lt;/a&gt; sites. Some on-going examples of ETSC support include:&lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Modeling of possible dam breach at the Argonaut Mine (Jackson, CA) &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;p&gt;ETSC in conjunction with a contractor is working on a debris flow model for the Argonaut Mine in Jackson, CA. This model will estimate the effects if a breach of the Eastwood Multiple Arch Dam occurs. This dam contains tailings from the Argonaut mine.&lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Black Butte Mine and Cottage Grove Reservoir (Willamette Valley, OR)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;p&gt;The Black Butte Mine is a historic mercury (Hg) mine located in the Willamette Valley, OR. It produced approximately 700 tons of elemental Hg. The site was added to the Superfund list in part due to the community’s concern about Hg levels in the reservoir fish. The majority of the Hg that accumulates in the fish is an organic form of mercury (methylmercury-MeHg). MeHg is more toxic than elemental mercury. From 2012 to 2014, Region 10 and ETSC scientists collaborated to understand the fate and transport mechanisms at play transforming the elemental Hg to MeHg. The research team gathered and analyzed samples. The research indicates that seasonal water level fluctuations and elemental sulfur cycling within the reservoir influences elemental Hg transformation to MeHg. EPA&#039;s research effort now focuses on controlling parameters in the watershed that can reduce the production of MeHg.&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#pane-3&quot; title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Publications &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
		&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;pane-3&quot;&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://cfpub.epa.gov/si/si_public_search_results.cfm?simpleSearch=1&amp;amp;searchAll=etsc&quot;&gt;Reports Highlighting Current Activities&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Resources&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
		&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;pane-4&quot;&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;ETSC connects regional staff with the specialized technical engineering expertise. Available resources include&lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;a core team of scientists and engineers providing a readily available source of interdisciplinary support;&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;li&gt;scientists and engineers with experience in a broad range of disciplines related to land and water remediation and pollution control available for consultation;&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;li&gt;expert technical support from universities and research institutions; and&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;li&gt;additional support from contractors, and specialized consultants.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#pane-5&quot; title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Technical Contact&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
		&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;pane-5&quot;&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;Contact us to ask a question, provide feedback, or report a problem.&lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;mailto:mckernan.john@epa.gov&quot;&gt;John McKernan&lt;/a&gt;, ScD, CIH&lt;br /&gt;
				Captain, U.S. Public Health Service&lt;br /&gt;
				Director, Engineering Technical Support Center&lt;br /&gt;
				513-569-7415&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Related Information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://clu-in.org/remediation/&quot;&gt;Contamination Clean-up Information: About Remediation Technologies&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jul 2015 15:05:25 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>Anonymous</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">99687 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Technical Support Centers</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/land-research/technical-support-centers</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;ORD has five technical support centers that help integrate science and technology into hazardous waste cleanup activities: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol class=&quot;roomy&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/water-research/ground-water-technical-support-center-gwtsc&quot;&gt;Ground Water Technical Support Center&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/land-research/site-characterization-and-monitoring-technical-support-center-scmtsc&quot;&gt;Site Characterization and Modeling Technical Support Center&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/land-research/engineering-technical-support-center-etsc&quot;&gt;Engineering Technical Support Center&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Superfund Health Risk Technical Support Center&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Ecological Risk Technical Support Center&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;These centers, located around the country, offer scientific expertise and services to the EPA’s program and regional offices on site characterization, modeling, monitoring, assessment, and remediation. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 21 Apr 2015 18:18:51 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>Anonymous</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">81331 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Site Characterization and Monitoring Technical Support Center (SCMTSC)</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/land-research/site-characterization-and-monitoring-technical-support-center-scmtsc</link>
    <description>&lt;div&gt;On this page:&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#do&quot;&gt;What We Can Do for You&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#resources&quot;&gt;Resources&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#assistance&quot;&gt;Site-Specific Technical Assistance&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#highlights&quot;&gt;Current Projects and Highlights&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#contact&quot;&gt;Contact&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Site Characterization and Monitoring Technical Support Center (SCMTSC) provides technical assistance to regional programs on complex hazardous waste site characterization issues. When on-site work is required, the SCMTSC provides specialized teams of ORD and contract scientists equipped to aid the regions with screening and site characterization. The diversity of expertise available through the SCMTSC allows it to work with the regional programs at any time during a site characterization event. Often these projects lead to identification of further research needs or development of protocols for experimental or sampling design. The SCMTSC works with other EPA support centers as part of the &lt;a href=&quot;/remedytech/technical-support-project-cleaning-contaminated-sites&quot;&gt;EPA’s Technical Support Project&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;do&quot; id=&quot;do&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What We Can Do For You&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The SCMTSC provides quick-response technical assistance to remedial project managers and other decision makers on site-specific problems at Superfund, RCRA, and Brownfields sites by:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Evaluating reports, models and work plans related to field sampling and measurement&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Reviewing field sampling and monitoring and contaminant measurement activities, including:
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;soil-gas measurements&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;site characterization technologies&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;waste  fingerprinting&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;geophysics&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Assisting with statistical needs for site characterization&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Developing issue papers&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Performing special analytical services&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Providing evaluations on vapor intrusion, environmental forensics and remote sensing technology&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;resources&quot; id=&quot;resources&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Resources&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The SCMTSC’s structure allows for rapid response to requests for assistance on site-specific issues and access to experts in environmental sampling and investigation. Available resources include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;A core team of scientists and engineers providing a readily available source of technical support&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;A broad scientific base of scientists and engineers specializing in the field sampling, analysis, and characterization of contaminants&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Access to technology oriented firms, support contractors, and specialized consultants&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;assistance&quot; id=&quot;assistance&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Site-Specific Assistance&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The SCMTSC provides technical assistance for more than 100 short-term information requests and over 20 long-term site-specific projects every year. This support includes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Technical guidance on site characterization and the selection of investigative or monitoring techniques&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Review and interpretation of site-specific statistical methods and analysis of data&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Assistance in the review, development, or interpretation of sampling and monitoring plans&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Analysis and evaluation of site data&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Interpretation and development of conceptual site models&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;highlights&quot; id=&quot;highlights&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recent Project Highlights&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Red River, Oklahoma (EPA Region 6)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Between 2011 and 2013, four fish kills occurred in the Red River watershed in southeastern Oklahoma. The SCMTSC assisted EPA Region 6 and the State of Oklahoma Department of Environmental Quality in identifying unknown contaminants that were present at the time of the kills.  Using mass spectrometry, the conditional assignments of the molecular weights and chemical formulas of the unknown contaminants were determined.  A final external &lt;a href=&quot;http://cfpub.epa.gov/si/si_public_record_report.cfm?dirEntryId=273756&amp;amp;fed_org_id=770&amp;amp;SIType=PR&amp;amp;TIMSType=&amp;amp;showCriteria=0&amp;amp;address=nerl/pubs.html&amp;amp;view=citation&amp;amp;sortBy=pubDateYear&amp;amp;count=100&amp;amp;dateBeginPublishedPresented=01/01/2010&quot;&gt;report&lt;/a&gt; was published in 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Atlantic, Iowa (EPA Region 7) &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The municipal water supply well field in this small town in western Iowa is contaminated with perchloroethylene (PCE). EPA believes the source of the contamination is a former dry cleaners facility.  SCMTSC has provided support to regional project managers to better understand ground water conditions at the site.  This support included evaluating a ground water pump and treat system and the impacts of source treatment on fate and transport of the aqueous-phase PCE plume.  SCMTSC also assisted with developing a conceptual site model and constructing a ground water flow and contaminant transport model.  The models were used to evaluate the impacts of remedial alternatives. Predictive simulations executed with the models suggest that remediation of the remaining PCE source in the clays and silts does not have a dramatic impact on the shape of the plume or on the magnitude and remediation timeframes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The models, data and information generated by SCMTSC will help make more cost-effective source removal and ground water cleanup decisions at this site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;contact&quot; id=&quot;contact&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contact&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;mailto:barnett.felicia@epa.gov&quot;&gt;Felicia Barnett&lt;/a&gt;, Director&lt;br /&gt;
	Site Characterization and Monitoring Technical Support Center&lt;br /&gt;
	barnett.felicia@epa.gov&lt;br /&gt;
	(404) 562-8659&lt;br /&gt;
	 &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 21 Apr 2015 18:10:34 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>Anonymous</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">81325 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Contact Us About Land and Waste Management Research</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/land-research/forms/contact-us-about-land-and-waste-management-research</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Please use the form below to send us comments or questions. Be sure to include your e-mail address if you’d like a response.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;box right&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;box left&quot; href=&quot;/enforcement/report-environmental-violations&quot; style=&quot;width:93.4375px&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Report an environmental violation&quot; src=&quot;/sites/all/themes/epa/img/badge.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

	&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/enforcement/report-environmental-violations&quot;&gt;Report a Violation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

	&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;Report possible violations of environmental laws and regulations.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Send e-mail to: &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;mailto:ferster.aaron@epa.gov&quot;&gt;Aaron Ferster&lt;/a&gt; (ferster.aaron@epa.gov)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mailing Address:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	US EPA Research&lt;br /&gt;
	Office of Science Information Management&lt;br /&gt;
	Mail Drop: D343-04&lt;br /&gt;
	109 Alexander Drive&lt;br /&gt;
	Durham, NC 27711&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 09 Apr 2015 12:59:06 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cbooker</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">79833 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Obtaining Technical Support for Superfund, RCRA and Brownfields Site Issues Fact Sheet</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/land-research/obtaining-technical-support-superfund-rcra-and-brownfields-site-issues-fact-sheet</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;EPA’s Technical Support Centers (TSCs) and other technical support services are available to Regional Remedial Project Managers, Corrective Action Staff, and On-Scene Coordinators needing specialized technical expertise for specific tasks or projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-116955&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-03/documents/final_tech_support_ctr_assist_5-22-14.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=339273&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Obtaining Technical Support for Superfund, RCRA and Brownfields Site Issues (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(2 pp, 339 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 18 Mar 2015 14:24:40 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cbooker</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">78199 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Superfund and Technology Liaison Program Fact Sheet</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/land-research/superfund-and-technology-liaison-program-fact-sheet</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;The Superfund and Technology Liaison (STL) Program was established to facilitate regional access to ORD laboratories, provide technical support, and assist with the integration of science and technology into decision-making for hazardous waste programs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-116953&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-03/documents/stl_factsheet122014.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=411111&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Superfund and Technology Liaison Program (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(1 pg, 411 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 18 Mar 2015 14:19:52 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cbooker</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">78195 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  </channel>
</rss>

<!-- Page cached by Boost @ 2017-01-25 17:42:42, expires @ 2017-01-26 05:42:42, lifetime 12 hours -->