<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?><rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.epa.gov/feed/49641/rss.xml" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/" xmlns:og="http://ogp.me/ns#" xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#" xmlns:sioc="http://rdfs.org/sioc/ns#" xmlns:sioct="http://rdfs.org/sioc/types#" xmlns:skos="http://www.w3.org/2004/02/skos/core#" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#">
  <channel>
    <title>Clean Water Rule</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/feed/49641/rss.xml</link>
    <description>Updated Clean Water Rule content from the US Environmental Protection Agency</description>
    <language>en</language>
     <atom:link href="https://www.epa.gov/feed/49641/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      <item>
    <title>Supreme Court Decisions Relevant to &quot;Waters of the United States&quot;</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/cleanwaterrule/supreme-court-decisions-relevant-waters-united-states</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;The Supreme Court has issued three decisions that provide critical context and guidance in determining the appropriate scope of &quot;waters of the United States&quot; covered by the Clean Water Act: &lt;/span&gt;&lt;em&gt;United States v. Riverside Bayview Homes, Inc.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;span&gt;, 474 U.S. 121 (1985); &lt;/span&gt;&lt;em&gt;Solid Waste Agency of Northern Cook County v. U.S. Army Corps of Engineers&lt;/em&gt;&lt;span&gt;, 531 U.S. 159 (2001); and &lt;/span&gt;&lt;em&gt;Rapanos v. United States&lt;/em&gt;&lt;span&gt;, 547 U.S. 715 (2006). &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-277927&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-04/documents/riversidebayviewhomes_opinion.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=169070&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;United States v. Riverside Bayview Homes, Inc. - December 4, 1985  (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(10 pp, 169 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-277929&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-04/documents/swancc_decision_2001.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=162287&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Solid Waste Agency of Northern Cook County v. U.S. Army Corps - January 9, 2001 (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(39 pp, 162 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-277931&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-04/documents/rapanos_decision_2006.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=806212&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Rapanos v. United States - June 19, 2006 (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(104 pp, 806 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 00:30:48 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>rkwok</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">147029 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Populations that Get Drinking Water from Streams</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/cleanwaterrule/populations-get-drinking-water-streams</link>
    <description>&lt;p id=&quot;intro&quot;&gt;The map depicts populations that get drinking water from streams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe height=&quot;665px&quot; src=&quot;https://epa.maps.arcgis.com/apps/MapSeries/index.html?appid=010e6a5699614c2d8b2a000083b52e23&quot; width=&quot;1030px&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 24 Sep 2015 19:31:56 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>kwilkers</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">116977 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Clean Water Rule Litigation Statement</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/cleanwaterrule/clean-water-rule-litigation-statement</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;EPA and the Department of the Army remain committed to strengthening coordination between the agencies and increasing transparency for clean water programs. On November 16, 2015, EPA Administrator Gina McCarthy and Assistant Secretary of the Army (Civil Works) Jo-Ellen Darcy issued a &lt;a href=&quot;/sites/production/files/2015-11/documents/2015-11-16_signed_cwr_post-stay_coordination_memo.pdf&quot;&gt;joint memorandum&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(3 pp, 541 K, &lt;a href=&quot;/home/pdf-files&quot;&gt;About PDF&lt;/a&gt;) &lt;/span&gt;to their staff directing that the agencies work together to improve implementation of the national Clean Water Act section 404 program. These measures will improve transparency, strengthen the coordination processes between the agencies, increase public participation, promote use of the best available science and technical data for making case-specific significant nexus determinations, and promote public health and environmental protection for all Americans who depend on reliable and abundant sources of clean water.  These steps will be taken under the agencies&#039; existing regulations and policies and be consistent with the stay of the Clean Water Rule issued by the Sixth Circuit Court of Appeals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On October 9, 2015, the U.S. Court of Appeals for the Sixth Circuit stayed the Clean Water Rule nationwide pending further action of the court. EPA and the Department of the Army are fully complying with the stay.  The court acknowledges that clarification of the Clean Water Act is needed and that “agencies conscientiously endeavored, within their technical expertise and experience, and based on reliable peer-reviewed science, to promulgate new standards to protect water quality that conform to the Supreme Court’s guidance.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In response to this decision, EPA and the Department of Army resumed nationwide use of the agencies’ prior regulations defining the term “waters of the United States.” Those regulations will be implemented as they were prior to August 27, 2015, by applying relevant case law, applicable policy, and the best science and technical data on a case-by-case basis in determining which waters are protected by the Clean Water Act.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The agencies look forward to vigorously defending the merits of the Clean Water Rule, which the agencies continue to believe is fully consistent with the law and based on the best available peer-reviewed science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Clean Water Rule was developed by the agencies to respond to an urgent need to improve and simplify the process for identifying waters that are and are not protected under the Clean Water Act, and is based on the latest science and the law. The Clean Water Rule represents the agencies’ continuing commitment to protecting and restoring the nation’s water resources that are vital for our health, environment, and economy.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Fri, 28 Aug 2015 17:10:00 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>rkwok</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">109493 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Technical Questions and Answers For Implementation of the Clean Water Rule </title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/cleanwaterrule/technical-questions-and-answers-implementation-clean-water-rule</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;The U.S. Army Corps of Engineers and the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency have jointly prepared the following Questions and Answers regarding implementation of the Clean Water Rule. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;The final rule became effective on August 28, 2015. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/cleanwaterrule/clean-water-rule-litigation-statement&quot;&gt;Click here for EPA and the Department of Army&#039;s statement on the relevance of recent court rulings&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt;. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;The agencies will periodically update these Questions and Answers &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;as experience with the rule grows. &lt;span&gt;If there are slight differences, the language in the &lt;a href=&quot;/cleanwaterrule/final-clean-water-rule&quot;&gt;final preamble and rule&lt;/a&gt; controls and should be used for purposes of understanding the scope and requirements of the final rule.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Implementation – Grandfathering&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;indented&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Q: Are preliminary jurisdictional determinations affected by the new rule?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;indented&quot;&gt;Preliminary jurisdictional determinations (PJDs) from the Corps for Clean Water Act Section 404 purposes are not affected by the new rule.  A PJD is a non-binding “. . . written indication that there may be waters of the United States, including wetlands, on a parcel” and may be used to voluntarily waive or set aside questions regarding jurisdiction over a particular site, usually in the interest of allowing the landowner or other “affected party” to move ahead expeditiously to obtain a Corps permit. Landowners may rely on existing PJDs regarding a specific authorization/verification even after the new rule is in effect.  Landowners may continue to request a PJD in lieu of an approved jurisdictional determination under the new rule.  In addition, landowners with an existing PJD may request an approved jurisdictional determination under the new rule if they choose, which would be finalized after the effective date of the new rule. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;indented&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Q: What is the status of an approved jurisdictional determination associated with a pending complete nationwide permit pre-construction notification (PCN)?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;indented&quot;&gt;For an approved jurisdictional determination associated with a complete Section 404 pre-construction notification (per Nationwide Permit General Condition #31 and any related Corps district-specific regional conditions) pending on or before publication date of the new rule (i.e., June 29, 2015), the approved jurisdictional determination will be finalized consistent with the former rule, regardless of the date of the NWP verification decision. However, the applicant has discretion to request that the Corps apply the new rule, in which case the Corps would finalize the approved jurisdictional determination after the effective date under the new rule. Pending PCNs must not be withdrawn and resubmitted for the old rules to apply.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;indented&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Q: For how long are Approved Jurisdictional Determinations valid and under what circumstances would they be revised prior to expiration&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;indented&quot;&gt;Approved JDs are valid for five years, unless new site-specific information warrants a revision.  The Corps has determined this new rule does not constitute new site-specific information.  Once the new rule takes effect, if new site-specific information warrants a revision to the Approved JD before it expires, the Approved JD will be reconsidered and finalized under the new rule. Approved JDs may be reconsidered under the new rule prior to expiration at the landowner’s request.  However, finalization of that reconsidered Approved JD will occur after the effective date of the new rule. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;indented&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Q: What is the status of an Approved JD associated with existing issued permits and verifications&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;indented&quot;&gt;Approved JDs associated with issued permits and verifications are valid until the expiration date of the permit or verification, including time extensions for permits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;indented&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Q: If a stand-alone Approved JD is finalized after the effective date of the new rule, is it issued under the former rule or the Clean Water Rule&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;indented&quot;&gt;Stand-alone Approved JDs completed after the effective date are finalized under the new rule.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;indented&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Q: What is the status of an Approved JD associated with a pending individual permit application where the application was determined complete on or before publication date of the new rule&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;indented&quot;&gt;For an Approved JD associated with complete individual permit applications (per regulation at 33 CFR 325.1) pending on or before publication date of the new rule, the Approved JD will be verified consistent with the former rule, regardless of the date of the permit decision, unless the applicant requests the Corps apply the new rule, in which case the Corps would finalize the Approved JD after the effective date under the new rule.  Note that a finalized JD is not among the required contents of a complete application described at 33 CFR 325.1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Adjacent Waters&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;indented&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Q: What waters may be covered under the adjacent category of waters?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;indented&quot;&gt;The Rule includes all waters adjacent to a water identified in paragraphs (a)(1) through (a)(5) – the traditional navigable waters interstate waters, territorial seas, impoundments, and tributaries. These adjacent waters may include wetlands, ponds, lakes, oxbows, impoundments, and similar waters. Adjacent waters do not include waters that are subject to established normal farming, silviculture, and ranching activities as those terms are used in Section 404(f) of the CWA.  However, such waters may be subject to a case-specific significant nexus analysis under paragraph (a)(7) or (a)(8).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;indented&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Q: How is the 100-year floodplain determined when Federal Emergency Management Agency (FEMA) maps are either unavailable or inaccurate&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;indented&quot;&gt;The 100-year floodplain is the area that will be inundated by the flood event having a one percent chance of being equaled or exceeded in any given year, which is consistent with the FEMA definition of the “100-year flood.”  When FEMA maps are unavailable or inaccurate, the agencies will rely on other available tools to identify the 100-year floodplain, including other federal, state, or local floodplain maps, Natural Resources Conservation Service (NRCS) Soil Surveys (Flooding Frequency Classes), tidal gage data, and site-specific modeling.  Additional supporting information can include historical evidence such as photographs, prior delineations, topographic maps, and existing site characteristics.  The Corps and EPA will coordinate with other federal and state agencies to develop additional information to further improve tools for identifying the 100-year floodplain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;indented&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Q: Is distance thresholds measured as straight-line distances or do they account for vertical changes&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;indented&quot;&gt;Distance thresholds should be measured perpendicular to the ordinary high water mark or high tide line, whichever is applicable, in straight-line distance extending landward.  Such distance measurements do not account for vertical changes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;indented&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Q: To be considered “normal farming,” does the farming activity have to have started prior to 1977&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;indented&quot;&gt;No.  To be considered “normal farming,” a practice needs to be part of a legally established ongoing farming, silviculture, or ranching operation, and there is no requirement that the operation has been underway prior to 1977.  Activities on areas lying fallow as part of a conventional rotational cycle are part of an established operation.  Activities which bring an area into farming, silviculture or ranching use, or convert from one use to another, are not part of an established operation.  Regulations at 33 CFR 323.4 and 40 CFR 232.3(c)(1) provide more information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(a)(7) Case-Specific Waters Similarly Situated by Rule&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;indented&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Q: What analyses are required to find a water jurisdictional under (a) (7)&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;indented&quot;&gt;Field staff should first determine if a water is one of the five types listed under (a)(7), if so, then field staff would identify additional waters in the same single point of entry watershed that are of the same type as the water being evaluated.  Field staff will perform a significant nexus analysis on all the waters of the same type in the same single point of entry watershed, except those that are already jurisdictional categorically under the Clean Water Rule.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(a)(8) Case-Specific Waters&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;indented&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Q: What waters may be covered under the site-specific significant nexus categories of waters under paragraph (a)(8)?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;indented&quot;&gt;A water that is determined not to be adjacent under the Rule but that is within the 100-year floodplain of a traditional navigable water, interstate water, or territorial sea is jurisdictional where it has a significant nexus to a traditional navigable water, interstate water, or territorial sea either alone or in combination with similarly situated waters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;indented&quot;&gt;A water that is determined not to be adjacent under the Rule but is within 4,000 feet of the high tide line or ordinary high water mark of a traditional navigable water, interstate water, territorial sea, impoundment, or tributary is jurisdictional where it has a significant nexus to a traditional navigable water, interstate water, or territorial sea either alone or in combination with similarly situated waters.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;indented&quot;&gt;All significant nexus findings must be effectively documented with relevant site-specific factors that support the jurisdictional finding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;indented&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Q: What are considered wetland waters under the Rule?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;indented&quot;&gt;The definition of “wetland” does not change under the Rule: “The term &lt;em&gt;wetlands&lt;/em&gt; means those areas that are inundated or saturated by surface or groundwater at a frequency and duration sufficient to support, and that under normal circumstances do support, a prevalence of vegetation typically adapted for life in saturated soil conditions.  Wetlands generally include swamps, marshes, bogs, and similar areas.”  Wetlands are delineated using the 1987 Corps Wetland Delineation Manual including its Regional Supplements. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;indented&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Q: What types of non-wetland waters are included as adjacent waters or as site-specific significant nexus waters?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;indented&quot;&gt;Ponds, lakes, oxbows, impoundments, and similar waters are considered non-wetland waters that can be found to be jurisdictional as either adjacent or as site-specific significant nexus waters.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;indented&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Q: What analyses are required to find a water jurisdictional under (a)(8)&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;indented&quot;&gt;Field staff should first determine the single point of entry watershed for the water being evaluated and then determine if that water should be considered alone or in combination with similarly situated waters.  Field staff will perform a significant nexus analysis on those water(s).  In determining if waters are similarly situated, field staff can only consider other potential (a)(8) waters within the distance thresholds.  For determining whether waters are similarly situated, considerations could include, for example, whether waters are sufficiently close to each other, and whether they perform similar functions, such as habitat, water storage, sediment retention and pollution sequestration. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Characteristics of Tributaries and Erosional Features&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;indented&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Q: What is the difference between tributaries under the Clean Water Rule and erosional features which are not considered “waters of the U.S.” under the Rule?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;indented&quot;&gt;For the purposes of the Rule, a tributary is a water that contributes flow, either directly or through another water, to a traditional navigable water, interstate water, or the territorial seas that exhibits physical indicators of flow through a bed and banks and an ordinary high water mark (OHWM). Ephemeral erosional features, such as gullies, rills, and non-wetland swales, do not have the physical features of tributaries and are specifically excluded from the definition of waters of the U.S. Concentrated surface runoff may occur within an erosional feature, but without creating the physical characteristics associated with bed and banks and an ordinary high water mark, the feature will not be jurisdictional.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;indented&quot;&gt;It should be noted that some ephemeral streams are colloquially called “gullies” or the like even where they exhibit a bed and banks and an ordinary high water mark; regardless of the name they are given locally, waters that meet the definition of tributary are not excluded erosional features.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;indented&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Q: What is a “bed and banks”?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;indented&quot;&gt;The bed and banks is the substrate (the bottom) and sides of a channel between which flow is confined.  The banks constitute a break in slope between the edge of the bed and the surrounding terrain.  This break in slope may vary from gradual to steep, depending on the landscape position of the channel.  The bed may be devoid of vegetation or may be fully vegetated depending on precipitation levels, volume, frequency, and duration of flow. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;indented&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Q: What is an “ordinary high water mark” (OHWM) and what are its indicators?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;indented&quot;&gt;The OHWM is that line on the shore established by the fluctuations of water and indicated by physical characteristics such as a clear, natural line impressed on the bank, shelving, changes in the character of soil, destruction of terrestrial vegetation, the presence of litter and debris, or other appropriate means that consider the characteristics of the surrounding areas.  The OHWMs can take on a variety of appearances and have a wide range of indicators depending on location, recent flow conditions, and other factors.  These factors and other relevant indicators are discussed in detail in applicable Corps guidance documents and manuals on OHWM identification. The OHWM manuals can be found at: http://www.erdc.usace.army.mil/OHWM/.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;indented&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Q: Where do erosional features occur?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;indented&quot;&gt;Erosional features occur where there is enough concentrated surface runoff to form a channel, but that channel has insufficient volume, frequency, and duration of flow to exhibit the physical characteristics of a bed and banks and/or OHWM.  In some circumstances a tributary may demonstrate breaks in the presence of bed and banks and/or OHWM along the connection to the downstream traditional navigable water, interstate water, or territorial sea while hydrologic connectivity remains.  Such breaks in bed, banks and or OHWM may include an erosional feature. Flow through a non-jurisdictional erosional feature does not preclude the water from remaining a tributary so long as the bed and banks and an OHWM are present upstream of the break. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;indented&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Q: How can I determine the difference between a tributary and an erosional feature in the field?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;indented&quot;&gt;If the feature is a tributary you will generally be able to identify bed and banks and another indicator of an OHWM unless disturbed conditions exist, such as during or shortly after extreme flow events or due to man-made alterations.  As explained above, erosional features lack a bed and banks and/or an OHWM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Exclusions—Generally&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;indented&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Q: What is “dry land&lt;/em&gt;?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;indented&quot;&gt;Dry land is those areas that are not water features, such as streams, wetlands, lakes, ponds, and the like.  It is important to note that a “water of the United States” is not considered dry land just because it lacks water at a given time.  An area remains dry land even if it is wet after a rainfall event so long as it is not a stream, lake, pond, or wetland and the like. So features such as puddles, wet spots and gullies are still considered dry land. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Exclusions – Ditches&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;indented&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Q: Can a ditch be considered adjacent&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;indented&quot;&gt;No.  Ditches are jurisdictional under the rule only if they both meet the definition of “tributary” and are not excluded under paragraph (b)(3) of the rule.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Exclusions—Other&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;indented&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Q: Can parts of a Municipal Separate Storm Sewer System (MS4) be a water of the US, and other parts be excluded&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;indented&quot;&gt;Yes.  It is a longstanding EPA position that MS4s can contain jurisdictional waters. MS4s often rely on a drainage network consisting of jurisdictional waters as well as constructed conveyance structures to transport stormwater. Where MS4s incorporate creeks and streams, which may be channelized, piped or otherwise modified within their drainage network, the creeks and streams remain jurisdictional waters even if they are considered to be a part of the MS4.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;indented&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Q: Are stormwater control features constructed in uplands that have developed into wetlands (meeting the three parameters of soils, vegetation, and hydrology under the 1987 Corps Wetlands Delineation Manual) jurisdictional under the Clean Water Rule?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;indented&quot;&gt;No. The new stormwater exclusion covers all stormwater control features that are built in dry land.  The exclusion is broadly defined to cover stormwater control measures that are constructed to convey, treat, or store stormwater built in dry land, and does not specify particular control measures that qualify for the exclusion. Stormwater professionals and NPDES regulations refer to stormwater control features as Best Management Practices or BMPs. The Agencies decided not to list specific measures or features because the lack of uniform definitions for many of the features could miss some features and fail to anticipate future control features that should be captured by the exclusion.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Fri, 31 Jul 2015 19:52:18 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>rkwok</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">101881 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Memoranda Regarding Implementation of the Clean Water Rule</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/cleanwaterrule/memoranda-regarding-implementation-clean-water-rule</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;The memoranda on implemention of the Clean Water Rule were signed by Gina McCarthy, EPA Administrator, and Jo-Ellen Darcy, Assistant Secretary of the Army (Civil Works). The &lt;a href=&quot;/cleanwaterrule/final-clean-water-rule&quot;&gt;Clean Water Rule&lt;/a&gt; was published in the &lt;em&gt;Federal Register &lt;/em&gt;on June 29, 2015 and became effective on August 28, 2015. &lt;a href=&quot;/cleanwaterrule/clean-water-rule-litigation-statement&quot;&gt;Click here for EPA and the Department of Army&#039;s statement on the relevance of recent court rulings&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-169227&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-07/documents/clean_water_rule_implemtation_memo.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=600013&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Clean Water Rule Implementation Memorandum (July 2015) (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(3 pp, 600 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-229341&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-11/documents/2015-11-16_signed_cwr_post-stay_coordination_memo.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=541195&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Administration of Clean Water Programs in Light of the Stay of the Clean Water Rule; Improving Transparency and Strengthening Coordination (November 2015) (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(3 pp, 541 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Fri, 31 Jul 2015 16:35:50 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>rkwok</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">101767 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Clean Water Rule Presentations</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/cleanwaterrule/clean-water-rule-presentations</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;Presentations on the Clean Water Rule. &lt;a href=&quot;/cleanwaterrule/clean-water-rule-litigation-statement&quot;&gt;Click here for EPA and the Department of Army&#039;s statement on the relevance of recent court rulings&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-151537&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-06/documents/clean_water_rule_presentation_6-11-15.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=2934569&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;The Clean Water Rule - A June 11, 2015 Presentation (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(43 pp, 3 MB)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-184457&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-08/documents/clean_water_rule_08-27-15.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=1738749&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;The Clean Water Rule - August 27, 2015 Presentation (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(10 pp, 2 MB)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 24 Jun 2015 20:15:48 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>rkwok</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">94295 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Response to Comments for the Clean Water Rule: Definition of &quot;Waters of the United States&quot;</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/cleanwaterrule/response-comments-clean-water-rule-definition-waters-united-states</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;The Response to Comments Document, together with the preamble to the final Clean Water Rule, presents the responses of the EPA and the Department of the Army to the more than one million public comments received on the proposed rule (79 FR 22188 (Apr. 21, 2014)). The agencies have addressed all significant issues raised in the public comments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of the volume of comments received, the Response to Comment Document is presented in a number of different topical compendiums. Each of these compendiums is available below. The compendiums were numbered for convenience based on the database used to track incoming comments, and no particular meaning is intended by the numbering system.  In total, all of these compendiums represent the agencies’ formal Response to Comment Document.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These compendiums have been formatted to be compliant with section 508 of the Rehabilitation Act, which requires Federal agencies to make their electronic and information technology accessible to people with disabilities. In addition, the compendiums have been reformatted to ensure margins, typeface, comment and response numbers, and identification of pictures with text are consistent throughout. There have been no changes to the content or substance of the Response to Comment document that was prepared at signature of the Clean Water Rule.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Response to Comments Document, together with the preamble to the Clean Water Rule and the information contained in the Technical Support Document, the Science Report, and the rest of the administrative record should be considered collectively as the agencies’ response to all of the significant comments submitted on the proposed rule. Where there are slight differences, the language in the final preamble and rule controls and should be used for purposes of understanding the scope, requirements, and basis of the final rule.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-150189&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-06/documents/cwr_response_to_comments_mass_mailing_campaigns.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=2948077&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Clean Water Rule Response to Comments - Mass Mailing Campaigns (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(262 pp, 3 MB)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-150161&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-06/documents/cwr_response_to_comments_1_general.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=3558818&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Clean Water Rule Response to Comments - Topic 1 General (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(372 pp, 4 MB)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-150169&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-06/documents/cwr_response_to_comments_2_tnw.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=1503929&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Clean Water Rule Response to Comments - Topic 2 Traditional Navigable Waters, Interstate Waters, Territorial Seas, and Impoundments (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(106 pp, 2 MB)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-150185&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-06/documents/cwr_response_to_comments_3_adjacent_waters.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=4267441&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Clean Water Rule Response to Comments - Topic 3 Adjacent Waters (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(407 pp, 4 MB)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-150187&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-06/documents/cwr_response_to_comments_4_other_waters.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=5386507&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Clean Water Rule Response to Comments - Topic 4 Other Waters (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(587 pp, 5 MB)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-150193&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-06/documents/cwr_response_to_comments_5_sig_nex.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=3121554&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Clean Water Rule Response to Comments - Topic 5 Significant Nexus (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(315 pp, 3 MB)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-150195&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-06/documents/cwr_response_to_comments_6_ditches.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=5136370&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Clean Water Rule Response to Comments - Topic 6 Ditches (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(503 pp, 5 MB)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-150197&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-06/documents/cwr_response_to_comments_7_njd.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=6413725&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Clean Water Rule Response to Comments - Topic 7 Features and Waters Not Jurisdictional (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(682 pp, 6 MB)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-150199&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-06/documents/cwr_response_to_comments_8_tributaries.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=6476006&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Clean Water Rule Response to Comments - Topic 8 Tributaries (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(631 pp, 6 MB)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-150201&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-06/documents/cwr_response_to_comments_9_science.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=2348642&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Clean Water Rule Response to Comments - Topic 9 Scientific Evidence Support the Rule (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(201 pp, 2 MB)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-150203&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-06/documents/cwr_response_to_comments_10_legal.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=6066560&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Clean Water Rule Response to Comments - Topic 10 Legal Analysis (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(602 pp, 6 MB)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-150205&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-06/documents/cwr_response_to_comments_11_econ_vol1.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=2665243&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Clean Water Rule Response to Comments - Topic 11 Costs/Benefits (Volume 1) (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(216 pp, 3 MB)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-150207&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-06/documents/cwr_response_to_comments_11_econ_vol2.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=5215413&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Clean Water Rule Response to Comments - Topic 11 Costs/Benefits (Volume 2) (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(378 pp, 5 MB)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-150209&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-06/documents/cwr_response_to_comments_12_implementation.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=8237085&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Clean Water Rule Response to Comments - Topic 12 Implementation Issues (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(861 pp, 8 MB)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-150213&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-06/documents/cwr_response_to_comments_13_process_concerns_and_admin.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=3546124&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Clean Water Rule Response to Comments - Topic 13 Process Concerns and Administrative Requirements (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(368 pp, 4 MB)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-150215&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-06/documents/cwr_response_to_comments_13_process_concerns_and_admin_0.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=3522971&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Clean Water Rule Response to Comments - Topic 14 Miscellaneous (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(365 pp, 4 MB)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-150219&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-06/documents/cwr_response_to_comments_17_non_technical_comments_vol1.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=6965951&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Clean Water Rule Response to Comments - Topic 17 Non-technical Comments (Volume 1) (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(816 pp, 7 MB)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-150221&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-06/documents/cwr_response_to_comments_17_non_technical_comments_vol2.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=1238338&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Clean Water Rule Response to Comments - Topic 17 Non-technical Comments (Volume 2) (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(93 pp, 1 MB)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jun 2015 20:55:23 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>rkwok</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">93593 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Seasonal and Rain-Dependent Streams</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/cleanwaterrule/seasonal-and-rain-dependent-streams</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;The map below shows the extent of intermittent and ephemeral streams across the U.S.&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:928px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;The map shows the percentage of intermittent and ephemeral streams, relative to total stream length, within each watershed across the U.S. Excluding Alaska, 59% of the linear streams are intermittent and ephemeral.&quot; height=&quot;680&quot; width=&quot;928&quot; class=&quot;media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2015-05/stream_percentage_high.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
     <pubDate>Fri, 29 May 2015 16:44:58 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>kwilkers</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">86057 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Clean Water Rule Environmental Assessment - Finding of No Significant Impact</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/cleanwaterrule/clean-water-rule-environmental-assessment-finding-no-significant-impact</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;Environmental Assessment - Findng of No Significant Impact Regarding Adoption of the Clean Water Rule: Definition of Waters of the United States&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-135495&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-05/documents/finding_of_no_significant_impact_the_clean_water_rule_52715.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=733780&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Environmental Assessment - Finding of No Significant Impact (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(104 pp, 734 K)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;field field-name-field-document-description field-type-text field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    Environmental Assessment - Finding of No Significant Impact for Clean Water Rule  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 28 May 2015 19:18:01 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>kwilkers</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">85871 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  </channel>
</rss>

<!-- Page cached by Boost @ 2017-01-26 04:04:53, expires @ 2017-01-26 16:04:53, lifetime 12 hours -->