<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?><rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.epa.gov/feed/34933/rss.xml" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/" xmlns:og="http://ogp.me/ns#" xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#" xmlns:sioc="http://rdfs.org/sioc/ns#" xmlns:sioct="http://rdfs.org/sioc/types#" xmlns:skos="http://www.w3.org/2004/02/skos/core#" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#">
  <channel>
    <title>Pollution Prevention (P2)</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/feed/34933/rss.xml</link>
    <description>Updated Pollution Prevention (P2) content from the US Environmental Protection Agency</description>
    <language>en</language>
     <atom:link href="https://www.epa.gov/feed/34933/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      <item>
    <title>Quarterly Webinar for National Emphasis Area (NEA) Grantees</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/p2/quarterly-webinar-national-emphasis-area-nea-grantees-0</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;This webinar occurred on November 3, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The EPA National Pollution Prevention Program has established three national emphasis areas (NEAs) to give the program a more centralized focus and direction that will result in more impactful, measurable results. Through these webinars, we are hoping to share best practices among the states and regions in order to amplify all the great work we are doing in this country to support the goals of the NEAs. We had two great speakers for our kick-off meeting in the month of November.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These grants are part of the State and Community Approaches to Hazardous Materials Source Reduction NEA, but we are inviting all grantees to these calls in case you would like more information on the other NEA workgroups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Agenda:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Introduction of Panelists (Tina Guthrie) - 5 minutes&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rich Bizzozero&lt;/strong&gt; of the Massachusetts Office of Technical Assistance (MA OTA) will present on their three- year P2 State Technical Assistance Grant involving an innovative “train the trainer” approach to community hazardous material source reduction and climate resilience for businesses using hazardous materials in Massachusetts. Rich will discuss how MA OTA is providing grant funding to eight regional planning agencies that will each hold two training events designed to build models for incorporating toxics use reduction into community and regional emergency preparedness and climate resiliency planning - 20 minutes&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Helaine Barr &lt;/strong&gt;of the New Jersey Department of Environmental protection (NJDEP) will provide an overview of the New Jersey Sustainable Business Registry, which has identified 50 small businesses in the region and will discuss the sustainability efforts of these small businesses. These businesses have reduced their power, cut waste and have achieved other environmental results that have to date collectively saved nearly $2.5 million dollars. - 20 minutes&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Q&amp;amp;A 15 minutes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rich Bizzozero&lt;/strong&gt;, from the Massachusetts Office of Technical Assistance and the state&#039;s Toxics Use Reduction Act (TURA) program, has more than 25 years of experience. He has provided technical assistance to manufacturers, and for the past eight years he has serves as the OTA Director. In addition to his OTA responsibilities, Rich serves as Executive Director of the Massachusetts Toxics Use Reduction Administrative Council, a policy-making body that reviews proposed regulations and chemical policies to protect the health and safety of workers and the public at large and promotes increased coordination in the enforcement of toxics laws and regulations statewide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Helaine Barr, &lt;/strong&gt;from the New Jersey Department of Environmental Protection (NJDEP), is committed to advancing sustainability principals and programs that support New Jersey’s communities and businesses. As a Research Scientist, her responsibilities include coordination of the New Jersey Sustainable Business Registry, along with a number of other sustainability initiatives.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;file-329241&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-vndopenxmlformats-officedocumentpresentationmlpresentation&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/sites/production/files/2016-11/communitychemicalsafetyclimatechangeperparedness.pptx&quot; type=&quot;application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.presentationml.presentation; length=4923328&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Community Chemical Safety Climate Change Preparedness (PPTX)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(1 pg, 5 MB)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;file-329243&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-vndopenxmlformats-officedocumentpresentationmlpresentation&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/sites/production/files/2016-11/cultivatingsmallbusinesssustainability.pptx&quot; type=&quot;application/vnd.openxmlformats-officedocument.presentationml.presentation; length=9560248&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Cultivating Small Business Sustainability (PPTX)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(1 pg, 10 MB)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-329239&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-11/documents/epa_webinar_final_11_2_2016.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=2065892&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Cultivating Small Business Sustainability: Lessons Learned from the NJ Sustainable Business Registry (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(21 pp, 2 MB)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 03 Nov 2016 15:25:15 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>tgelaber</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">164453 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Quarterly Webinar for National Emphasis Area (NEA) Grantees</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/p2/quarterly-webinar-national-emphasis-area-nea-grantees</link>
    <description></description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 27 Oct 2016 12:25:34 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>tgelaber</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">163611 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Case Studies on Safer Alternatives for Solvent Degreasing Applications</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/p2/case-studies-safer-alternatives-solvent-degreasing-applications</link>
    <description>&lt;div class=&quot;box multi news right&quot; style=&quot;width:300px&quot;&gt;
	&lt;h3 class=&quot;pane-title&quot;&gt;Featured Solvents&lt;/h3&gt;

	&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Trichloroethylene (TCE)&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Methyl chloroform (TCA)&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Dichloromethane (DCM, methylene chloride)&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#pdf&quot;&gt;You may download a PDF version of this page below.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The transition to sustainable manufacturing is best accomplished by using pollution prevention (P2) approaches. This paper summarizes a number of case studies that highlight the P2 approach of switching to aqueous and less toxic metal cleaners to reduce health risks and manufacturing costs. EPA compiled these case studies as a supplement to &quot;&lt;a href=&quot;/toxics-release-inventory-tri-program/reducing-trichloroethylene-tce-waste-fabricated-metals-sector&quot;&gt;Pollution Prevention (P2) Spotlight: Reducing Trichloroethylene (TCE) Waste in the Fabricated Metals Sector&lt;/a&gt;.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;What are cleaning solvents and how are they used?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cleaning solvents are used to remove oil, grease, solder flux, and other contaminants. Facilities that produce metal products often use solvents and other chemicals as degreasers to clean metal parts in preparation for further finishing operations, like painting or welding. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Trends in the reduced use of TCE reported by the fabricated metals sector to EPA’s Toxic Release Inventory (TRI) database:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;box multi news right&quot; style=&quot;width:300px&quot;&gt;
	&lt;h3 class=&quot;pane-title&quot;&gt;Featured Solvents&lt;/h3&gt;

	&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Quantity of TCE releases to air decreased from 3 million lbs in 2001 to 0.6 million lbs. in 2012.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;The number of fabricated metal facilities reporting TCE decreased to 44 from 141, suggesting many facilities have eliminated TCE use entirely or reduced its use below the 10,000 pound reporting threshold.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Trichloroethylene (TCE)&lt;/strong&gt;: used as a solvent for metal degreasing, as well as a refrigerant and in dry cleaning fluid. TCE is a volatile organic compound (VOC) that poses a human health hazard to the central nervous system, kidney, liver, immune system, reproductive system, and to the developing fetus. TCE is also characterized by U.S. Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) as carcinogenic to humans by all routes of exposure (i.e., by inhalation, ingestion, and dermal exposure). &lt;a href=&quot;/assessing-and-managing-chemicals-under-tsca/trichloroethylene-tce&quot;&gt;Learn more about TCE&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Methyl chloroform (TCA)&lt;/strong&gt;: used as a solvent and in some consumer products. Exposure to TCA can result in mild motor impairment (e.g., increased reaction time), lightheadedness, impaired balance, and lack of muscle control in acutely exposed humans. Cardiac arrhythmia and respiratory arrest may result from the depression of the central nervous system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dichloromethane (DCM, methylene chloride)&lt;/strong&gt;: used as a solvent in paint strippers, a process solvent in the manufacture of pharmaceuticals and film coatings, a propellant in aerosols, and a solvent for metal cleaning and finishing in electronics manufacturing. Effects of short-term (acute) exposures to workers and consumers, including bystanders, can result in harm to the central nervous system, or neurotoxicity. Effects of longer periods of exposure (chronic) for workers includes liver toxicity, liver cancer, and lung cancer. &lt;a href=&quot;/assessing-and-managing-chemicals-under-tsca/fact-sheet-methylene-choride-or-dichloromethane-dcm&quot;&gt;Learn more about DCM&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Case Studies:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1. Schick (formerly American Safety Razor) in Verona, Virginia, manufactures a variety of blades and tools from steel stock. TCE was used as a cleaning solvent in both liquid and vapor cleaning/degreasing operations at a newly acquired facility. Schick&#039;s prior experience with TCE as a potential environmental contaminant, combined with increasing costs associated with its distillation and waste disposal and higher regulatory risk, made TCE elimination a priority.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Schick installed aqueous “wash boxes” on production lines to replace TCE-based cleaning processes, and also used an alcohol-based vapor degreaser as an effective substitute. TCE use has been completely eliminated at this plant. In addition to risk reduction, these P2 measures have resulted in an estimated cost reduction of $250,000 a year from reduced energy, material and hazardous waste disposal costs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/p2/pollution-prevention-accomplishments-schick-manufacturing-verona-virginia&quot;&gt;Learn more: www.epa.gov/p2/pollution-prevention-accomplishments-schick-manufacturing-verona-virginia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2. Lightolier in Fall River, Massachusetts, fabricates aluminum reflectors for lighting product lines. The facility was using large amounts of TCE and acids annually. Only 10 percent of the used TCE was captured for recycling. In addition, the company became aware of hidden costs such as liability, worker safety, and opportunities for increased productivity. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;box simple right&quot; style=&quot;width:300px&quot;&gt;
	&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;Lightolier found that 10 percent of one employee’s time was spent monitoring the TCE degreasers and manifesting the used TCE sent to a recycler, a week’s worth of labor was dedicated to Emergency Planning and Community Right-to-Know Act (EPCRA) reporting for TCE, and 40 percent was spent on Right-to-Know training strictly for TCE.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, Lightolier’s degreasing systems were old and required increasing maintenance. The company replaced the TCE degreasers with an aqueous degreaser and a powder coat degreaser. In addition, switching from pure petroleum lubricants to water-soluble coolants would eliminate the generation of oily parts in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since removing the degreasers and making other improvements such as installing still-rinse tanks, implementing countercurrent rinsing, and increasing the drip time to reduce acid discharges, the company has eliminated approximately 1.25 million lbs of TCE and saved an estimated $170,000. Volatile organic compound (VOC) emissions have dropped 90 percent from 125,000 to 12,000 lbs per year, also significantly reducing air compliance costs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.turi.org/TURI_Publications/Case_Studies/Process_Efficiency/&quot;&gt;Learn more: www.turi.org/TURI_Publications/Case_Studies/Process_Efficiency/&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3. V.H. Blackinton &amp;amp; Co., Inc in North Attleboro, MA, is a large manufacturing operation -- blanking, stamping, punching and machining raw stock prior to cleaning, enameling, brazing, polishing, plating and refinishing -- of metal plated items. The facility had used ozone-depleting Freon, as well as TCE and other VOCs and ammonia but was able to eliminate them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blackinton eliminated the use of Freon by replacing the existing finished work dryer with one that uses a deionized water rinse and hot air. The TCE cleaning operations were replaced with an aqueous cleaning system. Approximately 45 gallons of water-based cleaner is used annually, achieved by carefully monitoring the bath chemistry and ultra-filtering the cleaner weekly for reuse. In addition, a small in-tank filter, an oil skimmer, and conversion to compatible water-based pressing and stamping oils, made the new aqueous cleaning system more efficient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More recently, new brazing furnaces with belts twice as wide as those in the old furnaces were installed, doubling the process capacity. The new furnaces use a 25 percent hydrogen and 75 percent nitrogen mix, eliminating over 20,000 lbs a year of disassociated anhydrous ammonia used in the old furnaces. The cost of the new system and quality of the finished product is the same or better. A close looped cooling water system that reuses water for the furnaces conserves 5000 gallons per day and additional water conservation activities eliminate the use of more than 25,000 gallons per day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.turi.org/Our_Work/Business/Industry_Sectors/Metal_Finishing/May-20-2004-Metal-Finishing-Forum/Handouts/Case-Studies/Case-Study-V.-H.-Blackington-Company&quot;&gt;Learn more: www.turi.org/Our_Work/Business/Industry_Sectors/Metal_Finishing/May-20-2004-Metal-Finishing-Forum/Handouts/Case-Studies/Case-Study-V.-H.-Blackington-Company&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4. Danfoss Chatleff LLC in Buda, Texas, manufactures refrigeration and air conditioning components, and had been using a TCE-based degreaser to remove machine oil from metal parts. The facility replaced TCE with an aqueous degreaser/parts washer and evaporator eliminating 9,900 lbs of hazardous waste per year and saving the facility $36,000/year. (Danfoss estimates saving approximately $10,000 per year in disposal costs and $1,000 in training and reporting costs.) The new cleaning process requires less operator time, estimated to be worth $25,000/year. By eliminating the use of TCE, Danfoss also significantly reduced future environmental risk/liability associated with the shipping, storage, and use of a hazardous chemical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.zerowastenetwork.org/success/story.cfm?StoryID=1155&amp;amp;RegionalCenter&quot;&gt;Learn more: www.zerowastenetwork.org/success/story.cfm?StoryID=1155&amp;amp;RegionalCenter&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;5. Perkins Products Inc. in Chicago, Illinois, was using mineral spirits for parts cleaning to remove straight cutting oil from metal work pieces in the milling department. The company replaced these solvents with aqueous detergents. The detergent was found to be safer for employees, better for the environment, less expensive and compatible with current production process. A total of 1,600 gallons of solvent were eliminated, 10,400 lbs of VOCs were avoided, and $500 saved per year, with only a one-year return on investment period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.istc.illinois.edu/info/library_docs/TN/TN15-116.pdf&quot;&gt;Learn more: www.istc.illinois.edu/info/library_docs/TN/TN15-116.pdf&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(2 pp, 668.6 K, &lt;a href=&quot;/home/pdf-files&quot;&gt;About PDF&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;6. Marathon in Ashland, Minnesota, had been using a terpene-based cleaner and petroleum distillate for external cleaning of large equipment. The terpene solvent was suspected to be impairing the biological processes of the refinery’s wastewater treatment plant. During testing, two aqueous cleaners were applied as a foam that adhered to vertical surfaces for several minutes -- enough time for the cleaner to work -- then rinsed off with hot water. The refinery staff using one of the foaming agents described the result as &quot;requiring less chemical, less time and less water, while providing better results&quot; compared to the terpene-based cleaner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mntap.umn.edu/mach/resources/marathon.htm&quot;&gt;Learn more: www.mntap.umn.edu/mach/resources/marathon.htm&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;7. Lockheed Martin Defense Systems in Pittsfield, Minnesota, used 125 tons each year of 1,1,1- trichloroethane (trichlor, 1,1,1-TCA, methyl chloroform) and chloroflourocarbon-113 (CFC-113, Freon) in 39 vapor degreasers to clean precision products, emitting 70 tons of these chemicals each year into the air.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The company evaluated alternative cleaners for economic and technical feasibility and potential worker health and safety impact. Ultimately, seven aqueous systems and two semi-aqueous systems replaced 36 of the 39 degreasers and reduced facility solvent use to less than 2 tons per year, and air emissions to less than 1 ton per year. Cost savings included: $497,000 in solvent procurement; $17,500 in waste disposal and $65,000 in permitting and record keeping. The company incorporated a “closed loop” aqueous cleaning system in the transmission assembly and repair process. The system included a variety of substrates (steel, stainless steel, aluminum, cast iron, and bronze) and contaminants (plastic and oil, grease, wax and metal, plastic or rubber shavings) requiring removal. This process reduced consumption of 2,000,000 gallons of water per year and saved $3,450 in water and sewer costs.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.turi.org/content/download/931/4573/file/AqueousCleaning.pdf&quot;&gt;Learn more: www.turi.org/content/download/931/4573/file/AqueousCleaning.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;8. Dayton Rogers metal stamping facility in Minneapolis, Minnesota, was using TCA as a vapor degreaser to remove forming lubricant oil from parts prior to dry-sander deburring. The solvent was eliminated by upgrading its deburring operation to deburr and clean parts simultaneously. The company modified the vibratory tumbling machines to increase throughput, added a wet sander and switched to a water-based lubricant so that removing the forming lubricants would be easier in the water-based deburring system. This resulted in saving $26,575 per year and a payback period for the equipment of approximately three months. This approach would be suitable in stamping and machining operation where deburring is done, but precision cleaning is not necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://mntap.umn.edu/mach/resources/87-Deburring.htm&quot;&gt;Learn more: mntap.umn.edu/mach/resources/87-Deburring.htm&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;9. Rosemount Aerospace Inc. in Burnsville, Minnesota, used TCA during sensor cleaning at a large manufacturer of aircraft data instrumentation. After sensor assembly, the TCA comes in contact with silicone oil during testing to remove the oil before a soldering process. Aqueous cleaners tested on the sensors removed light oils and fingerprints at least as well as the existing vapor degreasing system and eliminated worker exposure to TCA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mntap.umn.edu/mach/resources/Rose-it6.htm&quot;&gt;Learn more: www.mntap.umn.edu/mach/resources/Rose-it6.htm&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;10. APS Materials Inc., a small metal finishing company in Dayton, Ohio, used TCA and methanol in its degreasing operation to clean orthopedic implants such as those used for metal knee and hip replacements. A dilute limonene solution was tested as replacement cleaner. This dilute terpene-based cleaner adequately cleaned metal parts without adversely affecting the performance of the plasma-arc coating application. The replacement cleaner resulted in a cost savings of $4,800 per year and a payback period of 4.5 months. Elimination of the disposal problems associated with methanol and TCA, coupled with the maintenance of plasma-arc coating quality, makes the use of terpene-based cleaners attractive to other plasma spray coating processes as well as other metal cleaning/coating operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://citeseerx.ist.psu.edu/viewdoc/download?doi=10.1.1.405.5454&amp;amp;rep=rep1&amp;amp;type=pdf&quot;&gt;Learn more: citeseerx.ist.psu.edu/viewdoc/download?doi=10.1.1.405.5454&amp;amp;rep=rep1&amp;amp;type=pdf&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(11 pp, 463.6 K, &lt;a href=&quot;/home/pdf-files&quot;&gt;About PDF&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;box simple right&quot; style=&quot;width:300px&quot;&gt;
	&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/toxics-release-inventory-tri-program/reducing-dichloromethane-waste&quot;&gt;According to an EPA analysis of TRI data, in 2013&lt;/a&gt;, 61 out of 280 facilities reporting the use of DCM in the U.S. reported newly implemented source reduction activities. Two examples include:&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;An organic chemical manufacturer that previously used DCM to clean equipment when changing from one process to another, switched to a less hazardous cleaning solution of water and limonene; and,&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;An optical instrument manufacturer started using aqueous cleaning solutions instead of DCM.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;11. Roberts Automatic Products, a third generation family-owned precision production machining company in Chanhassen, Minnesota specializes in precise and complex computer numeric control (CNC) machining and screw machine parts. Roberts used DCM as a degreasing solvent to clean its parts and reported to TRI as much as 40,000 pounds a year of DCM wastes that were released or treated by the plant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Roberts purchased the Serec closed-loop vacuum degreasing unit in 2011 and put it into service in 2012. Roberts reduced its DCM waste to 13,636 pounds from more than 44,000 pounds the previous year. The facility is no longer required to file TRI reports for DCM and has eliminated DCM as a source of toxic waste and a hazardous air pollutant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/toxics-release-inventory-tri-program/reducing-dichloromethane-waste&quot;&gt;Learn more: www.epa.gov/toxics-release-inventory-tri-program/reducing-dichloromethane-waste&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;pdf&quot; name=&quot;pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-344519&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2017-01/documents/safer_alternatives_for_solvent_degreasing_applications_.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=417169&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Safer Alternatives for Solvent Degreasing Applications (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(4 pp, 417 K, 
  September 2016)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2016 16:38:10 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>tgelaber</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">159173 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Fiscal Year 2015 Source Reduction Assistance (SRA) Grant Summaries</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/p2/fiscal-year-2015-source-reduction-assistance-sra-grant-summaries</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;In fiscal year 2015, EPA awarded approximately $1 million in federal funding under the Source Reduction Assistance (SRA) Grants Program to support pollution prevention (P2) activities across all environmental media — air, water and land.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Activities proposed by grantees would develop and enhance P2 activities that relate to:  research, investigations, experiments, education, training, surveys, studies and/or demonstration of innovative techniques. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eligibility included: state agencies, federally-recognized tribes, and colleges and universities (that are instrumentalities of a state), local, city and township governments, nonprofit and community based grassroots organizations, and independent school districts and private institutions of higher education.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The number and amount of grants awarded depended on congressional appropriation and the quality of proposals received. During the FY 2015 competition cycle, applicants were instructed to address as part of their proposed activity one or more of the P2 Program’s National Emphasis Areas – climate change mitigation/prevention of greenhouse gas emissions; food manufacturing and processing; or state/community approaches to hazardous materials source reduction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This page provides summaries for the public and P2 practitioners on SRA grants awarded between June 2015-September 2015. The summaries include the applicant&#039;s name, the federal dollar amount (for the first year, in cases of multiple year grants) and a brief description of the project. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#region2&quot;&gt;Region 2 (NJ, NY, PR, VI)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#region3&quot;&gt;Region 3 (DE, DC, MD, PA, VA, WV)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#region4&quot;&gt;Region 4 (AL, FL, GA, KY, MS, NC, SC, TN)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#region5&quot;&gt;Region 5 (IL, IN, MI, MN, OH, WI)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#region6&quot;&gt;Region 6 (AR, LA, NM, OK, TX)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#region7&quot;&gt;Region 7 (IA, KS, MO, NE)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#region8&quot;&gt;Region 8 (CO, MT, ND, SD, UT, WY)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#region9&quot;&gt;Region 9 (AZ, CA, HI, NV, AS, GU)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#region10&quot;&gt;Region 10 (AK, ID, OR, WA)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;region2&quot; name=&quot;region2&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Region 2 (NJ, NY, PR, VI)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NEW YORK&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;New York State Restaurant Association Educational Foundation&lt;br /&gt;
	EPA Grant: $34,750&lt;br /&gt;
	P2 Program National Emphasis Area — Food Manufacturing and Processing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The grant recipient will provide P2 technical assistance to restaurants in areas at risk of climate change impacts during storms or other catastrophic events.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The recipient will work with New York City food manufacturers and restaurants to reduce hazardous materials in their cleaning and pest control practices by conducting group and on-site trainings, and by designing brochures and hosting webinars. The primary targets are businesses in communities that are highly susceptible to flooding, such as Red Hook, Brooklyn and the Rockaways. The recipient will share lessons learned from trainings in New York City with members of the Puerto Rican Restaurant Association.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The recipient will also continue to provide green restaurant training to 350 restaurants to assist them in reducing water and energy consumption, reduce hazardous material releases, and realize cost savings. A green restaurant handbook will be distributed to restaurants through the recipient’s website. In addition, the recipient will offer training to restaurants on sustainability planning.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;REGION WIDE&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Manomet&lt;br /&gt;
	EPA Grant: $33,894&lt;br /&gt;
	P2 Program National Emphasis Area — Food Manufacturing and Processing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The grant recipient will provide on-site technical assistance to approximately 40 Wakefern grocery store managers in EPA’s Region 2 area on applying best management practices. The training will focus on energy conservation and reduction of the generation and release of hazardous materials. The stores will receive instructional workbooks specifically tailored to the particular grocery stores.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The recipient will also provide on-site technical assistance to approximately five dairy farm managers on energy conservation and reduction of the generation and release of hazardous materials. The dairy farms will receive hands-on workbooks specifically tailored to the particular dairy farms. In their technical assistance to grocery stores and dairy farms, the recipient will also promote their use of EPA voluntary programs such as &lt;a href=&quot;/greenchill&quot;&gt;GreenChilll&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/sustainable-management-food/food-recovery-challenge-frc&quot;&gt;Food Recovery Challenge&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/smm/wastewise&quot;&gt;WasteWise&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.energystar.gov/&quot;&gt;Energy Star&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;region3&quot; name=&quot;region3&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Region 3 (DE, DC, MD, PA, VA, WV)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PENNSYLVANIA &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Villanova University&lt;br /&gt;
	EPA Grant: $35,972&lt;br /&gt;
	P2 Program National Emphasis Area — Food Manufacturing and Processing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The grant recipient will determine methods to improve energy efficiency in corporate and educational dining facilities. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Penn State University&lt;br /&gt;
	EPA Grant: $25,000&lt;br /&gt;
	P2 Program National Emphasis Area — State or Community Based Approaches to Hazardous Materials Source Reduction&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The grant recipient will promote the reuse of solvents to reduce hazardous materials.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;region4&quot; name=&quot;region4&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Region 4 (AL, FL, GA, KY, MS, NC, SC, TN)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;KENTUCKY&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kentucky Department of Environmental Protection&lt;br /&gt;
	EPA Grant: $45,000&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;P2 Program National Emphasis Area — Climate Change Mitigation/Prevention of Greenhouse Gas Emissions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The grant recipient will encourage the development of sustainable food systems and promoting green practices to those involved in the production, transport, use and reuse of local food. The recipient plans to develop a farm certification program through the &lt;a href=&quot;http://dca.ky.gov/kyexcel/Pages/default.aspx&quot;&gt;KY EXCEL&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt; program to help recognize producers who are working to identify source reduction opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TENNESSEE&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;University of Tennessee&lt;br /&gt;
	EPA Grant: $45,000&lt;br /&gt;
	P2 Program National Emphasis Area — Food Manufacturing and Processing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The grant recipient will fund source-reduction technical assistance and guidance to a food manufacturer over a two-year period. The assistance will enable the participating firm to develop and implement a source- reduction playbook and scorecard that can serve as a guide for other food manufacturers across the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The University of Tennessee Center for Industrial Services, in partnership with several state universities and other service providers, will provide technical assistance and use this experience as a basis for future training and assistance for the food manufacturing sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;region5&quot; name=&quot;region5&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Region 5 (IL, IN, MI, MN, OH, WI)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ILLINOIS&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;University of Illinois&lt;br /&gt;
	EPA Grant: $61,750&lt;br /&gt;
	P2 Program National Emphasis Area — State or Community Approaches to Hazardous Materials Source Reduction&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The grant recipient will identify and implement water and energy reduction measures in industrial facilities located in Cook and DuPage counties, focusing on environmental justice communities. P2, &lt;a href=&quot;/lean&quot;&gt;Le&lt;/a&gt;an, and energy efficiency assessments will be conducted for five facilities. The Illinois Manufacturing Extension Center will conduct Lean assessments; utility companies, ComEd and Nicor will conduct energy efficiency assessments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;REGION-WIDE&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TechSolve&lt;br /&gt;
	EPA Grant: $52,250&lt;br /&gt;
	P2 Program National Emphasis Area — State or Community Approaches to Hazardous Materials Source Reduction&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The grant recipient will recruit and train student interns to provide P2 technical assistance to 12 businesses. The grantee will also conduct 24 bi-monthly manufacturer roundtables that will serve as an educational, community-based forum to discuss approaches to hazardous materials source reduction. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;region6&quot; name=&quot;region6&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Region 6 (AR, LA, NM, OK, TX)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TEXAS&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;University of Texas at Arlington&lt;br /&gt;
	EPA Grant: $52,353&lt;br /&gt;
	P2 Program National Emphasis Area — Climate Change Mitigation/Prevention of Greenhouse Gas Emissions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The grant recipient will conduct research using a new ring-carbonyl-containing zeolitic imidazolate to advance low-cost carbon capture and storage that will help alleviate the threats from global climate change. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NEW MEXICO&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;New Mexico State University&lt;br /&gt;
	EPA Grant: $96,368&lt;br /&gt;
	P2 Program National Emphasis Area — State or Community Approaches to Hazardous Materials Source Reduction&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The grant recipient will focus on newer hydraulic fracturing (fracking) techniques, seeking up-to-date source techniques for these operations; provide outreach and education to companies; and develop methods for upstream oil and gas producers to reduce pollution at the source.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;region7&quot; name=&quot;region7&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Region 7 (IA, KS, MO, NE)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;IOWA&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Iowa Department of Natural Resources&lt;br /&gt;
	EPA Grant: $65,053&lt;br /&gt;
	P2 Program National Emphasis Area — Climate Change Mitigation/Prevention of Greenhouse Gas Emissions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The grant recipient will conduct three P2 internships to assist Iowa industry to reduce greenhouse gas (GHG) emissions and provide a webinar for instruction and assistance in reducing GHG emissions. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NEBRASKA&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;University of Nebraska – Lincoln&lt;br /&gt;
	EPA Grant: $59,845&lt;br /&gt;
	P2 Program National Emphasis Area — Climate Change Mitigation/Prevention of Greenhouse Gas Emissions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The grant recipient will provide on-site technical assistance for Nebraska agricultural producers to reduce water, energy use for pumping to reduce greenhouse gas emissions and groundwater nitrate contamination. Work will be accomplished by using P2 educational tools and resources and assistance from three student interns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;region8&quot; name=&quot;region8&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Region 8 (CO, MT, ND, SD, UT, WY)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;WYOMING&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Yellowstone Teton Clean Energy Coalition&lt;br /&gt;
	EPA Grant: $67,207&lt;br /&gt;
	P2 Program National Emphasis Area — Climate Change Mitigation/Prevention of Greenhouse Gas Emissions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The grant recipient will increase electric vehicle charging infrastructure in the greater Yellowstone ecosystem, including education and outreach on P2 techniques to visitors and residents. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;region9&quot; name=&quot;region9&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Region 9 (AZ, CA, HI, NV, AS, GU)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;REGIONWIDE&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Clean Water Fund&lt;br /&gt;
	EPA Grant: $55,298&lt;br /&gt;
	P2 Program National Emphasis Area — Climate Change Mitigation/Prevention of Greenhouse Gas Emissions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The grant recipient will:  reduce the use of disposable tableware at large catering operations; develop a calculator to measure greenhouse gas reductions from implemented changes; and develop environmentally preferable purchasing guidelines to reduce toxics in disposables tableware. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;region10&quot; name=&quot;region10&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Region 10 (AK, ID, OR, WA)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;WASHINGTON &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Northwest Pollution Prevention Resource Center&lt;br /&gt;
	EPA Grant: $117,600&lt;br /&gt;
	P2 Program National Emphasis Area — State or Community Approaches to Hazardous Materials Source Reduction&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The grant recipient will:  host and facilitate the annual Region 10 Roundtable; provide technical assistance to Region 10 states on &lt;a href=&quot;/e3&quot;&gt;E3: Economy, Energy and Environment&lt;/a&gt; resources and tools, outreach and communication strategies; and manage state and community-based projects that focus on reducing toxic materials released into the environment. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jun 2016 14:15:50 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>tgelaber</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">151889 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Fiscal Year 2015 Pollution Prevention Grant Summaries</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/p2/fiscal-year-2015-pollution-prevention-grant-summaries</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;In fiscal year 2015, EPA awarded approximately $3.97 million in federal funding under the Pollution Prevention (P2) Grant Program to support P2 activities across all environmental media — air, water and land. Grant applicants represented state agencies, federally-recognized tribes, intertribal consortia and colleges and universities that are instrumentalities of a state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the FY 2015 competition cycle, applicants were instructed to address as part of their proposed activity one or more of the P2 Program’s National Emphasis Areas – climate change mitigation/prevention of greenhouse gas emissions; food manufacturing and processing; or state/community approaches to hazardous materials source reduction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The number and amounts of grants awarded depended on our congressional appropriation and the quality of proposals received.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This page provides summaries for the public and P2 practitioners on P2 grants awarded between June 2015-September 2015. The summaries include the applicant&#039;s name, the federal dollar amount (for the first year, in cases of multiple year grants) and a brief description of the project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#region1&quot;&gt;Region 1 (CT, ME, MA, NH, RI, VT)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#region2&quot;&gt;Region 2 (NJ, NY, PR, VI)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#region3&quot;&gt;Region 3 (DE, DC, MD, PA, VA, WV)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#region4&quot;&gt;Region 4 (AL, FL, GA, KY, MS, NC, SC, TN)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#region5&quot;&gt;Region 5 (IL, IN, MI, MN, OH, WI)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#region6&quot;&gt;Region 6 (AR, LA, NM, OK, TX)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#region7&quot;&gt;Region 7 (IA, KS, MO, NE)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#region8&quot;&gt;Region 8 (CO, MT, ND, SD, UT, WY)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#region9&quot;&gt;Region 9 (AZ, CA, HI, NV, AS, GU)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#region10&quot;&gt;Region 10 (AK, ID, OR, WA)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;region1&quot; name=&quot;region1&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Region 1 (CT, ME, MA, NH, RI, VT)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CONNECTICUT &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Connecticut Department of Energy and Environmental Protection&lt;br /&gt;
	EPA Grant: $80,000&lt;br /&gt;
	P2 Program National Emphasis Area — State or Community Approaches to Hazardous Materials Source Reduction&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The grant recipient will perform the following activities:  1) encourage energy efficiency for nursing homes; 2) work with drycleaners to reduce toxics and greenhouse gas emissions by replacing traditional drycleaning services with environmentally-preferred professional wet cleaning; 3) publish the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ct.gov/deep/cwp/view.asp?A=2708&amp;amp;Q=324064&quot;&gt;P2 View: A Pollution Prevention Newsletter&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;; 4) administer the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ct.gov/deep/cwp/view.asp?a=2708&amp;amp;q=438218&amp;amp;deepNav_GID=1763%20&quot;&gt;Connecticut Green Lodging/Tourism Program&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt; to bring at least 10 new hotels into the program; 5) foster continuous improvement in P2 by improving website information, web-based resource tools and outreach materials; and 6) coordinate with &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ct.gov/deep/cwp/view.asp?a=4423&amp;amp;q=521742&amp;amp;deepNav_GID=2121&quot;&gt;Connecticut&#039;s Climate Change office&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt; and other state programs to integrate P2 and sustainability into the state’s climate action and resilience strategies for businesses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;MASSACHUSETTS&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Massachusetts Office of Technical Assistance&lt;br /&gt;
	EPA Grant: $142,000&lt;br /&gt;
	P2 Program National Emphasis Area — State or Community Approaches to Hazardous Materials Source Reduction&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The grant recipient will work with state regional planning agencies to educate local emergency planning commissions and facilities handling and storing hazardous chemicals to incorporate toxics use reduction into their emergency preparedness plans. This effort will aim to reduce risks of chemicals released into the environment due to extreme weather events or floods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NEW HAMPSHIRE&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;New Hampshire Department of Environmental Services&lt;br /&gt;
	EPA Grant: $80,000&lt;br /&gt;
	P2 Program National Emphasis Area — Food Manufacturing and Processing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The grant recipient will: 1) work with 37 micro-breweries in New Hampshire to help reduce waste and minimize energy and water use, and; 2) provide climate change mitigation and preparedness training for hazardous waste generators in the state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;VERMONT&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vermont Department of Environmental Conservation&lt;br /&gt;
	EPA Grant: $80,000&lt;br /&gt;
	P2 Program National Emphasis Area — Food Manufacturing and Processing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The grant recipient will perform the following activities:  1) manage Vermont’s environmental leadership program for small businesses; 2) administer the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fedcenter.gov/Bookmarks/index.cfm?id=1389&quot;&gt;Governor&#039;s Awards for Environmental Excellence and Pollution Prevention&lt;/a&gt;; and 3) provide outreach and assistance to the food manufacturing sector targeting 400 food processing and manufacturing businesses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;region2&quot; name=&quot;region2&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Region 2 (NJ, NY, PR, VI)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NEW JERSEY&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rutgers University&lt;br /&gt;
	EPA Grant: $79,234&lt;br /&gt;
	P2 Program National Emphasis Area — Food Manufacturing and Processing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The grant recipient will provide technical assistance to small and mid-sized businesses in the food-manufacturing sector with a focus on food production, processing, storage, and distribution in Newark and the surrounding region. Businesses will receive assistance in ammonia refrigeration and other refrigeration alternatives, guidance on conducting energy efficiency assessments, and strategies for increasing water conservation practices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The recipient will work with the New Jersey Department of Environmental Protection’s Small Business Environmental Assistance Program and food industry associations to reach sector businesses. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;region3&quot; name=&quot;region3&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Region 3 (DE, DC, MD, PA, VA, WV)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PENNSYLVANIA &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pennsylvania State University, PennTAP&lt;br /&gt;
	EPA Grant: $90,000&lt;br /&gt;
	P2 Program National Emphasis Area — Food Manufacturing and Processing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The grant recipient will provide technical assistance to manufacturers, including one &lt;a href=&quot;/e3&quot;&gt;E3: Economy, Energy and Environment&lt;/a&gt; assessment, with a focus on food manufacturers, as well as offering P2 training to engineering interns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;VIRGINIA          &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Virginia Department of Environmental Quality&lt;br /&gt;
	EPA Grant: $40,000&lt;br /&gt;
	P2 Program National Emphasis Area — Food Manufacturing and Processing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The grant recipient will provide P2 outreach and training and on-site technical assistance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wytheville Community College&lt;br /&gt;
	EPA Grant: $60,000&lt;br /&gt;
	P2 Program National Emphasis Area — Food Manufacturing and Processing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The grant recipient will provide &lt;a href=&quot;/e3&quot;&gt;E3: Economy, Energy and Environment&lt;/a&gt; and other technical assistance to manufacturers with a focus on food manufacturers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;region4&quot; name=&quot;region4&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Region 4 (AL, FL, GA, KY, MS, NC, SC, TN)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;FLORIDA&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Florida Department of Environmental Protection&lt;br /&gt;
	EPA Grant: $79,327&lt;br /&gt;
	P2 Program National Emphasis Area — Climate Change Mitigation/Prevention of Greenhouse Gas Emissions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The grant recipient will conduct three projects to provide technical assistance and enhance statewide recognition programs for marina, lodging and school sectors with an emphasis on reducing hazardous waste released from storms or floods. The grant recipient will also train universities and local government staff on P2 and promote environmentally-preferred cleaning products.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;GEORGIA&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Georgia Tech University&lt;br /&gt;
	EPA Grant: $80,000&lt;br /&gt;
	P2 Program National Emphasis Area — Climate Change Mitigation/Prevention of Greenhouse Gas Emissions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The grant recipient will perform the following activities:  1) support the Partnership for a Sustainable Georgia – a coordinated federal and local technical assistance program and 2) conduct P2 assessments and training on green principles to enhance environmental performance through energy efficiency and improved resource usage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;KENTUCKY&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kentucky Department of Environmental Protection&lt;br /&gt;
	EPA Grant: $80,000&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;P2 Program National Emphasis Area — Climate Change Mitigation/Prevention of Greenhouse Gas Emissions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The grant recipient will collaborate with stakeholders to develop and deliver technical assistance and education related to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Toxics use and greenhouse gas reductions&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Resource and water conservation&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Promoting P2 integration&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Using energy efficiency and waste reduction techniques to support sustainability and improve competitiveness.&lt;strong&gt;  &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;MISSISSIPPI&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mississippi Department of Environmental Quality&lt;br /&gt;
	EPA Grant: $72,807&lt;br /&gt;
	P2 Program National Emphasis Area — Food Manufacturing and Processing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The grant recipient will provide waste reduction training and technical assistance to businesses and industries in the state. The environmental stewardship program will use the &lt;a href=&quot;/e3&quot;&gt;E3: Economy, Energy and Environment&lt;/a&gt; technical assistance framework to assist manufacturers with assessments of operations to reduce energy consumption, reduce greenhouse gas emissions and prevent pollution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;North Carolina&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;North Carolina Department of Environmental Quality&lt;br /&gt;
	EPA Grant: $80,000&lt;br /&gt;
	P2 Program National Emphasis Area — Food Manufacturing and Processing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The grant recipient will support the environmental stewardship initiative to manage an environmental leadership program and offer: technical assistance, regional events on P2 and training opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;South Carolina&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Clemson University&lt;br /&gt;
	EPA Grant: $80,000&lt;br /&gt;
	P2 Program National Emphasis Area — Climate Change Mitigation/Prevention of Greenhouse Gas Emissions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The grant recipient will s&lt;span&gt;upport a two-year partnership with the Department of Environmental Engineering and Earth Sciences at Clemson University, the Department of Industrial Engineering at Clemson University and Duke Energy.  &lt;/span&gt;The partnership will perform &lt;a href=&quot;/e3&quot;&gt;E3: Economy, Energy and Environment&lt;/a&gt; assessments that include energy, Lean and green technical assistance to small and medium-sized manufacturing firms in South Carolina.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TENNESSEE&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tennessee Department of Environment &amp;amp; Conservation&lt;br /&gt;
	EPA Grant: $80,000&lt;br /&gt;
	P2 Program National Emphasis Area — Food Manufacturing and Processing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The grant recipient will provide on-site technical assistance, workshops, roundtables and support to Tennessee businesses, government entities and food manufacturers. This work will be aimed at achieving measurable results in P2 while also reducing costs and focusing on climate change, as it relates to greenhouse gas reductions in the food manufacturing sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The program will also recognize outstanding environmental leaders through the Tennessee Green Star program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;region5&quot; name=&quot;region5&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Region 5 (IL, IN, MI, MN, OH, WI)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ILLINOIS&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;University of Illinois&lt;br /&gt;
	EPA Grant: $133,000&lt;br /&gt;
	P2 Program National Emphasis Areas — Climate Change Mitigation/Prevention of Greenhouse Gas Emissions, Food Manufacturing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The grant recipient will work with Illinois industrial facilities (including food manufacturers) and communities to conserve energy, reduce water consumption and wastewater generation, reduce carbon emissions and save money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, it will help facilities identify and implement practices and technologies that reduce hazardous materials and waste.  The grantee will partner with the Illinois Manufacturing Excellence Center to bring &lt;a href=&quot;/lean&quot;&gt;Lean&lt;/a&gt; assessments into the P2 and energy work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;MINNESOTA&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Minnesota Pollution Control Agency&lt;br /&gt;
	EPA Grant: $75,000&lt;br /&gt;
	P2 Program National Emphasis Areas — State or Community Approaches to Hazardous Materials Source Reduction&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The grant recipient will conduct an &lt;a href=&quot;/e3&quot;&gt;E3: Economy, Energy, and Environment&lt;/a&gt; pilot to provide direct technical assistance on painting and coating processes used in manufacturing to achieve natural resource (water and materials) reductions, time, motion and energy efficiencies, and cost savings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to working with manufacturers engaging in painting and coating processes, the grantee will work with the manufacturers’ supply chains. Environmental, energy efficiency and &lt;a href=&quot;/lean&quot;&gt;Lean&lt;/a&gt; assessments will be provided. The grantee will follow up with companies participating in the pilot to determine steps that were taken as a result of the assessments and the outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;OHIO&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;University of Toledo&lt;br /&gt;
	EPA Grant: $46,888&lt;br /&gt;
	P2 National Emphasis Areas — Climate Change Mitigation/Prevention of Greenhouse Gas Emissions, Food Manufacturing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The University of Toledo&#039;s Department of Engineering and its partners, Center for Innovative Food Technology, or CIFT, and TechSolve, an organization that provides consulting services to manufacturers, will achieve greenhouse gas reduction, toxic and hazardous materials reduction, and resource conservation by holding no-cost seminars and using graduate-level interns to assist with P2 assessments at small- and medium- sized businesses in the food, service and manufacturing sectors in Northwest Ohio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;WISCONSIN&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wisconsin State Energy Office&lt;br /&gt;
	EPA Grant: $102,190&lt;br /&gt;
	P2 Program National Emphasis Areas — Climate Change Mitigation/Prevention of Greenhouse Gas Emissions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through a contract with Sustain Dane, a not-for-profit organization based in the Dane County/Madison area, the Wisconsin Office of Energy Innovation will provide technical assistance to businesses in the greater Madison area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://sustaindane.org/going-sustainable/at-work/mpower-business/&quot;&gt;MPower Business Champions Program&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt; with Sustain Dane will utilize state and local resources to support businesses to implement P2 practices, including energy efficiency, while saving costs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the two-year grant, Sustain Dane will target 25 businesses that will identify, document, and implement a series of projects.  A total of 125 technical assistance projects will be led during the grant period. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;University of Wisconsin&lt;br /&gt;
	EPA Grant: $142,804&lt;br /&gt;
	P2 Program National Emphasis Areas — Climate Change Mitigation/Prevention of Greenhouse Gas Emissions, Food Manufacturing, State or Community Approaches to Hazardous Materials Source Reduction&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The grant recipient will provide technical assistance to cheese manufacturers and printers based on facilities that have reported source-reduction practices in EPA’s Toxic Release Inventory Database, develop a scoping study to determine heat-loss prevention opportunities in Wisconsin manufacturing facilities, identify Wisconsin manufacturers in or near floodplains that are at risk for spills/releases, and offer P2 assistance for safer substitutions or reduced use of materials in those areas at risk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;region6&quot; name=&quot;region6&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Region 6 (AR, LA, NM, OK, TX)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ARKANSAS&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Arkansas Department of Environmental Quality&lt;br /&gt;
	EPA Grant: $36,481&lt;br /&gt;
	P2 Program National Emphasis Area — Food Manufacturing and Processing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The grant recipient will perform the following activities: 1) partner with the University of Arkansas at Little Rock to develop a summer P2 internship program for engineering students; 2) partner with the &lt;a href=&quot;http://zerowastenetwork.org/&quot;&gt;Zero Waste Network&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt; to present P2 101 training; 3) continue to partner with Arkansas Manufacturing Solutions on &lt;a href=&quot;/e3&quot;&gt;E3: Economy, Energy and Environment &lt;/a&gt; projects and the bimonthly Putting Green to Work lunch series; 4) conduct  P2 site assistance visits to Arkansas businesses – specifically, targeting food manufacturers; and 5) evaluate the Arkansas Environmental Steward Award applications.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TEXAS&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;University of Texas at Arlington/Texas Manufacturing Assistance Center&lt;br /&gt;
	EPA Grant: $103,000&lt;br /&gt;
	P2 Program National Emphasis Area — Climate Change Mitigation/Prevention of Greenhouse Gas Emissions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The grant recipient will use technical assistance and training to promote source reduction through the use of &lt;a href=&quot;/e3&quot;&gt;E3: Economy, Energy and Environment &lt;/a&gt; and P2 techniques with partners in EPA Region 6.  The plan calls for developing and enhancing source-reduction approaches by engaging state, local and business partners. The grant recipient will also continue its partnership with New Mexico State University providing E3 assessments for businesses in the El Paso and Las Cruces areas of Texas and New Mexico.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;OKLAHOMA&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Otoe-Missouria Tribe&lt;br /&gt;
	EPA Grant: $38,000&lt;br /&gt;
	P2 Program National Emphasis Area — Climate Change Mitigation/Prevention of Greenhouse Gas Emissions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The grant recipient will provide training and technical assistance for seven tribal businesses and three departments within the tribal government.  Training topics include P2, energy use awareness, energy and water conservation and chemicals and hazardous materials.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NEW MEXICO&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;New Mexico Environment Department&lt;br /&gt;
	EPA Grant: $77,519&lt;br /&gt;
	P2 Program National Emphasis Area — Food Manufacturing and Processing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The grant recipient will provide on-site environmental assessments, P2 trainings, and source-reduction project assistance. Grant funding will also support the state’s environmental recognition program, the Green Zia Environmental Leadership Program and the P2 Intern Program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;New Mexico State University – Institute for Energy and the Environment&lt;br /&gt;
	EPA Grant: $54,729&lt;br /&gt;
	P2 Program National Emphasis Area — Food Manufacturing and Processing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The grant recipient will support new and existing approaches by:  1) continuing &lt;a href=&quot;/lean&quot;&gt;Lean and Green&lt;/a&gt; activities with the manufacturing sector; 2) continuing &lt;a href=&quot;/e3&quot;&gt;E3: Economy, Energy and Environment&lt;/a&gt; program outreach and training – working collaboratively with partners in Texas; 3) introducing E3 activities into New Mexico’s food manufacturing sector; and 4) continuing to collaborate with the New Mexico Environment Department’s Green Zia Environmental Leadership Program and P2 internship program.&lt;a name=&quot;region7&quot; id=&quot;region7&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Region 7 (IA, KS, MO, NE)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;IOWA&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Iowa Department of Natural Resources&lt;br /&gt;
	EPA Grant: $135,454&lt;br /&gt;
	P2 Program National Emphasis Area — Food Manufacturing and Processing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The grant recipient will conduct 22 P2 assessments and partner with Iowa’s food manufacturers to identify and implement P2 opportunities through four P2 internships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;KANSAS&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kansas Department of Health and Environment&lt;br /&gt;
	EPA Grant: $159,449&lt;br /&gt;
	P2 Program National Emphasis Area — Food Manufacturing and Processing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The grant recipient will partner with Kansas State University to provide a P2 internship program with a food manufacturing focus, provide direct technical assistance to businesses and raise P2 awareness and recognition within the business community.  Project outputs will include P2 internships, site visits with P2 recommendations, P2 awards and P2 sessions at Kansas&#039; Environmental Conference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NEBRASKA&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;University of Nebraska – Lincoln&lt;br /&gt;
	EPA Grant: $76,414&lt;br /&gt;
	P2 Program National Emphasis Area — Food Manufacturing and Processing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The grant recipient will focus on the beef processing industry to assist at least three food processing manufacturers in measuring and mapping their water and energy use and wastewater production; allocating costs and identifying relevant waste reduction strategies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;region8&quot; name=&quot;region8&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Region 8 (CO, MT, ND, SD, UT, WY)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;COLORADO&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Colorado Department of Public Health and Environment&lt;br /&gt;
	EPA Grant: $119,400&lt;br /&gt;
	P2 Program National Emphasis Area — Food Manufacturing and Processing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The grant recipient will support the Beyond Compliance Award and Recognition Program and a P2 program, including P2 technical assistance and outreach to businesses, integration of P2 concepts and regulatory framework and development of state-wide use of innovative P2 concepts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;MONTANA&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Montana State University&lt;br /&gt;
	EPA Grant: $165,059&lt;br /&gt;
	P2 Program National Emphasis Area — Climate Change Mitigation/Prevention of Greenhouse Gas Emissions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The grant recipient will support the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.montana.edu/pollution-prevention/ecostar.html&quot;&gt;Ecostar Pollution Prevention Award&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt; program for small businesses, promote new initiatives that offer technical assistance and training on solar hot water systems, and will create a P2 Potential Partners workshop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UTAH&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Utah Department of Environmental Quality&lt;br /&gt;
	EPA Grant: $94,041&lt;br /&gt;
	P2 Program National Emphasis Area — Climate Change Mitigation/Prevention of Greenhouse Gas Emissions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The grant recipient will help businesses adopt and implement P2 tools and techniques and provide technical assistance to water utilities to reduce storm water pollution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;WYOMING&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wyoming Department of Environmental Quality&lt;br /&gt;
	EPA Grant: $64,309&lt;br /&gt;
	P2 Program National Emphasis Area — Food Manufacturing and Processing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The grant recipient will provide technical assistance to agricultural businesses – six swine and dairy concentrated animal feeding operations and a beet sugar processing facility to analyze energy use and provide recommendations to increase energy efficiency and create an energy management plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;region9&quot; name=&quot;region9&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Region 9 (AZ, CA, HI, NV, AS, GU)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ARIZONA&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Arizona Department of Environmental Quality&lt;br /&gt;
	EPA Grant: $161,561&lt;br /&gt;
	P2 Program National Emphasis Area — State or Community Approaches to Hazardous Materials Source Reduction&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The grant recipient will expand outreach activities and technical assistance to Arizona facilities required to submit P2 reports based on Toxics Release Inventory (TRI) by partnering with student interns from Arizona State University.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CALIFORNIA&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;California Air Resources Board&lt;br /&gt;
	EPA Grant: $107,517&lt;br /&gt;
	P2 Program National Emphasis Area — State or Community Approaches to Hazardous Materials Source Reduction&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The grant recipient will provide in-person technical assistance and training for businesses in under-served and disadvantaged areas as identified by the California Environmental Protection Agency’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://oehha.ca.gov/calenviroscreen/report/calenviroscreen-version-20&quot;&gt;CalEnviro Screen version 2.0&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt; The program will increase participation from businesses representing under-served and disadvantaged communities (DACs) where green business programs exist. The recipient will also establish a new California certified green business program in a DAC city or county.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;region10&quot; name=&quot;region10&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Region 10 (AK, ID, OR, WA)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ALASKA&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Knik Tribal Council&lt;br /&gt;
	EPA Grant: $96,300&lt;br /&gt;
	P2 Program National Emphasis Area — Climate Change Mitigation/Prevention of Greenhouse Gas Emissions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The grant recipient will provide technical assistance to businesses, support the &lt;a href=&quot;http://akforum.org/green-star/&quot;&gt;Green Star Communities Program&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.akforum.com/green-star/&quot;&gt;Green Star Business Certification program&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt; – focusing on breweries and housing management.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;IDAHO&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Idaho Department of Environmental Quality&lt;br /&gt;
	EPA Grant: $85,000&lt;br /&gt;
	P2 Program National Emphasis Area — Food Manufacturing and Processing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The grant recipient will provide technical assistance to businesses, support &lt;a href=&quot;/e3&quot;&gt;E3: Economy, Energy and Environment&lt;/a&gt; projects, green chemistry, refrigerant alternatives to reduce greenhouse gas emissions, support the Green Air Zone program, a green chemistry school certification program and the Idaho Environmental guide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;OREGON&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Portland State University&lt;br /&gt;
	EPA Grant: $95,000&lt;br /&gt;
	P2 Program National Emphasis Area — Food Manufacturing and Processing&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The grant recipient will provide technical assistance for idle reduction and electrification for food distributor companies with refrigeration units.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;WASHINGTON &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Washington State Department of Ecology&lt;br /&gt;
	EPA Grant: $105,700&lt;br /&gt;
	P2 Program National Emphasis Areas — Food Manufacturing and Processing and Climate Change Mitigation/Prevention of Greenhouse Gas Emissions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The grant recipient will provide training for businesses and Washington State Department of Ecology staff on toxics use reduction, safer chemical alternatives and chemical hazard assessments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jun 2016 17:43:28 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>tgelaber</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">151719 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Pollution Prevention Information Network (PPIN) Grant Summaries 2015</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/p2/pollution-prevention-information-network-ppin-grant-summaries-2015</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;The Pollution Prevention Information Network (PPIN) grant program funds a national network of regional centers that serve both regional and national pollution prevention (P2) information needs. These centers are known as the &lt;a href=&quot;/p2/pollution-prevention-resource-exchange-p2rx&quot;&gt;Pollution Prevention Resource Exchange (P2Rx)&lt;/a&gt;. Grantees determine audience needs, develop and deliver quality information and training to businesses for which a lack of information may be an impediment to implementing source reduction, preventing pollution or adopting sustainable practices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below are the summaries of PPIN grants awarded in 2015. The summaries name the state organization and the federal dollar amount of the grant. Federal funding must be matched dollar for dollar by the grantee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#on1&quot;&gt;New Hampshire&lt;/a&gt;- Serves Regions 1 and 2&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#on4&quot;&gt;Kentucky&lt;/a&gt;- Serves Regions 3 and 4&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#on5&quot;&gt;Illinois&lt;/a&gt;- Serves Great Lakes&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#on6&quot;&gt;Texas&lt;/a&gt;- Serves Region 6&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#on7&quot;&gt;Nebraska&lt;/a&gt;- Serves Region 7&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#on8&quot;&gt;Montana&lt;/a&gt;- Serves Region 8&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#on9&quot;&gt;Nevada&lt;/a&gt;- Serves Region 9&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#on10&quot;&gt;Washington&lt;/a&gt;- Serves Region 10&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id=&quot;on1&quot;&gt;New Hampshire&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;New Hampshire Department of Environmental Services (DES)&lt;br /&gt;
	EPA grant: $59,607&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New Hampshire Department of Environmental Services in partnership with the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.newmoa.org/&quot;&gt;Northeast Waste Management Officials Association (NEWMOA)&lt;/a&gt; will support P2 information services in Regions 1 and 2. The work plan includes: promoting the use of safer alternatives to traditional dry cleaning chemicals, facilitating a P2 and sustainability roundtable; enhancing a regional sustainable grocer’s initiative and advancing 3 professional network and P2 information sites – relating to sustainable lodging, green chemistry and zerowaste.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;on4&quot;&gt;Kentucky&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;University of Louisville, Kentucky Pollution Prevention Center (KPPC)&lt;br /&gt;
	EPA grant: $109,279&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The University of Louisville Kentucky Pollution Prevention Center supports the &lt;a href=&quot;http://esrconline.org/&quot;&gt;Environmental Sustainability Resource Center&lt;/a&gt; that serves EPA Regions 3 and 4.  The project will support technical assistance providers in methods of promoting energy efficiency and waste minimization to reduce greenhouse gas emissions through assessments and training.  Regional services the center provides includes a website, webinars, training and telephone responses to questions from businesses and technical assistance providers. This year the center will perform a needs assessment survey technical assistance providers that use the center’s services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;on5&quot;&gt;Illinois&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Board of Trustees of the University of Illinois&lt;br /&gt;
	EPA grant: $109,279&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.glrppr.org/&quot;&gt;The Great Lakes Regional Pollution Prevention Roundtable (GLRPPR)&lt;/a&gt; is part of the Illinois Sustainable Technology Center and is located within the University of Illinois at Champaign.  The work plan will advance pollution prevention (P2) information exchange by developing and promoting information resources and training for and facilitating networking among pollution prevention technical assistance providers in the Great Lakes region and beyond. Funding will support analysis of public environmental and economic data sets to develop web-based tools to enable technical assistance providers to make data-driven decisions when choosing technical assistance targets. The center will develop new training and information resources to support the identified needs of the region’s P2 technical assistance providers, especially in U.S. EPA&#039;s National Emphasis Areas.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;on6&quot;&gt;Texas&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;University of Texas at Arlington&lt;br /&gt;
	EPA grant: $69,000&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.zerowastenetwork.org/&quot;&gt;The Zero Waste Network&lt;/a&gt; is a program of the University of Texas at Arlington, Division for Enterprise Development that provides support to State and local P2 programs and businesses in Region 6.  The work plan will provide in person source reduction training in national and regional workshops and support the &quot;P2 Planner&quot; which assists businesses in developing a P2 plan. This center supports a national P2 case study database.  The applicant has documented environmental outcomes resulting from following up with participants in their training and those who use the &quot;P2 Planner&quot;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;on7&quot;&gt;Nebraska&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nebraska: University of Nebraska – Omaha&lt;br /&gt;
	EPA grant: $59,607&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Nebraska Business Development center at the University of Nebraska at Omaha houses the &lt;a href=&quot;https://p2ric.org/&quot;&gt;P2 Regional Information Center&lt;/a&gt; for Region 7.  The work plan includes: collecting, curating and promoting P2 technical information for Technical Assistance Providers- through such services as a calendar, digital library, and social media.  Funding also supports planning for a regional roundtable in 2017 and developing and conducting an Information Center customer satisfaction survey. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;on8&quot;&gt;Montana&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Montana State University&lt;br /&gt;
	EPA grant: $109,279&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Montana State University supports the &lt;a href=&quot;http://peakstoprairies.org/&quot;&gt;Peaks to Prairies P2 Information Center&lt;/a&gt; that serves the states in Region 8 and a national network of 300 Tribal environmental professionals. The center will amplify dissemination of P2 information and tools to mitigate climate change, provide training in energy efficiency assessments in the agricultural business sector, and convene multi-state roundtables.  The center will provide hazardous material source reduction training for Tribes and Region 8’s technical assistance providers, in addition to training on use of the Toxics Release inventory to identify P2 practices relevant to Region 8 businesses.  Specific training for Tribes will be provided in the area of reducing greenhouse gas emissions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;on9&quot;&gt;Nevada&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;University of Nevada, Board of Regents&lt;br /&gt;
	EPA grant: $59,278&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Business Environmental Program at the University of Nevada at Reno supports &lt;a href=&quot;http://wsppn.org/&quot;&gt;The Western Sustainability &amp;amp; Pollution Prevention Network (WSPPN) &lt;/a&gt;. The goal of the program is to assist business and industry with identifying better environmental strategies and solutions for reducing or eliminating waste. Information is provided thru the center’s website, webinars and videos used for training.  The work plan includes: expanding information on reducing greenhouse gases from fleet operations; supporting sustainable hospitality; and working to expand the CA green business program network to encourage standard practices and outcomes for green business recognition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;on10&quot;&gt;Washington&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Washington Department of Ecology&lt;br /&gt;
	EPA grant: $109,279&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The proposal from Washington State Department of Ecology in partnership with the non-profit &lt;a href=&quot;http://pprc.org/&quot;&gt;Pacific Northwest Pollution Prevention Resource Center&lt;/a&gt; will provide regional and national P2 assistance, measurement tools and information products for technical assistance providers, businesses, communities, and local governments. Work will focus on energy efficiency in manufacturing, and craft breweries to decrease greenhouse gas emissions. In addition training for Hispanic workers in the area of spray painting will be provided. The center will continue to support a national web-based resource to help sports teams &quot;green&quot; their facilities.  Reducing toxics in stormwater will also be a regional effort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Mon, 09 May 2016 13:02:39 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>tgelaber</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">148927 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>P2 Guide for Making a Visible Difference in Communities During Extreme Weather Events</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/p2/p2-guide-making-visible-difference-communities-during-extreme-weather-events</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;This guide discusses developing procedures for minimizing hazardous materials releases during extreme weather events as an integral part of a community’s emergency management planning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-316821&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-09/documents/p2_guide_for_making_a_visible_difference_in_communities_during_extreme_weather_events_final_v2.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=292864&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;P2 Guide For Communities During Extreme Weather Events (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(2 pp, 293 K, 
  September 2016)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Fri, 29 Apr 2016 15:29:42 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>llamonic</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">148101 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Scrap Metal Merchants Sector Insights Bulletin</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/p2/scrap-metal-merchants-sector-insights-bulletin</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;Metal scrap recycling is a large complex industry requiring many processing techniques that may pose a range of health and safety concerns for employees and the environment. This bulletin highlights pollution prevention opportunities, including those on the use of environmentally-friendly products and practices to avoid the release of liquid hazardous materials, such as oils and lead-acid battery contents, and air conditioning refrigerants, such as chlorofluorocarbons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-280529&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-04/documents/scrap_metal_final_v4.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=554047&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Scrap Metal Merchants Sector Insights Bulletin (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(2 pp, 554 K, 
  September 2016)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Fri, 29 Apr 2016 15:06:58 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>llamonic</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">148099 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Metal Finishing Sector Insights Bulletin</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/p2/metal-finishing-sector-insights-bulletin</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;Heavy metals and cyanides used in the plating industry are dangerous to the health of employees and can be brought home on clothing thus affecting others. Children and pregnant women are more susceptible to the health risks of heavy metals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This bulletin highlights pollution prevention opportunities for increasing the success, competitiveness, and overall resilience of metal finishing businesses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-280523&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-04/documents/metal_finishing_final_v4.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=547430&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Metal Finishing Sector Insights Bulletin (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(2 pp, 547 K, 
  September 2016)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Fri, 29 Apr 2016 14:56:54 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>llamonic</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">148095 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  </channel>
</rss>

<!-- Page cached by Boost @ 2017-01-26 10:59:14, expires @ 2017-01-26 22:59:14, lifetime 12 hours -->