<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?><rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.epa.gov/feed/3095/rss.xml" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/" xmlns:og="http://ogp.me/ns#" xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#" xmlns:sioc="http://rdfs.org/sioc/ns#" xmlns:sioct="http://rdfs.org/sioc/types#" xmlns:skos="http://www.w3.org/2004/02/skos/core#" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#">
  <channel>
    <title>Mosquito Control</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/feed/3095/rss.xml</link>
    <description>Updated Mosquito Control content from the US Environmental Protection Agency</description>
    <language>en</language>
     <atom:link href="https://www.epa.gov/feed/3095/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      <item>
    <title>Aerial Application of Malathion: Information for Mosquito Control Professionals</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/mosquitocontrol/aerial-application-malathion-information-mosquito-control-professionals</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;As part of its ongoing pesticide reevaluation program EPA recently completed the malathion draft human health risk assessment for all uses, including the aerial mosquito adulticide use. In the following letter, EPA has provided mosquito control professionals in local governments and mosquito control districts with advice on malathion aerial spraying to reduce risks. While EPA would normally not make risk management recommendations based on a draft risk assessment, we have provided this information to mosquito control professionals in the interim so they can be confident in the safety of malathion aerial spraying. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/mosquitocontrol/malathion&quot;&gt;Read more about malathion and its use in mosquito control&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-315509&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-09/documents/letter-to-amca-from-opp-9.14.16.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=91867&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Malathion Aerial Mosquito Control Application Parameters – Letter to AMCA (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(3 pp, 92 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 14 Sep 2016 19:30:50 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>morganic</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">160137 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Naled for Mosquito Control Fact Sheet</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/mosquitocontrol/naled-mosquito-control-fact-sheet</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://espanol.epa.gov/control-de-plagas/naled-para-el-control-del-mosquito&quot;&gt;Lea esta información en español&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following document provides answers to frequently asked questions on the use of naled for mosquito control. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Information current as of August 12, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-308559&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-08/documents/naled_web_page_edits-final_for_pdf.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=43030&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Naled for Mosquito Control Fact Sheet  (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(3 pp, 43 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 06 Jul 2016 18:12:36 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cgesalma</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">154225 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Bti for Mosquito Control Fact Sheet</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/mosquitocontrol/bti-mosquito-control-fact-sheet</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://espanol.epa.gov/control-de-plagas/bti-para-el-control-del-mosquito&quot;&gt;Lea esta información en español&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following document provides answers to frequently asked questions on the use of Bti for mosquito control. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Information current as of August 12, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-308561&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-08/documents/revised_bti_web_page-final_for_pdf.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=33838&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;BTI for Mosquito Control Fact Sheet  (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(2 pp, 34 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 06 Jul 2016 18:10:10 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cgesalma</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">154221 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Naled for Mosquito Control</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/mosquitocontrol/naled-mosquito-control</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://espanol.epa.gov/control-de-plagas/naled-para-el-control-del-mosquito&quot;&gt;Esta página Web está disponible en español&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/mosquitocontrol/naled-mosquito-control-fact-sheet&quot;&gt;Download a PDF version of the following frequently asked questions on the use of naled for mosquito control.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;On this page:&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;##1&quot;&gt;What is naled?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;##2&quot;&gt;Does naled pose health risks to humans?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;##3&quot;&gt;Has EPA estimated risks to children specifically?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;##4&quot;&gt;Where has naled been used for mosquito control?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;##5&quot;&gt;Does naled work on mosquitos carrying Zika?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;##6&quot;&gt;Are insects becoming resistant to naled?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;##7&quot;&gt;Are there any special precautions to be taken during naled spraying?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;##8&quot;&gt;How will I know if aerial spraying is going to take place?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;##9&quot;&gt;Does naled pose risk to crops or water supplies?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;##10&quot;&gt;Is naled harmful to wildlife including honey bees?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;##11&quot;&gt;How can beekeepers reduce the risk of bee exposure to naled?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;##12&quot;&gt;Is there a medical test to show whether I&#039;ve been exposed to naled?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;##13&quot;&gt;What other measures should be take to control mosquitoes besides aerial spraying?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. What is naled?&lt;a name=&quot;#1&quot; id=&quot;#1&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;Naled is an insecticide that has been registered since 1959 for use in the United States. It is used primarily for controlling adult mosquitoes, but is also used on food and feed crops, and in greenhouses.  For mosquito control, naled is applied as an ultra-low volume (ULV) spray. ULV sprayers dispense very fine aerosol droplets containing small quantities of active ingredient insecticide that drift through the air and kill mosquitoes on contact. The amount that reaches the ground is small. For mosquito control, the maximum rate for ground and aerial application is very small.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Does naled pose health risks to humans?&lt;a name=&quot;#2&quot; id=&quot;#2&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;When applied according to label instructions, naled can be used for public health mosquito control programs without posing risks to people. People aren’t likely to breathe or touch anything that has enough insecticide on it to harm them. Direct exposure to naled during or immediately after application should not occur. However, anyone who has a particular concern because of an existing health problem should talk to their doctor. Also, those who tend to be sensitive to chemicals in general, including household chemicals, could experience short-term effects such as skin, eye and nose irritation.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. Has EPA estimated risks to children specifically?&lt;a name=&quot;#3&quot; id=&quot;#3&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;EPA has estimated the exposure and risks to both adults and children posed by ULV aerial and ground applications of naled. Because of the very small amount of active ingredient released per acre of ground, exposures were below an amount that might pose a health concern. These estimates assumed several spraying events over a period of weeks and also assumed that a toddler would consume some soil and grass in addition to skin and inhalation exposure.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. Where has naled been used for mosquito control?&lt;a name=&quot;#4&quot; id=&quot;#4&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;Naled is currently being applied by aerial spraying to about 16 million acres within the mainland United States as part of routine mosquito control, but it can also be used following natural disasters such as hurricanes and floods:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;In 2004, it was used extensively to treat eight million acres across Florida as part of the emergency responses to hurricanes.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;In 2005 after Hurricane Katrina, five million acres of Louisiana, Mississippi, and Texas were treated with naled to kill mosquitoes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Naled has been used in highly populated major metropolitan areas as well as other areas. Historically, naled has been used in Puerto Rico in attempts to control dengue. In 1987, the CDC carried out aerial spraying of naled across 177,000 acres of metropolitan San Juan. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5. Does naled work on mosquitos carrying Zika?&lt;a name=&quot;#5&quot; id=&quot;#5&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Naled has been successfully used for many years in the mainland United States and would be effective in the ongoing effort to control mosquitos carrying Zika, dengue, and chikungunya in Puerto Rico and other areas where these diseases have been identified. Tests carried out in February and March 2016 by the CDC on 14 separate populations of &lt;em&gt;Aedes aegypti &lt;/em&gt;from across Puerto Rico showed that the chemical was highly effective. In each test, 100% mortality of female &lt;em&gt;Aedes aegypti &lt;/em&gt;was achieved. These results, combined with the success of aerial trials with naled in Florida, are compelling reasons to use aerial application of naled for the current Zika emergency situation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;6. &lt;/span&gt;Are insects becoming resistant to naled&lt;span&gt;?&lt;a name=&quot;#6&quot; id=&quot;#6&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Resistance is not an issue at this time for naled. Despite many acres across Florida being sprayed with naled each year, no resistance issues have been detected. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;7. Are there special precautions to be taken during naled spraying?&lt;a name=&quot;#7&quot; id=&quot;#7&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the majority of people, no special precautions need to be taken during spraying. You do not have to leave the area when spraying takes place. However, as a general matter it is a good idea to reduce unnecessary exposure to pesticides whenever possible. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;Some people who are especially concerned&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt; may choose to take some of these steps to help reduce exposure even more. This may include people who are sensitive to chemicals and those with pre-existing respiratory problems.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;span&gt;Stay indoors with the windows closed during spraying.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;span&gt;If you are outdoors during spraying operations and you can see the spray, avoid contact with it. If you can’t avoid contact, rinse your skin and eyes with water.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Wash fruits and vegetables from your garden before storing, cooking or eating.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;span&gt;Cover outside items like furniture and grills while the spraying is occurring. Bring pets and items like pet food dishes and children’s toys indoors. Rinse any items left uncovered outside before using.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;span&gt;If you think you have had a reaction to the mosquito spray, talk to your doctor or call the regional Poison Control Center at 1-800-222-1222.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;8. How will I know if aerial spraying is going to take place?&lt;a name=&quot;#8&quot; id=&quot;#8&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;Decisions about where and when to spray will be made by local officials. Listen for announcements in your community with the dates, times and locations of upcoming sprayings. They are usually announced a day or two before they are scheduled to occur.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;9. Does naled pose risk to crops or water supplies?&lt;a name=&quot;#9&quot; id=&quot;#9&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;No. Naled is approved for use on many crops and EPA has established safe residue levels for all crops. Aerial ULV sprays dispense very fine aerosol droplets containing small quantities of active ingredient that stay aloft and kill mosquitoes on contact. The amount that reaches the ground is tiny and it dissipates very quickly.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;10. Is naled harmful to wildlife including honey bees?&lt;a name=&quot;#10&quot; id=&quot;#10&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;Although naled does pose some risk to aquatic invertebrates (such as shrimp and water fleas) and terrestrial wildlife, it dissipates rapidly and does not persist in the environment. Therefore, risks to aquatic and terrestrial wildlife exist for only a short time, and long term exposure from its use for mosquito control is unlikely.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;Applications made between dusk and dawn, while bees are not typically foraging, can reduce exposure to honey bees.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;11. How can beekeepers reduce the risk of bee exposure to naled?&lt;a name=&quot;#11&quot; id=&quot;#11&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;Although we do not anticipate significant exposure to bees, bee keepers and naled applicators must work together to ensure bee health. Many mosquito control districts maintain lists of beekeepers in their region. When applications are made, these districts will notify bee keeprs so they may take extra precautions if desired. Beekeepers, even with one small hive, can request to be placed on this list.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;Beekeepers can reduce exposure to bee colonies by covering colonies and preventing bees from exiting colonies during designated treatment periods, or if possible, relocating colonies to an untreated site. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;Providing clean sources of food (supplemental sugar water and protein diets) and clean drinking water to honey bee colonies during application can further reduce exposure.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;12. Is there a medical test to show whether I&#039;ve been exposed to naled?&lt;a name=&quot;#12&quot; id=&quot;#12&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are exposed to naled, it can be detected in your blood and its breakdown products can be detected in your urine, but only within a few hours after your last exposure. If exposure is known or suspected, a test can be done that measures cholinesterase levels in your blood. Low levels of cholinesterase may be a result of naled exposure or may be caused by other factors. These tests are not usually available at your doctor&#039;s office, but your doctor can send the samples to a laboratory that can perform the tests. None of these tests, however, will predict whether you will experience any health effects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;13. What other measures should be taken to control mosquitoes besides aerial spraying?&lt;a name=&quot;#13&quot; id=&quot;#13&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;span&gt;Help eliminate any standing water (even tiny amounts) to prevent infected mosquitoes from laying their eggs (breeding) in standing water.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Use window and door screens to block infected mosquitoes from entering your home, workplace or children’s schools.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Use EPA-registered insect repellents to prevent getting bitten. EPA-registered means the product works and is safe when you follow the directions.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;span&gt;Dress in light-colored clothing, long pants, and long sleeves and try to avoid areas where mosquitoes are present.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;For information on the regulatory status of naled, including the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www3.epa.gov/pesticides/chem_search/reg_actions/reregistration/red_PC-034401_31-Jul-06.pdf&quot;&gt;Reregistration Eligibility Decision (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(152 pp, 983 K, &lt;a href=&quot;/home/pdf-files&quot;&gt;About PDF&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;, see the &lt;a href=&quot;https://iaspub.epa.gov/apex/pesticides/f?p=CHEMICALSEARCH:31:0::NO:1,3,31,7,12,25:P3_XCHEMICAL_ID:3013&quot;&gt;Chemical Search page for naled&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 05 Jul 2016 15:18:38 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cgesalma</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">154117 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Bti for Mosquito Control</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/mosquitocontrol/bti-mosquito-control</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://espanol.epa.gov/control-de-plagas/bti-para-el-control-del-mosquito&quot;&gt;Esta página Web está disponible en español&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/mosquitocontrol/bti-mosquito-control-fact-sheet&quot;&gt;Download a PDF version of the following frequently asked questions on the use of Bti for mosquito control.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;On this page:&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;##1&quot;&gt;What is Bti?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;##2&quot;&gt;Does Bti pose health risks to humans?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;##3&quot;&gt;Where has Bti been used for mosquito control?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;##4&quot;&gt;Will Bti work to control mosquito larvae?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;##5&quot;&gt;Are insects becoming resistant to Bti?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;##6&quot;&gt;Are there special precautions to be taken during Bti spraying?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;##7&quot;&gt;How will I know if aerial spraying is going to take place?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;##8&quot;&gt;Does Bti pose risk to crops or water supplies?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;##9&quot;&gt;Is Bti harmful to wildlife including honey bees?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;##10&quot;&gt;Is there a medical test to show whether I&#039;ve been exposed to Bti?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;##11&quot;&gt;What other measures should be taken to control mosquitoes besides aerial spraying?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. What is Bti?&lt;a name=&quot;#1&quot; id=&quot;#1&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bti is a biological or a naturally occurring bacterium found in soils. (Bti is short for &lt;em&gt;Bacillus thuringiensis&lt;/em&gt; subspecies &lt;em&gt;israelensis&lt;/em&gt;.) It contains spores that produce toxins that specifically target and only affect the larvae of the mosquito, blackfly and fungus gnat. EPA has registered five different strains of Bti found in 48 pesticide products that are approved for use in residential, commercial and agricultural settings primarily for control of mosquito larvae.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Does Bti pose health risks to humans?&lt;a name=&quot;#2&quot; id=&quot;#2&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No. Bti has no toxicity to people and is approved for use for pest control in organic farming operations. It has been well tested by many studies on acute toxicity and pathogenicity (ability to cause disease) for &lt;em&gt;Bacillus thuringiensis&lt;/em&gt; including studies specifically on Bti. Based on these studies, EPA has concluded that Bti does not pose a risk to humans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. Where has Bti been used for mosquito control?&lt;a name=&quot;#3&quot; id=&quot;#3&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bti is used across the United States for mosquito control. Bti is approved for aerial spraying, which has taken place in Massachusetts, Pennsylvania, Maryland and Michigan, among other states.  Bti can be sprayed over waterbodies such as ponds, lakes, rivers and streams.  Bti is used to kill developing mosquito larvae by being applied to standing water where those larvae are found. Bti can be used around homes in areas and containers where water can collect, such as flower pots, tires, and bird baths. Bti can also be used to treat larger bodies of water like ponds, lakes and irrigation ditches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. Will Bti work to control mosquito larvae?&lt;a name=&quot;#4&quot; id=&quot;#4&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, Bti has been shown to be effective in reducing mosquito larval populations and could be effective in controlling mosquitos carrying Zika, dengue and chikungunya in places like Puerto Rico and other areas where these diseases have been identified.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5. Are insects becoming resistant to Bti? &lt;a name=&quot;#5&quot; id=&quot;#5&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No. There is no documented resistance to Bti as a larvicide. A &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3970644/&quot;&gt;recent study (Tetreau et al. 2013) confirmed previous research showing a lack of Bti resistance&lt;/a&gt; in mosquito populations that had been treated for decades with Bti.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;6. Are there special precautions to be taken during Bti spraying?&lt;a name=&quot;#6&quot; id=&quot;#6&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No special precautions are needed for applying Bti. A number of Bti products are sold as “homeowner” products and are easy and safe to use. People do not need to leave areas being treated. However, as is the case with many microbial pesticides, some commercial use Bti products may require applicators to wear a dust/mist filtering mask.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;7. How will I know if aerial spraying is going to take place?&lt;a name=&quot;#7&quot; id=&quot;#7&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Decisions about where and when to spray will be made by local officials. Listen for announcements in your community with the dates, times and locations of upcoming sprayings on social media sites, newspapers or radios.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;8. Does Bti pose risk to crops or water supplies?&lt;a name=&quot;#8&quot; id=&quot;#8&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No. Bti has no toxicity to people, so it can be applied safely to mosquito habitat without a detrimental impact on food crops or water supplies.  In fact, Bti can be used for pest control in organic farming operations. It is important to follow the label for any Bti product to ensure that the product is being used correctly. There are multiple Bti products and some are allowed to be used on certain drinking water (e.g., cisterns) while others are not intended for that use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;9. Is Bti harmful to wildlife including honey bees?&lt;a name=&quot;#9&quot; id=&quot;#9&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Studies indicate Bti has minimal toxicity to honey bees. Bti produces toxins that specifically affect the larvae of only mosquitoes, black flies and fungus gnats. These toxins do not affect other types of insects including honey bees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;10. Is there a medical test to show whether I&#039;ve been exposed to Bti?&lt;a name=&quot;#10&quot; id=&quot;#10&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since Bti has no toxicity to humans, a medical test to show exposure to the active ingredient has not been developed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;11. What other measures should be taken to control mosquitoes besides aerial spraying?&lt;a name=&quot;#11&quot; id=&quot;#11&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Eliminate any standing water (even tiny amounts) to prevent infected mosquitoes from laying their eggs (breeding) in standing water.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Use window and door screens to block infected mosquitoes from entering your home, workplace or children’s schools.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Use EPA-registered insect repellents to prevent getting bitten. EPA-registered means the product works and is safe when you follow the directions.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Dress in light-colored clothing, long pants, and long sleeves and try to avoid areas where mosquitoes are present.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 05 Jul 2016 14:51:15 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>ctran</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">154109 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Mosquito Control Activities in Puerto Rico</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/mosquitocontrol/mosquito-control-activities-puerto-rico</link>
    <description>&lt;div class=&quot;box multi related-info right&quot;&gt;
	&lt;h2 class=&quot;pane-title&quot;&gt;Additional Resources&lt;/h2&gt;

	&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/insect-repellents/using-repellent-products-protect-against-mosquito-borne-illnesses&quot;&gt;Using insect repellents to protect against mosquito-borne illnesses&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/insect-repellents/find-insect-repellent-right-you&quot;&gt;Find the insect repellent that&#039;s right for you&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cdc.gov/zika/index.html&quot;&gt;CDC information on the Zika virus&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://espanol.epa.gov/control-de-plagas/actividades-de-control-de-mosquito-en-puerto-rico&quot;&gt;Esta página Web está disponible en español&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Puerto Rico is actively working to control mosquitoes that transmit Zika, dengue and chikungunya; however, mosquito populations are increasing and additional methods are needed to control the mosquitos during their adult stage. EPA and the Centers for Disease Control (CDC) are working together to help Puerto Rico develop a successful, sustainable approach to controlling mosquitoes that transmit Zika, dengue, chikungunya, and other diseases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/newsreleases/us-centers-disease-control-and-prevention-and-environmental-protection-agency-urge&quot;&gt;CDC and EPA urge Commonwealth of Puerto Rico to consider aerial spraying as part of integrated mosquito control to reduce Zika-associated birth defects.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/mosquitocontrol/success-mosquito-control-integrated-approach&quot;&gt;Read our comprehensive approach for controlling mosquitoes throughout their lifecycle.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Learn about common mosquito control pesticides:
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/mosquitocontrol/naled-mosquito-control&quot;&gt;Naled is an insecticide used to quickly and effectively control adult mosquitoes.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/mosquitocontrol/bti-mosquito-control&quot;&gt;BTI is a naturally occurring bacteria found in soils that can be used to control mosquito larvae.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 05 Jul 2016 14:42:53 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cdunton</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">154107 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Success in Mosquito Control: An Integrated Approach</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/mosquitocontrol/success-mosquito-control-integrated-approach</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://espanol.epa.gov/control-de-plagas/el-exito-en-el-control-del-mosquito-un-enfoque-integrado&quot;&gt;Esta página Web está disponible en español&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Controlling Mosquitoes Effectively Requires a Comprehensive Approach that has been Scientifically Tested and Proven&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Centers for Disease Control (CDC) and the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) collaborate on mosquito control activities throughout the United States to control diseases. By looking at biological information about the life and reproduction of the mosquito and epidemiological information about the disease, the two organizations have developed a methodology on how best to control mosquitoes. Both CDC and EPA are helping Puerto Rico apply this methodology to develop a successful, sustainable program and approach to controlling mosquitoes that transmit Zika, dengue, chikungunya, and other diseases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Successful mosquito management requires intervening at some point during the mosquito’s life cycle before they bite and infect a human.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best approach to controlling mosquitoes takes advantage of every life stage of a mosquito to achieve control, using a unified approach referred to as integrated pest management (IPM).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Integrated Pest Management&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA and CDC encourage all communities and mosquito control districts, including those in territories like Puerto Rico, to strictly adhere to IPM. IPM is a science-based, common-sense approach for managing pests and vectors, such as mosquitoes. IPM uses a variety of pest management techniques that focus on pest prevention, pest reduction, and the elimination of conditions that lead to pest infestations. IPM programs also rely heavily on resident education and pest monitoring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A successful IPM strategy can use pesticides.  IPM uses a combination of ways to control mosquito populations with decisions based on surveillance, such as keeping track or count of the numbers and types of mosquitoes in an area. Surveillance is a critical component to any successful IPM program because the results from the surveillance will help determine the appropriate response to an infestation. Extensive infestations, or those where disease is present, merit a different response than will lower levels of infestations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both CDC and EPA recognize a legitimate and compelling need for the use of chemical interventions, under certain circumstances, to control adult mosquitoes. This is especially true during periods of mosquito-borne disease transmission or when source reduction and larval control have failed or are not feasible. &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Puerto Rico has been actively working to control mosquitoes that transmit Zika (and dengue and chikungunya) for about six months; however, mosquito populations are increasing and additional methods are needed to control the mosquitoes during their adult stage.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A successful integrated mosquito control strategy includes several tactics to eliminate mosquitoes and their habitat. Four critical tactics include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#remove habitats&quot;&gt;Remove Mosquito Habitats&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#structural barriers&quot;&gt;Use Structural Barriers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#larval stage&quot;&gt;Control Mosquitoes at the Larval Stage&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#adult mosquitoes&quot;&gt;Control Adult Mosquitoes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. Remove Mosquito Habitats&lt;a name=&quot;remove habitats&quot; id=&quot;remove habitats&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An important part of mosquito control around homes is making sure that mosquitoes don&#039;t have a place to lay their eggs. Because mosquitoes need water for two stages of their life cycle, it&#039;s important to monitor standing water sources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Get rid of standing water in rain gutters, old tires, buckets, plastic covers, toys or any other container where mosquitoes can breed.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;CDC is providing a large amount of funding to purchase tire shredders for Puerto Rico. This is important because used or waste tires can collect standing water that attracts mosquitoes and leads to increased mosquito breeding.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Empty and change the water in bird baths, fountains, wading pools, rain barrels and potted plant trays at least once a week to eliminate potential mosquito habitats.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Drain temporary pools of water or fill with dirt.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Keep swimming pool water treated and circulating.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Use Structural Barriers&lt;a name=&quot;structural barriers&quot; id=&quot;structural barriers&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because &lt;em&gt;Aedes&lt;/em&gt; mosquitoes frequently bite indoors, using structural barriers is an important way to reduce the incidence of bites. Examples of structural barriers include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Install window and door screens if they are not already in place.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Cover all gaps in walls, doors and windows to prevent mosquitoes from entering.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Make sure window and door screens are &quot;bug tight.&quot;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Completely cover baby carriers and beds with netting. Nets can be especially important for protecting a sick person from getting more mosquito bites, which could transmit the disease to other people.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;strong&gt; 3. Control Mosquitoes at the Larval Stage&lt;a name=&quot;larval stage&quot; id=&quot;larval stage&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The greatest impact on mosquito populations will occur when they are &lt;em&gt;concentrated, immobile&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;accessible&lt;/em&gt;. This emphasis focuses on habitat management and controlling the immature stages (egg, larva, and pupa) before the mosquitoes emerge as adults. This approach maximizes the effectiveness of pesticide application and minimizes the use from widespread pesticide application. Larvicides target larvae in the breeding habitat before they can mature into adult mosquitoes and disperse. Larvicide treatment of breeding habitats helps reduce the adult mosquito population in nearby areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Aedes aegypti &lt;/em&gt;mosquitoes can use natural locations or habitats (for example tree holes and crevices in plants) and artificial containers with water to lay their eggs. They lay eggs during the day in water containing organic material (e.g., decaying leaves, algae, etc.) in containers with wide openings.  They prefer dark-colored containers located in the shade.  Other sites where they may lay their eggs include: old tires, buckets, toys, potted plant trays and saucers, plastic covers and even places as small as bottle caps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Egg and larva interventions are generally the most effective, least costly, way to control mosquitoes. However, these interventions are unlikely to be 100% effective, especially for mosquitoes like the &lt;em&gt;Aedes aegypti&lt;/em&gt; that breed in varied and scattered locations. In these cases, eliminating or treating all or even most standing water can be nearly impossible. Successful control efforts will need to supplement habitat removal with other means of control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Involvement of the community is essential to these interventions, especially in urban areas such as San Juan, Puerto Rico. Residents, neighbors, and landlords can all be proactive in eliminating standing water or alerting others to its presence to eliminate even the smallest sources of standing water. &lt;em&gt;Aedes aegypti &lt;/em&gt;have evolved so that they can reproduce in even the most challenging environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a number of EPA-registered active ingredients used in larvicides. Choosing which larvicide to use in a given area is best done by experts and will depend on a variety of factors, including potential human or environmental risk, cost, resistance, and ease of use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. Control Adult Mosquitoes&lt;a name=&quot;adult mosquitoes&quot; id=&quot;adult mosquitoes&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using an EPA-registered pesticide is one of the fastest and best options to combat an outbreak of mosquito-borne disease being transmitted by adult mosquitoes. The pesticides registered for this use are known as adulticides.  Adulticides are applied either using aerial applications by aircraft or on the ground by truck-mounted sprayers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aerial spraying techniques can treat large areas with only small amounts of pesticide and have been used safely for more than 50 years. These aerial sprays are been fully evaluated by EPA and don’t pose risks to people or the environment when used according to the directions on the label. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mosquito adulticides are applied as ultra-low volume (ULV) sprays. ULV sprayers dispense extremely small droplets. The naled insecticide, for example, uses 80 microns or less which means hundreds of thousands of droplets could fit inside something as small as one pea. When released from an airplane, these tiny droplets are intended to stay airborne as long as possible and drift through an area above the ground killing the mosquitoes in the air on contact. The small droplet size makes the pesticide more effective, which means less pesticide is used to better protect people and the environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Extensive scientific research has been conducted by academia, industry, and government agencies to identify appropriate droplet sizes for individual compounds. The equipment nozzles undergo rigorous testing before being sold to the mosquito controllers. ULV applications involve very small quantities of pesticide active ingredient in relation to the size of the area treated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a number of registered adulticides to choose from. Choosing which adulticide to use in a given area is a job best done by experts and will depend on a variety of factors such as the type of mosquito, whether the mosquitoes are resistant to particular types of pesticides, weather, etc. In Puerto Rico, naled was the only existing product to show 100% mosquito death in all populations tested.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mainland U.S. has successfully used naled to quickly reduce mosquito populations.. This pesticide has been used for routine mosquito control and following natural disasters such as hurricanes and floods on millions of acres across the U.S. Naled was used recently for mosquito control in FL, TX, LA, GA, SC, GA, WA, CA, NV, and in a number of other states. The insecticide is used highly populated metropolitan areas, such as Miami, and in less populated areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2004, naled was used extensively to treat eight million acres across Florida as part of the emergency responses to hurricanes.  In 2005 after Hurricane Katrina, five million acres of Louisiana, Mississippi, and Texas were treated with naled to kill mosquitoes.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Naled is effective at controlling Zika, dengue and chikungunya.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 05 Jul 2016 12:11:24 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cgesalma</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">154103 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Mosquito Misting Systems</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/mosquitocontrol/mosquito-misting-systems</link>
    <description>&lt;h2&gt;Outdoor Residential Misting Systems&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;figure image mode-medium caption right&quot; style=&quot;width:242px&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/sites/production/files/2013-06/misting_system.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg view-mode-medium&quot; style=&quot;width:242px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;outdoor residential misting system&quot; title=&quot;Outdoor Residential Misting System&quot; height=&quot;199&quot; width=&quot;242&quot; class=&quot;media-element file-medium&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/medium/public/2013-06/misting_system.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

	&lt;div class=&quot;figcaption&quot;&gt;Mosquito Mister installed in fencing. Kansas State University&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An increasing number of households have purchased timed-release outdoor residential misting systems to control mosquitoes and other insects around the home. However, advertisers, the media, and other sources sometimes provide information about misting systems that is difficult to understand or might conflict with other information. This fact sheet page will help consumers:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;decide if residential pesticide misting systems are appropriate for their home&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;understand safety precautions about using outdoor misting systems&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;find related information on Integrated Pest Management -- using a variety of methods for mosquito control&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;understand the role of the EPA and state agencies in regulating misters.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Check your instruction manual or contact the manufacturer if you have questions about how to operate or maintain your home misting system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please note, this page does not address use of misting systems in livestock barns, boat docks, or in or around restaurants, factories, or other public spaces. More information &lt;a href=&quot;/pesticide-contacts/contacting-epa-about-regulating-pesticides-issues&quot;&gt;about regulating and use of pesticides&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On this page:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#misting&quot;&gt;What are outdoor residential misting systems?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#pesticides&quot;&gt;What pesticides are used in the misting systems?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#safe&quot;&gt;Are residential misting systems safe?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#effective&quot;&gt;Are residential misting systems effective in controlling insect pests?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#regulate&quot;&gt;Are misting systems regulated by EPA or the states?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#install&quot;&gt;Installing and using misting systems&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#emergency&quot;&gt;In case of an emergency&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;misting&quot; id=&quot;misting&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;What are outdoor residential misting systems?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Outdoor residential misting systems (sometimes called &quot;mosquito misters&quot;) are application systems designed to spray pesticides in a fine mist to kill mosquitoes and other insects outdoors. Misting systems include spray nozzles that are mounted around the perimeter of a home in the lawn or landscaping, or on parts of the house or fence. The spray nozzles are connected by tubing to a supply of insecticide. Some misting systems may be turned on at preset intervals using a timer. Others may be turned on using a remote controller, while others may be activated using a switch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;pesticides&quot; id=&quot;pesticides&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;What pesticides are used in the misting systems?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The insecticide products most often used in outdoor residential misting systems contain pyrethrins and permethrin. These products may also contain piperonyl butoxide. To be sure what type of insecticide you are using, check the list of active ingredients on the container label.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Certain &lt;a href=&quot;/minimum-risk-pesticides&quot;&gt;minimal risk pesticides&lt;/a&gt; may also be used in some misting systems. Although not regulated by EPA, many states do regulate these pesticides. &lt;a href=&quot;http://npic.orst.edu/reg/state_agencies.html&quot;&gt;Check with your state agency&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span&gt;about any requirements or warnings you need to be aware of before you use the pesticide. EPA has not evaluated the potential risk or effectiveness of these minimal risk chemicals in misting systems.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is illegal to use a pesticide in a misting system if the pesticide label contains a prohibition against use in these systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;box&quot;&gt;
	&lt;h4&gt;The Label Is The Law&lt;/h4&gt;

	&lt;div class=&quot;figure image mode-teaser right&quot; style=&quot;width:62px&quot;&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-gif view-mode-teaser&quot; style=&quot;width:62px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;read the label&quot; title=&quot;Read the Label&quot; height=&quot;62&quot; width=&quot;62&quot; class=&quot;media-element file-teaser&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/small/public/2013-06/readthelabel.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

	&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Pesticide labels provide instructions about proper handling, use, and application rates of the product, and precautions to protect people and the environment.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;Label directions are derived from scientific testing by manufacturers and evaluation by EPA scientists to ensure that products can be used with minimal risk to people and the environment.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/pesticide-labels&quot;&gt;READ THE LABEL FIRST!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;effective&quot; id=&quot;effective&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Are residential misting systems effective in controlling insect pests?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;box multi related-info right&quot;&gt;
	&lt;h2 class=&quot;pane-title&quot;&gt;Information on Controlling Insects&lt;/h2&gt;

	&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/mosquitocontrol&quot;&gt;Mosquito Control&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mosquito.org/&quot;&gt;American Mosquito Control Association&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://westnile.ca.gov/mosquito_control.htm&quot;&gt;State of California Mosquito Control&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Other Insect Control
				&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://npic.orst.edu/&quot;&gt;National Pesticide Information Center&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA, as well as the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) and many mosquito control professionals, believe that a combination of approaches generally known as Integrated Pest Management (IPM) is most effective at combating mosquito populations. For example, mosquitoes breed in water, so the elimination of standing water around your home is an essential part of any approach to controlling mosquitoes. Almost any size container such as empty jars or cans, flower pot saucers, cinderblocks or old tires can provide a habitat for mosquitoes to hatch if they remain filled with water for more than a few days. Killing mosquito larvae by draining water before they emerge as adults can reduce or eliminate the need to spray pesticides to kill adult mosquitoes. Because mosquitoes may travel several miles as adults, any management efforts may provide only temporary control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Outdoor residential misting systems have not yet been studied sufficiently to document their effectiveness in controlling mosquitoes or other yard and garden pests, nor have they been scientifically proven to control or prevent the spread of West Nile Virus or other diseases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While pest management begins with you, effective mosquito control is often community-based. Contact your local health department or mosquito abatement district to report severe annoyance or potential mosquito sources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For pests other than mosquitoes, a combination of pest management practices tailored for the specific pest may offer the best results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#content&quot;&gt;Top of page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;safe&quot; id=&quot;safe&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Are residential misting systems safe?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People and pets may be exposed to pesticides used in a residential misting system through direct contact with sprays, by touching plants or other objects in the treated area, or by inhaling small amounts of pesticide remaining in the air. EPA has assessed the human health and environmental risks of the pesticides most commonly used in misting systems. Most of these pesticides last only short periods in the environment, so long-term exposure to humans is not expected. Based on its assessment, using toxicity data and exposure estimates, EPA does not expect risks of concern to humans when these chemicals are used in outdoor residential systems according to labeling specific for use in these systems. However, excessive use or accidents may pose risks. No pesticide should be regarded as 100% risk free.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since pyrethrins and permethrin are toxic to all insects, they may kill beneficial insects such as honeybees, ladybugs, butterflies and other non-target species. In addition, permethrin is very highly toxic to fish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA&#039;s most recent regulatory reviews of the pesticides commonly used in misting systems are available:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/mosquitocontrol/permethrin-resmethrin-d-phenothrin-sumithrinr-synthetic-pyrethroids-mosquito-control&quot;&gt;Permethrin&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/ingredients-used-pesticide-products/pyrethrins-and-pyrethroids&quot;&gt;Pyrethrins&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/endocrine-disruption/endocrine-disruptor-screening-program-tier-1-screening-determinations-and&quot;&gt;Piperonyl butoxide&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;EPA has not evaluated if other pesticides can be labeled for use in these misting systems without possible harm to human health and the environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;regulate&quot; id=&quot;regulate&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Are misting systems regulated by EPA or the states?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;h4&gt;States&lt;/h4&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;Regulations for these systems may vary from state to state. Some states may forbid the use of certain pesticides, or any pesticides at all in these systems in residential areas, others may require that signs be posted, while others may not regulate their use at all. For the most updated and accurate regulations in your state, consider consulting your &lt;a href=&quot;http://npic.orst.edu/reg/state_agencies.html&quot;&gt;state pesticide regulatory agency&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span&gt;for details before you purchase, hire a company to install, or use a misting system.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;h4&gt;EPA&lt;/h4&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;EPA does not regulate residential outdoor misting system equipment. Misting system components are considered &quot;application equipment&quot; and therefore are not regulated by EPA. Misting systems also are not classified as &quot;&lt;a href=&quot;/safepestcontrol/pesticide-devices-guide-consumers&quot;&gt;pesticide devices&lt;/a&gt;.&quot;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
			EPA &lt;a href=&quot;/pesticide-registration/pesticide-registration-manual-chapter-2-registering-pesticide-product&quot;&gt;registers pesticides&lt;/a&gt; that may be used in misting systems. EPA examines the ingredients of the pesticide; the particular site on which it is to be used; and the amount, frequency, and timing of its use. EPA evaluates pesticides to ensure that they will not have unreasonable adverse effects on humans, the environment, and non-target species when used according to label directions.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;install&quot; id=&quot;install&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Installing and Using Misting Systems&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When using a misting system, following a few simple guidelines will minimize potential exposure to people, pets, and the environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;When Having a System Installed:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Always use installers and service technicians that comply with the state&#039;s license, certification, and registration requirements.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Make sure that the installer has calibrated the system to apply no more than the maximum daily application rate as specified on the pesticide label.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Make sure the nozzles are directed to spray toward the target area and away from eating/cooking areas and any water body including swimming pools and fish ponds (some pesticides are toxic to aquatic organisms).&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Placing nozzles less than 10 ft from the ground will reduce chemical drift. Chemical drift may affect other people, animals and surrounding environment not in your yard area.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Set nozzles to direct mist away from outside air conditioners or other home air intakes.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Make sure both the reservoir and operating system are securely locked and inaccessible to children at all times to avoid potential poisoning accidents.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;When practical, install wind, rain, and motion sensors to reduce unnecessary pesticide usage and inadvertent application when people or pets are present.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h4&gt;When Using a System:&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Do not apply the pesticide when people, pets, or foods are present.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Set automatic timers for times when people and pets are unlikely to be sprayed.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Only use the system when pests are most active. For example, certain varieties of mosquitoes are most active in the early morning and evening hours.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Avoid using the system during high wind (&amp;gt;10 mph), rainfall, fog, or when outside air temperatures fall below 50 Fahrenheit or other times when insects are generally not active.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Obtain and READ the pesticide label to know the pesticide precautions and its appropriate use in the system.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Be aware of the maximum daily rate specified on the product label and how your system operates.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Be a good neighbor - some neighbors may have sensitivities to the pesticides or object to drift of chemicals onto their property.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Avoid damage or misuse from a leaking or malfunctioning system - regularly maintain and inspect it.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Turn the system off when not needed for extended periods of time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;emergency&quot; id=&quot;emergency&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;In Case of an Emergency&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important to understand that improper installation of a misting system, over-exposure to pesticides, or unforeseen incidents can lead to serious injury to you and your family and others, as well as to the environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;h4&gt;Equipment leaking or not working right?&lt;/h4&gt;

		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Turn off the system immediately and contact your installation company.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Ask the company about any safety precautions you need to follow.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Always - keep children and pets away from pesticides and pesticide equipment.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;h4&gt;Keep handy for emergencies:&lt;/h4&gt;

		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;EPA Registration number of the pesticide used in the misting system&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Phone numbers for:
				&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;National Poisoning Hotline at (800-222-1222)&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/pesticide-incidents/first-aid-case-pesticide-exposure&quot;&gt;More about poison emergencies&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;Your local fire department or emergency responder&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;National Pesticide Information Center at 800-858-7378&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;Your service technician&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Mon, 29 Jul 2013 11:58:43 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>morganic</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">37407 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Joint Statement on Mosquito Control in the United States</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/mosquitocontrol/joint-statement-mosquito-control-united-states</link>
    <description>&lt;h2&gt;Joint Statement on Mosquito Control in the United States from the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) and the U.S. Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Current as of: September 2012&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;On this page:&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#government&quot;&gt;The Role of Government Agencies and the Public&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#diseases&quot;&gt;Diseases Transmitted by mosquitoes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#lifecycle&quot;&gt;Mosquito Life Cycle&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#programs&quot;&gt;Mosquito Control Programs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#ipm&quot;&gt;Integrated Pest Management&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#education&quot;&gt;Education&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#info&quot;&gt;For More Information&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;government&quot; id=&quot;government&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The Role of Government Agencies and the Public&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mosquito-borne diseases are among the world&#039;s leading causes of illness and death today. The World Health Organization estimates that more than 300 million clinical cases each year are attributable to mosquito-borne illnesses. Despite great strides over the last 50 years, mosquito-borne illnesses continue to pose significant risks to parts of the population in the United States. Current challenges posed by the emergence of West Nile virus in the Western hemisphere illustrate the importance of cooperation and partnership at all levels of government to protect public health. The Environmental Protection Agency (EPA, the Agency) and the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) are working closely with each other and with other federal, state, and local agencies to protect the public from mosquito-borne diseases such as the West Nile virus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CDC, working closely with state and local health departments, monitors the potential sources and outbreaks of mosquito-borne diseases and provides advice and consultation on prevention and control of these diseases. CDC works with a network of experts in human and veterinary medicine, entomology, epidemiology, zoology, and ecology to obtain quick and accurate information on emerging trends which they develop into national strategies that reduce the risk of disease transmission.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA ensures that state and local mosquito control departments have access to effective mosquito control tools that they can use without posing unreasonable risk to human health and the environment. EPA encourages nonchemical mosquito prevention efforts, such as eliminating standing water that provide breeding sites. The Agency educates the public through outreach efforts to encourage proper use of insect repellents and mosquitocides. Additionally, EPA&#039;s rigorous pesticide review process is designed to ensure that registered mosquitocides used according to label directions and precautions can further reduce disease-carrying mosquito populations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;State and local government agencies play a critical role in protecting public health from mosquito-borne diseases. They serve on the front line, providing information through their outreach programs to the medical and environmental surveillance networks that first identify possible outbreaks. They also manage the mosquito control programs that carry out prevention, public education and vector population management.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The public&#039;s role in eliminating potential breeding habitats for mosquitoes -- such as getting rid of any standing water around the home -- is a critical step in reducing the risk of mosquito-borne disease transmission. The public is also encouraged to make sure window screens and screen doors are in good repair. When venturing into areas with &lt;i&gt;high&lt;/i&gt; mosquito populations, the public should wear personal protection such as long sleeve shirts and long pants, preferably treated with a repellent.. People should use mosquito repellents when necessary, and always follow label instructions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;diseases&quot; id=&quot;diseases&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Diseases Transmitted by Mosquitoes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mosquitoes are found throughout the world and many transmit pathogens which may cause disease. These diseases include mosquito-borne viral encephalitis, dengue, yellow fever, malaria, and filariasis. Most of these diseases have been prominent as endemic or epidemic diseases in the United States in the past, but today, only the insect-borne (arboviral) encephalitides occur annually and dengue occurs periodically in this country. The major types of viral encephalitis in the United States include St. Louis, LaCrosse, Eastern equine and Western equine. These viruses are normally infections of birds or small mammals. During such infections, the level of the virus may increase in these infected animals facilitating transmission to humans by mosquitoes. The West Nile virus, which can also cause encephalitis, was found in the northeastern United States for the first time in 1999, is a good example of this mode of transmission. Human cases of encephalitis range from mild to very severe illnesses that, in a few cases, can be fatal. Dengue is a viral disease transmitted from person to person by mosquitoes. It is usually an acute, nonfatal disease, characterized by sudden onset of fever, headache, backache, joint pains, nausea, and vomiting. While most infections result in a mild illness, some may cause the severe forms of the disease. Dengue hemorrhagic fever, for example, is characterized by severe rash, nosebleeds, gastrointestinal bleeding and circulatory failure resulting in dengue shock syndrome and even death. Dengue is endemic in the Caribbean, Central and South America. Recently, dengue has occurred with increasing frequency in Texas. Other pathogens transmitted by mosquitoes include a protozoan parasite which causes malaria, and &lt;em&gt;Dirofilaria immitis&lt;/em&gt;, a parasitic roundworm and the causative agent of dog heartworm. Disease carrying mosquito species are found throughout the U.S., especially in urban areas and coastal or in inland areas where flooding of low lands frequently occurs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;lifecycle&quot; id=&quot;lifecycle&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Mosquito Life Cycle&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;figure image mode-full right&quot; style=&quot;width:309px&quot;&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:309px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Mosquito life cycle&quot; title=&quot;Mosquito life cycle&quot; height=&quot;307&quot; width=&quot;309&quot; class=&quot;media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2013-06/lifecycle.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The life cycle of all mosquitoes consists of four distinct life stages: egg, larva, pupa and adult. The first three stages occur in water, but the adult is an active flying insect that feeds upon the blood of humans and/or animals. The female mosquito lays the eggs directly on water or on moist substrates that may be flooded with water. The egg later hatches into the larva, the elongated aquatic stage most commonly observed as it swims in the water. The larva transforms into the pupa where internal changes occur and the adult mosquito takes form. After two days to a week in the pupal stage, the adult mosquito emerges onto the water&#039;s surface and flies away. Only the female mosquito takes blood which they usually require for her eggs to develop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The practice of mosquito control focuses on the unique biology and behavior of the mosquito species of concern. Mosquito biology can follow two general scenarios. The first involves those species that lay their eggs in masses or rafts on the water&#039;s surface. Some of these species, which are found throughout the U.S., often lay their eggs in natural or artificial water-holding containers found in the domestic environment, or in naturally occurring pools. The second scenario involves mosquitoes that lay their eggs on moist soil or other substrates in areas that will be flooded with water later. After about two days, these eggs are ready to hatch, but if not flooded, can withstand drying for months. In inland areas of the U.S. where these mosquitoes breed, heavy rains and flooding can produce millions of mosquitoes in a short time. Similar situations occur along coastal areas with mosquitoes adapted to salt marsh habitats. Some salt marsh mosquitoes are strong fliers and can sometimes travel up to 50 miles from the breeding site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;programs&quot; id=&quot;programs&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Mosquito Control Programs&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In response to these potential disease carrying pests, communities organized the earliest mosquito control programs in the eastern U.S. in the early 1900s. Eventually, other communities created similar programs throughout the country in areas where mosquito problems occurred and where citizens demanded action by local officials. Modern mosquito control programs in the U.S. are multifaceted and include surveillance, source reduction, and a variety of larval and adult mosquito control strategies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Surveillance methods include studying habitats by air, aerial photographs, and topographic maps, and evaluating larval populations. Mosquito control officials also monitor mosquito traps, biting counts, and complaints and reports from the public. Mosquito control activities are initiated once established mosquito threshold populations are exceeded. Seasonal records are kept in concurrence with weather data to predict mosquito larval occurrence and adult flights. Some mosquito control programs conduct surveillance for diseases harbored by birds, including crows, other wild birds, sentinel chicken flocks, and for these diseases in mosquitoes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Source reduction involves eliminating the habitat or modifying the aquatic habitat to prevent mosquitoes from breeding. This measure includes sanitation measures where artificial containers, including discarded automobile tires, which can become mosquito habitats, are collected and properly disposed. Habitat modification may also involve management of impounded water or open marshes to reduce production and survival of the flood water mosquitoes. If habitat modification is not feasible, biological control using fish may be possible. Mosquito control officials often apply biological or chemical &lt;em&gt;larvicides, &lt;/em&gt;with selective action and moderate residual activity, to the aquatic habitats. To have the maximum impact on the mosquito population, larvicides are applied during those periods when immature stages are concentrated in the breeding sites and before the adult forms emerge and disperse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some mosquitoes can fly from flood plains, coastal marsh areas, or protected habitats to impact urban residential areas. In these cases, it is often necessary to apply pesticides to kill adult mosquitoes. Surveillance data may prompt insecticide applications when mosquitoes are abundant. Applications usually coincide with the maximum adult mosquito activity in urban residential areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be successful, mosquito control officials must apply insecticides under proper environmental conditions (e.g., temperature and wind) and at the time of day when the target species is most active. They must also apply these pesticides with carefully calibrated equipment that generates the proper-sized insecticide droplets that will impinge on adult mosquitoes while they are at rest or flying. If the droplets are too large, they will fall to the ground. If they are too small, the prevailing winds will carry them away from the target area. Once the insecticide spray mist dissipates, they break down in the environment (generally within 24 hours) producing little residual effect. Depending on the situation, mosquito control officials may safely apply these insecticides from spray equipment mounted on trucks, airplanes or helicopters. All insecticides used in the U.S. for public health use have been approved and registered by the EPA following the review of many scientific studies. The EPA has assessed these chemicals and found that, when used according to label directions, they do not pose unreasonable risk to public health and the environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mosquito control officials have also developed water management strategies that take advantage of opportunities to maximize the impact of indigenous natural enemies to eliminate immature mosquitoes. The EPA and CDC encourage the use of these practices wherever they are environmentally sound, effective, and reduce pesticide use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;ipm&quot; id=&quot;ipm&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Integrated Pest Management&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mosquito control activities are important to the public health, and responsibility for carrying out these programs rests with state and local governments. The federal government assists states in emergencies and provides training and consultation in vector and vector-borne disease problems when requested by the states. The current interests in ecology and environmental impact of mosquito control measures, and the increasing problems that have resulted from insecticide resistance emphasize the need for &quot;integrated&quot; control programs. EPA and CDC encourage maximum adherence to &lt;em&gt;integrated pest management&lt;/em&gt; (IPM). IPM is an ecologically based strategy that relies heavily on natural mortality factors and seeks out control tactics that are compatible with or disrupt these factors as little as possible. IPM uses pesticides, but only after systematic monitoring of pest populations indicates a need. Ideally, an IPM program considers all available control actions, including no action, and evaluates the interaction among various control practices, cultural practices, weather, and habitat structure. This approach thus uses a combination of resource management techniques to control mosquito populations with decisions based on surveillance. Fish and game specialists and natural resources biologists should be involved in planning control measures whenever delicate ecosystems could be impacted by mosquito control practices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The underlying philosophy of mosquito control is based on the fact that the greatest control impact on mosquito populations will occur when they are &lt;em&gt;concentrated, immobile&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;accessible&lt;/em&gt;. This emphasis focuses on habitat management and controlling the immature stages before the mosquitoes emerge as adults. This policy reduces the need for widespread pesticide application in urban areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA and CDC recommend that professional mosquito control organizations throughout the U.S. continue to use IPM strategies. Both agencies recognize a legitimate and compelling need for the prudent use of space sprays, under certain circumstances, to control adult mosquitoes. This is especially true during periods of mosquito-borne disease transmission or when source reduction and larval control have failed or are not feasible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;education&quot; id=&quot;education&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Education&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be of maximum effectiveness, the people, for whom protection is provided, must understand and support mosquito control. An integral part of most organized mosquito control programs is public education. It is important that residents have a good understanding of mosquitoes, the benefits realized from their control and the role people have in preventing certain mosquito-borne diseases. Being aware of pesticide application times is also important for individuals so they may decide on precautions they may need to take. While this usually involves education of the public through announcements in the media, some control programs have staffs that develop and present educational programs in public schools. People who are informed about mosquito biology and controls are more likely to mosquito-proof their homes, and eliminate mosquito breeding places on their own property.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;info&quot; id=&quot;info&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;For More Information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information about mosquito control in your area, contact your state or local health department. The Centers for Disease Control and Prevention is a source of information on disease control, and their Internet web site includes a listing of state health departments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To contact the &lt;em&gt;Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC)&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	Telephone: 970-221-6400&lt;br /&gt;
	Fax: 970-221-6476&lt;br /&gt;
	E-mail: &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:dvbid@cdc.gov&quot;&gt;dvbid@cdc.gov&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	web site: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cdc.gov&quot;&gt;http://www.cdc.gov&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Information on pesticides used in mosquito control can be obtained from the state agency which regulates pesticides, or from the &lt;em&gt;National Pesticide Information Center (NPIC)&lt;/em&gt; West Nile Resource Guide &lt;a href=&quot;http://npic.orst.edu/pest/mosquito/wnv.html&quot;&gt;http://npic.orst.edu/pest/mosquito/wnv.html&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;National Pesticide Information Center&lt;br /&gt;
	1-800-858-7378 - daily except holidays. Callers outside normal hours can leave a voice mail message.&lt;br /&gt;
	E-mail: &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:npic@ace.orst.edu&quot;&gt;npic@ace.orst.edu&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	Web site: &lt;a href=&quot;http://npic.orst.edu/&quot;&gt;http://npic.orst.edu/&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Information on mosquito control programs can also be obtained from the &lt;em&gt;American Mosquito Control Association (AMCA)&lt;/em&gt; web site: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mosquito.org&quot;&gt;http://www.mosquito.org&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span&gt;This site also lists many county mosquito agencies.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information regarding the federal pesticide regulatory programs, contact:&lt;br /&gt;
	EPA &lt;em&gt;Office of Pesticide Programs&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://publicaccess.zendesk.com/hc/en-us/sections/202364868-Pesticides&quot;&gt;Ask a question&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	Website: &lt;a href=&quot;/pesticides&quot;&gt;http://www.epa.gov/pesticides&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 25 Jul 2013 13:09:54 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>morganic</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">37313 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  </channel>
</rss>

<!-- Page cached by Boost @ 2017-01-26 11:48:00, expires @ 2017-01-27 11:48:00, lifetime 1 day -->