<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?><rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.epa.gov/feed/109295/rss.xml" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/" xmlns:og="http://ogp.me/ns#" xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#" xmlns:sioc="http://rdfs.org/sioc/ns#" xmlns:sioct="http://rdfs.org/sioc/types#" xmlns:skos="http://www.w3.org/2004/02/skos/core#" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#">
  <channel>
    <title>Corrective Action Sites around the Nation</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/feed/109295/rss.xml</link>
    <description>Updated Corrective Action Sites around the Nation content from the US Environmental Protection Agency</description>
    <language>en</language>
     <atom:link href="https://www.epa.gov/feed/109295/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      <item>
    <title>Documents, Reports and Photographs of Former Chevron USA Products Company #122208 in Chillum, Maryland</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/hwcorrectiveactionsites/documents-reports-and-photographs-former-chevron-usa-products-company-122208</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt; Some of Chevron&#039;s key Resource Conservation and Recovery Act (RCRA) corrective action documents, reports and photographs are accessible online:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-344957&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2017-01/documents/epa_aoc_and_comments_for_chillum_chevron.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=540367&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;EPA Administrative Order on Consent for Chevron in Chillum Maryland (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(18 pp, 540 K)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;field field-name-field-document-description field-type-text field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    Administrative Order on Consent   &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-344979&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2017-01/documents/epa_fdrtc_for_chillum_volume1_of_2.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=652298&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Corrective Action Final Decision &amp;amp; Response to Comments Volume 1  Former Chevron USA Products Company # 122208 in Chillum, Maryland (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(44 pp, 652 K)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;field field-name-field-document-description field-type-text field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    RCRA Final Decision and Reponse to Comments   &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-344983&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2017-01/documents/epa_fdrtc_for_chillum_volume_2_of_2.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=7981563&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Corrective Action Final Decision &amp;amp; Response to Comments Volume 2 for  Former Chevron USA Products Company # 122208 in Chillum, Maryland (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(83 pp, 8 MB)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;field field-name-field-document-description field-type-text field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    Corrective Action Final Decision and Response to Comments  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-344985&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2017-01/documents/epa_statement_of_basis_for_chillum.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=1343693&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Corrective Action Statement of Basis for  RCRA Corrective Actio nStatement of Basis for Former Chevron USA Products Company # 122208 in Chillum, Maryland (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(23 pp, 1 MB)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;field field-name-field-document-description field-type-text field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    Statement of Basis for RCRA Corrective Action   &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-344987&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2017-01/documents/chillum_fact_sheet_03-10-11-final.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=228273&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Corrective Action Factsheet for  EPA Corrective Action Factsheet for Former Chevron USA Products Company # 122208 in Chillum, Maryland March 2011 (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(2 pp, 228 K, 
  3/1/2011)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;field field-name-field-document-description field-type-text field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    RCRA Corrective Action Factsheet   &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-344991&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2017-01/documents/chillum_factsheet_may_2008.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=173630&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;RCRA Corrective Action Factsheet for  EPA Corrective Action Factsheet for Former Chevron USA Products Company # 122208 in Chillum, Maryland ,May 2008 (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(2 pp, 174 K, 
  5/1/2008)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;field field-name-field-document-description field-type-text field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    RCRA Corrective Action Factsheet   &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-344997&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2017-01/documents/chillum_riggs_standardscomparison-_01-09_final.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=144372&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;ATDSR Indoor Air Quality Comparison Charts for Former Chevron USA Products Company # 122208 in Chillum, Maryland March 2011 (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(2 pp, 144 K)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;field field-name-field-document-description field-type-text field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    ATDSR Indoor Air Quality Comparison Charts  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-345007&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2017-01/documents/chillum_letter_from_health_consultant_perc_site_11-3-2009.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=25800&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;ATDSR Risk Review for Former Chevron USA Products Company # 122208 in Chillum, Maryland March 2011 (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(6 pp, 26 K, 
  11/3/2009)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;field field-name-field-document-description field-type-text field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    ADTSR Risk Review  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jan 2017 19:29:21 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>dforman</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">168763 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Hazardous Waste Cleanup: Former Chevron USA Products Company #122208 in Chillum, Maryland</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/hwcorrectiveactionsites/hazardous-waste-cleanup-former-chevron-usa-products-company-122208-chillum</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On this page:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Status&quot;&gt;Cleanup Status&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Description&quot;&gt;Site Description&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Contaminants&quot;&gt;Contaminants at this Facility&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Controls&quot;&gt;Institutional/Engineer Controls&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Reuse&quot;&gt;Land Reuse&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Responsibility&quot;&gt;Site Responsibility&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;box multi related-info right&quot;&gt;
	&lt;h2 class=&quot;pane-title&quot;&gt;Site Facts&lt;/h2&gt;

	&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;EPA ID: &lt;/strong&gt;MD0000052803&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Location&lt;/strong&gt;: 5801 Riggs Road&lt;br /&gt;
			Chillum, MD 20783&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Property Area&lt;/strong&gt;: 212 Acre&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Other Names:&lt;/strong&gt; N/A&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cleanup Status:&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;span&gt;Complete With Controls&lt;/span&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Human Exposures under Control:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/hwcorrectiveactionsites/documents-reports-and-photographs-former-chevron-usa-products-company-122208&quot;&gt;Yes, Controlled&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Groundwater under Control: &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/hwcorrectiveactionsites/documents-reports-and-photographs-former-chevron-usa-products-company-122208&quot;&gt;Yes, Controlled&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Last Update&lt;/strong&gt;:  March 2011&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;



&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;Status&quot; name=&quot;Status&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Cleanup Status&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The U.S. Environmental Protection Agency has issued its final decision describing the remedy for a gasoline release that occurred at a former Chevron service station located at 5801 Riggs Road, Chillum, Md., which impacted the adjacent community in the Washington D.C. neighborhood known as Lamond-Riggs Park. The gasoline release occurred in 1989 and reportedly migrated underground to the residential neighborhood in 2001.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	EPA&#039;s final decision includes key ideas from our proposed plan presented to the community last fall. The EPA also modified the cleanup plans to be even more protective in response to significant comments from the community and D.C. environmental agencies.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA&#039;s final decision for the Chevron cleanup includes three components that were included in the Statement of Basis that was presented to the community in fall 2007: &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	(1) Continued operation of the existing groundwater remediation system in Maryland;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	(2) Expansion of the existing system by installing angle recovery wells under Eastern Avenue into the District. The additional wells will enhance cleanup of contaminated ground water resulting from the Chevron release. The drinking water for the area comes from a public water supply. As such, there is no known risk to the drinking water from the underground contamination;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	(3) Installation of individual vapor mitigation systems in those homes located above the contaminated groundwater plume with measured vapor levels that exceed EPA’s remediation standards for indoor air established in the Statement of Basis.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	In response to comments, EPA has strengthened its plan by adding:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	(1) Installation of an independent remediation system on the District-side of Eastern Avenue which uses an innovative recovery well design combining soil vapor extraction, recirculation groundwater pumping, and air sparging. Treatment takes place inside a large diameter well underground, minimizing both space requirements and disruption to the community. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	(2) Installation of an oxygen curtain above Nicholson Street to speed the natural degradation of the groundwater plume.  The area above Nicholson Street has a low oxygen level and injecting oxygen will accelerate the natural degradation of dissolved petroleum constituents. The oxygen curtain is a non-mechanical system operated by pressure. It requires little space and will generate minimal noise, so it should not be disruptive to the community except during construction. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	Implementation of EPA’s final decision will begin after EPA issues Chevron an implementation order which is a legally binding agreement. EPA will attend a future community forum to outline its final decision and to discuss the next steps in the cleanup process.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cleanup Background &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In October 1989, there was a reported release of an unknown amount of gasoline from a Service Station owned and operated by Chevron Products Company, located at 5801 Riggs Road in Chillum, Maryland. The release was initially addressed by the Maryland Department of the Environment(MDE).  MDE required Chevron to install a pump and treat system which has been in operation since 1990. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In April 2001, the gasoline plume was reported to have migrated into the District of Columbia, underlying a residential area known as the Lamond-Riggs Park community. Subsequent investigation also discovered that Perchloroethylene (PERC), a dry cleaner solvent, was present in groundwater at elevated  concentrations, which led to EPA&#039;s involvement. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In October 2001, EPA assumed responsibility for the gasoline release investigation and on November 26, 2002, EPA issued a Unilateral Order to Chevron for a site investigation.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the summer of 2002, as a result of the Site Investigation, perchlorethylene (PERC) was discovered in the gasoline plume. Since PERC is not a contaminant associated with gasoline, but rather is commonly associated with dry cleaning activities, EPA determined that PERC is not a Facility related contaminant. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On November 26, 2002 the United States Environmental Protection Agency issued an Unilateral Order pursuant to the authority of the Resource Conservation and Recovery Act (RCRA) Section 7003 &quot;Imminent and Substantial Endangerment to Health or the Environment&quot; to Chevron U.S.A., Inc. (Chevron) for investigation and remedy development for the release of petroleum related constituents from the former Chevron Gasoline Service Station No. 122208, located at 5801 Riggs Road, Chillum, Maryland. The Order was effective on December 11, 2002.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As required by the Order, Chevron collected soil, soil vapor, indoor air and groundwater samples, and has conducted pilot tests to upgrade the existing groundwater remediation system. Between 2001 and 2007, Chevron installed 232 temporary Geoprobe wells, 80 groundwater monitoring wells, 7 product recovery wells, and 4 soil vapor monitoring wells. Cumulatively, during the same period, Chevron has collected over 3000 groundwater samples, 300 soil samples, 250 soil vapor samples from 90 properties, 50 indoor and ambient air samples from 20 properties, and 14 basement sump samples. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Between 2002 and 2005, EPA collected indoor air samples from 32 properties and installed 24 soil vapor wells for its PERC investigation; and the U.S. Army Corps of Engineer (ACE), on behalf of EPA,  reviewed data from over half the properties sampled by Chevron. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on soil, soil vapor, indoor air and groundwater data collected through September 2005, EPA has delineated a shallow benzene plume and a shallow methyl tertiarybutyl ether (MTBE) plume. The shallow benzene plume extended approximately 700 feet from the Facility into the District of Columbia, and the shallow MTBE plume is about twice as long, extending about 1400 feet from the Facility into the District of Columbia. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On August 30, 2007, the United States Environmental Protection Agency announced its proposed remedy for the cleanup of the former Chevron gas station (refer to : &quot;&lt;a href=&quot;/hwcorrectiveactionsites/documents-reports-and-photographs-former-chevron-usa-products-company-122208&quot;&gt;Reports, Documents and Photographs : &lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/hwcorrectiveactionsites/documents-reports-and-photographs-former-chevron-usa-products-company-122208&quot;&gt;Corrective Action Statement of Basis&quot;)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The April 16, 2008  the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency has issued its final decision describing the remedy for a gasoline release that occurred at a former (refer to:  &quot; &lt;a href=&quot;/hwcorrectiveactionsites/documents-reports-and-photographs-former-chevron-usa-products-company-122208&quot;&gt;Reports, Documents and Photographs :&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/hwcorrectiveactionsites/documents-reports-and-photographs-former-chevron-usa-products-company-122208&quot;&gt;  Corrective Action Final Decision&quot;&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/em&gt;.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On August 25, 2008, U.S. Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) issued a proposed Administrative Order on Consent (AOC) entered into between EPA and Chevron U.S.A. Inc. (Chevron) to clean up releases at or from the former Chevron gasoline service station and requested public comments on the AOC. (refer to:  &quot; &lt;a href=&quot;/hwcorrectiveactionsites/documents-reports-and-photographs-former-chevron-usa-products-company-122208&quot;&gt;Reports, Documents and Photographs:  &lt;em&gt;EPA&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Administrative Order on Consent&quot;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;).   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Administrative Order on Consent (AOC) to implement the final remedy became effective as on or about January 19, 2009. During the public comment period, EPA received five sets of comments. EPA has responded to those comments and determined that no modifications to the AOC is necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;Description&quot; name=&quot;Description&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Site Description&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;box multi related-info right clear-right&quot;&gt;
	&lt;h2 class=&quot;pane-title&quot;&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;Reports&quot; name=&quot;Reports&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Additional Site Information&lt;/h2&gt;

	&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/hwcorrectiveactionsites/contact-information-corrective-action-hazardous-waste-clean-ups-delaware&quot;&gt;Contacts for this Clean Up&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/hwcorrectiveactionsites/documents-reports-and-photographs-former-chevron-usa-products-company-122208&quot;&gt;Documents, Reports and Photographs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;More Information from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://iaspub.epa.gov/enviro/fii_query_dtl.disp_program_facility?p_registry_id=110009024643&quot;&gt;Envirofacts database&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Facility is located at the eastern corner of the intersection of Eastern Avenue and Riggs Road in Chillum, Maryland (also known as Hyattsville Maryland).  The north side of the rightofway of Eastern Avenue delineates the boundary between Prince George’s County, Maryland and the District of Columbia. The southern extent of the Facility property abuts the District. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gulf Oil Corporation (Gulf) constructed a service station on the Facility property on or about 1954. Standard Oil Company of California merged with Gulf in 1984, and after restructuring, changed its name to Chevron. Chevron owned and operated the Facility until it was sold to an independent owner in 1993.  The Facility is currently a Sunoco Service Station.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;Contaminants&quot; name=&quot;Contaminants&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Contaminants at this Facility&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The contaminant of primary concern were benzene plume and a shallow methyl tertiarybutyl ether (MTBE) plume. Also Perchloroethylene (PERC), a dry cleaner solvent,  was present in groundwater (which did not come from The Facility).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;Controls&quot; name=&quot;Controls&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Institutional and Engineering Controls at this Facility&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The facility remedy, as stated in the &quot;Cleanup Status&quot; Section, includes groundwater remediation systems in Maryland and the District of Columbia plus a vapor mitigation system &lt;span lang=&quot;EN&quot; xml:lang=&quot;EN&quot;&gt;in those homes located above the contaminated groundwater plume with measured vapor levels that exceed EPA’s remediation &lt;/span&gt;standards for indoor air.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;  &lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;Reuse&quot; name=&quot;Reuse&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Land Reuse Information at this Facility&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The facility is under continued use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;Responsibility&quot; name=&quot;Responsibility&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Site Responsiblity at this Facility&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Resource Conservation and Recovery Act (RCRA) Corrective Action activities at this facility are conducted under the direction of the EPA Region 3 with assistance from Maryland DEP and DIstrict of Columbia DEP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jan 2017 18:07:34 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>gpatay</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">168735 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Documents, Reports and Photographs about Saint Helena Manufacturing (Former Millennium Specialty Chemicals) in Baltimore, Maryland</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/hwcorrectiveactionsites/documents-reports-and-photographs-about-saint-helena-manufacturing-former</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt; Some of Saint Helena Manufacturing (Former Millennium Specialty Chemicals) Resource Conservation and Recovery Act (RCRA) corrective action documents and reports are accessible online:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-337019&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-12/documents/hh_mdd003093507.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=1028468&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Environmental Indicator Human Exposure for Saint Helena Manufacturing (Former Millennium Specialty Chemicals) in Baltimore, Maryland (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(6 pp, 1 MB)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;field field-name-field-document-description field-type-text field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    RCRA Environmental Indicator - Current Human Exposures under Control  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 07 Dec 2016 15:28:04 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>gpatay</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">166569 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Documents, Reports and Photographs for Fisher Scientific Company in Indiana, Pennsylvania</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/hwcorrectiveactionsites/documents-reports-and-photographs-fisher-scientific-company-indiana</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt; Some of Fisher Scientific Company&#039;s Resource Conservation and Recovery Act (RCRA) corrective action documents, reports and photographs are accessible online:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-323141&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-10/documents/hh_pad004321527.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=2363636&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Environmental Indicator Human Exposure for Fisher Scientific Company in Indiana, Pennsylvania (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(12 pp, 2 MB)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;field field-name-field-document-description field-type-text field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    RCRA Environmental Indicator - Current Human Exposures under Control  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-323143&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-10/documents/gw_pad004321527.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=1992735&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Environmental Indicator Groundwater for Fisher Scientific Company in Indiana, Pennsylvania (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(12 pp, 2 MB)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;field field-name-field-document-description field-type-text field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    RCRA Environmental Indicator - Migration of Contaminated Groundwater under Control  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 12 Oct 2016 19:05:59 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>dforman</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">162497 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Documents, Reports and Photographs for Dana Automotive Systems Group LLC in Reading, Pennsylvania</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/hwcorrectiveactionsites/documents-reports-and-photographs-dana-automotive-systems-group-llc-reading</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt; Some of Dana Automotive Systems Group&#039;s Resource Conservation and Recovery Act (RCRA) corrective action documents, reports and photographs are accessible online:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-323127&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-10/documents/hh_pad002343630.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=1200882&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Environmental Indicator Human Exposure for Dana Automotive Systems Group LLC in Reading, Pennsylvania (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(8 pp, 1 MB)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;field field-name-field-document-description field-type-text field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    RCRA Environmental Indicator - Current Human Exposures under Control  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-323129&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-10/documents/gw_pad002343630.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=1322441&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Environmental Indicator Groundwater for Dana Automotive Systems Group LLC in Reading, Pennsylvania (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(10 pp, 1 MB)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;field field-name-field-document-description field-type-text field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    RCRA Environmental Indicator - Migration of Contaminated Groundwater under Control  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 12 Oct 2016 18:49:01 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>dforman</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">162493 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Documents, Reports and Photographs for Lockheed Martin Information Systems and Global Systems in King of Prussia, Pennsylvania</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/hwcorrectiveactionsites/documents-reports-and-photographs-lockheed-martin-information-systems-and</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt; Some of Lockheed Martin Information Systems and Global Systems&#039; Resource Conservation and Recovery Act (RCRA) corrective action documents, reports and photographs are accessible online:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-322243&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-10/documents/hh_pad001680719.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=1054734&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Environmental Indicator Human Exposure for Lockheed Martin Information Systems and Global Systems in King of Prussia, Pennsylvania (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(6 pp, 1 MB)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;field field-name-field-document-description field-type-text field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    RCRA Environmental Indicator - Current Human Exposures under Control  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Fri, 07 Oct 2016 17:21:43 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>dforman</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">162283 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Documents, Reports and Photographs for GE Betz Incorporated (Formerly: GE Water and Process Technologies) in Trevose, Pennsylvania</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/hwcorrectiveactionsites/documents-reports-and-photographs-ge-betz-incorporated-formerly-ge-water-and</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt; Some of GE Betz Incorporated&#039;s corrective action documents, reports and photographs are accessible online:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-321461&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-10/documents/hh_pad009722265.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=1116776&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Environmental Indicator Human Exposure for GE Betz Incorporated (Formerly: GE Water and Process Technologies) in Trevose, Pennsylvania (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(8 pp, 1 MB)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;field field-name-field-document-description field-type-text field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    RCRA Environmental Indicator - Current Human Exposures under Control  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 05 Oct 2016 18:17:20 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>dforman</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">162029 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Documents, Reports and Photographs of Omnova Solutions Incorporated in Jeannette, Pennsylvania</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/hwcorrectiveactionsites/documents-reports-and-photographs-omnova-solutions-incorporated-jeannette</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt; Some of Omnova Solutions Incorporated&#039;s key Resource Conservation and Recovery Act (RCRA) corrective action documents and reports are accessible online:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-316385&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-09/documents/omnovasolutionsinc_sb_0.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=158391&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Corrective Action Statement of Basis for Omnova Solutions Incorporated in Jeannette, Pennsylvania (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(6 pp, 158 K)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;field field-name-field-document-description field-type-text field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    Statement of Basis for RCRA Corrective Action Remedy  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-316387&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-09/documents/hh_pad004338000.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=1200493&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Environmental Indicator Human Exposure for Omnova Solutions Incorporated in Jeannette, Pennsylvania  (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(6 pp, 1 MB)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;field field-name-field-document-description field-type-text field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    RCRA Environmental Indicator - Current Human Exposures under Control  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-316389&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-09/documents/gw_pad004338000.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=1275815&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Environmental Indicator Groundwater for  Omnova Solutions Incorporated in Jeannette, Pennsylvania (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(8 pp, 1 MB)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;field field-name-field-document-description field-type-text field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    RCRA Environmental Indicator - Migration of Contaminated Groundwater under Control  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Mon, 19 Sep 2016 18:21:23 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>gpatay</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">160663 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Documents, Reports and Photographs of  Eastman Specialties Corporation in Chestertown, Maryland</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/hwcorrectiveactionsites/documents-reports-and-photographs-eastman-specialties-corporation</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt; Some of Eastman Specialties Corporation&#039;s key Resource Conservation and Recovery Act (RCRA) corrective action documents and reports are accessible online:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-316377&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-09/documents/hh_mdd001890060.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=1613748&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Environmental Indicator Human Exposure for Eastman Specialties Corporation in Chestertown, Maryland (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(8 pp, 2 MB)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;field field-name-field-document-description field-type-text field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    RCRA Environmental Indicator - Current Human Exposures under Control  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-316379&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-09/documents/gw_mdd001890060.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=1502613&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Environmental Indicator Groundwater for Eastman Specialties Corporation in Chestertown, Maryland (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(23 pp, 2 MB)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;field field-name-field-document-description field-type-text field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    RCRA Environmental Indicator - Migration of Contaminated Groundwater under Control  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Mon, 19 Sep 2016 17:58:36 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>gpatay</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">160659 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  </channel>
</rss>

<!-- Page cached by Boost @ 2017-01-25 17:05:12, expires @ 2017-01-26 05:05:12, lifetime 12 hours -->