<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?><rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.epa.gov/feed/1361/rss.xml" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/" xmlns:og="http://ogp.me/ns#" xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#" xmlns:sioc="http://rdfs.org/sioc/ns#" xmlns:sioct="http://rdfs.org/sioc/types#" xmlns:skos="http://www.w3.org/2004/02/skos/core#" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#">
  <channel>
    <title>Green Chemistry</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/feed/1361/rss.xml</link>
    <description>Updated Green Chemistry content from the US Environmental Protection Agency</description>
    <language>en</language>
     <atom:link href="https://www.epa.gov/feed/1361/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      <item>
    <title>Presidential Green Chemistry Challenge: 2016 Academic Award</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/greenchemistry/presidential-green-chemistry-challenge-2016-academic-award</link>
    <description>&lt;h2&gt;Professor Paul J. Chirik of Princeton University&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;em&gt;Catalysis with Earth Abundant Transition Metals&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Discovered catalysts that don&#039;t use hard-to-obtain platinum to make silicones that are used in:
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;silicone rubber;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;tires;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;shampoos;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;furniture fibers;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;paper coatings; and&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;other consumer goods.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;This new class of catalysts could reduce the mining of many tons of ore which reduces costs and:
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;energy usage by 85 billion BTUs per year;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;waste generation by 8.5 million kilograms per year; and&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;carbon generation by 21.7 million kilograms per year.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Summary of Technology: &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Metal-catalyzed chemical reactions have enabled many of the technological innovations of modern society with applications ranging from the synthesis of advanced materials to new medicines. For decades, catalyst technology has relied on some of the least abundant elements in the Earth’s crust – palladium, platinum, rhodium, and iridium. In addition to their high cost, price volatility, and toxicity, extraction of these elements has significant environmental consequences. Obtaining one ounce of a precious metal, for example, often requires mining approximately 10 tons of ore which creates a CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; footprint that is estimated to be 6,000 times that of abundant metals such as iron.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Alkene hydrosilylation is an example of a metal-catalyzed chemical reaction that is used on an industrial scale in the manufacture of silicones from alkenes and silanes. Silicones are found in a range of consumer products including adhesives, household utensils, medical devices, health care products, and low rolling resistance tires. The platinum catalyst used in alkene hydrosilylation reactions is often not recovered, however, which results in a significant environmental footprint for this commercially important process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Professor Chirik and his research group, in collaboration with Momentive Performance Materials, discovered a new class of hydrosilylation catalysts based on earth-abundant transition metals such as iron and cobalt that have superior performance to existing platinum catalysts. This base metal catalyst technology offers the opportunity to enable new chemical processes that provide the desired product exclusively, eliminate distillation steps, and avoid generation of byproducts and unnecessary waste. This technology is based upon “metal-ligand cooperativity,” a broad catalysis concept pioneered by the Chirik group, where electron changes occur concomitantly between the metal and the supporting ligand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hydrosilylations to produce various commercial silicone products have been conducted on multi-gram scales using this new technology. The discovery of these air-stable, readily-synthesized iron and cobalt catalysts with unprecedented activity and selectivity may ultimately transform the industrial approach to commercial silicone products.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;p id=&quot;resources&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Other resources:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/greenchemistry&quot;&gt;Learn more about green chemistry&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://chemists.princeton.edu/chirik/&quot;&gt;Learn more about Professor Paul J. Chirik and his research&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.princeton.edu/main/news/newsmedia/releases/&quot;&gt;Read the press release from Princeton University&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;/greenchemistry/presidential-green-chemistry-challenge-disclaimer-note&quot;&gt;Disclaimer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/greenchemistry/presidential-green-chemistry-challenge-winners&quot;&gt;Return to the list of all winners including the 2016 Award Winners. &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jun 2016 14:36:50 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>bdrake</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">151381 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Presidential Green Chemistry Challenge: 2016 Designing Greener Chemicals and Specific Environmental Benefit: Climate Change Awards</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/greenchemistry/presidential-green-chemistry-challenge-2016-designing-greener-chemicals-and-specific</link>
    <description>&lt;h2&gt;Newlight Technologies&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;em&gt;AirCarbon: Greenhouse Gas Transformed into High-Performance Thermoplastic&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Developed a low-cost plastic made from methane-based greenhouse gas that is used to make:
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;bags;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;cell phone cases;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;containers;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;furniture; and&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;other products.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;The new plastic is:
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;net carbon negative; and&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;has equal or better performance than petroleum-based plastic products.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Summary of Technology: &lt;/strong&gt;Methane is emitted by natural sources such as wetlands. It is also the second most prevalent greenhouse gas emitted in the U.S. from human activities, such as leakage from natural gas systems and the raising of livestock. Methane&#039;s lifetime in the atmosphere is much shorter than carbon dioxide, but methane is more efficient at trapping radiation. Pound for pound, the comparative impact of methane on climate change is more than 25 times greater than carbon dioxide over a 100-year period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Newlight Technologies developed and commercialized a carbon capture technology that combines methane with air to produce AirCarbon™, a high-performance thermoplastic material that matches the performance of a wide range of petroleum-based plastics while out-competing on price. Newlight’s biocatalyst combines air and methane-based carbon to produce polymers at environmentally friendly, ambient conditions. Despite the conceptual simplicity, previous technologies utilizing carbon capture to manufacture plastics resulted in production costs that were significantly higher than petroleum-based manufacture of plastics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To overcome this long-standing cost challenge, Newlight developed a biocatalyst that does not “turn itself off” based on the amount of polymer being produced. To do this, Newlight developed a process to disable the negative feedback receptors on polyhydroxyalkanoate polymerase, the central polymer production enzyme in the biocatalyst. As a result, the biocatalyst is able to continue to polymerize significantly beyond previous maximum limits and generate a yield of nine kilograms of polymer for every one kilogram of biocatalyst (9:1) – nine times more material compared to previous technologies. Newlight’s AirCarbon™ technology also reduces unit operations by a factor of three and capital cost by a factor of five, resulting in a net operating cost that enables AirCarbon™ to be cost and performance advantageous compared to petrochemical incumbents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within 24 months of scaling in 2013, AirCarbon™ was adopted by a range of leading companies including Dell, Hewlett-Packard, IKEA, KI, Sprint, The Body Shop, and Virgin to make packaging bags, containers, cell phone cases, furniture, and a range of other products. These products use a greenhouse gas in a carbon-negative process as a cost-effective replacement for petroleum-based plastics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;p id=&quot;resources&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Other resources:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/greenchemistry&quot;&gt;Learn more about green chemistry&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://newlight.com/&quot;&gt;Read the press release from Newlight Technologies&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;/greenchemistry/presidential-green-chemistry-challenge-disclaimer-note&quot;&gt;Disclaimer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/greenchemistry/presidential-green-chemistry-challenge-winners&quot;&gt;Return to the list of all winners including the 2016 Award Winners. &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 31 May 2016 18:46:43 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>bdrake</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">150759 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Presidential Green Chemistry Challenge: 2016 Small Business Award</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/greenchemistry/presidential-green-chemistry-challenge-2016-small-business-award</link>
    <description>&lt;h2&gt;Verdezyne&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;em&gt;Renewable Nylon Through Commercialization of BIOLON&lt;sup&gt;TM&lt;/sup&gt; DDDA&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Engineered a yeast to make a USDA Certified Biobased chemical that is used to make nylon 6,12 for:
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;paintbrushes;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;hairbrushes;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;toothbrushes;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;adhesives;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;coatings;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;fragrances; and&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;automotive and aviation oils.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;This new process:
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;uses a plant-based feedstock;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;has lower greenhouse gas emissions; and&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;is safer because it does not use high temperatures or concentrated nitric acid.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Summary of Technology: &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Verdezyne developed a yeast fermentation technology platform to provide manufacturers and consumers with renewable alternatives to existing petroleum-based chemical intermediates. This technology focuses on the production of dicarboxylic acid chemical intermediates such as adipic acid, sebacic acid and dodecanedioic acid (DDDA). The first of these to be commercialized will be BIOLON™ DDDA, which will be used primarily in the manufacture of nylon 6,12 for engineered plastics that require special properties such as high chemical, moisture, or abrasion resistance. Other uses for DDDA are in the manufacture of adhesives, coatings, corrosion inhibitors, lubricants, and fragrances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The current global demand for DDDA is estimated to be 100 million pounds per year. All DDDA currently on the market is produced from fossil-based sources, with the largest volume manufactured via trimerization of butadiene, followed by hydrogenation and oxidation with nitric acid. Verdezyne’s process for production of BIOLON™ DDDA uses fatty acid feedstocks sourced from the co-products of vegetable oil refining as the starting raw material. In addition to providing a renewable alternative, this process offers a higher level of manufacturing safety since high temperature and pressure and concentrated nitric acid are no longer needed. Moreover, Verdezyne’s process also results in reduced greenhouse gas emissions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Verdezyne’s production of BIOLON™ DDDA is an aerobic fermentation process integrated with downstream product isolation and crystallization. The fermentation converts the twelve carbon fatty acid, lauric acid, to DDDA through the activity of Verdezyne’s proprietary, genetically engineered &lt;em&gt;Candida&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;sp.&lt;/em&gt; yeast. The biochemical pathway involved is the three-step ω-oxidation pathway that sequentially oxidizes the terminal end of an alkane (or a fatty acid) to a carboxylic acid. Verdezyne scientists specifically engineered this yeast to enable rapid, high-yield production of DDDA while minimizing the accumulation of pathway intermediates that can be toxic to the organism and detrimental to final product purity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Verdezyne’s proprietary method for producing renewable BIOLON™ DDDA has been successfully demonstrated on a larger scale, enabling the production of over 70,000 pounds thus far. The product has met all industry quality specifications and has also earned the USDA Certified Biobased product label. The company’s first commercial production facility is scheduled to open in 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;p id=&quot;resources&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Other resources:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/greenchemistry&quot;&gt;Learn more about green chemistry&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://verdezyne.com/news/press-releases/&quot;&gt;Read the press release from Verdezyne&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;/greenchemistry/presidential-green-chemistry-challenge-disclaimer-note&quot;&gt;Disclaimer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/greenchemistry/presidential-green-chemistry-challenge-winners&quot;&gt;Return to the list of all winners including the 2016 Award Winners. &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 31 May 2016 15:23:29 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>bdrake</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">150711 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Presidential Green Chemistry Challenge: 2016 Greener Reaction Conditions Award</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/greenchemistry/presidential-green-chemistry-challenge-2016-greener-reaction-conditions-award</link>
    <description>&lt;h2&gt;Dow AgroSciences LLC&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;em&gt;Instinct® Technology - Making Nitrogen Fertilizers Work More Effectively for Farmers and the Planet&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Reduces fertilizer nitrate leaching to ground and surface waters and atmospheric nitrous oxide emissions.
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Nutrient pollution is one of America’s most widespread, costly and challenging environmental problems.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Retains applied nitrogen longer in the plants’ root zone, optimizing crop utilization and yield, and reducing nutrient run-off.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;In 2014 this new technology:
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;added about 50 million bushels of additional corn equating to over $205 million in additional production revenue for U.S. corn growers; and&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;reduced carbon dioxide emissions by about 664,000 metric tons.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Summary of Technology: &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The demand for higher crop yields and agricultural productivity is ever increasing, and so are concerns for the negative impacts on the environment caused by agricultural activities. Human activities related to farming account for a significant percentage of nitrate in ground and surface waters as well as nitrous oxide emissions. An estimated 75 percent of all nitrous oxide emissions, for example, come from agricultural activities such as applied nitrogen fertilizers and manures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Crop genetics and precision application methods have improved the efficiency of applied nitrogen fertilizers, but losses to the environment are still significant after soil bacteria quickly convert nitrogen from the applied urea or ammoniacal form to nitrate. In the nitrate form, nitrogen fertilizer is susceptible to losses through leaching or as emissions in the form of nitrous oxide. Furthermore, nitrate fertilizer that leaches out of a plant’s root zone is no longer available to provide nutrients to the crop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scientists at The Dow Chemical Company discovered a powerful nitrification inhibitor that can inhibit soil bacteria from rapidly converting nitrogen in the ammoniacal form to nitrate, thereby retaining more nitrogen in the more stable ammoniacal form. By keeping nitrogen in the root zone for a longer period during the season, Dow’s nitrogen stabilizers improve Nitrogen Use Efficiency and reduce nitrogen loss through leaching and nitrous oxide emissions. N-Serve&lt;sup&gt;®&lt;/sup&gt; was the first commercial product introduced by Dow in 1974, but it is only suitable for use with anhydrous ammonia fertilizer applications due to the limitations of its physical-chemical properties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2010, Dow AgroSciences launched a novel, aqueous microcapsule suspension product, Instinct&lt;sup&gt;®&lt;/sup&gt;. This patented technology can be conveniently used with other commonly used nitrogen fertilizer sources, enabling adoption of the product for multiple crops in the U.S. and around the world. As an aqueous suspension of a microencapsulated active ingredient, Instinct&lt;sup&gt;®&lt;/sup&gt;, also provides additional environmental benefit by significantly reducing the amount of petroleum-based solvents used per treated acre.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In less than five years, acres treated with stabilized nitrogen have grown more than five-fold. In 2014 alone, based on calculated adoption of Instinct&lt;sup&gt;®&lt;/sup&gt; in the U.S., it is estimated that use of the technology reduced carbon dioxide equivalent emissions by about 664,000 metric tons and increased U.S. corn production by about 50 million bushels, equating to about $205,500,000 additional production revenue for U.S. corn growers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;p id=&quot;resources&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Other resources:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/greenchemistry&quot;&gt;Learn more about green chemistry&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dowagro.com/en-us/newsroom/pressreleases/2016/06/2016-green-chemistry-award#.V18GM03fPm4&quot;&gt;Read the press release from Dow AgroSciences LLC&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;/greenchemistry/presidential-green-chemistry-challenge-disclaimer-note&quot;&gt;Disclaimer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/greenchemistry/presidential-green-chemistry-challenge-winners&quot;&gt;Return to the list of all winners including the 2016 Award Winners. &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 31 May 2016 14:56:50 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>bdrake</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">150701 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Presidential Green Chemistry Challenge: 2016 Greener Synthetic Pathways Award</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/greenchemistry/presidential-green-chemistry-challenge-2016-greener-synthetic-pathways-award</link>
    <description>&lt;h2&gt;CB&amp;amp;I&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Albemarle&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;em&gt;AlkyClean® Technology:  An Inherently Safer Technology for the Production of Gasoline Alkylate&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Developed and commercialized an inherently safer technology to produce alkylate, a clean gasoline component.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;Replaced the traditional toxic and corrosive liquid acid catalysts with an inherently safer technology that also has a lower environmental impact.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;

	&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Summary of Technology: &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

	&lt;p&gt;Alkylate is a highly valued “clean fuels” blending component for motor gasoline. It consists of clean-combusting isoparaffins that have low vapor pressures and high octane values. Alkylate also does not contain toxic components such as aromatics, olefins, or sulfur compounds. Alkylate is the preferred gasoline blending component for compliance with relevant environmental regulations.&lt;/p&gt;

	&lt;p&gt;Alkylate is produced from the reaction of isobutane and light olefins (C3-C5). Alkylate production is currently about 30 billion gallons/year worldwide, of which 60% is located in North America. A challenge facing refineries today is that alkylate production requires the use of liquid acid catalyzed processes, typically hydrofluoric acid or sulfuric acid. Hydrofluoric acid, in particular, is extremely toxic and, upon release, forms clouds that can be lethal for up to five miles.&lt;/p&gt;

	&lt;p&gt;For more than 40 years, scientists have been trying to replace liquid acid technologies with a greener solid acid catalyst technology. Prior approaches failed because of poor product selectivity and/or excessively rapid catalyst deactivation, coupled with the lack of an acceptable catalyst regeneration procedure. In some cases, these catalysts used leachable corrosive components such as halogens, triflic acid, and boron trifluoride, which could migrate into product streams.&lt;/p&gt;

	&lt;p&gt;Albemarle and CB&amp;amp;I developed a catalyst-process combination technology, the AlkyClean&lt;sup&gt;®&lt;/sup&gt; solid acid alkylation process, which coupled with CB&amp;amp;I’s novel reactor scheme, produces high quality alkylate without the use of liquid acid catalysts. Additionally, neither acid-soluble oils nor spent acids are produced, and there is no need for product post-treatment of any kind.&lt;/p&gt;

	&lt;p&gt;Albemarle’s AlkyStar&lt;sup&gt;TM&lt;/sup&gt; catalyst was designed for use exclusively with the AlkyClean&lt;sup&gt;®&lt;/sup&gt; alkylation process. It uses a type of zeolite catalyst that is well-proven in the industry. The strength and the number of acid sites on the catalyst have been optimized to enhance hydrogen transfer reactions over multiple alkylation reactions. The catalyst particle size and porosity were also optimized using a pilot plant and a demo unit that allowed the investigation of regeneration procedures as well.&lt;/p&gt;

	&lt;p&gt;The world’s first commercial-scale, solid catalyst alkylation unit was started up in August, 2015. The unit employs the AlkyClean&lt;sup&gt;®&lt;/sup&gt; technology and has a capacity of 2,700 BPD alkylate production. The plant has met or exceeded all performance expectations and is producing an alkylate product of quality that is on par with existing technologies.&lt;/p&gt;

	&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;p id=&quot;resources&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Other resources:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

	&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/greenchemistry&quot;&gt;Learn more about green chemistry&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.snl.com/IRWebLinkX/file.aspx?iid=4234612&amp;amp;fid=34735760&quot;&gt;Read the press release from CB&amp;amp;I&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://investors.albemarle.com/phoenix.zhtml?c=117031&amp;amp;p=irol-newsArticle&amp;amp;ID=2177374&quot;&gt;Read the press release from Albemarle&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;/greenchemistry/presidential-green-chemistry-challenge-disclaimer-note&quot;&gt;Disclaimer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

	&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/greenchemistry/presidential-green-chemistry-challenge-winners&quot;&gt;Return to the list of all winners including the 2016 Award Winners&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 31 May 2016 14:21:10 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>bdrake</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">150695 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Presidential Green Chemistry Challenge Awards Program: Nomination Package for 2017 Awards</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/greenchemistry/presidential-green-chemistry-challenge-awards-program-nomination-package-2017-awards</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;Download the Nomination Package for the 2017 Presidential Green Chemistry Challenge Awards Program. Nominations are due December 31, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-323799&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-10/documents/nomination_package_for_2017_awards-web.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=185016&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Presidential Green Chemistry Challenge Awards Program: Nomination Package for 2017 Awards (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(14 pp, 185 K, 
  744K16001)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 24 Sep 2015 18:44:51 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>bdrake</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">116899 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Presidential Green Chemistry Challenge: 2015 Specific Environmental Benefit: Climate Change Award</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/greenchemistry/presidential-green-chemistry-challenge-2015-specific-environmental-benefit-climate</link>
    <description>&lt;h2&gt;Algenol&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Algenol Biofuel Process: Sustainable Production of Ethanol and Green Crude&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg right view-mode-full caption&quot; style=&quot;width:400px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Algenol - 2015 Specific Environmental Benefit: Climate Change Award winner&quot; height=&quot;267&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; class=&quot;right media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2015-07/algenol-team.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;figcaption&quot;&gt;Jim Jones, Assistant Administrator of EPA’s Office of Chemical Safety and Pollution Prevention, with awardees from Algenol&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Innovation and Benefits:&lt;/strong&gt; Algenol in Fort Myers, Florida, is being recognized for developing a blue-green algae to produce ethanol and other fuels. The algae uses CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; from air or industrial emitters with sunlight and saltwater to create fuel while dramatically reducing the carbon footprint, costs and water usage, with no reliance on food crops as feedstocks. This is a win-win for the company, the public, and the environment. It has the potential to revolutionize this industry and reduce the carbon footprint of fuel production.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Summary of Technology: &lt;/strong&gt;Ethanol can be used as a transportation fuel directly or blended with gasoline. Algenol has developed technologies for the recombinant and classical genetic improvement of cyanobacteria (blue-green algae), leading to strains that divert more than 80% of the photosynthetically fixed carbon into ethanol without a decrease in overall photosynthetic yield. This has led to improved biofuel productivity, higher economic returns, minimal waste production, and a lower carbon footprint.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Algenol’s hybrid algae are grown in saltwater in proprietary photobioreactors (PBRs) which minimize heterotrophic contamination and reduce water use. Photosaturation is a common limiting feature in aquatic photosynthesis and occurs when the rate of photon absorption exceeds the rate that the algae can use the energy for product formation (i.e., carbon fixation), such that the energy of the excess photons is wasted through non-photosynthetic processes. Algenol’s vertical PBR system offers a productivity advantage over horizontal systems by delivering a more dilute irradiance over a greater surface area of the PBR, thereby limiting photosaturation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Algenol has also developed proprietary downstream processes for energy-efficient recovery of fuel-grade ethanol. In collaboration with Pacific Northwest National Laboratory (PNNL), Algenol has applied hydrothermal liquefaction technology to convert the spent biomass into green crude. Algenol is also working with PNNL, National Renewable Energy Laboratory, and Georgia Tech on development of higher-value green chemical production concepts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Algenol has demonstrated about 15–20 times the productivity of corn-based ethanol on a per acre basis. In the past five years, Algenol moved this technology from laboratory scale to pilot scale and is currently completing the construction and commissioning of a 2-acre facility as part of the IBR Project ($52 million project with a $25 million grant from the U.S. Department of Energy). The overall process reduces the carbon footprint relative to gasoline by 60–80% according to peer-reviewed published work from Georgia Tech. A single 2,000 acre commercial Algenol module is the equivalent of planting 40 million trees or removing 36,000 cars from the road. Broad deployment of this technology, with its low-carbon footprint, can contribute to CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; emission reduction targets and lower dependence on fossil fuel resources. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;p id=&quot;resources&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Other resources:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/green-chemistry&quot;&gt;Learn more about green chemistry&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://algenol.com/biofuelproducts/&quot;&gt;Read more from Algenol&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;/green-chemistry/disclaimer-note&quot;&gt;Disclaimer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/green-chemistry/presidential-green-chemistry-challenge-winners#2015&quot;&gt;Return to the list of all winners including the 2015 Award Winners. &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jul 2015 15:36:16 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>bdrake</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">95723 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Presidential Green Chemistry Challenge: 2015 Academic Award</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/greenchemistry/presidential-green-chemistry-challenge-2015-academic-award</link>
    <description>&lt;h2&gt;Professor Eugene Y.-X. Chen of Colorado State University&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;em&gt;Greener Condensation Reactions for Renewable Chemicals, Liquid Fuels, and Biodegradable Polymers&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg right view-mode-full caption&quot; style=&quot;width:400px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Professor Eugene Y.-X. Chen of Colorado State University - 2015 Academic Award winner&quot; height=&quot;267&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; class=&quot;right media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2015-07/chen-winner.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;figcaption&quot;&gt;Jim Jones, Assistant Administrator of EPA&#039;s Office of Chemical Safety and Pollution Prevention, with Professor Eugene Chen&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Innovation and Benefits:&lt;/strong&gt; Professor Eugene Chen of Colorado State University is being recognized for developing a process that uses plant-based materials in the production of renewable chemicals and liquid fuels.  This new technology is waste-free and metal-free. It offers significant potential for the production of renewable chemicals, fuels, and bioplastics that can be used in a wide range of safer industrial and consumer products.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Summary of Technology: &lt;/strong&gt;In condensation reactions, as two molecules combine to form a larger molecule, small molecules split off. Because of the loss of this small molecule, such as water, hydrogen chloride, ethylene, methanol, or acetic acid, these reactions are intrinsically waste-generating. Additionally, condensation reactions are often mediated by metals. For the production of jet or other transportation fuels, fine chemicals, and bioplastics, biomass platform chemicals, such as 5-hydroxymethylfurfural (HMF), need to be upgraded  through the C‒C bond forming, condensation reaction into chain-extended, higher energy-density substances, such as 5,5&#039;-dihydroxymethylfuroin (DHMF). The 12-carbon DHMF is a new bio-derived building block that can be catalytically transformed into renewable fine chemicals, polymeric materials, and oxygenated biodiesel or premium alkane jet fuels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Direct HMF coupling is not possible through aldol self-condensation of HMF because it lacks a necessary hydrogen atom in the α-position to the carbonyl group. Existing alternative methods, such as metal-mediated cross-aldol condensation, have to use other enolizable petrochemicals. These methods also suffer from the unavoidable waste inherent in conventional condensation reactions. Professor Chen and his graduate student Dajiang (DJ) Liu developed a new condensation technology that uses an organic catalyst, such as an &lt;em&gt;N&lt;/em&gt;-heterocyclic carbene (NHC), to reverse the polarity of the HMF carbonyl (umpolung), to enabling a solvent-free direct condensation coupling of HMF into DHMF with quantitative yield and 100% atom-economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Professor Chen and his postdoctoral fellow Dr. Miao Hong also developed a polycondensation method, called “Proton-Transfer Polymerization” (HTP), which uses an NHC catalyst to polymerize dimethacrylates uniquely into biodegradable polyesters with 100% atom-economy. The resulting unsaturated polyesters are of interest for producing tailor-made biodegradable polyester materials through post-functionalization and cross-linking. The synthesis of such polyesters from dimethacrylates is not possible by a metal-based process, such as the Ru or Mo-mediated acyclic diene metathesis, because such methods are ineffective for polymerization of electron-deficient, conjugated or sterically demanding diolefins such as dimethacrylates. In contrast, existing methods polymerize dimethacrylates through non-condensation, polyaddition pathways into non-biodegradable polymethacrylates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new condensation technology not only offers two novel condensation synthetic pathways towards the HMF upgrading and polyester production from acrylic monomers, both processes of which are not possible by any existing technologies, it also exhibits important hallmarks of a green technology by being catalytic, metal-free and 100% atom-economical as well as solvent-free (for the HMF upgrading) or biodegradable (for the polyester production). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;p id=&quot;resources&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Other resources:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/green-chemistry&quot;&gt;Learn more about green chemistry&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.chem.colostate.edu/people/eychen/&quot;&gt;Learn more about Professor Eugene Y.-X. Chen and his research&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.chem.colostate.edu/chen-awarded-2015-presidential-green-chemistry-challenge-award/&quot;&gt;Read the press release from Colorado State University&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;/green-chemistry/disclaimer-note&quot;&gt;Disclaimer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/green-chemistry/presidential-green-chemistry-challenge-winners#2015&quot;&gt;Return to the list of all winners including the 2015 Award Winners. &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jul 2015 15:30:58 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>bdrake</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">95719 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Presidential Green Chemistry Challenge: 2015 Small Business Award</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/greenchemistry/presidential-green-chemistry-challenge-2015-small-business-award</link>
    <description>&lt;h2&gt;Renmatix&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Plantrose® Process: Supercritical Water as the Economic Enabler of Biobased Industry&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg right view-mode-full caption&quot; style=&quot;width:400px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Renmatix - 2015 Small Business Award winners&quot; height=&quot;267&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; class=&quot;right media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2015-07/renmatix-team.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;figcaption&quot;&gt;Jim Jones, Assistant Administrator of EPA&#039;s Office of Chemical Safety and Pollution Prevention, with awardees from Renmatix&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Innovation and Benefits:&lt;/strong&gt; Renmatix in King of Prussia, Pennsylvania, is being recognized for developing a process using supercritical water to more cost effectively break down plant material into sugars used as building blocks for renewable chemicals and fuels. This innovative low-cost process could result in a sizeable increase in the production of plant-based chemicals and fuels, and reduce the dependence on petroleum fuels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Summary of Technology: &lt;/strong&gt;Traditional sugar sources, like corn and cane, are expensive feedstocks for producing relatively low value, high volume products like fuels and chemicals. Unfortunately, the traditional second generation technologies (acid, enzymes, and solvents) that were designed to extract these low value cellulosic sugars lack the practical economics to even compete with first generation sugars, let alone traditional petrochemical sources. In part, this is due to the capital expense of historical technologies like mineral acids and enzymatic processes that hydrolyze cellulosic feedstocks. This reality has severely limited the market adoption and broad integration of cellulosics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Renmatix’s Plantrose&lt;sup&gt;®&lt;/sup&gt; process, which uses supercritical water to deconstruct biomass, provides cost‐advantaged cellulosic sugars by using primarily water for conversion reactions. The two-step continuous process deconstructs a range of plant material into renewable feedstocks to produce separate streams of xylose and glucose. After sugar extraction, remaining lignin solids can be burned to supply the bulk of the heat energy required for the process (or utilized in higher-value applications like adhesives or thermoplastics).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the first step, biomass and water are pumped together, heated, and fed into a fractionation reactor, where the hemicellulose is solubilized into a five-carbon sugar stream. In the second step, the cellulose and lignin that were filtered away from the initial sugar steam are pumped into the supercritical hydrolysis reactor. In the reactor, water acts as both a solvent and catalyst, decrystalizing and dissolving the cellulose and hydrolyzing the cellulose polymers. The temperature and pressure of the supercritical water system can be adjusted for very specific reaction condition control, enabling the use of smaller continuous reactors for large-scale commercial production.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Renmatix’s technological innovation, the use of water-based chemistry instead of enzymes, and/or acids, provides a cleaner, faster, and lower-cost method for deconstructing biomass into cellulosic sugars. Those sugars become the building blocks for a multitude of renewable downstream technologies to serve significant biochemical market demand – and begin providing meaningful volumes of plantrochemicals, in lieu of the conventional petroleum-derived equivalents. Renmatix partners and customers will build their own biorefineries by licensing the Plantrose&lt;sup&gt;®&lt;/sup&gt; process to convert locally available biomass into cellulosic sugars, enabling profitable scale-up of biochemical, cellulosic ethanol, and advanced biofuels markets worldwide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;p id=&quot;resources&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Other resources:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/greenchemistry&quot;&gt;Learn more about green chemistry&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://renmatix.com/technology/plantrose-technology/plantrose-process&quot;&gt;Learn more about the Plantrose&lt;span style=&quot;vertical-align:baseline&quot;&gt;®&lt;/span&gt; process on Renmatix’s website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Note:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;/greenchemistry/disclaimer-note&quot;&gt;Disclaimer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/greenchemistry/presidential-green-chemistry-challenge-winners&quot;&gt;Return to the list of all winners including the 2015 Award Winners. &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jul 2015 15:26:03 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>bdrake</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">95709 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
