<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?><rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.epa.gov/feed/72445/rss.xml" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/" xmlns:og="http://ogp.me/ns#" xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#" xmlns:sioc="http://rdfs.org/sioc/ns#" xmlns:sioct="http://rdfs.org/sioc/types#" xmlns:skos="http://www.w3.org/2004/02/skos/core#" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#">
  <channel>
    <title>Climate and Energy Resources for State, Local and Tribal Governments</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/feed/72445/rss.xml</link>
    <description>Updated Climate and Energy Resources for State, Local and Tribal Governments content from the US Environmental Protection Agency</description>
    <language>en</language>
     <atom:link href="https://www.epa.gov/feed/72445/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      <item>
    <title>GRID Alternatives: Solar Programs in Underserved Communities</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/statelocalclimate/grid-alternatives-solar-programs-underserved-communities</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;The nonprofit GRID Alternatives partners with a variety of public, community, utility, and other organizations with a goal of helping low-income communities access the benefits of solar technology. Its model seeks to address common barriers to solar deployment in single-family, multifamily, and community solar settings, as well as to support solar job training for community members. As a result, thousands of low-income residents have been able to lower their energy costs and thousands more have received job training related to solar installations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-347665&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2017-01/documents/grid_alternatives_profile_508.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=802315&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;GRID Alternatives: Solar Programs for Underserved Communities (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(5 pp, 802 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 19 Jan 2017 20:05:20 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>xrrandha</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">169617 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>EM&amp;V for Energy Efficiency Policies and Initiatives</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/statelocalclimate/emv-energy-efficiency-policies-and-initiatives-0</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;Evaluation, measurement, and verification (EM&amp;amp;V) helps investments in demand-side energy efficiency (EE) achieve intended environmental, energy, and economic goals. This paper briefly describes the status of EE policies and initiatives, identifies the associated objectives, and provides discussion and examples of how EM&amp;amp;V is typically tailored to the objectives for that policy or strategy. It is intended as a primer for representatives of jurisdictions, companies, electricity planning organizations, and other entities that are using or considering using EE to achieve their goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-347593&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2017-01/documents/emvframeworkpaper_2017-01-19.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=880950&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;EM&amp;amp;V for Energy Efficiency Policies and Initiatives (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(5 pp, 881 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 19 Jan 2017 19:15:01 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>xrrandha</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">169587 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Elevate Energy: Energy Efficiency Services for Affordable Multifamily Buildings</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/statelocalclimate/elevate-energy-energy-efficiency-services-affordable-multifamily-buildings</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;This document profiles the Chicago-area non-profit Elevate Energy, which offers a full-service energy efficiency retrofit program for owners of and tenants in affordable multifamily buildings in eleven states.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-346605&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2017-01/documents/elevate_energy_profile_508.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=748866&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Elevate Energy: Energy Efficiency Services for Affordable Multifamily Buildings (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(5 pp, 749 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jan 2017 19:32:36 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>xrrandha</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">169293 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Duluth Flood Recovery Program</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/statelocalclimate/duluth-flood-recovery-program</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;This document serves as the program profile for the Duluth Flood Recovery Program. In the wake of a natural disaster, the City of Duluth, Minnesota, and its partners found a way to evolve an existing residential energy program to ensure that energy efficiency was part of rebuilding efforts, reducing greenhouse gas emissions and bringing economic benefits and healthier homes to low-income residents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-346599&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2017-01/documents/duluth_profile_508.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=775477&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Duluth Flood Recovery Program (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(5 pp, 775 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jan 2017 19:28:39 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>xrrandha</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">169289 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Duke Energy: Neighborhood Energy Saver Program</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/statelocalclimate/duke-energy-neighborhood-energy-saver-program</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;This document serves as a program profile for the Duke Energy Neighborhood Energy Saver Program. The Duke Energy Neighborhood Energy Saver Program uses a community approach to swiftly reduce energy bills for a large number of participants. By targeting low-income neighborhoods, working with local leaders to build neighborhood engagement and buy-in, and conducting energy assessments, energy-saving improvements, and participant education at no cost, the program is able to upgrade hundreds of homes in a cost- and time-efficient manner while reducing carbon pollution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-346593&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2017-01/documents/duke_energy_profile_508.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=647766&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Duke Energy Neighborhood Energy Saver Program (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(5 pp, 648 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jan 2017 19:24:56 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>xrrandha</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">169287 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>EM&amp;V for Energy Efficiency Policies and Initiatives</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/statelocalclimate/emv-energy-efficiency-policies-and-initiatives</link>
    <description>&lt;div id=&quot;tabs&quot;&gt;
	&lt;ul class=&quot;tabs vertical&quot; id=&quot;tabsnav&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;menu-internal&quot; href=&quot;#tab-1&quot;&gt;EM&amp;amp;V Home&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;menu-internal&quot; href=&quot;#tab-2&quot;&gt;EE Policies and Initiatives&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;menu-internal&quot; href=&quot;#tab-3&quot;&gt;EM&amp;amp;V Basics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;menu-internal&quot; href=&quot;#tab-4&quot;&gt;EM&amp;amp;V for EE Policies and Strategies&lt;/a&gt;
			&lt;ul class=&quot;menu-internal&quot;&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;menu-internal&quot; href=&quot;#tab-5&quot;&gt;Related Paper&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;div id=&quot;tab-1&quot;&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;State and local governments, businesses, and electricity system planners are using a range of energy efficiency (EE) policies and initiatives to lower electricity use while also achieving important objectives, such as:&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Saving money on electricity bills&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Decreasing stress on the electricity system&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Stimulating local economic development and new jobs&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Reducing air pollutants (e.g., NOx, SO2, PM) and greenhouse gases (GHGs)&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Comprehensive evaluation, measurement, and verification (EM&amp;amp;V) helps ensure these objectives are achieved. EM&amp;amp;V refers to the procedures, methods, and analytic approaches used to quantify and verify electricity savings from EE.&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;This web page and accompanying &lt;a href=&quot;/statelocalclimate/emv-energy-efficiency-policies-and-initiatives-0&quot;&gt;paper &lt;/a&gt;describe the status of EE policies and initiatives, identify associated EE objectives, and provide discussion and examples of how EM&amp;amp;V is typically tailored to those policies or initiatives.&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;This information is intended as a primer for representatives of jurisdictions, businesses, electricity planning organizations, and other entities that are using or considering using EE to achieve their goals.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;

	&lt;div id=&quot;tab-2&quot;&gt;
		&lt;h3&gt;Energy Efficiency Policies and Initiatives&lt;/h3&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;Every U.S. state currently administers some type of EE program, and more than &lt;a class=&quot;colorbox-inline&quot; href=&quot;#colorbox-hidden&quot;&gt;half of them have adopted statewide EE policies&lt;/a&gt; such as energy efficiency resource standards (EERS) and goals to achieve “all cost-effective EE.” These policies and goals are achieved through EE programs for homeowners, businesses, and other electricity customers.&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;div id=&quot;hidden-content&quot;&gt;
			&lt;div class=&quot;colorbox-hidden&quot; id=&quot;colorbox-hidden&quot;&gt;
				&lt;h3 id=&quot;dialog-title&quot;&gt;Energy Efficiency Resource Standards&lt;/h3&gt;
				&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-png view-mode-full caption&quot; style=&quot;width:709px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Energy Efficiency Resource Standards Map&quot; height=&quot;531&quot; width=&quot;709&quot; class=&quot;media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2017-01/eers_map.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;figcaption&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Energy Efficiency Resource Standards Map&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;

		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Nationally, ACEEE estimates that &lt;a href=&quot;http://aceee.org/sites/default/files/publications/researchreports/u1604.pdf&quot;&gt;customers are saving $90 billion annually&lt;/a&gt; on electricity bills from EE programs for a total of nearly $790 billion in cumulative savings since 1990&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;The Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory has identified &lt;a href=&quot;https://emp.lbl.gov/sites/all/files/lbnl-5803e.pdf&quot;&gt;additional untapped potential for EE programs&lt;/a&gt; in every state over the next 5, 10, and 15 years&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Many states and cities have also adopted initiatives to promote EE improvements in their own facilities (often via performance contracts with private companies) and may further adopt building energy codes and equipment standards that exceed federal minimum efficiency requirements.&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;In addition, two electricity transmission system operators—ISO New England (ISO-NE) and PJM Interconnection—have established forward capacity markets (FCMs) that compensate EE on par with power plant generation for purposes of meeting regional capacity requirements and ensuring system reliability.&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;Each of these EE policies and initiatives is helping states meet a range of &lt;a href=&quot;/statelocalclimate/determining-state-policy-and-program-impacts&quot;&gt;environmental, energy, and economic objectives&lt;/a&gt;. As the electricity savings from EE has grown in recent years, state and local governments, businesses, and electricity system planners are &lt;a href=&quot;/statelocalclimate/energy-and-environment-guide-action&quot;&gt;increasingly turning to EE&lt;/a&gt; as a strategy to achieve these diverse objectives.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;

	&lt;div id=&quot;tab-3&quot;&gt;
		&lt;h3&gt;EM&amp;amp;V Basics&lt;/h3&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;The procedures, methods, and analytic approaches used to quantify and verify EE savings is referred to as evaluation, measurement, and verification (EM&amp;amp;V). EM&amp;amp;V compares measured electricity usage with an EE project or EE measure in place with the best estimate of the likely energy usage in the absence of the project or measure (the “counterfactual” scenario or baseline). MWh of electricity savings are quantified relative to this counterfactual baseline.&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;Specifying the baseline for a particular EE activity is a key challenge with EM&amp;amp;V. If the condition prior to the installation of an EE project or EE measure were always the baseline, this determination would be relatively straightforward. However, most EE take place in a context of ongoing changes in markets, technology, policy, and operations. Specifying a baseline requires consideration of this context.&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;For example, when the EE activity is a new equipment installation that would happen regardless of the efficiency level, the baseline can be defined in terms of the new (less efficient) equipment that would otherwise be installed. When this new EE equipment installation happens in the context of other EE activities, such as in a market affected by building codes or equipment standards, these other EE activities must be considered in determining the baseline for the new equipment.&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-png center view-mode-medium caption&quot; style=&quot;width:448px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Comparison of Total kWh Reduction vs. EE Savings Using a Hypothetical Baseline for the Installation of New Equipment &quot; height=&quot;324&quot; width=&quot;448&quot; class=&quot;center media-element file-medium center&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/medium/public/2017-01/new_equipment_comparison.png&quot; title=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;figcaption&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Comparison of Total kWh Reduction vs. EE Savings Using a Hypothetical Baseline for the Installation of New Equipment&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;Other components of a comprehensive EM&amp;amp;V approach for an EE project or EE measure include:&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Determining the effective useful life (&lt;a class=&quot;termlookup-tooltip&quot; href=&quot;#self&quot; occurrence=&quot;1&quot;&gt;EUL&lt;span class=&quot;termlookup-custom&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Help&quot; src=&quot;/sites/all/modules/custom/add_definitions/images/add_definitions_icon_popup_help.png&quot; width=&quot;48&quot; height=&quot;48&quot; /&gt;&lt;em&gt;EUL&lt;/em&gt;EUL is the duration of time an EE project or EE measure is anticipated to remain in place and operable with the potential to save electricity.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;) of the project or measure&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Selecting an appropriate EM&amp;amp;V method&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Verifying that the EE project or EE measure is installed and operating properly&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Accounting for interactive effects and independent variables that affect electricity use&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

	&lt;div id=&quot;tab-4&quot;&gt;
		&lt;h3&gt;EM&amp;amp;V for EE Policies and Initiatives&lt;/h3&gt;

		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#a1&quot;&gt;Ratepayer-Funded EE Programs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#a2&quot;&gt;Organization-Led Building EE Initiatives&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#a3&quot;&gt;Forward Capacity Markets&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#a4&quot;&gt;Air Pollution Reductions in State/Tribal Implementation Plans&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Despite a core set of standardized approaches and resources, EM&amp;amp;V is routinely and appropriately tailored to particular EE policies or initiatives. This is intended to help:&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Make EM&amp;amp;V information and outputs responsive to the associated objectives and quantification metrics&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Give EE providers, oversight entities, and other stakeholders the information they need to plan for and deploy EE in a way that maximizes the intended benefits&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Identify challenges and barriers to the effectiveness of the EE, allowing EE implementers to make necessary changes in real time&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Quantify savings with appropriate accuracy, rigor, and overall cost and with consideration of the full range of EE benefits and costs (e.g., to compare EE to other electricity resource options, including both demand- and supply-side resources)&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Compare EE to other electricity resource options, including both demand- and supply-side resources&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Examples of how state and local agencies, businesses, and electricity system planners may tailor their EM&amp;amp;V for different policies and initiatives is provided below. One implication of this tailoring is that the EM&amp;amp;V protocols, metrics, and assumptions that apply in one case may not be appropriate for use in another. &lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;This &lt;a class=&quot;colorbox-inline&quot; href=&quot;#colorbox-hidden-2&quot;&gt;table&lt;/a&gt; shows examples of how EM&amp;amp;V approaches may differ by EE policy and initiatives.&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;div id=&quot;hidden-content-2&quot;&gt;
			&lt;div class=&quot;colorbox-hidden&quot; id=&quot;colorbox-hidden-2&quot;&gt;
				&lt;h3 id=&quot;dialog-title-2&quot;&gt;Examples of EM&amp;amp;V Approach for EE Policies and Initiatives&lt;/h3&gt;
				&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg center view-mode-full caption&quot; style=&quot;width:928px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Additional Detail on EM&amp;amp;V Approaches Table&quot; height=&quot;578&quot; width=&quot;928&quot; class=&quot;center media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2017-01/table.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;figcaption&quot;&gt;Additional Detail on EM&amp;amp;V Approaches&amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;One implication of tailoring EM&amp;amp;V to EE policies and initiatives is that the protocols, metrics, and assumptions that apply in one context may not be appropriate for use in another. For example, an EM&amp;amp;V approach designed to support the quantification of capacity (MW) savings during a limited number of “peak” hours in a future year may not be appropriate to use in conjunction with EE policies focused on achieving energy (MWh) savings in the current year.&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;!--&lt;/div&gt;--&gt;

		&lt;h3 id=&quot;a1&quot;&gt;Ratepayer-Funded EE Programs&lt;/h3&gt;

		&lt;h4&gt;What are they?&lt;/h4&gt;

		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Organized efforts, typically overseen by a state public utility commission (PUC) and delivered by a utility, to promote the adoption of EE projects or EE measures in homes and businesses&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Approaches include providing financial incentives (e.g., rebates and loans), technical services (e.g., audits, direct installation, training and assistance for architects, engineers, and building owners), information intended to change customer behavior (e.g., feedback on electricity usage), and educational campaigns about the benefits of EE improvements.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h4&gt;What are the goals for EE?&lt;/h4&gt;

		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Lower customer energy bills, reduce pollution, create local jobs and avoid the need for new power plants&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Serve as an “electricity system resource”—on par with power plant generation—that states, utilities, and system planners can use to:
				&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Deliver annual EE savings equal to a specified percentage of total electricity sales&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;Meet forecasted electricity demand over a defined geographic area (i.e., a utility service territory) within a specified timeframe&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h4&gt;What are typical EM&amp;amp;V objectives?&lt;/h4&gt;

		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Help ensure that public spending on EE is prudent and cost-effective&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Quantify costs and benefits, including electricity savings (MWh), demand savings (MW), and non-energy benefits (e.g., avoided emissions, job creation)&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Improve EE programs for customers and guide future investment decisions&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Determine whether utilities receive performance-related incentives or penalties&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Select Resources&lt;/h4&gt;

		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;General Information:&lt;/strong&gt;

				&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/statelocalclimate/energy-and-environment-guide-action&quot;&gt;U.S. EPA Energy and Environment Guide to Action&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://energy.gov/oe/services/electricity-policy-coordination-and-implementation/state-and-regional-policy-assistanc-6&quot;&gt;U.S. DOE Ratepayer-Funded Energy Efficiency Website &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www4.eere.energy.gov/seeaction/topic-category/ratepayer-funded-efficiency-through-regulatory-policy&quot;&gt;State and Local Energy Efficiency Action Network (SEE Action) Website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;EM&amp;amp;V Related:&lt;/strong&gt;

				&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://energy.gov/sites/prod/files/2016/01/f28/mv_guide_4_0.pdf&quot;&gt;M&amp;amp;V Guidelines: Measurement &amp;amp; Verification for Performance-Based Contracts, Version 4.0, U.S. DOE Federal Energy Management Program (FEMP)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.energy.gov/eere/about-us/ump-protocols&quot;&gt;DOE Uniform Methods Project (UMP) &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www4.eere.energy.gov/seeaction/publication/energy-efficiency-program-impact-evaluation-guide&quot;&gt;SEE Action Energy Efficiency Program Impact Evaluation Guide &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://evo-world.org/en/&quot;&gt;International Performance Measurement and Verification Protocol (IPMVP), Efficiency Valuation Organization (EVO)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.calmac.org/publications/EvaluatorsProtocols_Final_AdoptedviaRuling_06-19-2006.pdf&quot;&gt;California Energy Efficiency Evaluation Protocols: Technical, Methodological, and Reporting Requirements for Evaluation Professionals (2006)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id=&quot;a2&quot;&gt;Organization-Led Building EE Initiatives&lt;/h3&gt;

		&lt;h4&gt;What are they?&lt;/h4&gt;

		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Actions that organizations take to improve efficiency and reduce energy costs in a single building or a portfolio of buildings&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Typically includes adopting an &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.energystar.gov/buildings/about-us/how-can-we-help-you/build-energy-program/guidelines&quot;&gt;energy management program&lt;/a&gt; that involves setting goals for energy performance, creating a plan to achieve them, and taking action&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Many organizations partner with energy service companies (ESCOs) to help them achieve their energy performance goals
				&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;“Performance-based contracts” commit ESCOs to installing new EE equipment and reducing customer energy usage by an agreed-upon percentage&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h4&gt;What are the goals for EE?&lt;/h4&gt;

		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Reduce energy waste (a typical commercial building in the United States wastes 30% of its overall energy use) &lt;a href=&quot;#footnote1&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Significantly improve the efficiency of buildings and save on energy bills&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Benchmark energy use to help prioritize cost-effective EE investments within and across buildings
				&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Custom databases or publicly available tools such as the EPA’s ENERGY STAR Portfolio Manager are typically used&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h4&gt;What are typical EM&amp;amp;V objectives?&lt;/h4&gt;

		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Support organizational goals for energy management and financial savings&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;For ESCOs, bolster performance-based contracts and reconcile differences between actual and guaranteed savings&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Select resources&lt;/h4&gt;

		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;General Information:&lt;/strong&gt;

				&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.energystar.gov/&quot;&gt;EPA ENERGY STAR &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.energystar.gov/buildings/tools-and-resources/energy-star-guidelines-energy-management&quot;&gt;ENERGY STAR Guidelines for Energy Management&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://energy.gov/eere/femp/energy-service-companies-0&quot;&gt;U.S. DOE Energy Service Companies Website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.energystar.gov/buildings/facility-owners-and-managers/existing-buildings/use-portfolio-manager&quot;&gt;ENERGY STAR Portfolio Manager&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;EM&amp;amp;V Related:&lt;/strong&gt;
				&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://energy.gov/sites/prod/files/2016/01/f28/mv_guide_4_0.pdf&quot;&gt;M&amp;amp;V Guidelines: Measurement &amp;amp; Verification for Performance-Based Contracts, Version 4.0, U.S. DOE Federal Energy Management Program (FEMP)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://evo-world.org/en/&quot;&gt;International Performance Measurement and Verification Protocol (IPMVP), Efficiency Valuation Organization (EVO)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;
		 

		&lt;h3 id=&quot;a3&quot;&gt;Forward Capacity Markets&lt;/h3&gt;

		&lt;h4&gt;What are they?&lt;/h4&gt;

		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Markets established and overseen by an independent system operator (ISO) or regional transmission operator (RTO) to ensure long-term grid reliability by procuring enough electricity to meet forecasted demand during peak periods and in the case of a grid emergency&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Market mechanism is an auction that:
				&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Sets prices at levels that help ensure capacity resources will be available when needed on a “forward” (future) basis&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;Signals that investors will be adequately compensated for investments in construction, permitting, and maintenance of capacity resources&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h4&gt;What are the goals for EE?&lt;/h4&gt;

		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Compete directly with traditional electric power suppliers, demand response (DR) providers, transmission companies, and other entities to provide capacity&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Provide unique value to the grid compared to other capacity resources. EE can be:
				&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Implemented without extended siting, environmental, and regulatory analyses&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;Targeted to locations where needed&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;A source of significant peak load reductions (e.g., efficient air conditioners in summer peaking regions)&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h4&gt;What are typical EM&amp;amp;V objectives?&lt;/h4&gt;

		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Quantify the portion of total savings from a demand-side EE resource that occurs during the relevant peak hours&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Determine associated capacity payments to EE providers&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Establish consistent, minimum requirements for quantifying savings across EE activities (e.g., ratepayer-funded EE programs and organization-led building EE initiatives) and jurisdictions&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Select resources&lt;/h4&gt;

		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;General Information:&lt;/strong&gt;

				&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://energy.gov/eere/femp/energy-service-companies-0&quot;&gt;ISO New England Forward Capacity Market Website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://learn.pjm.com/three-priorities/buying-and-selling-energy/capacity-markets.aspx&quot;&gt;PJM Learning Center Capacity Market Website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;EM&amp;amp;V Related:&lt;/strong&gt;

				&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www4.eere.energy.gov/seeaction/publication/energy-efficiency-program-impact-evaluation-guide&quot;&gt;SEE Action Energy Efficiency Program Impact Evaluation Guide&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://iso-ne.com/static-assets/documents/rules_proceds/isone_mnls/m_mvdr_measurement_and_verification_demand_reduction_revision_6_06_01_14.doc&quot;&gt;ISO New England Measurement and Verification of Demand Reduction Value from Demand Resources Manual&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://pjm.com/~/media/documents/manuals/m18b.ashx&quot;&gt;PJM Manual 18B: Energy Efficiency Measurement &amp;amp; Verification&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3 id=&quot;a4&quot;&gt;Air Pollution Reductions in State/Tribal Implementation Plans&lt;/h3&gt;

		&lt;h4&gt;What are they?&lt;/h4&gt;

		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;State or tribal implementation plans (SIPs) describe the emission control strategies, technical documentation, and agreements a state or tribe will use to attain the National Ambient Air Quality Standards (NAAQS) for six common air pollutants&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;EPA guidance describes an overall approach and set of acceptable quantification options that states and tribes can use to include EE policies and programs in SIPs
				&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Guidance on State Implementation Plan (SIP) Credits for Emission Reductions from Electric-Sector Energy Efficiency and Renewable Energy Measures&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;Roadmap for Incorporating Energy Efficiency/Renewable Energy Policies and Programs into State and Tribal Implementation Plans (EE/RE SIP Roadmap)&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;States have found that strong partnerships between their air and energy officials are critical for success
				&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Such collaborations help all parties understand EE details, forecast electricity savings over time, and quantify the magnitude of expected emission reductions&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h4&gt;What is the role for EE?&lt;/h4&gt;

		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Reduce power plant emissions, improve air quality, and contribute to meeting the NAAQS
				&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;EE policies and programs have the advantage of addressing multiple air pollutants simultaneously, whereas most pollution control devices are designed to address only one pollutant&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Provide an alternative emission reduction option that states and tribes can use for including EE in SIPs&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h4&gt;What are typical EM&amp;amp;V objectives?&lt;/h4&gt;

		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Confirm, on a retrospective basis over the NAAQS planning horizon, that emission reductions resulting from EE are quantifiable, permanent, enforceable, and &lt;a class=&quot;termlookup-tooltip&quot; href=&quot;#self&quot; occurrence=&quot;1&quot;&gt;surplus&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;a href=&quot;#footnote2&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;termlookup-tooltip&quot; href=&quot;#self&quot; occurrence=&quot;1&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;termlookup-custom&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Help&quot; src=&quot;/sites/all/modules/custom/add_definitions/images/add_definitions_icon_popup_help.png&quot; width=&quot;48&quot; height=&quot;48&quot; /&gt;&lt;em&gt;Surplus&lt;/em&gt; Surplus means that reductions from EE are “additional” or “incremental” to the baseline identified in the SIP. For example, a state using the “baseline emissions projection pathway” must document assumptions about which EE policies are already included—and which are incremental to—the electricity use forecast submitted as part of the SIP.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Establish consistent, minimum requirements for quantifying savings across EE activities (e.g., ratepayer-funded EE programs and organization-led building EE initiatives) and jurisdictions&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Help ensure that jurisdictions apply equivalent EM&amp;amp;V approaches for determining the amount of SIP credit they may claim&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h4&gt;Select resources&lt;/h4&gt;

		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;General Information:&lt;/strong&gt;

				&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/energy-efficiency-and-renewable-energy-sips-and-tips/energy-efficiencyrenewable-energy-roadmap&quot;&gt;Roadmap for Incorporating Energy Efficiency/Renewable Energy Policies and Programs into State and Tribal Implementation Plans (EE/RE SIP Roadmap)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/statelocalclimate/guidance-sip-credits-emission-reductions-electric-sector-energy-efficiency-and&quot;&gt;U.S. EPA Guidance on State Implementation Plan (SIP) Credits for Emission Reductions from Electric-Sector Energy Efficiency and Renewable Energy Measures&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;EM&amp;amp;V Related:&lt;/strong&gt;

				&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/statelocalclimate/avoided-emissions-and-generation-tool-avert&quot;&gt;Avoided Emissions and Generation Tool (AVERT)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/energy/egrid&quot;&gt;Emissions &amp;amp; Generation Resource Integrated Database (eGRID)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.eia.gov/forecasts/aeo/&quot;&gt;Annual Energy Outlook (AEO), U.S. Energy Information Administration (EIA)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.neep-reed.org/Registration.aspx?Source=http://www.neep-reed.org/default.aspx&quot;&gt;Northeast Energy Efficiency Partnerships’ Regional Energy Efficiency Database (REED)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www4.eere.energy.gov/seeaction/sites/default/files/pdfs/ratepayer_efficiency_irpportfoliomanagement.pdf&quot;&gt;Utility integrated resource plans (IRPs)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://energy.gov/eere/slsc/energy-efficiency-potential-studies-catalog&quot;&gt;EE potential studies&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eia.gov/efficiency/programs/inventory/&quot;&gt;EM&amp;amp;V reports&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;footnote1&quot; name=&quot;footnote1&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;1. See: https://www.energystar.gov/buildings/about-us/how-can-we-help-you/improve-building-and-plant-performance/improve-energy-use-commercial&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

				&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;footnote2&quot; name=&quot;footnote2&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;2. Surplus means that reductions from EE are “additional” or “incremental” to the baseline identified in the SIP. For example, a state using the “baseline emissions projection pathway” must document assumptions about which EE policies are already included—and which are incremental to—the electricity use forecast submitted as part of the SIP. Given that electricity load forecasting may occur at a single- or multi-state level, coordination between agencies, EE providers, and entities conducting EM&amp;amp;V can help identify which EE savings are included in the baseline forecast and which are not.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

	&lt;div id=&quot;tab-5&quot;&gt;
		&lt;h3&gt;Related Paper&lt;/h3&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;This &lt;a href=&quot;/statelocalclimate/emv-energy-efficiency-policies-and-initiatives-0&quot;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; describes the status of EE policies and initiatives, identifies associated EE objectives, and provides discussion and examples of how EM&amp;amp;V may be tailored to each policy or initiative. &lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;h3&gt;Additional Detail on EM&amp;amp;V Approaches &lt;/h3&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;The following table provides additional detail on EM&amp;amp;V approaches by EE policy and strategy. It is illustrative and does not represent how EM&amp;amp;V is planned and implemented in all cases. &lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg center view-mode-full caption&quot; style=&quot;width:928px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Additional Detail on EM&amp;amp;V Approaches Table&quot; height=&quot;578&quot; width=&quot;928&quot; class=&quot;center media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2017-01/table.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;figcaption&quot;&gt;Additional Detail on EM&amp;amp;V Approaches&amp;nbsp;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 12 Jan 2017 19:15:44 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>xrrandha</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">168953 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>State CO2 Emissions from Fossil Fuel Combustion, 1990-2014</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/statelocalclimate/state-co2-emissions-fossil-fuel-combustion-1990-2014</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;Chart depicting  the State CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; Emissions from Fossil Fuel Combustion, 1990-2014&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-306267&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-08/documents/co2ffc_2014.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=45633&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;State CO2 Emissions from Fossil Fuel Combustion, 1990-2014 (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(5 pp, 46 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 02 Aug 2016 16:58:59 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>xrrandha</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">156349 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Introduction and Program Finder</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/statelocalclimate/introduction-and-program-finder</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;This flyer introduces a series of case studies and program profiles EPA developed to help officials in state and local energy, environmental, housing, and social service agencies, non-profits, and utilities understand promising practices and successful models that they can use to reduce greenhouse gas emissions by bringing energy efficiency and renewable energy to low-income communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-290077&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-06/documents/low_income_flyer_6-2-16_508.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=556506&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Introduction and Program Finder flyer (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(2 pp, 557 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 02 Jun 2016 21:06:45 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>ebolleru</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">151047 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Chumash Community Energy Efficiency and Renewable Energy Project Profile</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/statelocalclimate/chumash-community-energy-efficiency-and-renewable-energy-project-profile</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;The Santa Ynez Chumash are a federally recognized tribe located in Santa Barbara County, California. Like many tribal nations, the Santa Ynez Chumash face barriers to achieving widespread deployment of both residential and commercial energy efficiency and renewable energy (EE/RE), such as a lack of information about and interest in EE/RE opportunities and difficulty in obtaining financing. The Santa Ynez Chumash Environmental Office created a program with the following elements designed to address each of these challenges: partnerships with local contractors to establish the Chumash Community Energy Program (CCEP), an EE/RE jobs training and apprenticeship program; an extensive outreach campaign, including door-to-door promotion by trusted members of the tribe; and a residential solar panel give-away program and utility rebates.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;Learn more about the key features, approaches, partners, funding sources, and achievements of this program. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-290223&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-06/documents/chumash_community_energy_efficiency_and_renewable_energy_project_profile_.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=803175&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Chumash Community Energy Efficiency and Renewable Energy Project Profile (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(4 pp, 803 K, 
  June 2016)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 02 Jun 2016 16:40:26 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>ebolleru</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">151001 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  </channel>
</rss>

<!-- Page cached by Boost @ 2017-01-26 12:28:09, expires @ 2017-01-27 12:28:09, lifetime 1 day -->