<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?><rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.epa.gov/feed/46129/rss.xml" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/" xmlns:og="http://ogp.me/ns#" xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#" xmlns:sioc="http://rdfs.org/sioc/ns#" xmlns:sioct="http://rdfs.org/sioc/types#" xmlns:skos="http://www.w3.org/2004/02/skos/core#" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#">
  <channel>
    <title>Earth Day</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/feed/46129/rss.xml</link>
    <description>Updated Earth Day content from the US Environmental Protection Agency</description>
    <language>en</language>
     <atom:link href="https://www.epa.gov/feed/46129/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      <item>
    <title>Earth Day Videos 2015</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/earthday/earth-day-videos-2015</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;Check out the videos below. Share with us what you think is worth protecting. &lt;strong&gt;#EarthDayEveryDay&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Leaded Gas&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/S81O2LGMiPU&quot; height=&quot;169&quot; width=&quot;300&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;For decades, leaded gasoline threatened the air our kids breathed. Lead from polluted air was absorbed into their bloodstreams, endangering their brain development and risking consequences like permanent nerve damage, anemia, and mental retardation. So EPA phased out leaded gas. Back in the late 1970s, 88 percent of American children had elevated levels of lead in their blood. By the mid-2000s, that number had dropped to less than 1 percent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Acid Rain&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/Ge50ePjpmRY&quot; height=&quot;169&quot; width=&quot;300&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;Caused by air pollution mixing with water vapor in the atmosphere, acid rain was once poisoning our rivers and lakes, killing fish, forests, and wildlife, and even eroding our buildings. The 1990 amendments to the Clean Air Act gave EPA the authority to regulate sulfur dioxide and nitrogen oxides, the pollutants causing acid rain, from power plants. EPA developed the first market-based cap-and-trade pollution reduction program—and it worked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the doomsday warnings from some in the power industry that the regulations would cause electricity prices to spike and lead to blackouts, over the last 25 years, acid rain levels are down 60 percent—while electricity prices have stayed stable, and the lights have stayed on. Thanks to hard work by EPA, states, and industry, our nation has put policies in place to solve the problem over the long haul.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Bald Eagle&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/LZV6lsQiqAs&quot; height=&quot;169&quot; width=&quot;300&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;The bald eagle once faced extinction. The culprit was DDT, a powerful pesticide that made birds&#039; eggshells too weak for the chicks to survive, and also caused liver cancer and reproductive problems in humans. EPA banned the use of DDT in 1972, and since then, bald eagles have made a huge comeback -- they were removed from the Endangered Species List in 2007 and our families are safer from harmful chemicals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Air Pollution&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/PV9Lm17yWN8&quot; height=&quot;169&quot; width=&quot;300&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;A newspaper headline once called the smog shrouding Los Angeles &quot;a dirty gray blanket flung across the city.&quot; L.A. and many other cities like this one were choked by severe air pollution, leading to asthma, respiratory illness, and certain cancers. But over the last 45 years, we&#039;ve cut air pollution 70 percent—and meanwhile our nation&#039;s economy has tripled. It goes to show that a strong economy and a safe environment go hand in hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Clean Air&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/L_liJ9hNPUw&quot; height=&quot;169&quot; width=&quot;300&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;Every day, EPA works toward cleaner air. &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.usc.edu/76761/las-environmental-success-story-cleaner-air-healthier-kids/&quot;&gt;One recent study found&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt; that, thanks to the strides we&#039;ve made in cutting air pollution in just the last 2 decades, children&#039;s lungs in Southern California are 10 percent bigger and stronger today than they were in children 20 years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last fall, we built on that success by proposing stricter standards for ozone pollution to protect those most vulnerable—children, the elderly, and those already suffering from respiratory illnesses like asthma. For our kids, that means avoiding up to a million missed school days, thousands of cases of acute bronchitis, and nearly a million asthma attacks. Adults could avoid hundreds of emergency room visits for cardiovascular reasons, up to 180,000 missed work days, and 4 million days where people have to deal with pollution-related symptoms. Every dollar we invest in these standards would return $3 in health benefits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Fri, 22 Apr 2016 14:48:52 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>jmorin</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">147405 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Earth Day Videos</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/earthday/earth-day-videos</link>
    <description>&lt;div class=&quot;box multi related-info right&quot;&gt;
	&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/earthday/earth-day-videos-2015&quot;&gt;Videos from 2015&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out the videos below. Let&#039;s work toward #NoWastedFood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most people don&#039;t realize how much food they throw away every day - from uneaten leftovers to spoiled produce. About 95 percent of the food we throw away ends up in landfills or combustion facilities. In 2013, we disposed more than 35 million tons of food waste. Once in landfills, food breaks down to produce methane, a potent greenhouse gas which contributes to climate change. &lt;a href=&quot;/recycle/reducing-wasted-food-home&quot;&gt;Learn more about reducing wasted food at home.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Shop your Fridge&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/NXROVgFYqU0&quot; height=&quot;169&quot; width=&quot;300&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;Looking to reduce wasted food and save money? Get creative and shop your fridge and pantry before heading out to the store. (NOTE: This video only has music. There are no captions.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Score Big for the Environment With Composting&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe src=&quot;https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/OGxNM2vfq0o&quot; height=&quot;169&quot; width=&quot;300&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;Most people don&#039;t realize how much food they throw away every day — from uneaten leftovers to spoiled produce. About 95 percent of the food we throw away ends up in landfills or combustion facilities. In 2013, we disposed more than 35 million tons of food waste. Once in landfills, food breaks down to produce methane, a potent greenhouse gas which contributes to climate change.Try composting instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Fri, 17 Apr 2015 14:05:55 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>jmorin</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">80881 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Earth Day Events</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/earthday/earth-day-events</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;No events are scheduled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To find local resources or more information on inviting EPA staff to visit your school, talk to your &lt;a href=&quot;/education/where-you-live&quot;&gt;Regional Environmental Education Coordinator.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2014 20:14:39 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>jmorin</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">46333 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Contact Us About Earth Day</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/earthday/forms/contact-us-about-earth-day</link>
    <description>&lt;div class=&quot;box right&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;box left&quot; href=&quot;/tips&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Report an environmental violation&quot; src=&quot;/sites/all/themes/epa/img/badge.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

	&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/tips&quot;&gt;Report a Violation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

	&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;Report possible violations of environmental laws and regulations.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please use the form below to send us comments or ask questions about the Earth Day website. If you&#039;d like a response, please be sure to include your e-mail address. &lt;strong&gt;If you have a question about EPA in general, please &lt;a href=&quot;/home/forms/contact-epa&quot;&gt;see this page&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;US Environmental Protection Agency (1701A)&lt;br /&gt;
	1200 Pennsylvania Ave NW&lt;br /&gt;
	Washington, DC 20460&lt;br /&gt;
	Attn: Earth Day&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or use this form:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2014 19:06:03 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>jmorin</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">46131 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
