<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?><rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.epa.gov/feed/57721/rss.xml" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/" xmlns:og="http://ogp.me/ns#" xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#" xmlns:sioc="http://rdfs.org/sioc/ns#" xmlns:sioct="http://rdfs.org/sioc/types#" xmlns:skos="http://www.w3.org/2004/02/skos/core#" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#">
  <channel>
    <title>Choose Fish and Shellfish Wisely</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/feed/57721/rss.xml</link>
    <description>Updated Choose Fish and Shellfish Wisely content from the US Environmental Protection Agency</description>
    <language>en</language>
     <atom:link href="https://www.epa.gov/feed/57721/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      <item>
    <title>National Shellfish Sanitation Program</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/choose-fish-and-shellfish-wisely/national-shellfish-sanitation-program</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;Information related to National Shellfish Sanitation Program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-198123&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-09/documents/exposure-to-waterborne-pathogens.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=23415&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Intergovernmental Protection of Public Health from Exposure to Waterborne, Illness-Causing Enteric Pathogens (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(4 pp, 23 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Mon, 21 Sep 2015 16:58:31 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>rkearney</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">115561 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Consumption Advice: Joint Federal Advisory for Mercury in Fish</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/choose-fish-and-shellfish-wisely/consumption-advice-joint-federal-advisory-mercury-fish</link>
    <description>&lt;h2&gt;Backgrounder for the 2004 FDA/EPA Consumer Advisory: What You Need to Know About Mercury in Fish and Shellfish&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FDA and EPA issued a joint consumer advisory about mercury in fish and shellfish. The advice is for: women who might become pregnant; women who are pregnant; nursing mothers; and young children. This is the first time FDA and EPA have combined their advice into a single uniform advisory. Previously FDA issued an advisory on consumption of commercially caught fish, while EPA issued advice on recreationally caught fish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FDA and EPA revised their existing advisories as a result of recommendations FDA received from its Foods Advisory Committee (FAC) in July 2002. At that meeting the FAC offered a number of recommendations intended to improve the clarity and understandability of the then current FDA advisory. One of the suggestions was that FDA and EPA combine their two independent advisories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The criteria for the advisory was that it be based on sound science; is easy to understand and apply; and protects the public health.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The purpose of the advisory is to inform women who may become pregnant, pregnant women, nursing mothers and the parents of young children on how to get the positive health benefits from eating fish and shellfish, while minimizing their mercury exposure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;accordion&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#pane-1&quot; title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot;&gt;Message to Consumers&lt;/a&gt;

		&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;pane-1&quot;&gt;
			&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Fish and shellfish are important parts of a healthy and balanced diet. They are good sources of high quality protein and other nutrients. However, depending on the amount and type of fish you consume it may be prudent to modify your diet if you are: planning to become pregnant; pregnant; nursing; or a young child. With a few simple adjustments, you can continue to enjoy these foods in a manner that is healthy and beneficial and reduce your unborn or young child&#039;s exposure to the harmful effects of mercury at the same time.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#pane-2&quot; title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot;&gt;Key Parts of the Advisory&lt;/a&gt;
		&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;pane-2&quot;&gt;
			&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Fish and shellfish are an important part of a healthy diet. Fish and shellfish contain high quality protein and other essential nutrients, are low in saturated fat and contain omega-3 fatty acids. A well balanced diet that includes a variety of fish and shellfish can contribute to heart health and children&#039;s proper growth and development. Thus, women and young children in particular should include fish or shellfish in their diets due to the many nutritional benefits.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;li&gt;By following these 3 recommendations for selecting and eating fish or shellfish, women and young children will receive the benefits of eating fish and shellfish and be confident that they have reduced their exposure to the harmful effects of mercury.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;Do not eat Shark, Swordfish, King Mackerel, or Tilefish because they contain high levels of mercury.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;li&gt;Eat up to 12 ounces (2 average meals) a week of a variety of fish and shellfish that are lower in mercury.
					&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Five of the most commonly eaten fish that are low in mercury are shrimp, canned light tuna, salmon, pollock, and catfish.&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;li&gt;Another commonly eaten fish, albacore (&quot;white&quot;) tuna has more mercury than canned light tuna. So, when choosing your two meals of fish and shellfish, you may eat up to 6 ounces (one average meal) of albacore tuna per week.&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;li&gt;Check local advisories about the safety of fish caught by family and friends in your local lakes, rivers, and coastal areas. If no advice is available, eat up to 6 ounces (one average meal) per week of fish you catch from local waters, but don&#039;t consume any other fish during that week.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Follow these same recommendations when feeding fish and shellfish to your young child, but serve smaller portions.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#pane-3&quot; title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot;&gt;The Difference Between This Advisory and Previous Advisories&lt;/a&gt;
		&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;pane-3&quot;&gt;
			&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;The advisory emphasizes the positive benefits of eating fish.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;li&gt;The advisory provides examples of commonly eaten fish that are low in mercury.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;li&gt;The advisory for the first time specifically addresses canned light tuna and canned albacore (&quot;white&quot;) tuna, as well as tuna steaks (in the questions and answers section).&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;li&gt;The advisory recommends not to eat any other fish in the same week as locally caught fish are consumed (the advice on the amount of locally caught fish to eat is the same as in the 2001 EPA advisory).&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;li&gt;The advisory contains a section that addresses frequently asked questions about mercury in fish.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#pane-4&quot; title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot;&gt;What the Risk is&lt;/a&gt;
		&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;pane-4&quot;&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;Research shows that most people&#039;s fish consumption does not cause a health concern. However, high levels of mercury in the bloodstream of unborn babies and young children may harm the developing nervous system. With this in mind, FDA and EPA designed an advisory that if followed should keep an individual&#039;s mercury consumption below levels that have been shown to cause harm. By following the advisory parents can be confident of reducing their unborn or young child&#039;s exposure to the harmful effects of mercury, while at the same time maintaining a healthy diet that includes the nutritional benefits of fish and shellfish.&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#pane-5&quot; title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot;&gt;General Methylmercury Information&lt;/a&gt;
		&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;pane-5&quot;&gt;
			&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;The methylmercury described in the advisory is not the same type of mercury found in some thermometers or in dental amalgam.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;li&gt;Mercury is a naturally occurring element in the environment and is also released into the air through industrial pollution. Mercury that falls from the air can accumulate in streams and oceans. Bacteria in the water cause chemical changes that transform mercury into methylmercury. Fish absorb the methylmercury as they feed in these waters. Methylmercury builds up more in some fish than others depending on what they eat how long they live, and how high up the food chain they are.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;li&gt;Fish and shellfish are the main sources of mercury exposure to humans and that mercury is in the form of methylmercury. Other forms of mercury, such as that in dental amalgams are minor contributors to human mercury exposure.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#pane-6&quot; title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot;&gt;General Dietary Advice&lt;/a&gt;
		&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;pane-6&quot;&gt;
			&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;FDA recommends that consumers eat a balanced diet, choosing a variety of foods including fruits and vegetables, foods that are low in trans fat and saturated fat, as well as foods rich in high fiber grains and nutrients. Fish and shellfish can be an important part of this diet.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#pane-7&quot; title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot;&gt;What&#039;s Next&lt;/a&gt;
		&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;pane-7&quot;&gt;
			&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;FDA and EPA want to ensure that women and young children continue to eat fish and shellfish because of the nutritional benefits and encourage them to follow the advisory so they can be confident in reducing their mercury exposure as well.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;li&gt;FDA and EPA are planning a comprehensive educational campaign to reach: women who might become pregnant; pregnant women; nursing mothers; and young children. The agencies will work with state, local and tribal health departments to get information out into their communities. Physicians, other health professionals, and health care associations will be sent information to distribute through their offices. Extensive outreach through the media is also planned. Radio and television stations, health editors at newspapers, magazines, and other popular media will be contacted to encourage them to carry the public service message. The methylmercury advisory will also be an important part of a comprehensive food safety education program to be used by educators of pregnant women. FDA plans to launch the comprehensive education program later this year.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;li&gt;EPA and FDA have begun discussions on how to coordinate other scientific assessments involving fish.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#pane-8&quot; title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot;&gt;Other&lt;/a&gt;
		&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;pane-8&quot;&gt;
			&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;FDA and EPA tested different versions of the revised advisory in 16 focus groups in 7 different locations throughout the United States. Based on responses we received we modified the advisory so that it is more easily understood.
					&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;In December 2003, after 8 focus groups had been conducted, a draft of the revised advisory was presented to the Foods Advisory Committee. Based on their feedback we conducted 8 additional focus groups and modified the advisory according to the feedback we received. The result is the 2004 FDA/EPA Consumer Advisory: &quot;What You Need to Know About Mercury in Fish and Shellfish&quot;.&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;li&gt;Since July 2002 FDA has tested over 3400 cans of tuna as well as 227 fish samples, comprising 12 different species, for mercury. These results were added to our previous sampling results.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;li&gt;FDA continues to sample fish and shellfish, testing for mercury.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#pane-9&quot; title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot;&gt;For more information&lt;/a&gt;
		&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;pane-9&quot;&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;For more information about the risks of mercury in fish and shellfish call the FDA&#039;s Food Information Hotline toll-free at 1-888-SAFEFOOD or visit &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fda.gov/food/foodborneillnesscontaminants/metals/ucm115644.htm&quot;&gt;FDA&#039;s Food Safety website&lt;/a&gt;. For more information about the safety of locally caught fish and shellfish, visit the Environmental Protection Agency&#039;s &lt;a href=&quot;/choose-fish-and-shellfish-wisely/fish-and-shellfish-advisories-and-safe-eating-guidelines&quot;&gt;Fish Advisory website&lt;/a&gt; or contact your state or local health department. Contact information for state and local health departments is also found at this site.&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 02 Sep 2015 12:53:20 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>rkearney</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">110623 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Lo que usted necesita saber sobre el mercurio en el pescado y los mariscos</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/choose-fish-and-shellfish-wisely/lo-que-usted-necesita-saber-sobre-el-mercurio-en-el-pescado-y-los</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;(&lt;a href=&quot;/choose-fish-and-shellfish-wisely/what-you-need-know-about-mercury-fish-and-shellfish&quot;&gt;en inglés&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aviso de la EPA y la FDA de 2004 para:&lt;br /&gt;
	Las mujeres en edad fértil, las mujeres embarazadas,&lt;br /&gt;
	las madres lactantes y los niños pequeños&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/choose-fish-and-shellfish-wisely/mercury-fish-and-shellfish-brochures&quot;&gt;Versión para imprimir&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;El pescado y los mariscos son una parte importante de una dieta saludable. El pescado y los mariscos contienen proteína de alta calidad y otros nutrientes esenciales que son bajos en grasas saturadas y contienen grasas omega-3. Una dieta bien balanceada que incluya una variedad de pescados y mariscos puede contribuir a la salud cardiaca y al crecimiento y desarrollo adecuado de los niños. Por tanto, las mujeres y los niños pequeños en particular deben incluir el pescado o el marisco en sus dietas debido a sus muchos beneficios nutricionales.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sin embargo, casi todos los pescados y mariscos contienen algunos rastros de mercurio. Para muchas personas, el riesgo del mercurio proveniente del pescado y el marisco no es una preocupación de salud. No obstante, algunos pescados y mariscos contienen altos niveles de mercurio que pueden perjudicar a un bebé que no haya nacido o puede afectar adversamente el sistema nervioso en vías de desarrollo de un niño pequeño. Los riesgos del mercurio en el pescado y el marisco dependen de la cantidad de pescado y marisco que coma y los niveles del mercurio en el pescado y el marisco. Por lo tanto, la Administración de Alimentos y Drogas (FDA, por sus siglas en inglés) y la Agencia de Protección Ambiental (EPA, por sus siglas en inglés) aconsejan a las mujeres en edad fértil, las mujeres embarazadas, las madres lactantes y los niños pequeños que eviten comer algunos tipos de pescado y que coman pescado y mariscos bajos en mercurio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Al seguir estas tres recomendaciones para seleccionar y comer el pescado o marisco, las mujeres y los niños recibirán los beneficios de comer pescado y mariscos y podrán confiar en que habrán reducido su exposición a los efectos dañinos del mercurio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;No coma carne de tiburón, pez espada, caballa, o lofolátilo porque contienen altos niveles de mercurio.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Puede comer hasta 12 onzas (dos comidas promedio) a la semana de una variedad de pescado o mariscos que sean bajos en mercurio.
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Cinco de los pescados que se comen con mayor frecuencia que son bajos en mercurio son los camarones, el atún enlatado claro, el salmón, el gado y el pez gato.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Otro pescado que se come comúnmente es el atún albacora (blanco) que tiene más mercurio que el atún enlatado claro. Por lo tanto, cuando escoja sus dos alimentos de pescado y mariscos, puede comer hasta seis onzas (una comida promedio) de atún albacora por semana.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Consulte los avisos locales sobre la seguridad de la pesca realizada por sus familiares y amigos en los lagos, ríos, y áreas costeras locales. Si no hay ninguna información disponible sobre dichos cuerpos de agua en su localidad, puede comer hasta seis onzas (una comida promedio) por semana de pescado de sus aguas locales, pero no consuma ningún otro tipo de pescado durante la semana.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Siga estas recomendaciones cuando alimente a su niño pequeño con pescado o mariscos, pero sírvale porciones menores.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;faqs&quot;&gt;PREGUNTAS FRECUENTES SOBRE EL MERCURIO EN EL PESCADO Y LOS MARISCOS:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#what&quot;&gt;¿Qué es el mercurio y mercurio metílico?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#notp&quot;&gt;¿Soy una mujer en edad fértil, pero no estoy embarazada-entonces por qué tengo que estar preocupada por el mercurio metílico?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#isthere&quot;&gt;¿Hay mercurio metílico en todos los peces y mariscos?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#donotsee&quot;&gt;Yo no veo el pescado que suelo comer identificado en el aviso. ¿Qué debo hacer?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fastfood&quot;&gt;¿Qué ocurre con los pescados procesados en &quot;palitos de pescado&quot; (fish sticks) y los sándwiches de comida rápida?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#tuna&quot;&gt;¿Los consejos sobre el atún enlatado están delineados en el aviso, pero qué se aconseja para las rodajas de atún?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#twelve&quot;&gt;¿Qué pasa si comemos más de la cantidad recomendada para el pescado y los mariscos en una semana?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#local&quot;&gt;¿Dónde puedo conseguir información sobre la seguridad del peces pescados de manera recreativa por la familia y amistades?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#info&quot;&gt;Para más información&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;h4 id=&quot;what&quot;&gt;1. ¿Qué es el mercurio y mercurio metílico?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;El mercurio ocurre naturalmente en el medio ambiente y también puede ser emitido al aire por medio de la contaminación industrial. El mercurio cae del aire y se acumula en corrientes fluviales y océanos y es convertido en mercurio metílico en el agua. Este es el tipo de mercurio que puede ser dañino para su bebé que aún no ha nacido o un niño pequeño. Los peces absorben el mercurio metílico a medida que se alimenten en dichas aguas y el mismo se acumula en sus cuerpos. El mercurio metílico se acumula más en algunas variedades de peces y mariscos que en otros, dependiendo del pescado que usted coma, por eso los niveles varían.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#faqs&quot;&gt;preguntas&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;notp&quot;&gt;2. ¿Soy una mujer en edad fértil, pero no estoy embarazada-entonces por qué tengo que estar preocupada por el mercurio metílico?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Si usted come regularmente tipos de pescado que tengan niveles elevados de mercurio metílico, puede acumularse en sus vías sanguíneas con el paso del tiempo. El mercurio metílico se elimina naturalmente del cuerpo, pero puede tomar un año para que los niveles bajen dramáticamente. Por ende, puede estar presente en una mujer aún antes de ella quedar embarazada. Esta es la razón por la cual las mujeres que estén tratando de quedar embarazadas también deben evitar comer varios tipos de pescado.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#faqs&quot;&gt;preguntas&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;isthere&quot;&gt;3. ¿Hay mercurio metílico en todos los peces y mariscos?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Casi todos los peces y mariscos contienen rastros de mercurio metílico. Sin embargo, los peces de mayor tamaño que hayan vivido más tienen niveles más altos de mercurio metílico porque han tenido más tiempo para acumularlo. Estos peces grandes (pez espada, tiburón, caballa, y lofolátilo) representan un riesgo mayor. Otros tipos de pescados y mariscos pueden ser ingeridos en cantidades recomendadas por la FDA y la EPA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#faqs&quot;&gt;preguntas&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;donotsee&quot;&gt;4. Yo no veo el pescado que suelo comer identificado en el aviso. ¿Qué debo hacer?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Si desea más información sobre los niveles en los varios tipos de pescados que come, vea el sitio &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fda.gov/food/foodborneillnesscontaminants/metals/ucm115644.htm&quot;&gt;Web de la FDA para la seguridad de los alimentos&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;/choose-fish-and-shellfish-wisely/fish-and-shellfish-advisories-and-safe-eating-guidelines&quot;&gt;el sitio Web de la EPA para los avisos de pescados&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#faqs&quot;&gt;preguntas&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;fastfood&quot;&gt;5. ¿Qué ocurre con los pescados procesados en &quot;palitos de pescado&quot; (fish sticks) y los sándwiches de comida rápida?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Los &quot;fish sticks&quot; y los sándwiches de comida rápida comúnmente son hechos con pescados bajos en mercurio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#faqs&quot;&gt;preguntas&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;tuna&quot;&gt;6. ¿Los consejos sobre el atún enlatado están delineados en el aviso, pero qué se aconseja para las rodajas de atún?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Debido a que las rodajas de atún generalmente contienen niveles más altos de mercurio que el atún claro enlatado, cuando escoja dos alimentos de pescado y marisco, puede comer hasta seis onzas (una comida regular) de rodajas de atún por semana.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#faqs&quot;&gt;preguntas&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;twelve&quot;&gt;7. ¿Qué pasa si comemos más de la cantidad recomendada para el pescado y los mariscos en una semana?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;El consumo semanal de pescado no debe cambiar el nivel del mercurio metílico en el cuerpo mucho. Si come mucho pescado en una semana, debe reducir la cantidad por las siguientes una o dos semanas. Sólo asegúrese de que coma el promedio de la cantidad recomendada cada semana.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#faqs&quot;&gt;preguntas&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;local&quot;&gt;8. ¿Dónde puedo conseguir información sobre la seguridad del peces pescados de manera recreativa por la familia y amistades?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Antes de pescar, consulte el folleto de regulaciones sobre la pesca para información sobre los peces pescados de manera recreativa. También puede consultar su departamento de salud local para información sobre los avisos locales. Debe consultar los avisos locales debido a que varios tipos de peces y mariscos pescados en sus aguas locales pueden tener niveles mayores o menores a los niveles promedios de mercurio. Esto depende de los niveles de mercurio en el agua donde los peces han sido pescados. Aquellos pescados que pueden tener niveles mucho más bajos pueden ser comidos con mayor frecuencia y en cantidades mayores.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#faqs&quot;&gt;preguntas&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;info&quot;&gt;Para más información&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Para más información sobre los riesgos del mercurio en el pescado y los mariscos, llame a la línea de información gratuita de la Administración de Alimentos y Drogas de los EE.UU. en el 1-888-SAFEFOOD o visite el sitio Web de la FDA sobre la seguridad alimenticia &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fda.gov/food/guidanceregulation/guidancedocumentsregulatoryinformation/seafood/ucm2006751.htm&quot;&gt;FDA&#039;s Food Safety website.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Para más información sobre la seguridad de los peces y mariscos pescados localmente visite el sitio Web de la EPA para los avisos de pesca &lt;a href=&quot;/choose-fish-and-shellfish-wisely/fish-and-shellfish-advisories-and-safe-eating-guidelines&quot;&gt;Environmental Protection Agency&#039;s Fish Advisory website&lt;/a&gt; o comuníquese con &lt;a href=&quot;https://fishadvisoryonline.epa.gov/Contacts.aspx&quot;&gt;el departamento de salud local de su estado&lt;/a&gt;. Para más información en inglés sobre las acciones de la EPA para controlar el mercurio, visite el sitio Web sobre el mercurio de la EPA &lt;a href=&quot;/cwa-methods&quot;&gt;mercury website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#content&quot;&gt;la cumbre&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jul 2015 21:21:14 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>rkearney</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">101683 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Mercury in Fish and Shellfish Technical Information</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/choose-fish-and-shellfish-wisely/mercury-fish-and-shellfish-technical-information</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;Information on the origin of the meal advice for the 2004 advisory and national mean mercury concentrations. If you have trouble accessing any content in the following documents, please contact &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:fontenelle.samantha@epa.gov&quot;&gt;Samantha Fontenelle&lt;/a&gt; at fontenelle.samantha@epa.gov.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-168543&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-07/documents/fish-advice-1-meal-per-week.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=67453&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Technical Memorandum: Origin of 1 meal / week Freshwater Fish Consumption Rate (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(5 pp, 67 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-168545&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-07/documents/mercurytissues-slide.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=166220&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;National Mean Mercury Concentration in Tissues of Selected Fish (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(1 pg, 166 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jul 2015 21:12:20 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>rkearney</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">101681 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Mercury in Fish and Shellfish Brochures</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/choose-fish-and-shellfish-wisely/mercury-fish-and-shellfish-brochures</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;Advice to women who may become pregnant, pregnant women, nursing mothers, and young children about consuming fish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-168487&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-07/documents/mercury-brochure.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=240193&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;What You Need to Know about Mercury in Fish and Shellfish Brochure (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(2 pp, 240 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-168393&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-07/documents/brochure-spanish.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=242553&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Spanish (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(2 pp, 243 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-168467&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-07/documents/brochure-cambodian.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=663103&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Cambodian (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(2 pp, 663 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-168469&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-07/documents/brochure-chinese.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=829815&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Chinese (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(2 pp, 830 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-168471&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-07/documents/brochure-hmong.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=852251&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Hmong (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(2 pp, 852 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-168473&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-07/documents/brochure-korean.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=807661&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Korean (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(2 pp, 808 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-168475&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-07/documents/brochure-portuguese.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=895202&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Portuguese (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(2 pp, 895 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-168481&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-07/documents/brochure-vietnamese.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=1086400&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Vietnamese (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(2 pp, 1 MB)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jul 2015 19:59:11 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>sfonte01</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">101655 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>What You Need to Know about Mercury in Fish and Shellfish</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/choose-fish-and-shellfish-wisely/what-you-need-know-about-mercury-fish-and-shellfish</link>
    <description>&lt;div class=&quot;box multi related-info right&quot;&gt;
	&lt;h2 class=&quot;pane-title&quot;&gt;Related Information&lt;/h2&gt;

	&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/fish-tech/reports-and-fact-sheets-about-fish-consumption-and-human-health&quot;&gt;Trends in Blood Mercury Levels&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fda.gov/food/foodborneillnesscontaminants/metals/ucm115644.htm&quot;&gt;Food &amp;amp; Drug Administration (FDA) Mercury Levels in Commercial Fish &amp;amp; Shellfish&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/mercury&quot;&gt;Mercury Home&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/choose-fish-and-shellfish-wisely/fish-and-shellfish-advisories-and-safe-eating-guidelines&quot;&gt;National Listing of Fish Advisories&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/nscep/retrieving-ordering-and-printing-nscep-publications&quot;&gt;Order publications&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;2017 EPA and FDA Advice for:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;Women of Childbearing Age (about 16-49 years old)&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;Pregnant and breastfeeding Women&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;Young Children&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/fish-tech/epa-fda-advice-about-eating-fish-and-shellfish&quot;&gt;EPA-FDA Advice about Eating Fish&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;2004 EPA and FDA Advice for:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Women Who Might Become Pregnant&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Women Who are Pregnant&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Nursing Mothers&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Young Children&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/choose-fish-and-shellfish-wisely/mercury-fish-and-shellfish-brochures&quot;&gt;Print Version of Brochure&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fish and shellfish are an important part of a healthy diet. Fish and shellfish contain high-quality protein and other essential nutrients, are low in saturated fat, and contain omega-3 fatty acids. A well-balanced diet that includes a variety of fish and shellfish can contribute to heart health and children&#039;s proper growth and development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, women and young children in particular should include fish or shellfish in their diets due to the many nutritional benefits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;box multi related-info right&quot;&gt;
	&lt;h2 class=&quot;pane-title&quot;&gt;Additional Translations&lt;/h2&gt;

	&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/choose-fish-and-shellfish-wisely/lo-que-usted-necesita-saber-sobre-el-mercurio-en-el-pescado-y-los&quot;&gt;en español&lt;/a&gt; | &lt;a href=&quot;/choose-fish-and-shellfish-wisely/mercury-fish-and-shellfish-brochures&quot;&gt;Spanish&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/choose-fish-and-shellfish-wisely/mercury-fish-and-shellfish-brochures&quot;&gt;Cambodian&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/choose-fish-and-shellfish-wisely/mercury-fish-and-shellfish-brochures&quot;&gt;Chinese&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/choose-fish-and-shellfish-wisely/mercury-fish-and-shellfish-brochures&quot;&gt;Hmong&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/choose-fish-and-shellfish-wisely/mercury-fish-and-shellfish-brochures&quot;&gt;Korean&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/choose-fish-and-shellfish-wisely/mercury-fish-and-shellfish-brochures&quot;&gt;Portuguese&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/choose-fish-and-shellfish-wisely/mercury-fish-and-shellfish-brochures&quot;&gt;Vietnamese&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, nearly all fish and shellfish contain traces of mercury. For most people, the risk from mercury by eating fish and shellfish is not a health concern. Yet, some fish and shellfish contain higher levels of mercury that may harm an unborn baby or young child&#039;s developing nervous system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The risks from mercury in fish and shellfish depend on the amount of fish and shellfish eaten and the levels of mercury in the fish and shellfish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, the Food and Drug Administration (FDA) and the Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) are advising women who may become pregnant, pregnant women, nursing mothers, and young children to avoid some types of fish and eat fish and shellfish that are lower in mercury.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By &lt;strong&gt;following these three recommendations&lt;/strong&gt; for selecting and eating fish or shellfish, women and young children will receive the benefits of eating fish and shellfish and be confident that they have reduced their exposure to the harmful effects of mercury.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;Do not eat Shark, Swordfish, King Mackerel, or Tilefish because they contain high levels of mercury.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Eat up to 12 ounces (2 average meals) a week of a variety of fish and shellfish that are lower in mercury.
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Five of the most commonly eaten fish that are low in mercury are shrimp, canned light tuna, salmon, pollock, and catfish.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Another commonly eaten fish, albacore (&quot;white&quot;) tuna has more mercury than canned light tuna. So, when choosing your two meals of fish and shellfish, you may eat up to 6 ounces (one average meal) of albacore tuna per week.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Check local advisories about the safety of fish caught by family and friends in your local lakes, rivers, and coastal areas. If no advice is available, eat up to 6 ounces (one average meal) per week of fish you catch from local waters, but don&#039;t consume any other fish during that week.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;Follow these same recommendations when feeding fish and shellfish to your young child, but serve smaller portions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;faqs&quot;&gt;Frequently Asked Questions about Mercury in Fish and Shellfish&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;accordion&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#pane-1&quot; title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot;&gt;1. What is mercury and methylmercury?&lt;/a&gt;

		&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;pane-1&quot;&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;Mercury occurs naturally in the environment and can also be released into the air through industrial pollution. Mercury falls from the air and can accumulate in streams and oceans and is turned into methylmercury in the water.&lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;p&gt;It is this type of mercury that can be harmful to your unborn baby and young child. Fish absorb the methylmercury as they feed in these waters and so it builds up in them. It builds up more in some types of fish and shellfish than others, depending on what the fish eat, which is why the levels vary.&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#pane-2&quot; title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot;&gt;2. I&#039;m a woman who could have children but I&#039;m not pregnant - so why should I be concerned about methylmercury?&lt;/a&gt;
		&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;pane-2&quot;&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;If you regularly eat types of fish that are high in methylmercury, it can accumulate in your blood stream over time. Methylmercury is removed from the body naturally, but it may take over a year for the levels to drop significantly.&lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;p&gt;Thus, it may be present in a woman even before she becomes pregnant. This is the reason why women who are trying to become pregnant should also avoid eating certain types of fish.&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#pane-3&quot; title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot;&gt;3. Is there methylmercury in all fish and shellfish?&lt;/a&gt;
		&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;pane-3&quot;&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;Nearly all fish and shellfish contain traces of methylmercury. However, larger fish that have lived longer have the highest levels of methylmercury because they&#039;ve had more time to accumulate it. These large fish (swordfish, shark, king mackerel and tilefish) pose the greatest risk. Other types of fish and shellfish may be eaten in the amounts recommended by FDA and EPA.&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#pane-4&quot; title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot;&gt;4. I don&#039;t see the fish I eat in the advisory. What should I do?&lt;/a&gt;
		&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;pane-4&quot;&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;If you want more information about the levels in the various types of fish you eat, see the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fda.gov/food/foodborneillnesscontaminants/metals/ucm115644.htm&quot;&gt;FDA Food Safety website&lt;/a&gt; or the &lt;a href=&quot;/choose-fish-and-shellfish-wisely/fish-and-shellfish-advisories-and-safe-eating-guidelines&quot;&gt;EPA Fish Advisory website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#pane-5&quot; title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot;&gt;5. What about fish sticks and fast food sandwiches?&lt;/a&gt;
		&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;pane-5&quot;&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;Fish sticks and &quot;fast-food&quot; sandwiches are commonly made from fish that are low in mercury.&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#pane-6&quot; title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot;&gt;6. The advice about canned tuna is in the advisory, but what&#039;s the advice about tuna steaks?&lt;/a&gt;
		&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;pane-6&quot;&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;Because tuna steak generally contains higher levels of mercury than canned light tuna, when choosing your two meals of fish and shellfish, you may eat up to 6 ounces (one average meal) of tuna steak per week.&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#pane-7&quot; title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot;&gt;7. What if I eat more than the recommended amount of fish and shellfish in a week?&lt;/a&gt;
		&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;pane-7&quot;&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;One week&#039;s consumption of fish does not change the level of methylmercury in the body much at all. If you eat a lot of fish one week, you can cut back for the next week or two. Just make sure you average the recommended amount per week.&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#pane-8&quot; title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot;&gt;8. Where do I get information about the safety of fish caught recreationally by family or friends?&lt;/a&gt;
		&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;pane-8&quot;&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;Before you go fishing, check your Fishing Regulations Booklet for information about recreationally caught fish. You can also contact your local health department for information about local advisories.&lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;p&gt;You need to check local advisories because some kinds of fish and shellfish caught in your local waters may have higher or much lower than average levels of mercury. This depends on the levels of mercury in the water in which the fish are caught. Those fish with much lower levels may be eaten more frequently and in larger amounts.&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#pane-9&quot; title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot;&gt;9. Further information&lt;/a&gt;
		&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;pane-9&quot;&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;For further information about the risks of mercury in fish and shellfish call the FDA&#039;s food information line toll-free at 1-888-SAFEFOOD or visit &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fda.gov/food/guidanceregulation/guidancedocumentsregulatoryinformation/seafood/ucm2006751.htm&quot;&gt;FDA&#039;s Food Safety website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;p&gt;For further information about the safety of locally caught fish and shellfish, visit the &lt;a href=&quot;/choose-fish-and-shellfish-wisely/fish-and-shellfish-advisories-and-safe-eating-guidelines&quot;&gt;EPA&#039;s Fish Advisory website&lt;/a&gt; or contact your &lt;a href=&quot;https://fishadvisoryonline.epa.gov/Contacts.aspx&quot;&gt;State Fish Advisory Program&lt;/a&gt;. For information on EPA&#039;s actions to control mercury, visit &lt;a href=&quot;/mercury&quot;&gt;EPA&#039;s mercury website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;accordion-title&quot; href=&quot;#pane-10&quot; title=&quot;Click to expand description&quot;&gt;10. Background information about the advisory&lt;/a&gt;
		&lt;div class=&quot;accordion-pane&quot; id=&quot;pane-10&quot;&gt;
			&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/choose-fish-and-shellfish-wisely/consumption-advice-joint-federal-advisory-mercury-fish&quot;&gt;Fact Sheet: Background information on the FDA/EPA Consumer Advisory on Mercury in Fish and Shellfish&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
					The process used to develop and test the advisory message, a summary of the key messages and of differences between the current and previous advisories.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://fishadvisoryonline.epa.gov/Contacts.aspx&quot;&gt;Advisory programs in your State&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
					State and tribal environmental programs and departments of health issue fish consumption advisories for their waterbodies. The contacts page lists fish consumption advisory program contact information and links to fish consumption advice from states, tribes, and territories.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;li&gt;Technical Information
					&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/choose-fish-and-shellfish-wisely/mercury-fish-and-shellfish-technical-information&quot;&gt;Technical Memorandum: Origin of 1 meal / week Freshwater Fish Consumption Rate&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
							The national advisory includes advise on eating fish caught by family and friends from local waters. The national advice says that in the absence of local advise, you can eat up to 6 ounces (one average meal) per week of fish you catch from local waters, but do not consume any other fish during that week. This technical memorandum documents the derivation of the 6 ounces per week.&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/choose-fish-and-shellfish-wisely/mercury-fish-and-shellfish-technical-information&quot;&gt;National Mean Mercury Concentration in Tissues of Selected Fish&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
							This graph shows measured levels of mercury in a variety of fish species commonly caught during recreational and subsistence fishing activity.&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jul 2015 18:57:29 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>rkearney</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">101621 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Should I Eat the Fish I Catch Brochure</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/choose-fish-and-shellfish-wisely/should-i-eat-fish-i-catch-brochure</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;To learn more about preparing the fish you catch, view the brochures below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-167933&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-07/documents/english_updated_fishbrochure.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=1651130&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;English Brochure (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(1 pg, 2 MB)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-167937&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-07/documents/spanish_updated_fishbrochurespanish.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=1602394&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Spanish Brochure (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(1 pg, 2 MB)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2015 14:37:18 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>Anonymous</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">72435 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>What is EPA Doing to Protect You From Contaminated Fish and Shellfish?</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/choose-fish-and-shellfish-wisely/what-epa-doing-protect-you-contaminated-fish-and-shellfish</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;EPA collaborates with states and tribes and develops information to assist them in issuing local fish advisories. To support this effort, EPA conducts and publishes research on fish contamination and fish tissue analyses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA also works with &lt;a href=&quot;/fish-tech/fish-advisory-contacts-and-partners&quot;&gt;state, tribal and federal partners&lt;/a&gt; to provide information about what species of fish are safe to eat, and ultimately works to reduce contaminants in the environment and protect aquatic habitats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;div id=&quot;tabs&quot;&gt;
	&lt;ul class=&quot;vertical tabs&quot; id=&quot;tabsnav&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;menu-internal&quot; href=&quot;#tab-1&quot;&gt;Assisting with Advisories&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;menu-internal&quot; href=&quot;#tab-2&quot;&gt;Studying Levels of Contamination&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;menu-internal&quot; href=&quot;#tab-3&quot;&gt;Informing the Public&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;menu-internal&quot; href=&quot;#tab-4&quot;&gt;Reducing Contaminants in the Environment&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;menu-internal&quot; href=&quot;#tab-5&quot;&gt;Addressing Shellfish Contamination&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;div id=&quot;tab-1&quot;&gt;
		&lt;h2&gt;Assisting with Advisories&lt;/h2&gt;

		&lt;div class=&quot;figure image mode-full caption left&quot; style=&quot;width:250px&quot;&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-png view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:482px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Men on a boat studying fish for contamination&quot; title=&quot;Men on a boat studying fish for contamination&quot; height=&quot;362&quot; width=&quot;482&quot; class=&quot;media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2014-11/boat-studying-fish.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
			&lt;div class=&quot;figcaption&quot;&gt;Men on a boat studying fish for contamination&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;EPA provides guidance to states, territories and tribes about issuing fish consumption advisories when contaminant levels in fish or water bodies are unsafe. In addition, EPA encourages states to issue safe eating guidelines to inform the public about which fish species are safe to eat without consumption restrictions.&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;EPA generates fish tissue contaminant data in order to determine safe human consumption rates.&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;In addition, EPA also provides educational and outreach materials related to fish and shellfish consumption and informs people about advisories where they live.&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/choose-fish-and-shellfish-wisely/fish-and-shellfish-advisories-and-safe-eating-guidelines&quot;&gt;Fish and Shellfish Advisories&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

	&lt;div id=&quot;tab-2&quot;&gt;
		&lt;h2&gt;Studying Levels of Contamination&lt;/h2&gt;

		&lt;div class=&quot;figure image mode-full caption left&quot; style=&quot;width:250px&quot;&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-png view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:546px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Woman working on fish contaminants in a lab&quot; title=&quot;Woman working on fish contaminants in a lab&quot; height=&quot;364&quot; width=&quot;546&quot; class=&quot;media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2014-11/contamination-lab.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
			&lt;div class=&quot;figcaption&quot;&gt;Woman working on fish contaminants in a lab&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;EPA works internally and with partners to conduct a variety of fish contamination studies. These studies provide data about concentrations of chemicals in fish tissue.&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/fish-tech/studies-fish-tissue-contamination&quot;&gt;Fish Contamination Studies&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

	&lt;div id=&quot;tab-3&quot;&gt;
		&lt;h2&gt;Informing the Public&lt;/h2&gt;

		&lt;div class=&quot;figure image mode-full caption left&quot; style=&quot;width:250px&quot;&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-png view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:554px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Two boys holding small fish that they caught&quot; title=&quot;Two boys holding small fish that they caught&quot; height=&quot;368&quot; width=&quot;554&quot; class=&quot;media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2014-11/two-boys-fishing.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
			&lt;div class=&quot;figcaption&quot;&gt;Two boys holding small fish that they caught&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;EPA collaborates with other federal agencies, as well as states and tribes, to inform people about the recommended level of consumption for fish caught in local waters. The goal is to provide up to date information to officials responsible for issuing fish consumption advisories and safe eating guidelines to protect public health.&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;EPA has worked closely with the Food and Drug Administration to advise at‐risk populations such as women who may become pregnant, pregnant women, nursing mothers, and young children to avoid some types of fish and to eat fish and shellfish that are lower in mercury.&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/choose-fish-and-shellfish-wisely/stay-healthy-eating-fish-and-shellfish-wisely&quot;&gt;Stay Healthy by Eating Wisely&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;
		
		&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

	&lt;div id=&quot;tab-4&quot;&gt;
		&lt;h2&gt;Reducing Contaminants in the Environment&lt;/h2&gt;

		&lt;div class=&quot;figure image mode-full caption left&quot; style=&quot;width:250px&quot;&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-png view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:404px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Man in a kayak on a body of water&quot; title=&quot;Man in a kayak on a body of water&quot; height=&quot;274&quot; width=&quot;404&quot; class=&quot;media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2014-11/man-kayaking.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
			&lt;div class=&quot;figcaption&quot;&gt;Man in a kayak on a body of water&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;EPA also works to reduce contaminants in the environment to ensure the habitat health of fish populations and other aquatic wildlife. The issues that concern human health are integrally related to ecosystem health. Therefore, EPA is working to reduce contaminants such as pesticides, chemicals and toxics, waste, and excess nutrients – providing benefits for all.&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/environmental-topics&quot;&gt;Learn more about the issues EPA is addressing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

	&lt;div id=&quot;tab-5&quot;&gt;
		&lt;h2&gt;Addressing Shellfish Contamination&lt;/h2&gt;

		&lt;div class=&quot;figure image mode-full caption left&quot; style=&quot;width:250px&quot;&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-png view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:318px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;A pile of clams&quot; title=&quot;A pile of clams&quot; height=&quot;219&quot; width=&quot;318&quot; class=&quot;media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2014-11/clams.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
			&lt;div class=&quot;figcaption&quot;&gt;A pile of clams&lt;/div&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;Some health departments test shellfish harvested within their jurisdictions to monitor toxin levels and assess the risk for contamination. Depending on the results of such testing, recreational and commercial shellfish harvesting may be prohibited locally during periods of risk.&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;State and federal regulatory agencies also monitor reported cases of marine toxin poisoning and health departments investigate possible outbreaks and devise control measures.&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.chesapeakebay.net/managementstrategies/strategy/oyster&quot;&gt;Chesapeake Bay Program&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://yosemite.epa.gov/opa/admpress.nsf/d0cf6618525a9efb85257359003fb69d/67f99440176a6b7d85257e14006bf773!opendocument&quot;&gt;Puget Sound Shellfish Beds&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2014 21:27:29 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>rkearney</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">67293 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Stay Healthy by Eating Fish and Shellfish Wisely</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/choose-fish-and-shellfish-wisely/stay-healthy-eating-fish-and-shellfish-wisely</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;Fish are an important part of a healthy diet. They are a lean, low‐calorie source of protein. However, some fish may contain chemicals that could pose health risks if these fish are eaten in large amounts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr class=&quot;clear-both&quot; /&gt;&lt;div id=&quot;tabs&quot;&gt;
	&lt;ul class=&quot;vertical tabs&quot; id=&quot;tabsnav&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;menu-internal&quot; href=&quot;#tab-1&quot;&gt;Protect Yourself&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;menu-internal&quot; href=&quot;#tab-2&quot;&gt;Protect Your Children&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;div id=&quot;tab-1&quot;&gt;
		&lt;h2&gt;Protect Yourself&lt;/h2&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;EPA works to make information accessible in a variety of formats to encourage people to eat fish as part of a healthy diet. These resources provide information on specific fish species that are safer to eat.&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;h3&gt;&quot;Should I Eat the Fish I Catch&quot; Brochure&lt;/h3&gt;

		&lt;div class=&quot;figure image mode-full right&quot; style=&quot;width:225px&quot;&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg view-mode-teaser&quot; style=&quot;width:160px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Fisherman holding a salmon he just caught.&quot; height=&quot;236&quot; width=&quot;160&quot; class=&quot;media-element file-teaser&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/small/public/2015-07/stay_healthy_by_eating_wisely.jpg&quot; title=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this brochure is not to discourage you from eating fish. It is to help you select and prepare fish that are low in chemical pollutants. By following these recommendations, you and your family can continue to enjoy the benefits of eating fish.&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/choose-fish-and-shellfish-wisely/should-i-eat-fish-i-catch-brochure&quot;&gt;English&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/choose-fish-and-shellfish-wisely/should-i-eat-fish-i-catch-brochure&quot;&gt;Spanish&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;
		 

		&lt;h3 class=&quot;clear-both&quot;&gt;Fresh and Frozen Seafood: Selecting and Serving it Safely&lt;/h3&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;The Food and Drug Administration (FDA) has developed basic food safety tips for buying, preparing, and storing fish and shellfish to help you and your family safely enjoy the fine taste and good nutrition of seafood.&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fda.gov/Food/FoodborneIllnessContaminants/BuyStoreServeSafeFood/ucm077331.htm&quot;&gt;Food Facts from FDA&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;In addition, FDA and EPA issue advice on eating fish and shellfish for women about 16-49 years old, especially pregnant and breastfeeding women, and young children.&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/fish-tech/epa-fda-advice-about-eating-fish-and-shellfish&quot;&gt;EPA-FDA Advice about Eating Fish&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

	&lt;div id=&quot;tab-2&quot;&gt;
		&lt;h2&gt;Protect Your Children&lt;/h2&gt;

		&lt;div class=&quot;figure image mode-full left&quot; style=&quot;width:250px&quot;&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-png view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:275px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img height=&quot;182&quot; width=&quot;275&quot; class=&quot;media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2014-11/three-pregnant-women.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;The nutritional value of fish is important during growth and development before birth, in early infancy for breastfed infants, and in childhood. The health risks from mercury in fish and shellfish depend on the amount of fish and shellfish a person eats and the levels of mercury in the specific fish and shellfish. Some fish contain higher levels of mercury that may harm an unborn baby or young child&#039;s developing nervous system. To address this, EPA and the Food and Drug Administration (FDA) joined forces to provide advice on eating fish.&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;The EPA-FDA “Advice about Eating Fish: What Pregnant Women and Parents Should Know” includes a chart of more than 60 types of fish and shellfish grouped into “best choices,” “good choices” and “choices to avoid.”&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/fish-tech/epa-fda-advice-about-eating-fish-and-shellfish&quot;&gt;EPA-FDA Advice about Eating Fish&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The advice recommends that children eat 1 to 2 servings of fish each week from choices that are lower in mercury, but in smaller portion sizes than adults. Children who are 2 to 3 years old should eat 1 ounce per serving, 4 to 7 years old should eat 2 ounces per serving, 8 to 10 years old should eat 3 ounces per serving, and children 11 and older can eat adult-sized portions of 4 ounces.&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;Women who are pregnant, might become pregnant, or are breastfeeding should eat 2-3 servings of fish each week from the “best choices” group or 1 serving a week from the “good choices” group&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;hr class=&quot;clear-both&quot; /&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Want to learn more?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/fish-tech&quot;&gt;EPA&#039;s Technical Resources&lt;/a&gt; provides more information for fish tissue studies information and other fish consumption advisory data and reports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2014 19:16:42 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>rkearney</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">66947 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  </channel>
</rss>

<!-- Page cached by Boost @ 2017-01-26 12:14:17, expires @ 2017-01-27 12:14:17, lifetime 1 day -->