<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?><rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.epa.gov/feed/79093/rss.xml" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/" xmlns:og="http://ogp.me/ns#" xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#" xmlns:sioc="http://rdfs.org/sioc/ns#" xmlns:sioct="http://rdfs.org/sioc/types#" xmlns:skos="http://www.w3.org/2004/02/skos/core#" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#">
  <channel>
    <title>C-FERST</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/feed/79093/rss.xml</link>
    <description>Updated C-FERST content from the US Environmental Protection Agency</description>
    <language>en</language>
     <atom:link href="https://www.epa.gov/feed/79093/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      <item>
    <title>C-FERST Fact Sheet</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/c-ferst/c-ferst-fact-sheet</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;View a short overview of the Community-Focused Exposure and Risk Screening Tool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-316255&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-09/documents/c-ferst_fact_sheet.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=328332&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;C-FERST Fact Sheet (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(2 pp, 328 K, 
  September 2016)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;field field-name-field-document-description field-type-text field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    This fact sheet answers the questions: What is C-FERST? Who should use C-FERST? How do I learn to use C-FERST? What can I do with C-FERST?    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Mon, 19 Sep 2016 15:05:10 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cberg</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">160619 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>C-FERST Community Data Table Quick Start Guide</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/c-ferst/c-ferst-community-data-table-quick-start-guide</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;View a guide for creating and using the C-FERST Community Data Table.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-317509&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-09/documents/c-ferst_cdtquickstartguide_revised_cm508.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=1546656&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;C-FERST Community Data Table Quick Start Guide (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(7 pp, 2 MB, 
  9/12/2016)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;field field-name-field-document-description field-type-text field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    C-FERST Community Data Table (CDT) allows users to view data for their census tract. This guide will introduce the CDT and provide guidance on how to create a CDT.  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 14 Sep 2016 19:49:36 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cberg</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">160139 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>EPA and USGS scientists conduct study to determine prevalence of newly-emerging contaminants in treated and untreated drinking water</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/c-ferst/epa-and-usgs-scientists-conduct-study-determine-prevalence-newly-emerging-contaminants</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;Scientists from the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) and U.S. Geological Survey (USGS) are collaborating on a research study to determine the presence of contaminants of emerging concern in treated and untreated drinking water collected from 25 drinking water treatment plants from across the United States.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-306263&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-08/documents/epa_and_usgs_drinkingwater.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=85237&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;EPA-USGS Study: Newly-Emerging Contaminants in Treated and Untreated Drinking Water (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(2 pp, 85 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 02 Aug 2016 16:59:27 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>dholla02</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">156351 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Michigan : West Michigan Environmental Action Education Foundation (A Former EPA CARE Project)</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/c-ferst/michigan-west-michigan-environmental-action-education-foundation-former-epa-care-project</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;The summary and links below provide a description of a Grand Rapids, Michigan project that received a cooperative agreement from EPA’s former Community Action for a Renewed Environment (CARE) project in 2007. These case studies serve as historic references, and conditions since the project was funded may have changed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;box multi related-info right&quot;&gt;
	&lt;h2 class=&quot;pane-title&quot;&gt;West Michigan Environmental Action Education Foundation&lt;/h2&gt;

	&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://nepis.epa.gov/Exe/ZyPDF.cgi?Dockey=P1007VOV.pdf#page=9&quot;&gt;Promising Practices to Improve Community Performance and Sustainability - Tip 3: Focus Actions around Children’s Health Protection (PDF)&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(32 pp, 3.9 MB, &lt;a href=&quot;/home/pdf-files&quot;&gt;About PDF&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The resources developed for this project provide communities with information about ways that other communities have addressed environmental issues. Communities can use these project results to reduce environmental impacts, understand risks and become stewards of their own environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;West Michigan Environmental Action Education Foundation &lt;br /&gt;
	Grand Rapids, Michigan&lt;br /&gt;
	EPA Region 5&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The West Michigan Children’s Environmental Health Initiative (CEHI) is the recipient of a Level II CARE cooperative agreement.  Organized in July 2006, the CEHI is a collaborative body of nonprofit, community-based, and governmental organizations. The CEHI is leading a collaborative campaign to improve children’s environmental health and represents Kent County, located in west-center Michigan in Grand Rapids, roughly 30 miles east of Lake Michigan.  Grand Rapids population is 197,800 of which over a third are minorities.  While the project will serve households throughout Kent County, it will deliver focused educational and preventative services to households in Grand Rapids’ economically disadvantaged neighborhoods.  The project intends to provide an educational campaign about indoor and outdoor environmental risk factors that affect the health and the quality of life for children and families.  The project will also provide affordable strategies to reduce unnecessary exposure to indoor and outdoor environmental toxics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Established CARE Partnership:&lt;/em&gt;  West Michigan Environmental Action Council; Kent County Health Department; Asthma Network of West Michigan; the Sustainable Research Group; Our Kitchen Table; Michigan Department of Environmental Quality; Michigan Family Resources, Inc.; Healthy Homes Coalition of West Michigan; Michigan Department of Community Health; Metro Health Hospital; and the City of Grand Rapids.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;</description>
     <pubDate>Fri, 29 Jul 2016 19:11:36 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cberg</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">156195 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Hawaii: Ka Wai Ola O Waiance- The Living Waters of Waiance (A Former EPA CARE Project)</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/c-ferst/hawaii-ka-wai-ola-o-waiance-living-waters-waiance-former-epa-care-project</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;The summary and links below provide a description and documentation of a Kailua, Hawaii project that received a Level I cooperative agreement from EPA’s former Community Action for a Renewed Environment (CARE) project in &lt;a href=&quot;#2008&quot;&gt;2008&lt;/a&gt; and a Level II CARE cooperative agreement in &lt;a href=&quot;#2011&quot;&gt;2011&lt;/a&gt;. These case studies serve as historic references, and conditions since the project was funded may have changed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The resources developed for this project provide communities with information about ways that other communities have addressed environmental issues. Communities can use these project results to reduce environmental impacts, understand risks and become stewards of their own environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;2008&quot; name=&quot;2008&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Wai’anaee Coast Oahu (2008)&lt;br /&gt;
	Kailua, Hawaii&lt;br /&gt;
	EPA Region 9&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Wai’anaee Coast Oahu is the recipient of a Level I CARE cooperative agreement. The Pacific American Foundation (PAF) is a non-profit organization that will be the lead for the CARE Wai’anaee Coast Oahu project. PAF serves the interest of Native Hawaiians for the purpose of planning, conducting, or administering programs for the benefit of Native Hawaiians and Pacific Islanders.  The CARE project will assess the impact of humans and pollutants on four area streams -- Nanakuli, Ulehawa, Kaupuni, and Makaha -- by gathering and consolidating existing water quality data and conducting site walks to gather visual data. Some human activities in and near streams adversely affect the subsistence and recreation use of the Wai’anaee coast near-shore waters. Some of the environmental impacts are runoff from agricultural lands (which includes pollutants or toxics such as silt, herbicides, pesticides and animal wastes), runoff from urban lands (which include toxics such as oils, grease and paint products), pollution from dumping trash in streambeds, and bioaccumulation of mercury in fish along the Wai’anaee coast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Prospective CARE Partners:&lt;/em&gt; City &amp;amp; County of Honolulu Department of Environmental Services Storm Water System, Chaminade University Environmental Studies, Makaha.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;2011&quot; name=&quot;2011&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Ka Wai Ola O Waiance- The Living Waters of Waiance (2011)&lt;br /&gt;
	Kailua, Hawaii&lt;br /&gt;
	Region 9&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Representative Jordan talks with EPA and Ka Wai Ola O Waianae to discuss illegal dumping and non point source pollution along the Waianae Coast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://vimeo.com/36300682&quot;&gt;Episode 11 - Ka Wai Ola Waiance, Part 1 &lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Ka Wai Ola O Waiance-The Living Waters of Waiance project is the recipient of a Level II CARE cooperative agreement, building on a 2008 successful level I project. The Pacific American Foundation (PAF), a national nonprofit organization, will be the organization leading this project. PAF has emerged as one of the leaders in the Native Hawaiian community in developing culture and place-based educational curriculum (k-12), teacher professional development, mentoring and career planning. The district of Waianae is recognized as one of the six traditional districts on the Hawaiian island of Oahu. Within the Waianae district there are nine ahupuaa, four of the most populated are; Nankuli, Lualualei, Waianae and Makaha. The work proposed under this CARE level II proposal focuses on caring for the land and water resources of these four ahupuaa, designated in this proposal as the Waianae Coast. The people living along the Waianae Coast face many environmental justice issues. The high percentage of minority and low-income populations along the Waianae Coast, along with the co-location of a power plant, an industrial park, Waimanalo Gulch solid waste landfill, a construction-debris landfill, and several military-use areas, epitomizes an environmental injustice area. Two community liaisons that have lived along the Waianae Coast their entire lives engaged their community to form the Ka Wai Ola O Waianae advisory committee through outreach to family, friends and local leaders. Through community-based consensus, the advisory committee decided to combine some of the environmental issues and prioritize for action as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Illegal dumping in and near streams&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Inactive and active landfills&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Non-point source pollution into streams and ocean&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Ka Wai Ola O Waianae level II project will engage the community to care for their environment, educate the community on how their actions impact their environment and how they can mitigate those impacts, execute activities in the community to reduce pollutants and evaluate for success in changing behaviors and preventing future pollution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Established CARE Partners:&lt;/em&gt; State of Hawaii Department of Health, Schnitzer, Planning Solutions Incorporated, Leeward Kai Canoe Club, Boys &amp;amp; Girls Club of Hawaii, KAHEA-The Hawaiian-Environmental Alliance, and Kupu. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;</description>
     <pubDate>Fri, 29 Jul 2016 17:13:03 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cberg</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">156187 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>New Mexico: Northwest New Mexico Council of Governments / Connections, Inc. (A Former EPA CARE Project)</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/c-ferst/new-mexico-northwest-new-mexico-council-governments-connections-inc-former-epa-care-project</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;The summary and links below provide a description and documentation of a Gallup, New Mexico project that received a Level I cooperative agreement from EPA’s former Community Action for a Renewed Environment (CARE) project in &lt;a href=&quot;#2005&quot;&gt;2005&lt;/a&gt; and a Level II CARE cooperative agreement in &lt;a href=&quot;#2009&quot;&gt;2009&lt;/a&gt;. These case studies serve as historic references, and conditions since the project was funded may have changed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The resources developed for this project provide communities with information about ways that other communities have addressed environmental issues. Communities can use these project results to reduce environmental impacts, understand risks and become stewards of their own environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;2005&quot; name=&quot;2005&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The Northwest New Mexico Council of Governments (2005)&lt;br /&gt;
	Gallup, New Mexico&lt;br /&gt;
	EPA Region 6&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Northwest New Mexico Council of Governments (NWNMCOG) is the recipient of a Level I CARE cooperative agreement. The NWNMCOG covers a largely rural area with 220,000 people in 3 counties. This proposal focuses on a wide range of environmental issues that will be addressed in collaboration with Native American tribes, municipalities, small towns, and widely disbursed rural settlements in the region. The NWNMCOG will use CARE funding to address the contamination of soil, air, and water primarily caused by industrial processes such as uranium mining, oil and gas development, and power plant emissions. It will focus on environmental health concerns that have been identified, and additional concerns that will be identified in the CARE process. Five top concerns that have been identified in one of the counties are: 1) the lack of adequate solid waste disposal systems, which leads to dumping in arroyos and other areas, 2) a lack of good quality water, as well as inappropriate wastewater disposal, 3) environmental justice, 4) poor air quality caused by refinery and power plant emissions and windblown dust, and 5) concern about unfenced livestock not being cared for properly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Prospective CARE Partners:&lt;/em&gt; The New Mexico Environment Department (the Office of the Secretary and District 5); the McKinley Community Health Alliance; the Northwest New Mexico Community Development Corporation; the Cibola Health Council; the Four Corners Ozone Task Force; the San Juan Citizens Alliance; the Durango-McKinley Paper Company; the Pueblo of Zuni; Connections, Inc.; the McKinley Soil and Water Conservation District; Work in Beauty, Inc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;2009&quot; name=&quot;2009&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Connections, Inc. (2009)&lt;br /&gt;
	Gallup, New Mexico&lt;br /&gt;
	Region 6&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Connections Inc. is the recipient of Level II CARE funding. The title for this Level II project is Nanizhozhi Waste Stream Reduction and was originally part of the 2005 NW New Mexico Council of Governments CARE Level I project. This project is designed to help a community of small, isolated and economically disadvantaged communities, in the sparsely populated, rural and multi-jurisdictional region of McKinley County in northwest New Mexico. Goals include the following: achieve positive environmental change and stewardship, with limited resources and expertise; reduce the proliferation of solid waste in both the landfills and illegal dump sites; and ensure collaborative waste stream reduction. This will be achieved by creating a recycling program, which renders waste reduction profitable and convenient, and alternative energy and green technology initiatives, which reduce consumption of exhaustible and polluting natural resources, by making better use of recycled and inexhaustible and polluting natural resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Established CARE Partners:&lt;/em&gt; NWNM Solid Waste Authority, McKinley Citizens Recycling Council, Gallup Solar, Durango-McKinley Paper Company, NWNM Council of Governments, University of NM Gallop, Pueblo of Zuni, Navajo Nation Chapter, Catholic Indian Center, Youth Conservation Corps, McKinley Community Health Alliance, McKinley Water Board, U.S. Indian Health Service, Sandia National Labs, Eastern Navajo Dine Again, Catholic Indian Center, McKinley County Smart Growth, Nizhonigo Nahat&#039;a Consulting, Zeca Corporation, National Forest Service, NM Water Management, NW Clean &amp;amp; Beautiful, and Peabody Energy. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-306801&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-08/documents/northwest_new_mexico_2005_nmcog1_report-508.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=152882&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Final Report:  Northwest New Mexico Council of Governments / Connections, Inc. (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(29 pp, 153 K, 
  2009)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Fri, 29 Jul 2016 16:36:23 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>jquacken</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">156185 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Oklahoma: Cherokee Nation Health Services Cancer Programs (A Former EPA CARE Project)</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/c-ferst/oklahoma-cherokee-nation-health-services-cancer-programs-former-epa-care-project</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;The summary given below provides a description and documentation of a Cherokee Nation project that received a Level I cooperative agreement from EPA’s former Community Action for a Renewed Environment (CARE) project in 2006. These case studies serve as historic references, and conditions since the project was funded may have changed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The resources developed for this project provide communities with information about ways that other communities have addressed environmental issues. Communities can use these project results to reduce environmental impacts, understand risks and become stewards of their own environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Cherokee Nation&lt;br /&gt;
	Health Services Cancer Programs&lt;br /&gt;
	Tahlequah, Oklahoma &lt;br /&gt;
	EPA Region 6&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cherokee Nation (CN) is the recipient of a Level I CARE cooperative agreement Nestled in the northeast corner of Oklahoma, the Cherokee Nation boasts the mountainous terrain of the nearby Ozark Mountains as well as commercial and recreational waterways provided by the Arkansas and Illinois Rivers within its 14-county jurisdiction. The richness of the physical environment is undoubtedly a factor for the growth of industry within the Cherokee tribal jurisdiction.  Under the CARE grant, various communities within the Cherokee Nation plan to collaborate and focus on identifying sources of toxic exposure, risk reduction, and environmental improvement. Preliminary discussions have led one group to focus on addressing the problem of polluted runoff from the poultry farms in Delaware County; and another group is already focused on addressing the problem of methamphetamine pollution and particulate matter in Sequoyah County. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Prospective CARE Partners:&lt;/em&gt;  University of Oklahoma College of Public Health, Oklahoma State Department of Health, Oklahoma Department of Environmental Quality, various agencies within the Cherokee Nation organization, including Cherokee Nation Community Services and Cherokee Nation Environmental Programs, and Cherokee Nation Anti-Meth Coalition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;</description>
     <pubDate>Fri, 29 Jul 2016 02:04:52 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cberg</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">156135 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>California: Environmental Health Coalition  Clean Ports, Healthy Communities in San Diego (A Former EPA CARE Project)</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/c-ferst/california-environmental-health-coalition-clean-ports-healthy-communities-san-diego-former</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;The summary given below provides a description and documentation of a National City, California project that received a Level II cooperative agreement from EPA’s former Community Action for a Renewed Environment (CARE) project in 2009. These case studies serve as historic references, and conditions since the project was funded may have changed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The resources developed for this project provide communities with information about ways that other communities have addressed environmental issues. Communities can use these project results to reduce environmental impacts, understand risks and become stewards of their own environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Environmental Health Coalition &lt;br /&gt;
	Clean Ports, Healthy Communities in San Diego&lt;br /&gt;
	National City, California &lt;br /&gt;
	Region 9&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Environmental Health Coalition (EHC) is a recipient of a CARE Level II cooperative agreement grant.  EHC is a non profit organization whose purpose is to empower the community and various stakeholders in order to achieve environmental and social justice. The Clean Ports, Healthy Communities in San Diego project targets the Barrio Logan and Old Town National City areas located along San Diego Bay’s working waterfront. This area is comprised of primarily low-income and Latino residents. The project area is located along the San Diego waterfront between downtown San Diego to the north and the City of Chula Vista to the south. Of Barrio Logan’s 4,045 residents, 24% are people of color, 9% live in poverty. Old Town’s population is also low income and a predominately Latino community with 85% of the residents people of color and 20% living in poverty.  EHC will implement risk reduction activities in order to accomplish its plans by 2012. The first goal is to reduce exposure to diesel emissions in the project area by 15%. The second goal is to reduce exposure to air pollution from industries in residential sections of the project area by 20%.  In addition, EHC’s program will monitor and evaluate the implementation of the community and port plans.     &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Established CARE Partners: &lt;/em&gt;Kimball Elementary, San Diego Unified School District, San Diego Community College, San Diego-Imperial Counties Labor Council, International Longshoremen Workers Union,  American Lung Association, Old Town Neighborhood Council, Working Waterfront Group, San Diego Tenants Association, National City Mayor, Old Town Smart Growth Coalition, Champion Real Estate, SoCall Chopper Shop, General Dynamics, Continental Maritime, Center City Development Corporation, United States Navy, Southeastern San Diego Planning Committee, San Diego Association of Governments, Chesapeake Fish Company, Dixieline Lumber and Home Services, Dole Fresh Fruit, Goodrich Corporation, and Dynegy, Inc.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;</description>
     <pubDate>Fri, 29 Jul 2016 01:30:05 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cberg</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">156133 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Alaska: Nunakauyarmiut Tribe Protecting our Health (A Former EPA CARE Project)</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/c-ferst/alaska-nunakauyarmiut-tribe-protecting-our-health-former-epa-care-project</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;The summary given below provides a description and documentation of a Toksook Bay, Alaska project that received a Level I cooperative agreement from EPA’s former Community Action for a Renewed Environment (CARE) project in &lt;a href=&quot;#2006&quot;&gt;2006&lt;/a&gt; and a Level II CARE cooperative agreement in &lt;a href=&quot;#2009&quot;&gt;2009&lt;/a&gt;. These case studies serve as historic references, and conditions since the project was funded may have changed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The resources developed for this project provide communities with information about ways that other communities have addressed environmental issues. Communities can use these project results to reduce environmental impacts, understand risks and become stewards of their own environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;2006&quot; name=&quot;2006&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Nunakauyarmiut Tribe (2006)&lt;br /&gt;
	Toksook Bay, Alaska&lt;br /&gt;
	EPA Region 10&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;unakauyarmiut Tribe is the recipient of a Level I CARE cooperative agreement.   The Nunakauyarmiut Tribe is the federally recognized Tribal government in Toksook Bay which is one of the members of the Nelson Island Consortium (NIC) of Caninermiut and Qaluyaat Communities, the closest translation from Yup’ik to English is “Working Together to Keep the Coastal and Nelson Island Communities and Environment Clean.”   In addition to Toksook Bay, the NIC consists of six other tribal communities: Chefornak, Newtok, Nightmute, Umkumiut, Tununak, and Kipnuk.  The villages range in size from 232 to 690 and on average about 25 percent of the community members live below the national poverty line which is not adjusted to take the high cost of living in “roadless” western Alaska into account.  This funding will allow the NIC and the Nunauyarmiut Tribe to work together to meet CARE project goals in Toksook Bay and other Nelson Island communities.  For thousands of years, the peoples of these communities have shared the Nelson Island area lands and waters for subsistence activities and have led a traditional subsistence way of life, including the retention of Yup’ik as their primary language.  The subsistence lands encompass much of the Yukon Delta National Wildlife Refuge.  The communities comprise several of the last few Native communities whose daily language for children, adults and elders is Yup’ik and who lead a fully traditional lifestyle.  Objectives include identifying, prioritizing, and reducing toxics through increased community participation in existing or planned programs and building sustainable community-based partnerships. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Prospective CARE Partners:&lt;/em&gt; Chefornak Clinic, Chefornak School, State Department of Transportation, City of Chefornak, Village of Chefornak Tribal Council, Chefarnrmute Incorporated, Chaputnguak School, Newtok Corporation, Newtok Village Council, Newtok Clinic, Tom’s Store, Ungusraq Power Company, Tununak IRA Council, Paul T. Albert Memorial School, City of Nightmute, Nightmute Power Plant, Chinuruk Incorporated, Nightmute Traditional Council, Umkumiut Village Council, Nightmute Post Office, Nightmute Health Clinic, Nightmute School, Nightmute Enterprises, City of Toksook Bay, Nunakauiak Yupik Corporation, Nunakauyak Traditional Council, Toksook Post Office, Toksook Bay Clinic, Kipnuk Village Council, Association of Village Council Presidents, Natural Resource Conservation Service, Coastal Village Relief Fund, City of Bethel Recycling, US Fish and Wildlife ServiceYukon Delta National Wildlife Refuge, Yukon Kuskokwim Health Corporation, Lower Kuskokwim School District, NOAA, World Wildlife Fund, University of Alaska: Bethel Kuskokwim Campus, and University of Alaska Fairbanks programs: AMAP, Cold Climate Research, Arctic Climate Research Center. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h3&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;2009&quot; name=&quot;2009&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Nunakauyarmiut Tribe (Nunakauyak Traditional Council)  (2009)&lt;br /&gt;
	Protecting our Health:  Implementing a Sustainable Collaborative Approach to Addressing our Priority Toxic Issues, Nelson Island Consortium, Alaska&lt;br /&gt;
	Toksook Bay, Alaska &lt;br /&gt;
	Region 10&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Nunakauyarmiut Tribe, a successful CARE Level I recipient in 2006, has now received a CARE Level II cooperative agreement grant.  Nunakauyak Traditional Council (NTC) is the governing body for the federally recognized Nunakauyarmiut Tribe of Toksook Bay – one of the Nelson Island Consortium members.  Nelson Island and the nearby coastal region are comprised of rural tribal community villages representing a geographic boundary that is both a watershed and traditional-shared land.  These communities, ranging in size from 232 to 690, are several of the last few Native villages whose daily language for children, adults and elders is Yup’ik and who lead a fully traditional subsistence lifestyle.   This grant serves 2,617 people. Of these over 98% are Alaska Native and an average of 25% live below the national poverty line.  The CARE Level I process allowed these Yup’ik villages to collaborate together at the local level to determine risks and strategies concerning environmental hazards.  NTC will execute strategic initiatives that address the priority risks identified through the CARE Level I project, resulting in substantial reduction of those risks. NTC plans to focus on lead acid batteries, household batteries, fluorescent lights, freon gas, and lead weight sinkers. These forms of waste are specifically targeted because they are being discarded at open dump sites and/or subsistence camps potentially exposing children and adults to harmful toxics such as heavy metals, mercury, freon gas, and lead.  NTC will also develop the sustainability of the collaborative partnership that has been initiated with local, regional, state, and federal stakeholders.  Their project will address the multiple environmental stressors that plague the Nelson Island Consortium communities and threaten their unique traditional lifestyle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Established CARE Partners:  Agency for Toxic Substances and Disease Registry, Alaska Health Department, NOAA/National Weather Service, Coastal Villages Region Fund, Association of Village Council Presidents, Cities of Chefornak, Nightmute, and Toksook Bay, Chefornak Post Office, Lower Kuskokwim School District, Local Schools, Chefarnrmute Incorporated and other Local Stores, all Councils in communities of Toksook Bay, Tununak, Nightmute, Chefornak, Newtok, Kipnuk, Umkumiut.    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;</description>
     <pubDate>Fri, 29 Jul 2016 01:05:37 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cberg</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">156131 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  </channel>
</rss>

<!-- Page cached by Boost @ 2017-01-25 16:30:25, expires @ 2017-01-26 04:30:25, lifetime 12 hours -->