<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?><rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.epa.gov/feed/65077/rss.xml" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/" xmlns:og="http://ogp.me/ns#" xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#" xmlns:sioc="http://rdfs.org/sioc/ns#" xmlns:sioct="http://rdfs.org/sioc/types#" xmlns:skos="http://www.w3.org/2004/02/skos/core#" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#">
  <channel>
    <title>Air Emission Measurement Center (EMC)</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/feed/65077/rss.xml</link>
    <description>Updated Air Emission Measurement Center (EMC) content from the US Environmental Protection Agency</description>
    <language>en</language>
     <atom:link href="https://www.epa.gov/feed/65077/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      <item>
    <title>Frequent Questions About the EMC</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/emc/frequent-questions-about-emc</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;Frequent Questions about the Air Emission Measurement Center (EMC)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-323113&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-10/documents/emc-faqs.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=112427&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Frequent Questions about the Air Emission Measurement Center (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(4 pp, 112 K, 
  Oct 5, 2016)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 12 Oct 2016 18:35:26 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>rcopland</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">162487 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>EMC Compliance Assurance Monitoring</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/emc/emc-compliance-assurance-monitoring</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;The Compliance Assurance Monitoring, or CAM, rule is designed to satisfy the requirements for monitoring and compliance certification in the Part 70 operating permits program and Title VII of the 1990 Clean Air Act Amendments. The CAM rule includes a new Part 64 and associated revisions to the Part 70 (permits program) monitoring and compliance certification requirements. The rule would establish criteria that define the monitoring, reporting, and record keeping that should be conducted by a source to provide a reasonable assurance of compliance with emission limitations and standards. These criteria address defining the applicable monitoring approach, obligation to complete corrective actions as indicated by the monitoring results, and how such data are used in the annual compliance certification.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The applicable monitoring approach for any operation or facility depends on the control technology used to meet the applicable emission limit and includes monitoring of operational and control device parameters indicative of pollution control performance and record keeping of work practice and inspection procedures necessary to assure compliance operation. The final CAM Rule was published in the Federal Register on October 22, 1997.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information, see &lt;a href=&quot;/air-emissions-monitoring-knowledge-base/compliance-assurance-monitoring&quot;&gt;Air Emissions Monitoring Knowledge Base - Compliance Assurance Monitoring&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Mon, 12 Sep 2016 18:58:38 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>jashley</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">159927 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>EMC Instructional Material</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/emc/emc-instructional-material</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/emc/emc-guideline-documents&quot;&gt;Guideline Documents&lt;/a&gt; - These documents were developed to clarify undefined technical areas of methods and performance specifications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/emc/emc-technical-information-documents&quot;&gt;Information Documents&lt;/a&gt; - These documents provide technical information necessary for regulatory agencies to make decisions about acceptance of data and alternative methods and monitoring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/emc/emc-workshop-and-meeting-materials&quot;&gt;Meetings, Conferences, Workshops&lt;/a&gt; - A list of upcoming and past meetings, conferences, and workshops presented by the Emission Measurement Center.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 07 Sep 2016 15:29:51 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>rcopland</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">159467 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Procedure 5 Quality Assurance Requirements For Vapor Phase Mercury Continuous Emissions Monitoring Systems And Sorbent Trap Monitoring Systems Used For Compliance Determination At Stationary Sources</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/emc/procedure-5-quality-assurance-requirements-vapor-phase-mercury-continuous-emissions-monitoring-0</link>
    <description>&lt;h2&gt;Applicable Performance Specifications&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/emc/performance-specification-12a-mercury&quot;&gt;PS-12A Mercury&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/emc/performance-specification-12b-mercury-sorbent-trap&quot;&gt;PS-12 Mercury - Sorbent Trap&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Procedure&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-312101&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-08/documents/appfproc5.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=38932&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Procedure 5 - Quality Assurance Requirements For Vapor Phase Mercury Continuous Emissions Monitoring Systems And Sorbent Trap Monitoring Systems Used For Compliance Determination At Stationary Sources (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(7 pp, 39 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 30 Aug 2016 13:35:00 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>aingram</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">158899 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Performance Specifications and Other Monitoring Information</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/emc/performance-specifications-and-other-monitoring-information</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;This page includes information related to &lt;a href=&quot;#performance&quot;&gt;Performance Specifications&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;#cem&quot;&gt;other monitoring information&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This other monitoring information includes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#cem&quot;&gt;Continuous Emission Monitoring&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#cam&quot;&gt;Compliance Assurance Monitoring&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#metals&quot;&gt;Metals and Mercury Emissions Monitoring&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;performance&quot; name=&quot;performance&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Performance Specifications&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div&gt;Performance specifications are used for evaluating the acceptability of the CEMS at the time of or soon after installation and whenever specified in the regulations. Quality assurance procedures in 40 CFR Part 60 Appendix F are used to evaluate the effectiveness of quality control (QC) and quality assurance (QA) procedures and the quality of data produced by any CEMS that is used for determining compliance with the emission standards on a continuous basis as specified in the applicable regulation.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	Performance Specifications are divided into:&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/emc/emc-performance-specifications&quot;&gt;Promulgated Performance Specifications&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/emc/emc-performance-specifications#proposedspecs&quot;&gt;Proposed Performance Specifications&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Other Monitoring Information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;cem&quot; name=&quot;cem&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Continuous Emission Monitoring&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A continuous emission monitoring system (CEMS) is the total equipment necessary for the determination of a gas or particulate matter concentration or emission rate using pollutant analyzer measurements and a conversion equation, graph, or computer program to produce results in units of the applicable emission limitation or standard. CEMS are required under some of the EPA regulations for either continual compliance determination or determination of exceedances of the standards. The individual subparts of the EPA rules specify the reference methods that are used to substantiate the accuracy and precision of the CEMS. A predictive emission monitoring system (PEMS) is the total equipment necessary for the determination of a gas concentration or emission rate using processor control device operating parameter measurements and a conversion equation, a graph, or computer program to produce results in units of the applicable emission limitation or standard. A performance specification for PEMS, &lt;a href=&quot;/emc/performance-specification-16-predictive-emissions-monitoring-systems&quot;&gt;Performance Specification 16&lt;/a&gt;, was finalized in March of 2009.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/emc/emc-continuous-emission-monitoring-systems&quot;&gt;CEMS Documents&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;cam&quot; name=&quot;cam&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Compliance Assurance Monitoring&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Compliance Assurance Monitoring, or CAM, rule is designed to satisfy the requirements for monitoring and compliance certification in the Part 70 operating permits program and Title VII of the 1990 Clean Air Act Amendments. The CAM rule includes a new Part 64 and associated revisions to the Part 70 (permits program) monitoring and compliance certification requirements. The rule would establish criteria that define the monitoring, reporting, and record keeping that should be conducted by a source to provide a reasonable assurance of compliance with emission limitations and standards. These criteria address defining the applicable monitoring approach, obligation to complete corrective actions as indicated by the monitoring results, and how such data are used in the annual compliance certification. The applicable monitoring approach for any operation or facility depends on the control technology used to meet the applicable emission limit and includes monitoring of operational and control device parameters indicative of pollution control performance and record keeping of work practice and inspection procedures necessary to assure compliance operation. The final CAM Rule was published in the Federal Register on October 22, 1997.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/emc/emc-compliance-assurance-monitoring&quot;&gt;CAM Documents&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;metals&quot; name=&quot;metals&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Metals and Mercury Emissions Monitoring&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Metals Monitoring: In 1996&lt;a href=&quot;https://www3.epa.gov/ttn/emc/propperf/ps-10.pdf&quot;&gt; Performance Specification 10 (PDF)&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;11pp, 42K, 1996)&lt;/span&gt; was proposed in conjunction with the original Hazardous Waste Combustor NESHAP, but because the measurement technology had not been fully developed and demonstrated, the specification was not promulgated. More recently, EPA has evaluated, at several facilities, a commercial version of an x-ray fluorescence metals CEMS capable of measuring most of the MACT hazardous metals in nearly real time (the instrument was built by a small business instrument developer, Cooper Environmental). Eli Lilly Company received approval from the EPA to use this instrument as a CEMS as an alternative in lieu of parameter monitoring on a hazardous waste incinerator. Lilly invested in much laboratory and field work to prove to the EPA that their CEMS is accurate, reliable, and verifiable. The US Army has successfully installed and evaluated one of these CEMS on a hazardous waste incinerator. These studies resulted in several monitoring methods and performance standards for the x-ray technology. These documents may be found under the &lt;a href=&quot;/emc/emc-other-test-methods&quot;&gt;Other Methods&lt;/a&gt; section of this web site.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	The EMC is presently evaluating ambient fence line multimetals monitoring for compliance determination, ambient health exposure studies, and for locating and evaluating unknown sources of metals emissions. The knowledge gained from, and the success of, the Lilly study has provided support in the transition to a study of the fence line monitoring platform of this x-ray fluorescence technology. A stakeholder group has been formed to provide feedback to EMC on the project. A validation field study is underway in Missouri to compare the fence line monitor to existing PM-10 ambient monitors.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	Mercury Monitoring: Like Performance Specification 10, Performance Specification 12 for mercury (Hg) CEMS was also proposed in conjunction with the original Hazardous Waste Combustor NESHAP, but because the measurement technology was not fully developed nor demonstrated at that time, it was never promulgated. Between 2003 and 2005, Performance Specification 12A for Hg CEMS was proposed and promulgated in conjunction with the Clean Air Mercury Rule (CAMR) after extensive demonstration of Hg CEMS and identification of appropriate performance parameters. In 2007, CAMR was vacated by the DC Circuit Court, which called into question the legality of using Performance Specification 12A. It has since been re-proposed in conjunction with amendments to the Portland Cement NESHAP.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	In order to obtain high quality mercury monitoring data, it is necessary to have Hg calibration gas standards of known concentration and known uncertainty. EPA&#039;s Clean Air Markets Division, working with EPA&#039;s Office of Research and Development and EMC, have recently completed &lt;a href=&quot;/emc/interim-epa-traceability-protocols-qualification-and-certification-elemental-and-oxidized&quot;&gt;two interim EPA traceability protocols&lt;/a&gt; to establish procedures for the qualification and certification of elemental and oxidized Hg gas generators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 23 Aug 2016 17:20:16 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>rcopland</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">158367 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>EMC Test Methods</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/emc/emc-test-methods</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Test methods can be divided into several categories:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#A&quot;&gt;Category A: Methods Proposed or Promulgated in the FR&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#B&quot;&gt;Category B: Source Category Approved Alternative Methods&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#C&quot;&gt;Category C: Other Methods&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;div&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#D&quot;&gt;Category D: Historic Conditional Methods&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Interim Policy on Posting Methods&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A fundamental component of the EMC web site is to provide information regarding relevant methods and procedures for emission testing and monitoring. We have modified our presentation of these methods into four different categories. The categories are based on the legal status of the methods with regard to their application under federally enforceable regulations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each category is explained below and each includes stipulations for use of the methods included therein. Further provisions regarding the use of a specific method are contained within the applicability statement of the method. Please note that the guidance provided by these categories and methods is meant to supplement, not override the stationary source emission measurement requirements of Title 40 of the Codes of Federal Regulations (CFR) Parts 51, 60, 61, and 63.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;A&quot; name=&quot;A&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Category A: Methods Proposed or Promulgated in the FR&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These methods have been proposed or promulgated in the Federal Register and codified in the Code of Federal Regulations (CFR). They carry an xx, 1xx, 2xx, or 3 xx alphanumeric designation. The xx, 1xx, and 3xx numbered methods are directly cited by specific regulations for determining compliance under 40 CFR Parts 60, 61, and 63, and may be used by sources for application as cited by the regulations and the method itself without further EPA approval.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2xx series methods are promulgated to facilitate incorporation in applicable State Implementation Plans. The 2xx methods, like the xx, 1xx, and 3xx series methods, include quality control and quality assurance procedures that must be met.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA staff can provide technical support on all methods in this category.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/emc/emc-promulgated-test-methods&quot;&gt;List of specific promulgated test methods&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/emc/emc-proposed-test-methods&quot;&gt;List of specific proposed test methods&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;B&quot; name=&quot;B&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Category B: Source Category Approved Alternative Methods&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These methods are approved alternatives to the methods required by 40 CFR Parts 60, 61 and 63 as described by the General Provisions of the corresponding Parts and as further explained in a Federal Register notice dated January 30, 2007. As such, the methods may be used by sources for determining compliance with the requirements of these Parts per their specified applicability provisions without further EPA approval. The Administrator, or designee (currently Steffan Johnson, Group Leader of the Measurement Technology Group in the Air Quality Assessment Division of the Office of Air Quality Planning and Standards), has approved these methods for the specified applications; this approval has been documented through an official EPA letter. These methods include quality control and quality assurance procedures that must be met. The EPA staff may not necessarily be the technical experts on these methods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/emc/broadly-applicable-approved-alternative-test-methods&quot;&gt;Federal Register Notice and List of Source Category Approved Alternative Methods&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;C&quot; name=&quot;C&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Category C: Other Methods&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This category includes test methods which have not yet been subject to the Federal rulemaking process. Each of these methods, as well as the available technical documentation supporting them, have been reviewed by the Emission Measurement Center staff and have been found to be potentially useful to the emission measurement community. The types of technical information reviewed include field and laboratory validation studies; results of collaborative testing; articles from peer-reviewed journals; peer-review comments; and quality assurance (QA) and quality control (QC) procedures in the method itself. A table summarizing the available technical information for each method can be found at the link below. The EPA strongly encourages the submission of additional supporting field and laboratory data as well as comments in regard to these methods.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These methods may be considered for use in Federally enforceable State and local programs (e.g., Title V permits, State Implementation Plans (SIP)) provided they are subject to an EPA Regional SIP approval process or permit veto opportunity and public notice with the opportunity for comment. The methods may also be considered to be candidates to be alternative methods to meet Federal requirements under 40 CFR Parts 60, 61, and 63. However, they must be approved as alternatives under 60.8, 61.13, or 63.7(f) before a source may use them for this purpose. Consideration of a method&#039;s applicability for a particular purpose should be based on the stated applicability as well as the supporting technical information outlined in the table. The methods are available for application without EPA oversight for other non-EPA program uses including state permitting programs and scientific and engineering applications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As many of these methods are submitted by parties outside the Agency, the EPA staff may not necessarily be the technical experts on these methods. Therefore, technical support from EPA for these methods is limited, but the table contains contact information for the developers so that you may contact them directly. Also, be aware that these methods are subject to change based on the review of additional validation studies or on public comment as a part of adoption as a Federal test method, the Title V permitting process, or inclusion in a SIP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/emc/emc-other-test-methods&quot;&gt;List of Other Methods&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;D&quot; name=&quot;D&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Category D: Historic Conditional Methods&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This category includes methods that were categorized as conditional test methods before our method categories were revised. Because some of these methods have been cited in state rules and permits under their Conditional Test Method (CTM) designation, we have created a category for them and called it &quot;Historic Conditional Methods&quot;. This category is closed and no new methods will be added to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These CTMs have been evaluated by the Agency and may be applicable to one or more categories of stationary sources. The EPA confidence in a method included in this category is based upon review of various technical information including, but not limited to, field and laboratory validation studies; EPA understanding of the most significant quality assurance (QA) and quality control (QC) issues; and EPA confirmation that the method addresses these QA/QC issues sufficiently to identify when the method may not be acquiring representative data. The method&#039;s QA/QC procedures are required as a condition of applicability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CTMs in Category D may be used by State and local programs in conjunction with Federally enforceable programs (e.g., Title V permits, State Implementation Plans (SIP)) provided they are subject to an EPA Regional SIP approval process or permit veto opportunity and public notice and opportunity for comment. They are available for application without EPA oversight for other non-EPA program uses including state permitting programs and scientific and engineering applications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The methods in Category D, however, must be approved as alternatives before a source may use them to meet Federal requirements under 40 CFR Part 60, 61, and 63. The EPA encourages the submission of additional field and laboratory data to further support a method.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The EPA staff may not necessarily be the technical experts on these methods. These methods are potentially subject to change based on the review of additional validation studies or on public comment as a part of adoption as a Federal test method (Category A).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/emc/emc-conditional-test-methods&quot;&gt;List of Historic Conditional Methods&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 23 Aug 2016 17:17:21 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>aingram</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">158365 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>EMC:  Metals and Mercury Emissions Monitoring</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/emc/emc-metals-and-mercury-emissions-monitoring</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Metals Monitoring:&lt;/strong&gt; In 1996 &lt;a href=&quot;https://www3.epa.gov/ttn/emc/propperf/ps-10.pdf&quot;&gt;Performance Specification 10 (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(11 pp, 42 K, April 1996)&lt;/span&gt; was proposed in conjunction with the original Hazardous Waste Combustor NESHAP, but because the measurement technology had not been fully developed and demonstrated, the specification was not promulgated. More recently, EPA has evaluated, at several facilities, a commercial version of an x-ray fluorescence metals CEMS capable of measuring most of the MACT hazardous metals in nearly real time (the instrument was built by a small business instrument developer, Cooper Environmental). Eli Lilly Company received approval from the EPA to use this instrument as a CEMS as an alternative in lieu of parameter monitoring on a hazardous waste incinerator. Lilly invested in much laboratory and field work to prove to the EPA that their CEMS is accurate, reliable, and verifiable. The US Army has successfully installed and evaluated one of these CEMS on a hazardous waste incinerator. These studies resulted in several monitoring methods and performance standards for the x-ray technology. These documents may be found under the &lt;a href=&quot;/emc/emc-other-test-methods&quot;&gt;Other Methods&lt;/a&gt; section of this web site.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	The EMC is presently evaluating ambient fence line multimetals monitoring for compliance determination, ambient health exposure studies, and for locating and evaluating unknown sources of metals emissions. The knowledge gained from, and the success of, the Lilly study has provided support in the transition to a study of the fence line monitoring platform of this x-ray fluorescence technology. A stakeholder group has been formed to provide feedback to EMC on the project. A validation field study is underway in Missouri to compare the fence line monitor to existing PM-10 ambient monitors.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mercury Monitoring:&lt;/strong&gt; Like Performance Specification 10, Performance Specification 12 for mercury (Hg) CEMS was also proposed in conjunction with the original Hazardous Waste Combustor NESHAP, but because the measurement technology was not fully developed nor demonstrated at that time, it was never promulgated. Between 2003 and 2005, Performance Specification 12A for Hg CEMS was proposed and promulgated in conjunction with the Clean Air Mercury Rule (CAMR) after extensive demonstration of Hg CEMS and identification of appropriate performance parameters. In 2007, CAMR was vacated by the DC Circuit Court, which called into question the legality of using Performance Specification 12A. It has since been re-proposed in conjunction with amendments to the Portland Cement NESHAP.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	In order to obtain high quality mercury monitoring data, it is necessary to have Hg calibration gas standards of known concentration and known uncertainty. EPA&#039;s Clean Air Markets Division, working with EPA&#039;s Office of Research and Development and EMC, have recently completed two &lt;a href=&quot;/emc/interim-epa-traceability-protocols-qualification-and-certification-elemental-and-oxidized&quot;&gt;interim EPA traceability protocols&lt;/a&gt; to establish procedures for the qualification and certification of elemental and oxidized Hg gas generators.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 23 Aug 2016 16:53:11 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>jcortely</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">158363 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Interim EPA Traceability Protocols for the Qualification and Certification of Elemental and Oxidized Mercury Gas Generators</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/emc/interim-epa-traceability-protocols-qualification-and-certification-elemental-and-oxidized</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;For regulatory purposes, mercury (Hg) calibration gas standards of known concentration and known uncertainty are needed to quality-assure data recorded by Hg continuous emission monitoring systems (CEMS) and measurements made with instrumental Hg reference test methods. Two interim EPA traceability protocols have been prepared that establish procedures for the qualification and certification of elemental and oxidized mercury gas generators. The interim protocols reflect the current state of development for generating and quantifying elemental Hg and mercuric chloride (HgCl2), a form of oxidized mercury.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The interim elemental Hg gas traceability protocol provides procedures to: (1) establish the quantitative output (i.e., “calibration”) of elemental Hg generators; and (2) determine the expanded, combined uncertainty values of the gas standards produced by the elemental Hg generators. The protocol also specifies the maximum allowable uncertainty for the elemental Hg gas standards. A Companion Document has also been prepared that summarizes the methodology used to calculate the certified elemental mercury gas concentrations and associated expanded, combined uncertainty values and includes example calculations of these certified gas concentrations and uncertainty values. Additionally, a series of generic elemental Hg generator spreadsheets have been prepared as templates for calculating these values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The interim oxidized Hg gas traceability protocol provides procedures for: (1) establishing the NIST traceability and quantitative performance of key components of HgCl2 generators; (2) determining the uncertainty contributed by each of these components; and (3) calculating certified output concentrations and expanded, combined uncertainty values for the gas standards produced by the generators. This protocol also specifies a target uncertainty for the HgCl2 gas standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For continuous emission monitoring system (CEMS) applications, these interim protocols apply only to Hg monitoring system span values greater than or equal to 5.0 micrograms per cubic meter (µg/m3).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have comments or questions regarding these files, please contact Scott Hedges by e-mail at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:hedges.scott@epa.gov&quot;&gt;hedges.scott@epa.gov,&lt;/a&gt; or by phone at 202-343-9622 or Robin Segall by e-mail at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:segall.robin@epa.gov&quot;&gt;segall.robin@epa.gov,&lt;/a&gt; or by phone at 919-541-0893. If possible, please submit your comments by e-mail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www3.epa.gov/ttn/emc/metals/ElemHgProtocol.pdf&quot;&gt;Interim EPA Traceability Protocol for Qualification and Certification of Elemental Mercury Gas Generators (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(39 pp, 178 K, 2009 &lt;a href=&quot;/home/pdf-files&quot;&gt;About PDF&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

		&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;A &lt;strong&gt;Companion Document&lt;/strong&gt; entitled, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www3.epa.gov/ttn/emc/metals/companiondoc.pdf&quot;&gt;Treatment of Elemental Mercury Gas Generator Certification Data and Calculation of Uncertainty in support of the Interim EPA Traceability Protocol for Qualification and Certification of Elemental Mercury Gas Generators. (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(20 pp, 215 K, &lt;a href=&quot;/home/pdf-files&quot;&gt;About PDF&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Five Generic Spreadsheet Files&lt;/strong&gt; to calculate the certified elemental mercury gas concentrations and associated uncertainty values: (Note: In addition to using these generic spreadsheets, it is recommended that you contact your specific mercury generator vendor to see if they have vendor-specific spreadsheets you can use.)
				&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www3.epa.gov/ttn/emc/metals/Certification.xls&quot;&gt;Certification from Bracketing (XLS)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(113 K)&lt;/span&gt;- This workbook can be used at several steps in the certification process (i.e., certifying Vendor Prime, Field Reference, or User generators), but is most likely to be used by a vendor, since its primary purpose is to bring together results from dual-bracketing or multi-bracketing certification procedures. It is not specific to the type of detection technology (such as a concentrating detector developed by Tekran or a continuous detector developed Thermo-Fisher Scientific). Vendors who do not have their own certification spreadsheet/software must use this workbook (along with the appropriate companion workbook below) for certifying Field Reference generators.&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www3.epa.gov/ttn/emc/metals/Concentrating.xls&quot;&gt;Concentrating Detector Bracketing Only (XLS)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(2.47 M)&lt;/span&gt; - This workbook processes the data from one bracketing procedure using a concentrating detector. It is not a stand-alone certification workbook. It is a companion to the &quot;Certification from Bracketing.xls&quot; workbook which receives processed data from two or more &quot;Bracketing only&quot; workbooks to certify generators. Vendors are the most likely users (using it to certify Field Reference generators), though field analysts may choose this certification option for User generators (e.g., if incorporating the Type-B default reproducibility causes the target uncertainty to be exceeded).&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www3.epa.gov/ttn/emc/metals/Continuous.xls&quot;&gt;Continuous Detector Bracketing Only (XLS)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(738 K)&lt;/span&gt; - This workbook processes the data from one bracketing procedure using a continuous detector. It is not a stand-alone certification workbook. It is a companion to the &quot;Certification from Bracketing.xls&quot; workbook which receives processed data from two or more &quot;Bracketing only&quot; workbooks to certify generators. Vendors are the most likely users (using it to certify Field Reference generators), though field analysts may choose this certification option for User generators (e.g., if incorporating the Type-B default reproducibility causes the target uncertainty to be exceeded).&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www3.epa.gov/ttn/emc/metals/UserGenConcentr.xls&quot;&gt;User Generator Certification with Concentrating Detector (XLS)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(2.50 M) &lt;/span&gt;- The primary purpose of this workbook is to provide a time-efficient option for certifying User generators in the field, though the interim elemental Hg gas protocol does not currently prohibit its use for certifying User generators at vendor facilities. The workbook is specific to concentrating detectors. It can not be used to certify Vendor Prime or Field Reference generators, because it only supports the Type-B default reproducibility calculation.&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www3.epa.gov/ttn/emc/metals/UserGenContin.xls&quot;&gt;User Generator Certification with Continuous Detector (XLS)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(782 M) &lt;/span&gt;- The primary purpose of this workbook is to provide a time-efficient option for certifying User generators in the field, though the interim protocol does not currently prohibit its use for certifying User generators at vendor facilities. The workbook is specific to continuous detectors. It can not be used to certify Vendor Prime or Field Reference generators, because it only supports the Type-B default reproducibility calculation.&lt;br /&gt;
						 &lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www3.epa.gov/ttn/emc/metals/OxHgProtocol.pdf&quot;&gt;Interim EPA Traceability Protocol for Qualification and Certification of Oxidized Mercury Gas Generators (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(30 pp, 200 K, 2009, &lt;a href=&quot;/home/pdf-files&quot;&gt;About PDF&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 23 Aug 2016 16:50:49 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>aingram</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">158361 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>EMC 2017 Measurement Technology Workshop</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/emc/emc-2017-measurement-technology-workshop</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;The 2017 Measurement Technology Workshop will be held January 24-26, 2017 at the EPA facility at 109 T.W. Alexander Drive, Research Triangle Park, North Carolina. The workshop is an opportunity for EPA Regional, State, local and tribal regulatory personnel to get together to learn about what is going on new in the stationary source world. It is an informal workshop that encourages an interactive exchange of ideas and experiences. The workshop is restricted to only regulatory agency personnel so everyone can talk freely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Included with this workshop announcement is a copy of the agenda for you to review. To register for the workshop please fill out the registration form and email to Candace Sorrell at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:sorrell.candace@epa.gov&quot;&gt;sorrell.candace@epa.gov&lt;/a&gt;. Here is also a link to a list of hotels in the Research Triangle Park. This is not a complete list but will provide you with some information. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.niehs.nih.gov/careers/assets/docs/hotels_in_the_research_triangle_park_area_508.pdf&quot;&gt;https://www.niehs.nih.gov/careers/assets/docs/hotels_in_the_research_triangle_park_area_508.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	Below is information about the current ID requirements for accessing a Federal facility. Here is a link to the latest information. &lt;a href=&quot;/aboutepa/visiting-epa-headquarters&quot;&gt;https://www.epa.gov/aboutepa/visiting-epa-headquarters&lt;/a&gt; Please review to make sure you have acceptable ID before coming to the workshop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have any questions concerning the workshop please contact Candace Sorrell at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:sorrell.candace@epa.gov&quot;&gt;sorrell.candace@epa.gov&lt;/a&gt; or Kim Garnett at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:garnett.kim@epa.gov&quot;&gt;garnett.kim@epa.gov&lt;/a&gt;. Look forward to seeing many of you at the workshop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-306309&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-08/documents/agenda-for-2017-measurement-technology-workshop.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=13390&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Agenda for 2017 Measurement Technology Workshop (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(3 pp, 13 K, 
  Aug 2, 2016)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-306313&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-08/documents/registration-for-2017-measurement-technology-workshop.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=95792&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Registration for 2017 Measurement Technology Workshop (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(1 pg, 96 K, 
  Aug 2, 2016)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 02 Aug 2016 18:02:07 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>rcopland</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">156365 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  </channel>
</rss>

<!-- Page cached by Boost @ 2017-01-25 17:39:21, expires @ 2017-01-26 05:39:21, lifetime 12 hours -->