<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?><rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.epa.gov/feed/148801/rss.xml" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/" xmlns:og="http://ogp.me/ns#" xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#" xmlns:sioc="http://rdfs.org/sioc/ns#" xmlns:sioct="http://rdfs.org/sioc/types#" xmlns:skos="http://www.w3.org/2004/02/skos/core#" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#">
  <channel>
    <title>Air Emissions Monitoring Knowledge Base</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/feed/148801/rss.xml</link>
    <description>Updated Air Emissions Monitoring Knowledge Base content from the US Environmental Protection Agency</description>
    <language>en</language>
     <atom:link href="https://www.epa.gov/feed/148801/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      <item>
    <title>Summary of Monitoring Requirements for Printing and Publishing NSPS and NESHAP</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/air-emissions-monitoring-knowledge-base/summary-monitoring-requirements-printing-and-publishing-nsps</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;The key monitoring requirements of the NSPS and NESHAP for the printing and publishing industry are summarized in a table.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-288741&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-05/documents/rulecomparisons.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=190538&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Summary of Monitoring Requirements for Printing and Publishing NSPS and NESHAP (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(6 pp, 191 K, 
  2003)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Fri, 27 May 2016 14:09:52 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>aingram</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">150631 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Study Supporting Innovative Air Permits</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/air-emissions-monitoring-knowledge-base/study-supporting-innovative-air-permits</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;One of the objectives of smart permits is to &quot;streamline&quot; requirements; that is to include only the most stringent requirement in the permit. This situation can apply to monitoring requirements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA conducted a study to evaluate six of the pilot innovative permits that had been implemented; the results of this study are documented in a series of reports. The report series includes a summary report entitled &quot;Evaluation of Implementation Experiences with Innovative Air Permits,&quot; as well as separate implementation review reports for each of the six permits evaluated. These white papers and reports are accessible via the links listed below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-171601&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-08/documents/wtppr-2.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=170466&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;White Paper Number 2 for Improved Implementation of The Part 70 Operating Permits Program (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(6 pp, 170 K)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;field field-name-field-document-description field-type-text field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    This document is part of the Title V Policy and Guidance Database  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-191429&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-09/documents/eval-implementation-experiences-innovative-air-permits.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=155787&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Evaluation of Implementation Experiences with Innovative Air Permits: Results of the U.S. EPA Flexible Permit Implementation Review (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(52 pp, 156 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-288429&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-05/documents/iap_eietm.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=6745&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;EPA Flexible Permit Implementation Review Initiative Report - Transmittal Memo (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(2 pp, 7 K, 
  2002)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-288443&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-05/documents/iap_3mprr.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=143036&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;EPA Flexible Permit Implementation Review: 3M Permit Review Report (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(47 pp, 143 K, 
  2002)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-288451&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-05/documents/iap_dcprr.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=149321&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;EPA Flexible Permit Implementation Review: DaimlerChrysler Permit Review Report (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(47 pp, 149 K, 
  2002)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-288459&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-05/documents/iap_inprr.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=127978&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;EPA Flexible Permit Implementation Review: Intel Permit Review Report (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(41 pp, 128 K, 
  2002)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-288465&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-05/documents/iap_iprr.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=143333&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;EPA Flexible Permit Implementation Review: Imation Permit Review Report (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(48 pp, 143 K, 
  2002)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-288469&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-05/documents/iap_lprr.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=132009&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;EPA Flexible Permit Implementation Review: Lasco Permit Review Report (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(39 pp, 132 K, 
  2002)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-288471&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-05/documents/iap_sprr.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=142671&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;EPA Flexible Permit Implementation Review: Saturn Permit Review Report (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(46 pp, 143 K, 
  2002)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 26 May 2016 15:16:27 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>aingram</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">150521 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Publications Supporting Air Emissions Monitoring</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/air-emissions-monitoring-knowledge-base/publications-supporting-air-emissions-monitoring</link>
    <description>&lt;h2&gt;Clean Air Act Amendments&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Clean Air Act (CAA) of 1970 set a national agenda for identifying areas of the nation with unhealthy air quality. It also established specific responsibilities for government and industry to promote healthy air quality nationwide. Twenty years later, the 1990 CAA Amendments (CAAA) clarified the direction for many of the established nationwide clean air programs and set out additional clean air program requirements deemed necessary to achieve the national agenda identified in 1970.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The CAA consists of sections, known as Titles, which direct: 1) EPA to establish national standards for ambient air quality, and 2) EPA and the States to implement, maintain, and enforce these standards through a variety of mechanisms. The CAA regulations appear in the Code of Federal Regulations (CFR) under 40 CFR Parts 50-99.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clean-air-act-overview/clean-air-act-text&quot;&gt;Learn more about the Clean Air Act&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/clean-air-act-overview/1990-clean-air-act-amendment-summary&quot;&gt;Learn more about the 1990 CAA Amendments (CAAA)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Compliance Assurance Monitoring (CAM) Technical Guidance Document &lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Compliance Assurance Monitoring, or CAM, rule is designed to satisfy the requirements for monitoring and compliance certification in the Part 70 operating permits program and Title VII of the 1990 Clean Air Act Amendments. The CAM rule includes a new Part 64 and associated revisions to the Part 70 (permits program) monitoring and compliance certification requirements. The rule establishes criteria that define the monitoring, reporting, and record keeping to be conducted by a source to provide a reasonable assurance of compliance with emission limitations and standards. These criteria address: 1) defining the applicable monitoring approach, 2) the obligation to complete corrective actions as indicated by the monitoring results, and 3) using the data in the annual compliance certification. The applicable monitoring approach for any operation or facility: 1) depends on the control technology used to meet the applicable emission limit, and 2) includes monitoring of operational control device parameters indicative of pollution control performance, and 3) includes record keeping of work practice and inspection procedures necessary to assure compliance operation. The final CAM Rule was published in the Federal Register on October 22, 1997.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	The &lt;a href=&quot;/air-emissions-monitoring-knowledge-base/compliance-assurance-monitoring-technical-guidance-document&quot;&gt;Compliance Assurance Monitoring (CAM) technical guidance document&lt;/a&gt; provides information on monitoring approaches for sources with active control devices (e.g., scrubbers, baghouses, thermal or catalytic oxidizers, or electrostatic precipitators).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gpo.gov/fdsys/pkg/FR-1997-10-22/pdf/97-27264.pdf&quot;&gt;The CAM Rule&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(48 pp, 408 K, &lt;a href=&quot;/home/pdf-files&quot;&gt;About PDF&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; - Federal Register - October 22, 1997&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 25 May 2016 15:55:05 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>aingram</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">150425 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Monitoring by Control Technique - Wet Scrubber For Particulate Matter</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/air-emissions-monitoring-knowledge-base/monitoring-control-technique-wet-scrubber-particulate-matter</link>
    <description>&lt;h2&gt;Description&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In wet scrubbing processes, liquid or solid particles are removed from a gas stream by transferring them to a liquid. The liquid most commonly used is water. A wet scrubber&#039;s particulate collection efficiency is directly related to the amount of energy expended in contacting the gas stream with the scrubber liquid. Most wet scrubbing systems operate with particulate collection efficiencies over 95 percent. Wet scrubbers can also be used to remove acid gas; however, this section addresses only wet scrubbers for control of particulate matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are three energy usage levels for wet scrubbers. A low energy wet scrubber utilizes pressure drops less than 5 inches of water column and are capable of efficiently removing particles greater than about 5-10 micrometers in diameter. A medium energy scrubber has a pressure drop from 5 to 25 inches of water column and is capable of removing micrometer-sized particles, but is not very efficient on sub-micrometer particles. A high energy scrubber expends the most energy and has a pressure drop of 25 to over 100 inches of water column, which is necessary to remove sub-micrometer particles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A spray tower scrubber is a low energy scrubber and is the simplest wet scrubber used for particulate control. It consists of an open vessel with one or more sets of spray nozzles to distribute the scrubbing liquid. Typically, the gas stream enters at the bottom and passes upward through the sprays. The particles are collected when they impact the droplets. This is referred to as counter-current operation. Spray towers can also be operated in a cross-current arrangement. In cross-current scrubbers, the gas flow is horizontal and the liquid sprays flow downward. Cross-current spray towers are not usually as efficient as counter-current units.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most common high energy wet scrubber is the venturi, although it can also be operated as a medium energy scrubber. In a fixed-throat venturi, the gas stream enters a converging section where it is accelerated toward the throat section. In the throat section, the high-velocity gas stream strikes liquid streams that are injected at right angles to the gas flow, shattering the liquid into small drops. The particles are collected when they impact the slower moving drops. Following the throat section, the gas stream passes through a diverging section that reduces the velocity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All wet scrubber designs incorporate mist eliminators or entrainment separators to remove entrained droplets. The process of contacting the gas and liquid streams results in entrained droplets, which contain the contaminants or particulate matter. The most common mist eliminators are chevrons, mesh pads, and cyclones. Chevrons are simply zig-zag baffles that cause the gas stream to turn several times as it passes through the mist eliminator. The liquid droplets are collected on the blades of the chevron and drain back into the scrubber. Mesh pads are made from interlaced fibers that serve as the collection area. A cyclone is typically used for the small droplets generated in a venturi scrubber. The gas stream exiting the venturi enters the bottom of a vertical cylinder tangentially. The droplets are removed by centrifugal force as the gas stream spirals upward to the outlet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wet scrubbing systems are susceptible to several operating problems. The most common of these include inadequate liquid flow, liquid re-entrainment, poor gas-liquid contact, corrosion, and plugged nozzles, beds, or mist eliminators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the types of wet scrubbers described above, there are condensation scrubbers, impingement plate scrubbers, mechanically-aided scrubbers, and orifice scrubbers. Descriptions of these scrubbers can be found from EPA Fact Sheets. Other specific information about wet scrubbers can be found from the EPA Air Pollution Control Cost Manual, Section 6, Chapter 2 – Wet Scrubbers (Sixth Edition).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information, see the box &lt;a href=&quot;/air-emissions-monitoring-knowledge-base/monitoring-control-technique-wet-scrubber-particulate-matter#box1&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;More about Wet Scrubber For Particulate Matter.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Monitoring Information&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div&gt;The primary indicators of wet scrubber performance are pressure differential, liquid flow rate, and scrubber liquid outlet concentration. The less significant indicators of gaseous pollutant control efficiency for wet scrubbers are gas flow rate, neutralizing chemical feed rate, and scrubber outlet gas temperature. Parameters to monitor as an alternative to scrubber liquid outlet concentration include scrubber liquid pH, scrubber liquid specific gravity, and scrubber makeup/blowdown rates. For systems that control gaseous streams with low particulate matter loadings, there is no advantage to monitoring the scrubbing liquid solids content.&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information, see the box &lt;a href=&quot;/air-emissions-monitoring-knowledge-base/monitoring-control-technique-wet-scrubber-particulate-matter#box2&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Monitoring and the CAM Rule.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Costs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Costs of wet scrubbers are discussed in the EPA Air Pollution Control Cost Manual&lt;sup&gt;*&lt;/sup&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www3.epa.gov/ttn/catc/dir1/cs6ch2.pdf&quot;&gt;Section 6, Chapter 2 - Wet Scrubbers (Sixth Edition)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(62 pp, 827 K, &lt;a href=&quot;/home/pdf-files&quot;&gt;About PDF&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;. Costs of monitoring systems, both Continuous Emission Monitors and parametric monitoring systems, are addressed in the EPA Air Pollution Control Cost Manual&lt;sup&gt;*&lt;/sup&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www3.epa.gov/ttn/catc/dir1/cs2ch4.pdf&quot;&gt;Section 2, Chapter 4 - Monitors&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(42 pp, 542 K, &lt;a href=&quot;/home/pdf-files&quot;&gt;About PDF&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;small&gt;*EPA is currently updating the Control Cost Manual. The most recent versions are available on the &lt;a href=&quot;/economic-and-cost-analysis-air-pollution-regulations/cost-reports-and-guidance-air-pollution&quot;&gt;Economic and Cost Analysis for Air Pollution Regulations website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 25 May 2016 14:55:56 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>aingram</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">150407 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Monitoring by Control Technique - Wet Scrubber For Gaseous Control</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/air-emissions-monitoring-knowledge-base/monitoring-control-technique-wet-scrubber-gaseous-control</link>
    <description>&lt;h2&gt;Description&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In wet scrubbing processes for gaseous control, a liquid is used to remove pollutants from an exhaust stream. The removal of pollutants in the gaseous stream is done by absorption. Wet scrubbers used for this type of pollutant control are often referred to as absorbers. Most absorbers have removal efficiencies in excess of 90 percent, depending on pollutant absorbed. The scrubbing liquid, usually water, is used to absorb the pollutant. Other liquids, such as dimethylaniline or amines, may be used as the absorbent for gases with low water solubility (i.e., hydrocarbons or hydrogen sulfide). The chosen absorbent should have a high solubility for the gaseous stream and should be relatively inexpensive. Wet scrubbers can also be used to remove particulate matter; however, this section addresses only wet scrubbers for gaseous control (e.g., acid gases, water soluble inorganic contaminants, and volatile organic compounds).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The driving force of the absorption process is related to the amount of soluble gas in the gas stream and the concentration of the solute gas in the liquid film in contact with the gas. When water is used as the absorbing material, other chemicals may be present to react with the pollutant being absorbed to reduce the concentration. Liquids other than water may require absorbent separation and scrubbing liquid regeneration to help lower costs of the scrubbing liquid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wet scrubbers utilize large surface areas to allow intimate contact between the liquid and gas stream. The creation of the large surface area is accomplished by passing the liquid over a variety of media (packing, meshing, grids, or trays) or by creating a spray of droplets. Wet scrubber designs include spray tower, tray-type, and packed-bed scrubbers, which are generally referred to as low-energy scrubbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Packed bed scrubbers are commonly used for gas absorption. This type of scrubber spreads the liquid over packing material in order to provide a large surface area for liquid/gas interaction. Packed bed scrubbers are classified according to the relative direction of the gas and liquid flows. In the counter-current design, the liquid is introduced at the top of the tower using sprays or weirs and flows downward over the packing material. The contaminated gas stream enters at the bottom of the tower and flows upward through the packing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wet scrubbing systems are susceptible to several operating problems, especially if the pressure differential, liquid flow, and gas flow are not kept relatively constant. Common problems include: low gas flow rate; low liquid flow rate; condensation of aerosols in the system; poor liquid distribution; use of liquid with high pollutant concentration; tray/plate collapse; air inleakage; pollutant re-entrainment; freezing/pluggage of lines; and scaling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Specific information about wet scrubbers can be found from EPA Fact Sheets and the EPA Air Pollution Control Cost Manual, Section 5, Chapter 1 - Wet Scrubbers for Acid Gases (Sixth Edition).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information, see the box &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/air-emissions-monitoring-knowledge-base/monitoring-control-technique-wet-scrubber-gaseous-control#box1&quot;&gt;More about Wet Scrubber For Gaseous Control&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Monitoring Information&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The primary indicators of wet scrubber performance are pressure differential, liquid flow rate, and scrubber liquid outlet concentration. The less significant indicators of gaseous pollutant control efficiency for wet scrubbers are gas flow rate, neutralizing chemical feed rate, and scrubber outlet gas temperature. Parameters to monitor as an alternative to scrubber liquid outlet concentration include scrubber liquid pH, scrubber liquid specific gravity, and scrubber makeup/blowdown rates. For systems that control gaseous streams with low particulate matter loadings, there is no advantage to monitoring the scrubbing liquid solids content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information, see the box &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/air-emissions-monitoring-knowledge-base/monitoring-control-technique-wet-scrubber-gaseous-control#box2&quot;&gt;Monitoring and the CAM Rule&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Costs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Costs of wet scrubbers are discussed in the EPA Air Pollution Control Cost Manual&lt;sup&gt;*&lt;/sup&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www3.epa.gov/ttn/catc/dir1/cs5-2ch1.pdf&quot;&gt;Section 5, Chapter 1 - Wet Scrubbers for Acid Gases (Sixth Edition) (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(60 pp, 290 K, &lt;a href=&quot;/home/pdf-files&quot;&gt;About PDF&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;. Costs of monitoring systems, both Continuous Emission Monitors and parametric monitoring systems, are addressed in the EPA Air Pollution Control Cost Manual&lt;sup&gt;*&lt;/sup&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www3.epa.gov/ttn/catc/dir1/cs2ch4.pdf&quot;&gt;Section 2, Chapter 4 - Monitors&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(42 pp, 542 K, &lt;a href=&quot;/home/pdf-files&quot;&gt;About PDF&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;small&gt;*EPA is currently updating the Control Cost Manual. The most recent versions are available on the &lt;a href=&quot;/economic-and-cost-analysis-air-pollution-regulations/cost-reports-and-guidance-air-pollution&quot;&gt;Economic and Cost Analysis for Air Pollution Regulations website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 25 May 2016 14:10:18 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>aingram</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">150389 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Monitoring by Control Technique - Thermal Oxidizer</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/air-emissions-monitoring-knowledge-base/monitoring-control-technique-thermal-oxidizer</link>
    <description>
				&lt;h2&gt;Description&lt;/h2&gt;

				&lt;p&gt;Thermal oxidizers, or thermal incinerators, are combustion devices that control VOC, CO, and volatile HAP emissions by combusting them to carbon dioxide (CO&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt;) and water. Thermal oxidizers are similar to catalytic oxidizers (catalytic oxidizers use a catalyst to promote the oxidation reaction). Important design factors include temperature (a temperature high enough to ignite the organic constituents in the waste stream), residence time (sufficient time for the combustion reaction to occur), and turbulence or mixing of the combustion air with the waste gas.&lt;/p&gt;

				&lt;p&gt;To reduce fuel usage required for oxidation, thermal oxidizers frequently have some form of heat recovery. The percentage of heat recovery in the design of thermal oxidizers generally increases with decreasing inlet VOC/HAP concentration. Heat recovery may either be recuperative or regenerative. In recuperative heat recovery, heat is recovered by passing the hot exhaust gases through a non-contact air-to-air heat exchanger, to heat the incoming air to the oxidizer. In regenerative heat recovery, hot exhaust gases and cool inlet gases are alternatively passed through a fixed bed, typically employing ceramics. See the link below for a schematic of a basic thermal oxidizer.&lt;/p&gt;

				&lt;p&gt;A training tool developed for inspectors provides an overview of oxidizers (thermal and catalytic); this tool describes oxidizer types, operating principles, pollutants controlled, proper operating conditions, and performance monitoring of oxidizers. A training video provides similar information in an audio-video format (about 15 minutes in length). Other specific information about thermal oxidizers can be found from the EPA Air Pollution Control Cost Manual, Section 3.2, Chapter 2 - Incinerators and from EPA Fact Sheets.&lt;/p&gt;

				&lt;p&gt;For more information, see the box &lt;a href=&quot;/air-emissions-monitoring-knowledge-base/monitoring-control-technique-thermal-oxidizer#box1&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;More About Thermal Oxidizers.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

				&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Monitoring Information&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

				&lt;div&gt;
					&lt;p&gt;For VOC control, the primary indicators of thermal oxidizer performance are the outlet exhaust gas VOC concentration and the combustion chamber temperature. Other indicators of thermal oxidizer performance include outlet exhaust gas CO concentration, exhaust gas flow rate, fan current, outlet CO2 concentration, outlet O&lt;sub&gt;2&lt;/sub&gt; concentration, and auxiliary fuel line pressure. For CO control, the indicators of performance are the same as for VOC control, with the exception of outlet VOC and CO2 concentrations, which would not be monitored for a CO emissions limit.&lt;/p&gt;

					&lt;p&gt;The Compliance Assurance Monitoring (CAM) Technical Guidance Document (TGD) provides a source of information on monitoring approaches for different types of control devices.&lt;/p&gt;

					&lt;p&gt;Specific information provided in CAM TGD - Appendix A: Example CAM Submittals for Thermal Oxidizers, include example CAM submittals based on case studies of actual facilities.&lt;/p&gt;
				&lt;/div&gt;

				&lt;p&gt;For more information and to read the TGD, see the box &lt;a href=&quot;/air-emissions-monitoring-knowledge-base/monitoring-control-technique-thermal-oxidizer#box2&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Monitoring and the CAM Rule.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

				&lt;div&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Industry Specific Information&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

				&lt;p&gt;To search for additional monitoring information specific to an industry, see the &lt;a href=&quot;/air-emissions-monitoring-knowledge-base/monitoring-information-industry-printing-and-publishing&quot;&gt;monitoring information by industry type page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

				&lt;h2&gt;Costs&lt;/h2&gt;

				&lt;p&gt;Costs of thermal oxidation are discussed in the EPA Air Pollution Control Cost Manual&lt;sup&gt;*&lt;/sup&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www3.epa.gov/ttn/catc/dir1/cs3-2ch2.pdf&quot;&gt;Section 3.2, Chapter 2 - Incinerators&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(64 pp, 182 K, &lt;a href=&quot;/home/pdf-files&quot;&gt;About PDF&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;. Costs of monitoring systems, both Continuous Emission Monitors and parametric monitoring systems, are addressed in the EPA Air Pollution Control Cost Manual&lt;sup&gt;*&lt;/sup&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www3.epa.gov/ttn/catc/dir1/cs2ch4.pdf&quot;&gt;Section 2, Chapter 4 - Monitors&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(42 pp, 542 K, &lt;a href=&quot;/home/pdf-files&quot;&gt;About PDF&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

				&lt;p&gt;Costs for thermal oxidation of styrene emitted from fiber-reinforced plastics facilities is discussed in a report titled, Assessment of Styrene Emission Controls for FRP/C and Boat Building Industries (EPA-600/R-96-109). The report includes spreadsheets designed to quickly analyze the control cost for a thermal oxidation (and other VOC/HAP control technologies) based on control device input flow rate and pollutant loading (in tons per year or ppm). An introductory text file lists the controls that are analyzed and gives basic instructions for using the spreadsheets. The spreadsheets were developed for styrene (C8H8, 4.326 mg/m3 per ppm, 0.00475 Btu/ppm) and would need to be altered to address other pollutants.&lt;/p&gt;

				&lt;p&gt;For more information, see the box&lt;strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;/air-emissions-monitoring-knowledge-base/monitoring-control-technique-thermal-oxidizer#box3&quot;&gt;More About Thermal Oxidizers and Costs.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;small&gt;*EPA is currently updating the Control Cost Manual. The most recent versions are available on the &lt;a href=&quot;/economic-and-cost-analysis-air-pollution-regulations/cost-reports-and-guidance-air-pollution&quot;&gt;Economic and Cost Analysis for Air Pollution Regulations website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 25 May 2016 12:46:21 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>aingram</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">150373 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Monitoring by Control Technique - Fabric Filters</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/air-emissions-monitoring-knowledge-base/monitoring-control-technique-fabric-filters</link>
    <description>&lt;h2&gt;Description&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A fabric filter, sometimes referred to as a baghouse, utilizes fabric filtration to remove particles from the contaminated gas stream by depositing the particles on fabric material. The filter&#039;s ability to collect small micrometer and sub-micrometer particles is due to the accumulated dust cake and not the fabric itself. The filter is usually in the form of cylindrical fabric bags, hence the names &quot;fabric filter&quot; or &quot;bag house&quot;, but it may be in the form of cartridges that are constructed of fabric, sintered metal or porous ceramic. In general, fabric filters are capable of collection efficiencies greater than 99 percent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are three types of fabric filters. Each type differs in the method used to clean the filter material. As dust builds up on the filter surface, the pressure drop across the filter increases. In order to avoid excessively high pressure drops, the filter material is cleaned periodically. The most common methods of cleaning are shaking, reverse air, and reverse pulse or pulse jet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shaker fabric filter collectors clean the bags by gently shaking them. The shaker collector has a tube sheet between the vertical casing and the hopper. The open bottoms of cylindrical bags are attached to holes in the tube sheet, and the closed tops of the bags are attached to the shaking mechanism in the top of the casing. The contaminated gas stream enters the hopper, flows through the holes in the tube sheet and into the inside of the vertical bags. Since the bags are closed at the top, the gas stream flows through the bags, leaving a dust cake on the inside. Periodically, the gas flow through the collector or compartment is stopped and the bags are shaken to clean them. The dislodged dust cake falls into the hopper and is removed from the collector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reverse air fabric filter collectors are similar to shaker collectors. The reverse air collector has a tube sheet between the casing and the hopper. The bottoms of the bags are attached to holes in the tube sheet; however, the closed tops of the bags are attached to a support structure in the top of the casing that holds the bags under tension. The contaminated gas stream enters the hopper, flows into and through the bags, again leaving the dust cake on the inside. To clean the bags, the gas flow through the compartment is stopped and another gas flow is introduced that flows in the reverse direction. This gas flow is usually taken from the cleaned gas stream being discharged from the operating compartments. To keep the bags from fully collapsing during the reverse airflow, rigid rings are sewn into the bags at intervals along their length. The dust cake dislodged by the reverse airflow falls into the hopper and is removed from the collector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reverse pulse or pulse jet collectors clean the bags using short duration pulses of compressed air. The collector has a tube sheet that is located near the top of the vertical casing, and the bags hang from the holes in the tube sheet. A wire-mesh cage is located inside the bags to keep them from collapsing. The contaminated gas stream enters through the side or through the hopper of the collector and flows into the bags and up through the tube sheet, leaving the dust cake on the outside of the bags. Cleaning is accomplished by directing the compressed air pulse to one or a few rows of bags, while the other bags continue to provide filtration. The collector is usually not shut down or isolated from flow while cleaning. The dust cake dislodged by the compressed air pulse falls into the hopper and is removed from the collector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fabric filter performance can be effected by the conditions that the fabric is exposed to and the frequency of cleaning. Minimum operating temperature is especially important where acid gases are expected to be present in the gas stream. Lower temperatures mean acid gases have the potential to condense and corrode the fabric filter casing and other metal parts. Condensation can also cause bag blinding, which blocks air flow through the bag. Fabric filters are also susceptible to damage caused by high temperatures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Specific information about fabric filters can be found from EPA Fact Sheets and the EPA Air Pollution Control Cost Manual, Section 6, Chapter 1 Baghouses and Filters (Sixth Edition).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information, see the box &lt;a href=&quot;/air-emissions-monitoring-knowledge-base/monitoring-control-technique-fabric-filters#box1&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;More About Fabric Filters.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Monitoring Information&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;The best indicators of fabric filter performance is the particulate matter outlet concentration, which can be measured with a particulate matter continuous emissions monitoring system (CEMS) or a bag leak detection system used to monitor bag breakage and leakage. Opacity monitoring is also an indicator of fabric filter performance. Other indicators of performance include pressure differential, inlet temperature, temperature differential, exhaust gas flow rate, cleaning mechanism operation and fan current.&lt;/p&gt;

	&lt;p&gt;The Compliance Assurance Monitoring (CAM) Technical Guidance Document (TGD) is a source of information on monitoring approaches for different types of control devices. Specific information provided in the CAM TGD related to fabric filters include example CAM submittals based on case studies of actual facilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information, see the box &lt;a href=&quot;/air-emissions-monitoring-knowledge-base/monitoring-control-technique-fabric-filters#box2&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Monitoring and the CAM Rule.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Costs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;Costs of fabric filters are discussed in the EPA Air Pollution Control Cost Manual&lt;sup&gt;*&lt;/sup&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www3.epa.gov/ttn/catc/dir1/cs6ch1.pdf&quot;&gt;Section 6, Chapter 1 Baghouses and Filters (Sixth Edition)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(60 pp, 272 K, &lt;a href=&quot;/home/pdf-files&quot;&gt;About PDF&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/span&gt; Costs of monitoring systems, both Continuous Emission Monitors and parametric monitoring systems, are addressed in the EPA Air Pollution Control Cost Manual&lt;sup&gt;*&lt;/sup&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www3.epa.gov/ttn/catc/dir1/cs2ch4.pdf&quot;&gt;Section 2, Chapter 4 - Monitors (Sixth Edition)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(42 pp, 540 K, &lt;a href=&quot;/home/pdf-files&quot;&gt;About PDF&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Specific tools have been developed to estimate fabric filter costs when used to control particulate matter from coal-fired power plants and coal-fired utility boilers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As indicated above in the monitoring section, indicators of fabric filter performance include the particulate matter outlet concentration, which can be measured with a particulate matter CEMS. Costs associated with purchasing and installing a CEMS can be estimated using the EPA CEMS Cost Model Version 3.0&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information about costs and the CEMS Cost Model, see the box&lt;strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;/air-emissions-monitoring-knowledge-base/monitoring-control-technique-fabric-filters#box3&quot;&gt;More About Fabric Filters and Costs.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;small&gt;*EPA is currently updating the Control Cost Manual. The most recent versions are available on the &lt;a href=&quot;/economic-and-cost-analysis-air-pollution-regulations/cost-reports-and-guidance-air-pollution&quot;&gt;Economic and Cost Analysis for Air Pollution Regulations website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 24 May 2016 15:27:33 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>aingram</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">150299 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Monitoring by Control Technique - Electrostatic Precipitators</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/air-emissions-monitoring-knowledge-base/monitoring-control-technique-electrostatic-precipitators</link>
    <description>&lt;h2&gt;Description&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An electrostatic precipitator (ESP) removes particles from a gas stream by using electrical energy to charge particles either positively or negatively. The charged particles are then attracted to collector plates carrying the opposite charge. The collected particles may be removed from the collector plates as dry material (dry ESPs), or they may be washed from the plates with water (wet ESPs). ESPs are capable of collection efficiencies greater than 99 percent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An ESP is primarily made up of the following four components: gas distribution plates, discharge electrodes, collection surfaces (either plates or pipes) and rappers. The gas distribution plates consist of several perforated plates which help maintain proper flow distribution of the entering gas stream. The discharge electrodes are divided into fields. Most ESPs have three or four fields in series; however, very large units may have as many as fourteen fields in series. Discharge electrodes are energized by a single transformer-rectifier (T-R) set power supply. The energized electrodes create ions that collide with the particles and apply the electrical charge to the particles contained in the incoming gas stream. The collection plates or pipes provide the collection surfaces for the charged particulate matter. The rapping system is responsible for removing the collected particulate matter from the collection surfaces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ESPs are generally classified as dry ESPs (the most commonly used) and wet ESPs. The primary difference between the two classifications is the method by which the collector plates are cleaned. In dry ESPs, the collector plates are cleaned by applying mechanical impulses or vibration to the plates, which knocks loose the collected particulate matter (referred to as rapping). In wet ESPs, the collector plates are cleaned by rinsing with water. Wet ESPs are typically employed when gas streams contain sticky particles with low resistivity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ESP performance can be affected by particle resistivity. Particle resistivity is the property that influences the deposition and removal of particles from the collection plates. The desirable situation is to have particles that conduct away some of their charge once they reach the plate, so that the deposition of other particles is not inhibited, but retain enough of their charge to lightly hold them to the plate. The characteristic is termed moderate resistivity. If the particles have very high resistivity, they are slow to conduct away their charge, causing a negative charge to build up on the plates that inhibit other particles from depositing. If the particles have very low resistivity, they rapidly lose their charge when reaching the plate and pick up the charge of the plate, causing them to be repelled back into the gas stream where they are recharged negatively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information, see the box &lt;a href=&quot;/air-emissions-monitoring-knowledge-base/monitoring-control-technique-electrostatic-precipitators#box1&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;More About Electrostatic Precipitators.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Monitoring Information&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;The primary indicators of the performance of ESPs are the particulate matter outlet concentration, which can be measured with a particulate matter continuous emissions monitoring system (CEMS), opacity, secondary corona power, secondary voltage (voltage across the electrodes), and secondary current (current to the electrodes). Other indicators of performance are the spark rate, primary current, primary voltage, inlet gas temperature, gas flow rate, rapper operation, and number of fields in operation.&lt;/p&gt;

	&lt;p&gt;The Compliance Assurance Monitoring (CAM) Technical Guidance Document (TGD) is a source of information on monitoring approaches for different types of control devices. Specific information provided in the CAM TGD related to ESPs include example CAM submittals based on case studies of actual facilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information, see the box &lt;a href=&quot;/air-emissions-monitoring-knowledge-base/monitoring-control-technique-electrostatic-precipitators#box2&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Monitoring and the CAM Rule.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Costs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;Costs of electrostatic precipitators are discussed in the EPA Air Pollution Control Cost Manual&lt;sup&gt;*&lt;/sup&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www3.epa.gov/ttn/catc/dir1/cs6ch3.pdf&quot;&gt;Section 6, Chapter 3 - Electrostatic Precipitators (Sixth Edition)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(70 pp, 586 K, &lt;a href=&quot;/home/pdf-files&quot;&gt;About PDF&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/span&gt;. Costs of monitoring systems, both Continuous Emission Monitors and parametric monitoring systems, are addressed in the EPA Air Pollution Control Cost Manual&lt;sup&gt;*&lt;/sup&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www3.epa.gov/ttn/catc/dir1/cs2ch4.pdf&quot;&gt;Section 2, Chapter 4 - Monitors (Sixth Edition)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(42 pp, 540 K, &lt;a href=&quot;/home/pdf-files&quot;&gt;About PDF&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Specific tools have been developed to estimate ESP costs when used to control particulate matter from coal-fired power plants and coal-fired utility boilers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As indicated above in the monitoring section, indicators of ESP performance include the particulate matter outlet concentration, which can be measured with a particulate matter CEMS. Costs associated with purchasing and installing a CEMS can be estimated using the EPA CEMS Cost Model Version 3.0.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information, see the box&lt;strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;/air-emissions-monitoring-knowledge-base/monitoring-control-technique-electrostatic-precipitators#box3&quot;&gt;More About Electrostatic Precipitators and Costs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;small&gt;*EPA is currently updating the Control Cost Manual. The most recent versions are available on the &lt;a href=&quot;/economic-and-cost-analysis-air-pollution-regulations/cost-reports-and-guidance-air-pollution&quot;&gt;Economic and Cost Analysis for Air Pollution Regulations website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 24 May 2016 11:01:51 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>aingram</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">150279 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Monitoring by Control Technique - Electrified Filter Bed</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/air-emissions-monitoring-knowledge-base/monitoring-control-technique-electrified-filter-bed</link>
    <description>&lt;h2&gt;Description&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An electrified filter bed (EFB) uses electrostatic forces to attract particles, including fine dust and smoke particles, from flue gas streams to an electrically charged gravel bed. Example applications include wood waste-fired boilers and wood products dryers. EFB collection efficiency is dependent on the bed&#039;s electrode voltage and the dimensions of the particulate in the contaminated gas stream.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A typical EFB system has the following three sections: the ionizer (corona charger), the filter bed, and the gravel cleaning and recirculation system. The particulate in the gas stream is negatively charged in the ionizing section. A fan forces the gas through the gravel filter bed where the gravel is positively charged by means of the embedded electrode. The negatively charged dust sticks to the positively charged gravel. The pea-sized gravel is either periodically replaced or is continuously removed from the filter bed where it is cleaned in a pneumatic conveyor and returned to the filter bed. In some applications, the dust removed from the gravel cleaning process is directed to a baghouse. Cleaned gas collects in the outlet plenum and exits the system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The purpose of the gravel cleaning and recirculation system is to clean the gravel and elevate it to the top of the filter bed for reuse. Cleaning the gravel helps to maintain a constant gas flow and pressure differential across the system. The gravel travels from the bottom of the filter bed, through an infeed pipe, and into the lift line. Agitation in the lift line, along with the loss of gravel charge, dislodges dust from the gravel. The lift line discharges into the disengagement chamber, which decreases the lift air velocity. The cleaned gravel falls into the gravel reserve hopper, and the dust is either collected or conveyed with the lift air to a fabric filter. Other systems require manual removal of spent gravel and addition of new gravel on a weekly basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most common operational problem with EFBs is the buildup of glaze on the ionizer or the gravel. The combination of dust, condensed hydrocarbons, and condensed moisture in the gas stream forms a hard, powder-like substance, which settles on the ionizer and gravel. This buildup interferes with the corona charging of the ionizer and the electrode charging of the filter bed. Another operation problem is the EFB&#039;s narrow temperature operating range. Temperatures need to be high enough to ensure that water in the gas stream does not condense. Moisture condensation in the filter bed can result in an electrical short, in addition to contributing to the hydrocarbon glaze as described above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Monitoring Information&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;The primary indicators of EFB performance are ionizer voltage, ionizer current, filter bed voltage, filter bed current, filter bed temperature, and the inlet gas temperature. Other parameters indicating performance include pressure differential, gas flow rate, outlet particulate concentration, and opacity.&lt;/p&gt;

	&lt;p&gt;The Compliance Assurance Monitoring (CAM) Technical Guidance Document (TGD) is a source of information on monitoring approaches for different types of control devices. Specific information provided in the CAM TGD related to EFBs will include an example CAM submittal based on a case study of an actual facility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For more information, see the box &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/air-emissions-monitoring-knowledge-base/monitoring-control-technique-electrified-filter-bed#box2&quot;&gt;Monitoring and the CAM Rule&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Costs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Costs of monitoring systems, both Continuous Emission Monitors and parametric monitoring systems, are addressed in the EPA Air Pollution Control Cost Manual&lt;sup&gt;*&lt;/sup&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www3.epa.gov/ttn/catc/dir1/cs2ch4.pdf&quot;&gt;Section 2, Chapter 4-Monitors (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(42 pp, 542 K, &lt;a href=&quot;/home/pdf-files&quot;&gt;About PDF&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;small&gt;*EPA is currently updating the Control Cost Manual. The most recent versions are available on the &lt;a href=&quot;/economic-and-cost-analysis-air-pollution-regulations/cost-reports-and-guidance-air-pollution&quot;&gt;Economic and Cost Analysis for Air Pollution Regulations website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Mon, 23 May 2016 13:58:22 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>aingram</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">150207 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  </channel>
</rss>

<!-- Page cached by Boost @ 2017-01-25 04:36:26, expires @ 2017-01-25 16:36:26, lifetime 12 hours -->