<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?><rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.epa.gov/feed/61623/rss.xml" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/" xmlns:og="http://ogp.me/ns#" xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#" xmlns:sioc="http://rdfs.org/sioc/ns#" xmlns:sioct="http://rdfs.org/sioc/types#" xmlns:skos="http://www.w3.org/2004/02/skos/core#" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#">
  <channel>
    <title>EPA in District of Columbia</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/feed/61623/rss.xml</link>
    <description>Updated EPA in District of Columbia content from the US Environmental Protection Agency</description>
    <language>en</language>
     <atom:link href="https://www.epa.gov/feed/61623/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      <item>
    <title>Building Environmental Awareness</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/dc/building-environmental-awareness</link>
    <description>&lt;h2&gt;Stories of Progress in Achieving Healthy Waters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;U.S. EPA Region 3 Water Protection Division&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Washington, D.C. • December 8, 2016&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Middle school students from vulnerable communities in the Washington, D.C. area are gaining a greater appreciation for the environment this fall as part of a weekend program largely funded by EPA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 20 students from 14 different schools are participating in the Saturday Environmental Academy (SEA), a program of the Anacostia Watershed Society. The 10-week program, offered in the fall and spring, is supported this year by a $50,000 &lt;a href=&quot;/newsreleases/epa-awarding-13-million-revitalize-americas-urban-waters-and-surrounding-communities&quot;&gt;EPA Urban Waters grant&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SEA provides the 7th and 8th graders with hands-on learning activities and outdoor experiences to build their environmental interest, knowledge and awareness, and develop skills in team building, critical thinking and scientific investigation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The program’s theme this fall is “Celebrating Parks in Your Community,” inspired by the National Park Service’s centennial. The sessions have involved trips to national and local parks in the Anacostia and Potomac watersheds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“It’s going really well,” said SEA Program Director Catherine Estes. “The Urban Waters grant was extremely helpful and we’re very grateful for the funding.” The program is free to students.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among their activities, the students have helped conduct a tree inventory on the National Mall, competed in “Bio-Blitz” teams to identify species in Kenilworth Park &amp;amp; Aquatic Gardens, paddled canoes in the West River during a special weekend overnight trip, held local wildlife like pine snakes and box turtles, did nature journaling along Rock Creek, and learned how parkland helps to capture and filter stormwater and improve the health of the Anacostia River.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The student activities are captured on the program’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/pages/Saturday-Environmental-Academy/126372900707256&quot;&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot; class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt; page. One post from a trip to Huntley Meadows Park notes, “We participated in a naturalist-led program about the importance of parks and wetlands to wildlife, plants, and people. It&#039;s much more fun to get outside so a little rain didn&#039;t stop SEA from then hiking through the forest and out into the wetland. We learned about and saw beaver lodges, snapping turtles, green tree frogs, bull frogs, great egrets, and more.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Urban Waters grant to the Anacostia Watershed Society is one of two awarded in EPA’s Mid-Atlantic Region this year. The other was provided to Virginia Commonwealth University to develop a community greening and green infrastructure plan for its two campuses in downtown Richmond, as well as the Richmond Arts District.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-png left view-mode-medium&quot; style=&quot;width:448px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Map of Anacostia River Watershed, which covers the parts of Montgomery County and Prince George&amp;#039;s County Maryland and District of Columbia.&quot; height=&quot;346&quot; width=&quot;448&quot; class=&quot;left media-element file-medium left&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/medium/public/2016-06/dc_anacostiawatershed_20160408.png&quot; title=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-337329&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-12/documents/dc_progress_-_students_experiencing_the_environment.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=660881&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Building Environmental Awareness (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(1 pg, 661 K, 
  12/08/2016)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 08 Dec 2016 13:52:46 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>nholomuz</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">166663 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Class Outdoors in the District of Columbia</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/dc/class-outdoors-district-columbia</link>
    <description>&lt;h2&gt;Stories of Progress in Achieving Healthy Waters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;U.S. EPA Region 3 Water Protection Division&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Washington, D.C. • September 29, 2016&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Specially-designed outdoor education areas surrounded by rain gardens and other green features have been added to the grounds of three District of Columbia schools, providing students with hands-on learning experiences while reducing stormwater pollution to local waters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two sources of EPA funds – a $500,000 Clean Water Act Title VI Grant and a $391,000 Chesapeake Bay Implementation Grant – financed the schoolyard improvements at the Ludlow-Taylor and J. O. Wilson elementary schools and the Excel Academy Public Charter School.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The green features were built in the summer of 2016 as part of the District Department of Energy and Environment’s (DOEE’s) &lt;a href=&quot;http://doee.dc.gov/service/riversmart-schools&quot;&gt;RiverSmart Schools&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot; class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt; program that to date has provided this benefit to 85 District schools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among the criteria to participate, schools must organize two to four community action days for the planning, preparation and installation of the site, have a schoolyard teaching team that meets at least four times a year, and incorporate the schoolyard garden into the existing curriculum. Teachers attend workshops on watershed ecology and other topics that allow them to work with their students outdoors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At Ludlow-Taylor, rain gardens, a labyrinth built of infiltration planters, garden beds and outdoor education areas make up nearly 3,000 square feet of green space filled with plants and trees. The new features are located at a low point in the schoolyard and will capture and filter stormwater runoff from a surrounding 12,000 square foot area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Students have an opportunity to learn about a variety of environmental issues, including reducing stormwater pollution from school grounds. While many lessons are hands-on, students at Ludlow-Taylor have class on a canopied platform for presentations, reflection and discussion. At J.O. Wilson and Excel, the teaching areas have rings of cut logs for seating, and a sail for shade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Collectively, stormwater retention and wildlife habitat installed at all three schools include a total of 5,174 square feet of bioretention rain gardens, three 580-gallon rainwater harvesting cisterns, native plantings, a grove of canopy trees, shrubs and perennials, and the outdoor education areas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The three sites are each designed to retain all stormwater from rain events of 1.7 inches or less, according to DOEE. Mature canopy trees will capture additional stormwater over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg left view-mode-medium&quot; style=&quot;width:448px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;A map of Washington D.C.&quot; height=&quot;229&quot; width=&quot;448&quot; class=&quot;left media-element file-medium left&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/medium/public/2016-10/washington_dc.jpg&quot; title=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-323833&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-10/documents/dc_progress_-_class_outside_in_district_schools_-_20160929.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=642387&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Class Outdoors in the District of Columbia (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(1 pg, 642 K, 
  09/29/2016)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;field field-name-field-document-description field-type-text field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    Specially-designed outdoor education areas surrounded by rain gardens and other green features have been added to the grounds of three District of Columbia schools, providing students with hands-on learning experiences while reducing stormwater pollution to local waters.  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 13 Oct 2016 15:44:09 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>apruzins</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">162555 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>EPA News and Events for the District of Columbia</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/dc/epa-news-and-events-district-columbia</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;Click on data points for more information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;930&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; title=&quot;District of Columbia Map&quot; src=&quot;https://epa.maps.arcgis.com/apps/Embed/index.html?webmap=80f778a6840340bd855dc4e474412c17&amp;amp;extent=-77.209,38.8026,-76.82,38.9851&amp;amp;zoom=true&amp;amp;scale=true&amp;amp;scroll=true&amp;amp;theme=light&amp;amp;level=11&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 21 Sep 2016 17:58:06 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>jgrave04</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">160827 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Green Infrastructure in the Mix to Reduce District of Columbia Sewer Overflows</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/dc/green-infrastructure-mix-reduce-district-columbia-sewer-overflows</link>
    <description>&lt;h2&gt;Stories of Progress in Achieving Healthy Waters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;U.S. EPA Region 3 Water Protection Division&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Washington, D.C. • May 21, 2015&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The District of Columbia’s Long Term Control Plan to keep sewage out of the city’s rivers and creeks is being modified to include a substantial greening component for the first time, making it a dominant feature of two of the three drainage areas of the combined sewer system in the nation’s capital.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The modification gives DC Water the go-ahead to pursue an integrated green/gray infrastructure approach to address the stormwater- and sewage-driven water quality issues in the Rock Creek and Potomac watersheds. Green infrastructure uses vegetation, soils, and natural processes that mimic nature to soak up and store stormwater where it falls to control wet weather pollution and create healthier urban environments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The large-scale green infrastructure projects are scheduled to begin in 2015 and 2016 respectively, providing more immediate pollution reductions, enhancements to community livability, green jobs opportunities, and a sustainable model for other communities to follow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under the modified consent decree, DC Water will continue to churn ahead – literally – on the most significant aspect of the overall Clean Rivers program to control combined sewer overflows (CSOs) – construction of two tunnel systems and related projects to capture and provide storage for CSOs discharged in the Anacostia and Potomac watersheds. The Anacostia tunnel systems are being carved by giant boring machines, Lady Bird, Nellie and Lucy, that even have their &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.washingtonpost.com/express/wp/2015/04/20/meet-lucy-a-1582-ton-tunnel-boring-machine-that-tweets/&quot;&gt;own Twitter accounts&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot; class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;. When the Anacostia tunnel complex is fully completed in 2025, it will nearly eliminate CSOs to the Anacostia River in an average rainfall year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the Rock Creek and Potomac watersheds, there will be more than tunnel vision at work. Specifically, the agreement calls for:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Using green infrastructure to retain 1.2 inches of rainwater on 365 acres in the Rock Creek area, and 133 acres in the Potomac watershed. &lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Potentially eliminating the Rock Creek storage tunnel and significantly decreasing the size of the Potomac tunnel depending upon the success demonstrated by green infrastructure. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The modification, agreed to by EPA, DC Water and the District, also includes construction of an enhanced clarification unit, optimization of process flows, and tunnel enhancements. The changes are designed to ensure that the Blue Plains Advanced Wastewater Treatment Plant nutrient reduction system can achieve “limit of technology” reductions in 2018.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg left view-mode-medium&quot; style=&quot;width:448px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;A map of Washington D.C.&quot; height=&quot;229&quot; width=&quot;448&quot; class=&quot;left media-element file-medium left&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/medium/public/2016-10/washington_dc.jpg&quot; title=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-313585&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-09/documents/dc_progress_-_green_infrastructure_in_the_mix_to_reduce_district_of_columbia_sewer_overflows_-_20150521.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=643336&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Green Infrastructure in the Mix To Reduce District of Columbia Sewer Overflows (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(1 pg, 643 K, 
  05/21/2015)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;field field-name-field-document-description field-type-text field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    The District of Columbia’s Long Term Control Plan to keep sewage out of the city’s rivers and creeks is being modified to include a substantial greening component for the first time, making it a dominant feature of two of the three drainage areas of the combined sewer system in the nation’s capital.  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 07 Sep 2016 14:28:03 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>apruzins</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">159445 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>EPA, Amtrak Agreement Helps Ensure Drinking Water Safety on Trains</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/dc/epa-amtrak-agreement-helps-ensure-drinking-water-safety-trains</link>
    <description>&lt;h2&gt;Stories of Progress in Achieving Healthy Waters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;U.S. EPA Region 3 Water Protection Division&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Washington, D.C. • August 13, 2015&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A revised agreement between EPA and Amtrak continues to help ensure that drinking water on Amtrak’s interstate passenger rail cars is protected from bacterial contamination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The vast majority of water systems DO NOT MOVE. Water towers are bolted down; pipes are buried in the ground and connect to homes and other buildings. Planes and trains do move, though. Passenger rail cars are a special type of water system, called an Interstate Carrier Conveyance (ICC), covered under the &lt;a href=&quot;/dwstandardsregulations/background-drinking-water-standards-safe-drinking-water-act-sdwa&quot;&gt;Safe Drinking Water Act&lt;/a&gt;. Amtrak is based in Washington, D.C., and works directly with EPA’s Mid-Atlantic Region for drinking water compliance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each passenger rail car that supplies water through a drinking fountain, restroom, or café service is a separate water system. Prior to 2012, Amtrak conducted random sampling of drinking water on rail cars, but that left many unmonitored. In 2012, EPA and Amtrak signed an Administrative Order on Consent (AOC), through which Amtrak would periodically monitor the drinking water supplied on every passenger rail car and ensure that proper maintenance procedures are followed to minimize the risk of contamination to the tanks and pipes that supply water on the cars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The original 2012 agreement and its amended version signed in August 2015 require Amtrak to follow a specific maintenance plan to disinfect and flush the parts of the rail cars that supply water, from the holding tanks to the faucets in a dining car or restroom. Periodic monitoring of every rail car indicates whether or not there is any contamination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amtrak must also maintain communication with the water systems from which they receive water. If a problem is identified with that water supply, Amtrak will avoid filling their tanks at that location. If Amtrak finds contamination on a car that is in route with passengers on board, Amtrak must notify those customers and direct them to water in a different car. Monitoring results in 2013 and 2014 revealed fewer than three percent of samples were positive for coliform bacteria (an indicator test), and not one sample of over 1,500 collected was positive for E. coli (a health risk contaminant). In 2015, EPA and Amtrak modified the agreement, extending the monitoring for six more years. The order applies to approximately 1,500 Amtrak owned or operated rail cars nationwide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg left view-mode-medium&quot; style=&quot;width:448px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;A map of Washington D.C.&quot; height=&quot;229&quot; width=&quot;448&quot; class=&quot;left media-element file-medium left&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/medium/public/2016-10/washington_dc.jpg&quot; title=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-313559&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-09/documents/dc_progress_-_epa_amtrak_agreement_helps_ensure_drinking_water_safety_on_trains_-_20150813.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=701442&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;EPA, Amtrak Agreement Helps Ensure Drinking Water Safety on Trains (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(1 pg, 701 K, 
  08/13/2015)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;field field-name-field-document-description field-type-text field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    A revised agreement between EPA and Amtrak continues to help ensure that drinking water on Amtrak’s interstate passenger rail cars is protected from bacterial contamination.  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 07 Sep 2016 13:48:43 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>apruzins</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">159423 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Rain Garden Activity Blooming in District of Columbia</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/dc/rain-garden-activity-blooming-district-columbia</link>
    <description>&lt;h2&gt;Stories of Progress in Achieving Healthy Waters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;U.S. EPA Region 3 Water Protection Division&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Washington, D.C. • March 12, 2015&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rain gardens in downtown D.C. are sparking interest in additional green infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The non-profit organization that brought four EPA-funded rain gardens to a bustling downtown neighborhood in the District of Columbia has plans for more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Building on the momentum of the gardens at the corner of 19th and L streets, N.W., the Golden Triangle Business Improvement District (BID) is developing plans to extend them north and south along 19th Street, from K to M streets – two full city blocks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The expansion was prompted by “a lot of positive feedback and support for the rain gardens we put in,” said David Suls, the BID’s Director of Planning and Economic Development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, EPA participated in a ribbon cutting event for the four rain gardens, each 10’ x 57’, which capture stormwater and help prevent flooding. EPA Mid-Atlantic Water Protection Division Director Jon Capacasa, who spoke at the event, said, “As we turn main streets into green streets, we’re controlling urban runoff pollution and making a visible difference in the community.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The planted depressions mimic nature, allowing heavy rain to slowly absorb rather than rush into storm drains where it can overwhelm the combined sewer system and cause polluted discharges to local waters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The gardens help to reduce the amount of water flowing into the sewer system in an area subject to sewer overflows. They also complement the green infrastructure program featured in the District’s innovative municipal stormwater permit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA provided $100,000 in Clean Water Act Section 319 funds and $85,000 in Chesapeake Bay Implementation Grant funds through the District of Columbia Department of Energy and Environment for the project. The funds were matched by $15,000 from the BID.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rain gardens, with drought-resistant plants that attract butterflies, birds and bees, were recognized as a Certified Wildlife Habitat by the National Wildlife Foundation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the expansion, the BID received funding for preliminary plans from the Metropolitan Washington Council of Governments. The BID has approached District of Columbia agencies for funding for final plans and construction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg left view-mode-medium&quot; style=&quot;width:448px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;A map of Washington D.C.&quot; height=&quot;229&quot; width=&quot;448&quot; class=&quot;left media-element file-medium left&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/medium/public/2016-10/washington_dc.jpg&quot; title=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-313553&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-09/documents/dc_progress_-_rain_garden_activity_blooming_in_district_of_columbia_-_20150312.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=661747&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Rain Garden Activity Blooming in District of Columbia (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(1 pg, 662 K, 
  03/12/2015)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;field field-name-field-document-description field-type-text field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    Rain gardens in downtown D.C. are sparking interest in additional green infrastructure.  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 07 Sep 2016 13:25:36 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>apruzins</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">159419 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>RiverSmart Washington Curbing Stormwater Pollution</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/dc/riversmart-washington-curbing-stormwater-pollution</link>
    <description>&lt;h2&gt;Stories of Progress in Achieving Healthy Waters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;U.S. EPA Region 3 Water Protection Division&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Washington, D.C. • July 2, 2015&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With support from EPA’s Section 319 program, the District of Columbia Department of Energy and Environment (DOEE) is leading an effort to protect Rock Creek and other waters from stormwater pollution by installing and monitoring &lt;a href=&quot;http://water.epa.gov/infrastructure/greeninfrastructure/index.cfm&quot;&gt;green infrastructure&lt;/a&gt; in two D.C. neighborhoods – Chevy Chase and Petworth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The $3.2 million RiverSmart Washington project is capturing and filtering stormwater through low impact development (LID) practices that include permeable paving in alleys, roads and parking lanes, rain gardens, bioretention areas and curb “bumpouts.” DDOE anticipates that the practices can capture more than 440,000 gallons of stormwater per 1.2” rain event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stormwater runoff carries pollutants from hard surfaces into the District’s storm drain system and streams, contributing to problems in Rock Creek, the Potomac River and the Chesapeake Bay. The significant volumes of water erode stream banks and create poor conditions for aquatic life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a potential model for other areas of the District, RiverSmart Washington is quantifying and assessing the benefits of retrofits in reducing runoff, examining the potential for using LID as a supplement or substitute for “gray infrastructure” as a part of the District’s Long Term Control Plan, and studying durability, citizen acceptance, and ease of LID installation and maintenance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;RiverSmart Washington is a partnership led by DOEE that includes the District Department of Transportation, DC Water, the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.rockcreekconservancy.org/&quot;&gt;Rock Creek Conservancy&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot; class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt; and private companies. The project includes an $800,000 grant from the National Fish and Wildlife Foundation, $1 million from DC Water, and $1.4 million from District Stormwater Enterprise Funds. DDOE staff involved in the project are financed by EPA’s Clean Water Act Section 319 non-point source pollution program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More than one acre of permeable pavement was installed in alleys, roadways, parking lanes and sidewalks using various materials and techniques. Sixteen bioretention areas are capturing runoff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to DOEE, a key component of the project was outreach to the community. One project goal was to retrofit as many private properties as possible through the RiverSmart Homes program since about 40 percent of the impervious cover in the project areas was located on private property. Sixtyfour of the 134 property owners installed stormwater practices on their properties. DOEE expects greater stormwater capture than anticipated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg left view-mode-medium&quot; style=&quot;width:448px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;A map of Washington D.C.&quot; height=&quot;229&quot; width=&quot;448&quot; class=&quot;left media-element file-medium left&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/medium/public/2016-10/washington_dc.jpg&quot; title=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-313543&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-09/documents/dc_progress_-_riversmart_washington_curbing_stormwater_pollution_-_20150702.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=619329&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;RiverSmart Washington Curbing Stormwater Pollution (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(1 pg, 619 K, 
  07/02/2015)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;field field-name-field-document-description field-type-text field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    With support from EPA’s Section 319 program, the District of Columbia Department of the Environment (DDOE) is leading an effort to protect Rock Creek and other waters from stormwater pollution by installing and monitoring green infrastructure in two D.C. neighborhoods – Chevy Chase and Petworth.  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 07 Sep 2016 12:57:49 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>apruzins</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">159409 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Urban Farm Harvests Community, Environmental Bounty</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/dc/urban-farm-harvests-community-environmental-bounty</link>
    <description>&lt;h2&gt;Stories of Progress in Achieving Healthy Waters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;U.S. EPA Region 3 Water Protection Division&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Washington, D.C. • October 1, 2015&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An urban farm with community and environmental benefits is sprouting in an underserved area of the nation’s capital.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An alliance of government, community, business and academic partners is creating the East Capitol Urban Farm – a three-acre site near the Capitol Heights Metro Station in the District of Columbia’s Ward 7. The farm will include community garden space, a farmer’s market, public art, nature discovery space for children, a portable aquaponics system for raising fish, pollinator gardens, interpretive trails, rain gardens and other environmental touches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The city’s largest-scale urban farm is designed to be a model for community revitalization, stormwater management, and access to fresh produce and fish. EPA was the first of several federal agency partners to contribute to the project as part of the &lt;a href=&quot;/urbanwaterspartners&quot;&gt;Urban Waters Federal Partnership&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hundreds of volunteers, including EPA’s Jeff Corbin, Senior Advisor for the Chesapeake Bay and the Anacostia River, spent a recent Saturday helping to build the site and cut a ribbon for the unique project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the federal support, partners in the project include the &lt;a href=&quot;http://dcbia.org/&quot;&gt;District of Columbia Building Industry Association&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot; class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;, the University of the District of Columbia, the District of Columbia Housing Authority, Several D.C. government agencies, community organizations, businesses and the Metropolitan Memorial United Methodist Church.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA provided $60,000 in Clean Water Act Section 319 funds to create the green infrastructure features at the primary entry to the farm, including about 2,200 square feet of plantings, 1,650 square feet of porous brick pavers, and educational signage explaining the importance of stormwater management and how concepts at the site can be adapted for private yards and other locations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a press release, EPA Administrator Gina McCarthy said, “This unique project exemplifies the very best of the Urban Waters Federal Partnership and how government is working with communities to help address their priorities – whether it’s job development, more green space or improving public health. By working collectively, local, state and federal partnerships can help communities transform abandoned or underused urban spaces into community assets like the East Capitol Urban Farm.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg left view-mode-medium&quot; style=&quot;width:448px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;A map of Washington D.C.&quot; height=&quot;229&quot; width=&quot;448&quot; class=&quot;left media-element file-medium left&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/medium/public/2016-10/washington_dc.jpg&quot; title=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-313535&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-09/documents/dc_progress_-_urban_farm_harvests_community_environmental_bounty_-_20151001.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=635472&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Urban Farm Harvests Community, Environmental Bounty (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(1 pg, 635 K, 
  10/01/2015)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;field field-name-field-document-description field-type-text field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    An urban farm with community and environmental benefits is sprouting in an underserved area of the nation’s capital.  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 07 Sep 2016 12:38:32 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>apruzins</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">159405 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Stories of Progress in Achieving Healthy Waters in the District of Columbia</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/dc/stories-progress-achieving-healthy-waters-district-columbia</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;These District of Columbia snapshots show how EPA and partners are improving the environment and making a difference in waterways, communities, drinking water and more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/dc/building-environmental-awareness&quot;&gt;Building Environmental Awareness&lt;/a&gt; &lt;small&gt;(December 8, 2016) &lt;/small&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/dc/class-outdoors-district-columbia&quot;&gt;Class Outdoors in the District of Columbia&lt;/a&gt; &lt;small&gt;(September 29, 2016)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/chesapeake-bay-tmdl/wastewater-out-front-bay-restoration&quot;&gt;Wastewater Out Front in Bay Restoration&lt;/a&gt; &lt;small&gt;(June 23, 2016)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/dc/steps-taken-reduce-trash-anacostia&quot;&gt;Steps Taken to Reduce Trash in Anacostia&lt;/a&gt; &lt;small&gt;(April 14, 2016)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/dc/green-street-district-columbia-curbs-harmful-runoff&quot;&gt;Green Street in District of Columbia Curbs Harmful Runoff&lt;/a&gt; &lt;small&gt;(February 18, 2016)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/dc/urban-farm-harvests-community-environmental-bounty&quot;&gt;Urban Farm Harvests Community, Environmental Bounty&lt;/a&gt; &lt;small&gt;(October 1, 2015)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/dc/epa-amtrak-agreement-helps-ensure-drinking-water-safety-trains&quot;&gt;EPA, Amtrak Agreement Helps Ensure Drinking Water Safety on Trains&lt;/a&gt; &lt;small&gt;(August 13, 2015)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/dc/riversmart-washington-curbing-stormwater-pollution&quot;&gt;RiverSmart Washington Curbing Stormwater Pollution&lt;/a&gt; &lt;small&gt;(July 2, 2015)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/dc/green-infrastructure-mix-reduce-district-columbia-sewer-overflows&quot;&gt;Green Infrastructure in the Mix to Reduce District of Columbia Sewer Overflows&lt;/a&gt; &lt;small&gt;(May 21, 2015)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/dc/rain-garden-activity-blooming-district-columbia&quot;&gt;Rain Garden Activity Blooming in District of Columbia&lt;/a&gt; &lt;small&gt;(March 12, 2015)&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jun 2016 15:21:10 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>KWzorek</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">153425 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  </channel>
</rss>

<!-- Page cached by Boost @ 2017-01-26 11:01:02, expires @ 2017-01-26 23:01:02, lifetime 12 hours -->