<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?><rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.epa.gov/feed/105123/rss.xml" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/" xmlns:og="http://ogp.me/ns#" xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#" xmlns:sioc="http://rdfs.org/sioc/ns#" xmlns:sioct="http://rdfs.org/sioc/types#" xmlns:skos="http://www.w3.org/2004/02/skos/core#" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#">
  <channel>
    <title>Sustainable Materials Management</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/feed/105123/rss.xml</link>
    <description>Updated Sustainable Materials Management content from the US Environmental Protection Agency</description>
    <language>en</language>
     <atom:link href="https://www.epa.gov/feed/105123/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      <item>
    <title>Sustainable Materials Management (SMM) Web Academy Webinar: The Story and Highlights of Oregon’s 2050 Vision of Materials Management</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/smm/sustainable-materials-management-smm-web-academy-webinar-story-and-highlights-oregons-2050</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On this page:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#description&quot;&gt;Description&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#speakers&quot;&gt;Speakers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#slides&quot;&gt;Slides&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;description&quot; name=&quot;description&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Description:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Thursday &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;January 19, 2017 1:00pm - 2:30pm EST&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://attendee.gotowebinar.com/register/5371364270167244035&quot;&gt;Register here&lt;/a&gt; for this free webinar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sustainable materials management is a systemic approach to using and reusing materials more productively over their entire life cycles. Oregon’s &lt;em&gt;2050 Vision for Materials Management&lt;/em&gt; charts a major shift in the state’s programs, expanding from recycling and waste management to include a strong focus upstream, addressing production and consumption. This webinar will tell the story of Oregon’s shift from discards management to full life-cycle materials management, introduce Oregon’s &lt;em&gt;2050 Vision&lt;/em&gt;, discuss the reason for the shift, present recent legislative activity, and provide a sampling of new work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The webinar will also feature two specific projects, the consumption-based greenhouse gas emissions inventory and their statewide strategy to reduce the wasting of food in commercial and household kitchens. Oregon’s consumption-based greenhouse gas emissions inventory estimates the global, life-cycle emissions associated with all goods and services (including materials) purchased by Oregonians. While Oregon pioneered this approach at the sub-national scale in North America, consumption-based inventories are currently being developed for all members of the C40 Cities, a global network of 80 large cities committed to addressing climate change. Oregon is also producing a major statewide strategy to reduce the wasting of food in commercial and household kitchens through source reduction, or waste prevention, and edible food donation.  This strategy is pushing further up the hierarchy, beyond recovery and edible food donation to waste avoidance.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;speakers&quot; name=&quot;speakers&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Speakers:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg left view-mode-teaser&quot; style=&quot;width:160px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;this is a photograph of the speaker David Allaway&quot; height=&quot;214&quot; width=&quot;160&quot; class=&quot;left media-element file-teaser left&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/small/public/2016-12/davidallaway.jpg&quot; title=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;David Allaway, Senior Policy Analyst, Oregon Department of Environmental Quality:&lt;/strong&gt; David Allaway is a senior policy analyst at the Oregon Department of Environmental Quality’s Materials Management Program.  He coordinates a variety of projects related to materials (including waste) management, sustainable production and consumption, greenhouse gases, and life cycle analysis. In 2010, he helped to staff the Oregon Global Warming Commission’s “Roadmap to 2020” project. He also leads efforts to develop and update Oregon’s consumption-based greenhouse gas emissions inventory, contributed to the ICLEI US greenhouse gas accounting protocols for communities and recycling, and led the sustainable production and consumption elements of Oregon’s &lt;em&gt;2050 Vision&lt;/em&gt;. Before joining DEQ in 2000, David worked for 11 years in the solid waste consulting industry. A native of Oregon, David has a B.A. in physics from Carleton College, Minnesota.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg right view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:108px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;this is a photograph of the speaker Elaine Blatt&quot; height=&quot;109&quot; width=&quot;108&quot; class=&quot;right media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2016-12/elainblatt.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Elaine Blatt, Senior Policy and Program Analyst, Oregon Department of Environmental Quality:  &lt;/strong&gt;Elaine Blatt is a Senior Policy and Program Analyst at the Oregon Department of Environmental Quality. She joined DEQ in February 2016, and her primary focus is on sustainable consumption and production of materials, with an initial focus on preventing the wasting of food.  Her prior experience includes consulting and managing a variety of projects related to sustainable production and consumption, biodiversity, energy efficiency, finance, and supply chain management, including work for the US Agency for International Development and the European Commission.  She managed support for the US-Asia Environmental Partnership, a USAID program focused on working with local partners to address urban environmental issues, including air and water quality, waste management, energy efficiency and renewable energy.  While in Asia, she also helped develop and implement a groundbreaking project to bring cleaner production practices to more than 400 Thai manufacturers. She has a MA in Public Policy from the University of Chicago and a BA in Political Science from Carleton College&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;slides&quot; name=&quot;slides&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Slides:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-338859&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-12/documents/intro_smm_web_academy_1-19-17.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=396355&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;The Story and Highlights of Oregon’s 2050 Vision of Materials Management (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(4 pp, 396 K)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;field field-name-field-document-description field-type-text field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    SMM webinar introductory slides  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-347511&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2017-01/documents/oregon_deq_epa_smm_012017_final_presentation_only.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=2003041&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;The Story and Highlights of Oregon’s 2050 Vision of Materials Management (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(47 pp, 2 MB)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;field field-name-field-document-description field-type-text field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    Oregon DEQ&amp;#039;s webinar slide presentation  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 15 Dec 2016 17:33:28 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>carcari</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">167303 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Memorandum of Understanding Between the American Chemistry Council&#039;s Flexible Film Recycling Group, the Green Blue Institute&#039;s Sustainable Packaging Coalition, and the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/smm/memorandum-understanding-between-american-chemistry-councils-flexible-film-recycling-group-green</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;EPA signed a Memorandum of Understanding (MOU) with the American Chemistry Council (ACC) and the Sustainable Packaging Coalition to support the WRAP program efforts to promote the collection and recycling of plastic film materials. This existing program works with state and local governments to build capacity for the collection of flexible film plastic materials in retail stores and educate consumers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA and ACC also agreed to work more generally to promote the sustainable management of plastics. Through the partnership, EPA and ACC will work together to: 1) decrease disposal rates by tracking and lowering the overall amount of plastics disposed through activities that enable source reduction, reuse, recycling and prevention; 2) Reduce environmental impacts—including greenhouse gas emissions, water and energy use—of plastics throughout their life cycles; and 3) Increase stakeholder capacity to implement sustainable materials management through technical assistance and raising the per capita quantity of plastic recyclables recovered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-336957&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-12/documents/ffrg_usepa_mou_agreement.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=1708563&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Memorandum of Understanding Between the American Chemistry Council&amp;#039;s Flexible Film Recycling Group, the Green Blue Institute&amp;#039;s Sustainability Packaging Coalition, and the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(6 pp, 2 MB)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 06 Dec 2016 21:57:43 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>esundin</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">166551 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Sustainable Materials Management (SMM) Web Academy Webinar: Advancing Sustainable Materials Management: Facts and Figures 2014</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/smm/sustainable-materials-management-smm-web-academy-webinar-advancing-sustainable-materials-0</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On this page:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#description&quot;&gt;Description&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Speakers&quot;&gt;Speakers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Slides&quot;&gt;Slides&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;description&quot; id=&quot;description&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Description&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Advancing Sustainable Materials Management: Facts and Figures 2014 – Assessing Trends in Materials Generation, Recycling, Composting, Combustion with Energy Recovery and Landfilling in the United States&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Thursday December 15, &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1:00pm-2:00pm EST&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	Through a discussion of the upcoming Facts and Figures Report, participants in this webinar heard about the updated Advancing Sustainable Materials Management (SMM): Facts and Figures 2014 report. Previously called the Municipal Solid Waste (MSW) Characterization Report, this report provides national solid waste generation, recycling, composting, combustion with energy recovery and landfilling numbers. The new report also includes data on construction and demolition debris generation and economic analysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-png left view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:41px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;YouTube Logo&quot; title=&quot;Image of the YouTube logo.&quot; height=&quot;20&quot; width=&quot;41&quot; class=&quot;left media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2016-04/you_tube_logo_20pxh.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Video: &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=e7f7sZvBgHg&quot;&gt;Advancing Sustainable Materials Management: Facts and Figures 2014 &lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;Speakers&quot; id=&quot;Speakers&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Speakers&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Swarupa Ganguli, Measurement Team Leader, U.S. EPA Office of Resource Conservation and Recovery&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	Swarupa Ganguli is the Measurement Team Lead at the Environmental Protection Agency&#039;s (EPA) Resource Conservation and Sustainability Division (RCSD) within the Office of Land and Emergency Management (OLEM). She directs detailed analysis of program policies, major issues and strategies related to Sustainable Materials Management (SMM) and serves as a senior spokesperson and liaison with Federal agencies, States, Local Government, industry representatives, non-governmental organizations, and the public in developing policy, guidance and regulation related to SMM. Prior to this position, she was the Team Lead for the Landfill Methane Outreach Program (LMOP) at EPA’s Climate Change Division (CCD) within the Office of Air and Radiation (OAR), a voluntary program that encourages methane emissions reductions through the capture and beneficial use of landfill gas. She managed LMOP’s domestic and international programs by providing technical assistance on landfill gas energy and creating alliances between the EPA and states, the landfill gas industry and communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Swarupa has an M.A. in International Relations and Economics from the School of Advanced International Studies (SAIS) at the Johns Hopkins University, a B.Sc. in Economics and Finance from the University of Pennsylvania’s Wharton Business School, and a Certificate in Environmental Law and Policy from the U.S. Department of Agriculture (USDA) Graduate Programs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hope Pillsbury, Analyst, U.S. EPA Office of Resource Conservation and Recovery &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	Hope Pillsbury is an analyst in EPA’s Office of Resource Conservation and Recovery. She has managed the work on the Advancing Sustainable Materials Management report series for over 10 years. Other work at EPA has included working with the National Park Service to encourage recycling at national parks, working to improve scrap tire management and acting as technical coordinator of a cross-media environmental study in Baltimore. She has a master’s in environmental studies from Yale School of Forestry and Environmental Studies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;Slides&quot; id=&quot;Slides&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Slides&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-332459&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-11/documents/introsmmwebacademydecember.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=495540&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Advancing SMM: Facts and Figures 2014 Webinar Slides (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(2 pp, 496 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 16 Nov 2016 16:32:04 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DSulliva</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">165207 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>2016 Recycling Economic Information (REI) Report and Methodology</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/smm/2016-recycling-economic-information-rei-report-and-methodology</link>
    <description>&lt;div class=&quot;box multi related-info right&quot;&gt;
	&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/smm/recycling-economic-information-rei-report&quot;&gt;Read more about the REI Report, including Frequent Questions. &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2016, EPA released the newest iteration of the Recycling Economic Information (REI) Report, as well as a new, updated analytical methodology. This report provides updated information about the number of recycling jobs, wages, and tax revenues in the United States.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-330327&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-11/documents/final_2016_rei_report.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=177275&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;2016 Recycling Economic Information (REI) Report (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(8 pp, 177 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-345901&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2017-01/documents/final_epa_2016_rei_methodology_v3.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=2995037&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;2016 Recycling Economic Information (REI) Report Methodology (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(129 pp, 3 MB)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Fri, 04 Nov 2016 13:47:07 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>esundin</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">164573 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Recycling Economic Information (REI) Report</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/smm/recycling-economic-information-rei-report</link>
    <description>&lt;div class=&quot;box multi related-info right&quot;&gt;
	&lt;h2 class=&quot;pane-title&quot;&gt;Additional Resources&lt;/h2&gt;

	&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.epa.gov/blog/2016/11/the-economic-power-of-recycling-sustainable-materials-management/&quot;&gt;Blog on 2016 REI Report&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/recycle/america-recycles-day-2016&quot;&gt;America Recycles Day 2016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/smm/advancing-sustainable-materials-management-facts-and-figures&quot;&gt;Advancing Sustainable Materials Management: Facts and Figures Report&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/recycle/recycling-basics&quot;&gt;Benefits of Recycling&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Recycling Economic Information (REI) Report aims to increase the understanding of the economic implications of material reuse and recycling. How our society uses materials is fundamental to our economic and environmental future. Global competition for finite resources will intensify as world population and economies grow. More productive and less impactful use of materials helps our society remain economically competitive, contributes to our prosperity and protects the environment in a resource-constrained future. By converting waste materials into valuable raw materials, recycling creates jobs, builds more competitive manufacturing industries and significantly contributes to the U.S. economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On this page:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#background&quot;&gt;Background on the REI Report&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#findings&quot;&gt;Key Findings of the 2016 REI Report&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fqs&quot;&gt;Frequent Questions&lt;/a&gt;
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#q1&quot;&gt;What is the significance of the 2016 REI Report?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#q2&quot;&gt;What is the significance of the report&#039;s title?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#q3&quot;&gt;What is the new definition of recycling?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#q4&quot;&gt;How does the report relate to Sustainable Materials Management (SMM)?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#q5&quot;&gt;What are the main outcomes (takeaways) of the report?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#q6&quot;&gt;What was the methodology behind the 2016 REI Report and how does an input-output model work?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#q7&quot;&gt;Which methodological approach was used to provide the statistics and metrics?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#q8&quot;&gt;What are the data sources for this report?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#q9&quot;&gt;How does the 2016 REI Report differ from the 2001 REI Report?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#q10&quot;&gt;Why was there double counting in the 2001 REI Report? Is double counting still an issue with the 2016 REI Report?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#q11&quot;&gt;Does this report include &quot;pre-use&quot; or recycled materials that are reused within the manufacturing sector?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2 id=&quot;Materials&quot;&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;background&quot; name=&quot;background&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Background on the REI Report&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2001, to encourage the development of an economic market for recycling, EPA supported the creation of a national&lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.epa.gov/wastes/conserve/tools/rmd/web/html/index-3.html&quot;&gt; Recycling Economic Information (REI) Project&lt;/a&gt; and the related REI report, based upon the work of several states and regions. The REI report was a ground breaking national study demonstrating the economic value of recycling and reuse to the U.S. economy. Compiled through a cooperative agreement with the National Recycling Coalition, the study confirmed what many have known for decades: there are significant economic benefits in recycling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;findings&quot; name=&quot;findings&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Key Findings of the 2016 REI Report&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2016 REI Report includes updated information about the number of recycling jobs, wages, and tax revenue. The report shows that recycling and reuse of materials creates jobs, while also generating local and state tax revenues. In 2007, recycling and reuse activities in the United States accounted for:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;757,000 jobs&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;$36.6 billion in wages; and&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;$6.7 billion in tax revenues&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg right view-mode-medium&quot; style=&quot;width:448px;&quot;&gt;&lt;a
    href=&quot;/sites/production/files/2016-11/rei_graph.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Graph covering Wages, Tax and Jobs attributable to recycling&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; width=&quot;448&quot; class=&quot;right media-element file-medium right&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/medium/public/2016-11/rei_graph.jpg&quot; title=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;This equates to 1.57 jobs for every 1,000 tons of materials recycled. Construction and Demolition waste provides the largest contribution to all three categories (job, wage, and tax revenue), followed by ferrous metals and non-ferrous metals such as aluminum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2016 REI Report used an updated analytical framework and a new Waste Input-Output methodology, which focused on the life cycle of materials. These refinements offered significant improvements over the 2001 REI Study in terms of a better definition of recycling and a reduction in double counting. This new methodology will assist decision makers and researchers in more accurately estimating the economic benefits of recycling and create a foundation upon which additional studies can be built.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/smm/2016-recycling-economic-information-rei-report-and-methodology&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Read the 2016 REI Report and Methodology&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;fqs&quot; name=&quot;fqs&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Frequent Questions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;q1&quot; name=&quot;q1&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;1. What is the significance of the 2016 REI Report?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recycling conserves natural resources, strengthens our economy and creates jobs. Recycling is an essential part of Sustainable Materials Management (SMM), an approach that emphasizes the productive and sustainable use of materials across their entire life cycle, while minimizing their environmental impacts. In 2016, EPA released a new REI Report that utilizes an updated and refined analytical framework, and focuses on SMM. The 2016 REI Report covers the economic activities of nine sectors: ferrous metals, nonferrous metals (aluminum), glass, paper, plastics, rubber, construction and demolition (C&amp;amp;D), electronics and organics (including food and yard trimmings).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;q2&quot; name=&quot;q2&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;2. What is the significance of the report&#039;s title?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2016 Recycling Economic Information (REI) Report builds on the work from the 2001 REI study. The report focuses on the economic impacts of recycling rather than the environmental benefits, as the environmental benefits have been researched in detail. Accurately estimating the impact that recycling has on jobs, wages and taxes is important because the results can influence policy decisions and provide a more robust picture of recycling by adding an economic layer on top of the more heavily researched environmental impacts of recycling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;q3&quot; name=&quot;q3&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;3. What is the new definition of recycling?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recycling is defined as the recovery of materials, such as paper, glass, plastic, metals, construction and demolition (C&amp;amp;D) material and organics from the waste stream (e.g., municipal solid waste), along with the transformation of materials, to make new products and reduce the amount of virgin raw materials needed to meet consumer demands. In addition to updating the definition of recycling, the 2016 REI Report identified nine materials and investigated their direct and indirect impact on jobs, wages and taxes. In contrast, the 2001 REI Report identified recycling processes rather than materials and investigated the impact of the processes on jobs, wages and taxes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;q4&quot; name=&quot;q4&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;4. How does the report relate to Sustainable Materials Management (SMM)?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SMM refers to the use and reuse of materials in the most productive and sustainable way across their entire life cycle. On a broader scale, SMM examines social, environmental and economic factors, each playing a critical role, to get a more holistic view of the entire system. The benefits of maximizing this connection include conserving resources, reducing waste, slowing climate change and minimizing the environmental impacts of the materials we use. Since the third key element to SMM is economics, it was important to update the REI Report to provide an economic and systemic view of recycling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;q5&quot; name=&quot;q5&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;5. What are the main outcomes (takeaways) of the report?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2016 REI Report reiterated that recycling and recycled products play an important role in our economy and have significant positive impacts on jobs, wages and tax collections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th scope=&quot;row&quot;&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
			&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;Gross Totals&lt;/th&gt;
			&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;Economic Share&lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;&lt;caption&gt;Recycling and Reuse Activities in 2007&lt;/caption&gt;
	&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th scope=&quot;row&quot;&gt;Jobs&lt;/th&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Accounted for 757,000 jobs&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;0.52% of the U.S. economy&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th scope=&quot;row&quot;&gt;Wages&lt;/th&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Produced $36.6 billion in wages&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;0.62% of the U.S. economy&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th scope=&quot;row&quot;&gt;Taxes&lt;/th&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;Produced $6.7 billion in tax revenues&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;0.90% of the U.S. economy&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;p&gt;On a national average, there are 1.57 jobs, $76,030 million wages and $14,101 tax revenues attributable, for every 1,000 (US) tons of recyclables collected and recycled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;q6&quot; name=&quot;q6&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;6. What was the methodology behind the 2016 REI Report and how does an input-output model work?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA developed a waste input-output (WIO) model to provide an improved analytical framework for better understanding the contributions of recycling to the U.S. economy. Instead of examining the job codes within the context of an I-O model, the 2016 REI Report focused on nine material categories and follows the flow of materials through the WIO model. By focusing on material categories, the model identified direct impacts of recycling on jobs, wages and taxes and then upstream indirect impacts. The WIO model built on the official U.S. input-output (I-O) tables maintained by the Bureau of Economic Analysis (BEA). These tables describe the economic transactions between industries in the U.S. and are used to formulate U.S. monetary and fiscal policy. Using the I-O tables as the starting point, the WIO model added information about recyclable and recycled material flows in the U.S., and information about employment and local, state and federal tax revenue. Combining this information with the detailed statistics regarding economic transactions enables the estimation of the economic activity attributable to recycling. The combination of the WIO model results, along with detailed statistics regarding economic transactions, enabled the estimation of the economic activity attributable to recycling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;For more specific information about the methodology (including examples) please see the &lt;a href=&quot;/smm/2016-recycling-economic-information-rei-report-and-methodology&quot;&gt;methodology paper Chapter 3: Summary of the WIO Model Methodology&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;q7&quot; name=&quot;q7&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;7. Which methodological approach was used to provide the statistics and metrics?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;&quot;direct and indirect production of recycling&quot;&lt;/strong&gt;, also called the &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;intermediate approach&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; in the methodology document, was chosen to communicate the results of the study.&lt;br /&gt;
	The &lt;strong&gt;intermediate approach&lt;/strong&gt; accounted for not only direct, but also upstream supply chain economic activity attributable to recycling processes. In addition to the intermediate approach, three other approaches were analyzed and are explained in detail in the &lt;a href=&quot;/smm/2016-recycling-economic-information-rei-report-and-methodology&quot;&gt;methodology document&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt;.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;q8&quot; name=&quot;q8&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;8. What are the data sources for the report?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key data sources for this report include industry outreach, existing reports (including government, industry and other publicly available reports) and life cycle inventory datasets (such as Ecoinvent V.3.0 and CEDv.4.8). Below is a list of organizations and industry associations involved in the data sourcing for this report:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th scope=&quot;row&quot;&gt;Material&lt;/th&gt;
			&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;Organization/Industry Association&lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th scope=&quot;row&quot;&gt;Ferrous Metals&lt;/th&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Institute of Scrap Recycling Industries, Inc. (ISRI)&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;Steel Recycling Institute (SRI)&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th scope=&quot;row&quot;&gt;Nonferrous Metals&lt;/th&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;The Aluminum Association&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th scope=&quot;row&quot;&gt;Plastic&lt;/th&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;American Chemistry Council (ACC)&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;The Association of Postconsumer Plastic Recyclers (APR)&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;Society of the Plastics Industry (SPI)&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;KW Plastics&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th scope=&quot;row&quot;&gt;Rubber&lt;/th&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Rubber Manufacturers Association&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th scope=&quot;row&quot;&gt;Glass&lt;/th&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Glass Packaging Institute&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;Container Recycling Institute&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th scope=&quot;row&quot;&gt;Paper&lt;/th&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;American Forest and Paper Association (AF&amp;amp;PA)&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;American Wood Council (AWC)&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;U.S. Department of Agriculture (USDA)&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th scope=&quot;row&quot;&gt;Construction &amp;amp; Demolition&lt;/th&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Construction &amp;amp; Demolition Recycling Association&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th scope=&quot;row&quot;&gt;Electronics&lt;/th&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;EPA Office of Resource Conservation and Recovery (ORCR)&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;Electronics TakeBack Coalition&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th scope=&quot;row&quot;&gt;Organics&lt;/th&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;BioCycle&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;q9&quot; name=&quot;q9&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;9. How does the 2016 REI Report differ from the 2001 REI Report?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The differences between the 2001 REI Report and the 2016 REI Report were primarily in the definition of recycling, scope, proportioning of economic factors, methodology and base years of data and recycling trends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Definition of recycling processes:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;The 2001 RE Report identified recycling processes (e.g., material collection), processing and related activities (e.g., wholesaling), and estimates of direct economic contributions from recycling.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;The 2016 REI Report identified materials and industries directly engaged in recycling. The process associated with recycling these materials were counted as upstream or downstream processes that are captured in the indirect production of recycling approach. The indirect production of recycling approach included upstream and downstream processes associated with recycling the previously identified materials. The 2016 REI Report approach more accurately captured the jobs, wages and taxes associated with recycling and minimized the impact of double counting.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Scoping approach:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;The 2001 REI Report identified industry sectors directly or indirectly engaged in recycling based on the methodology established in earlier REI studies by the Northeast Recycling Coalition (NERC, 1998).&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;The 2016 REI Report identified the scope of recycling activity using a materials flow approach. Based on government and industry information documenting the flows and destination, nine primary recyclable materials were selected with industries directly engaged in recycling. Industries indirectly engaged in recycling were identified using the WIO model.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Proportioning economic factors:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;The two studies used a different approach for apportioning jobs and wages associated with processes that use a mix of recyclable and natural resources.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;The 2001 REI Report counted all jobs (and associated wages) engaged in processing recyclables regardless of the mix of recyclable and virgin materials in the process.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;The 2016 REI Report apportioned jobs and wages according to the mix of recyclables and the virgin materials for which recycles are used as a substitute.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Multiplier methodology for estimating indirect effects:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;The 2001 REI Report used local and regional multiplier estimates based on proprietary information, while the 2016 REI Report used national Input-Output tables with peer-reviewed factor input multipliers, which limited double counting in the 2016 REI Report estimates.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;The 2016 REI Report improved the multiplier models used to estimate the indirect estimate on jobs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Base year and recycling trends:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;The 2001 REI report used a base year of 1997.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;The 2016 REI report used a base year of 2007.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;The contributions of recycling to national economic activity can be affected by changes in conditions such as: economic output and employment in different sectors; recyclables recovery; recyclable and recycled material markets; and recycling technology.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;q10&quot; name=&quot;q10&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;10. Why was there double counting in the 2001 REI Report? Is double counting still an issue with the 2016 REI Report?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2001 REI Report acknowledged several challenges and limitations of the REI methodology, including the ability to isolate recycling activities within multi-faceted manufacturing sectors and identifying industry sectors directly or indirectly engaged in recycling. The 2001 REI Report counted all jobs engaged in processing recyclables regardless of the mix of recyclable and virgin material content, while the 2016 REI Report apportioned jobs according to the mix of virgin and recycled material, which more accurately estimates the impact of recyclables in the production process and the upstream effect on jobs. The 2016 REI Report improved the multiplier models used to estimate the indirect estimate on jobs. The 2001 REI Report used local and regional multiplier estimates based on proprietary information, while the 2016 REI Report used national Input-Output tables with peer-reviewed factor input multipliers, which limited double counting in the 2016 REI Report estimates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;For more detailed analysis and description of the double counting issue, please see &lt;a href=&quot;/smm/2016-recycling-economic-information-rei-report-and-methodology&quot;&gt;Figure 15 in the methodology document&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;q11&quot; name=&quot;q11&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;11. Does this report include &quot;pre-use&quot; or recycling materials that are reused within the manufacturing sector?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No. “Pre-use” or recycled materials that are reused within the manufacturing sector were not included primarily due to a lack of data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 03 Nov 2016 19:46:07 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>gharman</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">164523 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Sustainable Materials Management (SMM) Web Academy Webinar: Recycling Collection Programs - A Bigger Pinch Point Than We Thought</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/smm/sustainable-materials-management-smm-web-academy-webinar-recycling-collection-programs-bigger</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On this page:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#desc&quot;&gt;Description&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#speakers&quot;&gt;Speakers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#slides&quot;&gt;Slides&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;desc&quot; name=&quot;desc&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Description:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Thursday, November 17, 2016 at 1:00pm - 2:30pm EST&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marketing departments are largely to thank for the latest national study on recycling. For years, industry has substantiated claims of package recyclability with “access to recycling rates” – the percentage of consumers with a recycling program accepting the package. If the rate is high, then the package may be considered recyclable, and a number of studies have been produced to gather these important figures. The Sustainable Packaging Coalition (SPC), a broad industry working group led by the sustainability non-profit GreenBlue, has centralized industry efforts and released findings from a new study collectively funded by thirteen packaging trade associations and non-profit organizations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sustainablepackaging.org/content/?type=5&amp;amp;id=centralized-study-on-availability-of-recycling&quot;&gt; &lt;em&gt;SPC Centralized Study on Availability of Recycling&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt; went beyond its driver of “access to recycling rates” and gathered new information on the prevalence of residential recycling programs across the United States and the key characteristics of those programs. The study findings shed new light on the diversity of recycling collection programs and the prevalence of quality, convenient collection programs that are likely to be used. The top-level finding that 94 percent of Americans have a recycling program available to them is encouraging, but a deeper dive into the characteristics of those programs suggests all is not well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During this webinar Adam Gendell, Associate Director of the Sustainable Packaging Coalition, gave an overview of the study findings and paint a new national portrait of the types of recycling programs made available to Americans and the types of packaging accepted by those programs. Kelly Cramer, Senior Manager of the Sustainable Packaging Coalition, gave an overview of How2Recycle, the Sustainable Packaging Coalition&#039;s labeling system for package recyclability. Learn how How2Recycle leverages the study findings and provides recyclability messaging to hundreds of packages from a number of leading brands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-png left view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:41px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;YouTube Logo&quot; title=&quot;Image of the YouTube logo.&quot; height=&quot;20&quot; width=&quot;41&quot; class=&quot;left media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2016-04/you_tube_logo_20pxh.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Video:  &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/DlGSU_I-qEo&quot;&gt;Recycling Collection Programs - A Bigger Pinch Point Than We Thought &lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;speakers&quot; name=&quot;speakers&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Speakers:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg left view-mode-teaser&quot; style=&quot;width:160px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img height=&quot;160&quot; width=&quot;160&quot; class=&quot;left media-element file-teaser left&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/small/public/2016-10/adam.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Adam Gendell,&lt;/strong&gt; - &lt;em&gt;Associate Director, &lt;/em&gt;Sustainable Packaging Coalition -Adam is Associate Director of the Sustainable Packaging Coalition, the flagship project of the industry-facing sustainability non-profit GreenBlue. Adam’s work with the packaging value chain touches on goal-setting, design considerations, and integrating life cycle thinking into packaging decisions. Adam has developed and delivered training seminars for hundreds of packaging professionals, and he oversees the Coalition’s annual Fall conference &lt;em&gt;SPC Advance&lt;/em&gt;. He is a frequent speaker and writer on packaging sustainability.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg left view-mode-teaser&quot; style=&quot;width:160px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img height=&quot;160&quot; width=&quot;160&quot; class=&quot;left media-element file-teaser left&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/small/public/2016-10/kelly.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kelly Cramer,&lt;/strong&gt; -&lt;em&gt;Senior Manager&lt;/em&gt; -Sustainable Packaging Coalition -Kelly is leading one of its fastest growing programs, How2Recycle. Ultimately, she wants to promote creative change in how people conceptualize their relationship to the earth — and is interested in using the art of strategy and information to effectuate that goal. Kelly holds a J.D. in Environmental Law from Lewis &amp;amp; Clark Law School in Portland, Oregon and an undergraduate degree in psychology and Spanish from the University of Tennessee. Previous experience includes a judicial clerkship for the State of Oregon’s trial court in downtown Portland, as well as time spent at Earthrise Law Center, Northwest Environmental Defense Center, and San Diego Coastkeeper. Areas of interest include risk analysis, geopolitics, design, and systems thinking.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;slides&quot; name=&quot;slides&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Slides:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-327189&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-10/documents/updated_intro_smm_web_academy_november.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=358366&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Recycling Coalition Programs: A Bigger Pinch Point Than We Thought (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(3 pp, 358 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Mon, 24 Oct 2016 13:57:53 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>carcari</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">163277 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Sustainable Materials Management (SMM) Web Academy Webinar: New Tool Kit - Keeping Food out of the Landfill - Policy Ideas for States and Localities</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/smm/sustainable-materials-management-smm-web-academy-webinar-new-tool-kit-keeping-food-out-landfill</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On this page:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#desc&quot;&gt;Description&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#speakers&quot;&gt;Speakers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#slides&quot;&gt;Slides&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;desc&quot; name=&quot;desc&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Description:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Thursday, October 20, 2016 at 1:00pm - 2:30pm ET&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In September 2015, the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.usda.gov/oce/foodwaste/&quot;&gt;United States Department of Agriculture (USDA)&lt;/a&gt; and United States Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) announced the first ever &lt;a href=&quot;/sustainable-management-food/united-states-2030-food-loss-and-waste-reduction-goal&quot;&gt;domestic goal to reduce food loss and waste by half by the year 2030&lt;/a&gt; and are seeking to work with public and private partners to take action and make this happen over the next 14 years. The &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.chlpi.org/food-law-and-policy/&quot;&gt;Harvard Food Law and Policy Clinic (FLPC)&lt;/a&gt; is one of EPA’s partners and is at the forefront of identifying key areas where current laws create barriers to reducing this food waste or where policies can incentivize more food recovery, and is actively working on the federal and state level to help reform those laws. One way to assist with the proliferation of better food recovery laws and policies is by providing information to states and local governments regarding methods of increasing food recovery. In order to make such information more widely available, FLPC created a toolkit for state and local policymakers interested in reducing food waste. This toolkit brings together lessons from their research and policy work in date labeling, tax incentives, liability protections, organic waste bans, leftovers for livestock as well as other food waste policies, to provide state and local policy makers with a comprehensive menu of policy options to reduce food waste.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This webinar cover what is included in this toolkit, and how you can use it in your state or local food waste policy planning. Presenters will explain the content and how best to use the toolkit, with a focus on a few of the sections, and will answer questions from webinar participants about these and other examples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-png left view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:41px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;YouTube Logo&quot; title=&quot;Image of the YouTube logo.&quot; height=&quot;20&quot; width=&quot;41&quot; class=&quot;left media-element file-full&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2016-04/you_tube_logo_20pxh.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Video: &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/ZI7_jPLCz00&quot;&gt;New Tool Kit: Keeping Food out of the Landfill: Policy Ideas for States and Localities &lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;speakers&quot; name=&quot;speakers&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Speakers:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	 &lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg left view-mode-media_original&quot; style=&quot;width:150px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Picture of Emily Broad Leib&quot; title=&quot;Picture of Emily Broad Leib&quot; height=&quot;200&quot; width=&quot;150&quot; class=&quot;left media-element file-media-original&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/2016-09/leib.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;Emily Broad Leib, &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Assistant Clinical Professor of Law; Director of the Food Law and Policy Clinic and Deputy Director of the Center for Health Law and Policy Innovation, Harvard Law School&lt;/em&gt; -  Emily is an Assistant Clinical Professor of Law at Harvard Law School, as well as Deputy Director of the Center for Health Law and Policy Innovation. She founded and directs the Center’s Food Law and Policy Clinic, the first law school clinic in the nation devoted to studying and providing legal and policy solutions for the health, economic, and environmental challenges facing our food system. Emily’s groundbreaking work on food waste has been covered in such media outlets as CNN, The Today Show, MSNBC, TIME Magazine, Politico, and the Washington Post&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-png left view-mode-media_original&quot; style=&quot;width:150px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Picture of Christina Rice&quot; title=&quot;Picture of Christina Rice&quot; height=&quot;147&quot; width=&quot;150&quot; class=&quot;left media-element file-media-original&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/2016-09/rice.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;Christina Rice, &lt;/strong&gt; - &lt;em&gt;Clinical Fellow, Harvard Law School Food Law and Policy &lt;/em&gt; - Christina Rice is a Clinical Fellow in the Food Law and Policy Clinic at Harvard Law School, where she provides legal and policy guidance to community advocacy groups, state agencies and non-profits who are working to improve the food system. Christina helps lead the Clinic’s Food Waste Initiative, which advocates for policy change to decrease unnecessary food waste. Christina is licensed to practice law in North Carolina. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;slides&quot; name=&quot;slides&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Slides:&lt;/h2&gt;



&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-326359&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-10/documents/final_intro_and_new_tool_kit_keeping_food_out_of_landfills.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=2969196&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Keeping Food Out of the Landfill: Policy Ideas for State and Localities (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(47 pp, 3 MB)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 22 Sep 2016 16:35:41 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>carcari</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">160963 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Advancing Resource Efficiency in the Supply Chain - Observations and Opportunities for Action</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/smm/advancing-resource-efficiency-supply-chain-observations-and-opportunities-action</link>
    <description>&lt;div class=&quot;box multi related-info right&quot;&gt;
	&lt;h2 class=&quot;pane-title&quot;&gt;Related Information&lt;/h2&gt;

	&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/smm/workshop-resources-g7-alliance-resource-efficiency-us-hosted-workshop-use-life-cycle-concepts&quot;&gt;Other Workshop Resources&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This document provides U.S. EPA’s perspectives on the discussions at the &lt;a href=&quot;/smm/g7-alliance-resource-efficiency-us-hosted-workshop-use-life-cycle-concepts-supply-chain&quot;&gt;G7 Alliance on Resource Efficiency U.S.-hosted Workshop&lt;/a&gt; on the Use of Life Cycle Concepts in Supply Chain Management to Achieve Resource Efficiency that was held March 22-23, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this report is to distil the robust and constructive workshop discussions captured in the &lt;a href=&quot;/smm/workshop-summary-proceedings-document-g7-alliance-resource-efficiency-us-hosted-workshop-use&quot;&gt;Workshop Summary Proceedings&lt;/a&gt; released in June 2016 into critical areas for targeted life cycle-based resource efficiency dialogue and action that can facilitate efforts to mainstream and institutionalize resource efficiency. In particular, the seven critical needs areas that the U.S. EPA has identified for this report, based on workshop discussions, can inform future focused dialogues in appropriate forums on short- and long-term actions which individuals and organizations from various sectors of society can champion. Under each critical needs area, questions are posed that should be addressed in the context of the challenges, “best” practices, and potential actions which can be found in Appendix 1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-316541&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-09/documents/g7_us_workshop_opportunities_report_final_091416_508compliant_v3_-_copy.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=811893&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Advancing Resource Efficiency in the Supply Chain – Observations and Opportunities for Action (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(30 pp, 812 K, 
  September 14, 2016, 
  EPA 530-R-16-014)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 20 Sep 2016 03:24:04 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>carcari</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">160675 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Workshop Summary Proceedings Document: G7 Alliance on Resource Efficiency: U.S.-hosted Workshop on the Use of Life Cycle Concepts in Supply Chain Management to Achieve Resource Efficiency</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/smm/workshop-summary-proceedings-document-g7-alliance-resource-efficiency-us-hosted-workshop-use</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;This proceedings document summarizes prepared remarks, presentations and discussions from the G7 Alliance on Resource Efficiency: U.S.-hosted Workshop on the Use of Life Cycle Concepts in Supply Chain Management to Achieve Resource Efficiency. This document is not intended to contain any consensus findings, recommendations, or agreements made by participants or of the G7 Alliance on Resource Efficiency; rather, it should be viewed as a summary of individual workshop participant statements and ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-313881&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-09/documents/g7_us_workshop_summary_proceedings_final.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=642785&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;G7 U.S. Workshop Summary Proceedings (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(80 pp, 643 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 08 Sep 2016 14:54:04 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>esundin</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">159643 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  </channel>
</rss>

<!-- Page cached by Boost @ 2017-01-25 17:21:58, expires @ 2017-01-26 05:21:58, lifetime 12 hours -->