<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?><rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.epa.gov/feed/37231/rss.xml" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/" xmlns:og="http://ogp.me/ns#" xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#" xmlns:sioc="http://rdfs.org/sioc/ns#" xmlns:sioct="http://rdfs.org/sioc/types#" xmlns:skos="http://www.w3.org/2004/02/skos/core#" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#">
  <channel>
    <title>NEPA</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/feed/37231/rss.xml</link>
    <description>Updated NEPA content from the US Environmental Protection Agency</description>
    <language>en</language>
     <atom:link href="https://www.epa.gov/feed/37231/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      <item>
    <title>National Environmental Policy Act (NEPA) 2016 Annual Results</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/nepa/national-environmental-policy-act-nepa-2016-annual-results</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;In fulfillment of our responsibilities under Section 309 of the Clean Air Act, EPA issued comment letters on over 300 draft and final Environmental Impact Statements (EISs). These included EISs concerning:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;resource management plans – 10&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;oil and gas exploration or extraction – 11&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;mining - 8&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;transmission lines – 8&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;EPA met its performance goals in FY 2016 for the NEPA program: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;76 percent of the significant impacts identified in EPA’s comment letters on draft EISs were avoided, minimized, or compensated for (“mitigated”) by the lead agencies in the final EISs published in FY 2016.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;High Priority Infrastructure Projects&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	EPA worked with the Office of Management and Budget (OMB), the White House Council on Environmental Quality (CEQ), and other federal agencies to implement the Fixing America’s Surface Transportation (FAST) Act, which includes provisions in Title 41 related to the improvement of federal permitting and environmental review of infrastructure projects.  In particular, EPA worked with OMB, CEQ, and other federal agencies to develop implementation guidance, and to identify EPA covered projects, statutes, and permits.  &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 07 Dec 2016 23:09:26 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cschae02</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">166643 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>EPA Comments on the Draft Environmental Assessment for the Eagle Crest Energy Gen-Tie and Water Pipeline Project</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/nepa/epa-comments-draft-environmental-assessment-eagle-crest-energy-gen-tie-and-water-pipeline</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;The EPA has reviewed the Draft Environmental Assessment for the Eagle Crest Energy Gen-Tie and Water Pipeline Project located in Riverside County, California.  EPA&#039;s comments provide recommendations on the analyses and documentation that should be considered prior to making a determination on the significance of the potential impacts from the project. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-335441&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-11/documents/2016_11_08-epa_comments_eagle_crest_gentie_dea.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=4057453&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Draft Environmental Assessment for the Eagle Crest Energy Gen-Tie and Water Pipeline Project, Riverside, California (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(9 pp, 4 MB, 
  November 8, 2016)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 30 Nov 2016 01:19:51 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cschae02</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">165979 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Region 8 Comment Letter on Dakota Access Pipeline Project</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/nepa/region-8-comment-letter-dakota-access-pipeline-project</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;The proposed Dakota Access Pipeline project is a 1134-mile, 12-inch to 30-inch diameter pipeline that will transport crude oil from the Bakken/Three Forks oil fields in North Dakota to Illinois. EPA Region 8 provided comments on the U.S. Army Corps of Engineers (USACE) Dakota Access Pipeline Draft Environmental Assessment (EA).&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-334009&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-11/documents/dakota_access_pipeline_dea_cmts_1-8-16.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=160444&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Comment Letter on the USACE Dakota Access Pipeline EA (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(4 pp, 160 K, 
  January 8, 2016)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-334029&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-11/documents/dakota_access_2nd_dea_cmts_3-11-16.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=393434&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Additional Comments on the USACE Dakota Access Pipeline EA (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(5 pp, 393 K, 
  March 11, 2016)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 22 Nov 2016 22:30:25 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cschae02</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">165613 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Health Impact Assessment for National Environmental Policy Act Reviews</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/nepa/health-impact-assessment-national-environmental-policy-act-reviews</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;This memorandum provides information to promote the use of a health impact assessment in EPA&#039;s reviews conducted pursuant to the National Environmental Policy Act (NEPA) and Section 309 of the Clean Air Act. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-264381&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-03/documents/hia_memo_from_bromm.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=367105&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Promoting the Use of Health Impact Assessment to Address Human Health in Reviews Conducted Pursuant to the NEPA and Section 309 of the Clean Air Act (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(2 pp, 367 K, 
  November 10, 2015)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Fri, 11 Mar 2016 00:01:58 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cschae02</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">138217 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Environmental Impact Statement Rating System Criteria </title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/nepa/environmental-impact-statement-rating-system-criteria</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;EPA has developed a set of criteria for rating a draft Environmental Impact Statement (EIS). EPA rates the draft EIS on an alpha-numeric system and includes the designated rating in EPA&#039;s comment letter. In general, the rating is based on the lead agency&#039;s preferred alternative. The rating system provides a basis upon which EPA makes recommendations to the lead agency for improving the draft EIS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;The alphabetical categories listed below &lt;/span&gt;signify EPA&#039;s evaluation of the environmental impacts of the proposal:&lt;span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#LO (Lack of Objections)&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;LO (Lack of Objections) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#EC (Environmental Concerns)&quot;&gt;EC (Environmental Concerns)&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#EO (Environmental Objections)&quot;&gt;EO (Environmental Objections)&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#EU (Environmentally Unsatisfactory)&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;EU (Environmentally Unsatisfactory) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;The numerical categories listed below &lt;/span&gt;signify an evaluation of the adequacy of the draft EIS:&lt;span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Category 1 - Adequate&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;1 (Adequate)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Category 2 - Insufficient Information&quot;&gt;&lt;span&gt;2&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span&gt;(Insufficient Information)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Category 3 - Inadequate&quot;&gt;3 (Inadequate)&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;The rating of the draft EIS consists of one of the category combinations shown below:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;span&gt;LO&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;EC-1, EC-2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;EO-1, EO-2, EO-3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;EU-1, EU-2, EU-3, or 3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rating the Environmental Impact of the Action&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;LO (Lack of Objections)&quot; id=&quot;LO (Lack of Objections)&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;LO (Lack of Objections)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The review has not identified any potential environmental impacts requiring substantive changes to the preferred alternative. The review may have disclosed opportunities for application of mitigation measures that could be accomplished with no more than minor changes to the proposed action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;EC (Environmental Concerns)&quot; id=&quot;EC (Environmental Concerns)&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;EC (Environmental Concerns)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The review has identified environmental impacts that should be avoided in order to fully protect the environment. Corrective measures may require changes to the preferred alternative or application of mitigation measures that can reduce the environmental impact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;EO (Environmental Objections)&quot; id=&quot;EO (Environmental Objections)&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;strong&gt;EO (Environmental Objections)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The review has identified significant environmental impacts that should be avoided in order to adequately protect the environment. Corrective measures may require substantial changes to the preferred alternative or consideration of some other project alternative (including the no action alternative or a new alternative). The basis for environmental Objections can include situations:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;Where an action might violate or be inconsistent with achievement or maintenance of a national environmental standard;&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;Where the federal agency violates its own substantive environmental requirements that relate to EPA&#039;s areas of jurisdiction or expertise;&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;Where there is a violation of an EPA policy declaration;&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;Where there are no applicable standards or where applicable standards will not be violated but there is potential for significant environmental degradation that could be corrected by project modification or other feasible alternatives; or&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;Where proceeding with the proposed action would set a precedent for future actions that collectively could result in significant environmental impacts.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;EU (Environmentally Unsatisfactory)&quot; id=&quot;EU (Environmentally Unsatisfactory)&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;EU (Environmentally Unsatisfactory)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The review has identified adverse environmental impacts that are of sufficient magnitude that EPA believes the proposed action must not proceed as proposed. The basis for an environmentally unsatisfactory determination consists of identification of environmentally objectionable impacts as defined above and one or more of the following conditions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;The potential violation of, or inconsistency with, a national environmental standard is substantive and/or will occur on a long-term basis;&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;There are no applicable standards but the severity, duration, or geographical scope of the impacts associated with the proposed action warrant special attention; or&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;The potential environmental impacts resulting from the proposed action are of national importance because of the threat to national environmental resources or to environmental policies.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;!-- #BeginLibraryItem &quot;/Library/returntotop.lbi&quot; --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;!-- #EndLibraryItem --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rating the Adequacy of the Draft Environmental Impact Statement (EIS)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;Category 1 - Adequate&quot; id=&quot;Category 1 - Adequate&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Category 1 - Adequate&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The draft EIS adequately sets forth the environmental impact(s) of the preferred alternative and those of the alternatives reasonably available to the project or action. No further analysis or data collection is necessary, but the reviewer may suggest the addition of clarifying language or information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;Category 2 - Insufficient Information&quot; id=&quot;Category 2 - Insufficient Information&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Category 2 - Insufficient Information&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The draft EIS does not contain sufficient information to fully assess environmental impacts that should be avoided in order to fully protect the environment, or the reviewer has identified new reasonably available alternatives that are within the spectrum of alternatives analyzed in the draft EIS, which could reduce the environmental impacts of the proposal. The identified additional information, data, analyses, or discussion should be included in the final EIS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;Category 3 - Inadequate&quot; id=&quot;Category 3 - Inadequate&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Category 3 - Inadequate&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The draft EIS does not adequately assess the potentially significant environmental impacts of the proposal, or the reviewer has identified new, reasonably available, alternatives, that are outside of the spectrum of alternatives analyzed in the draft EIS, which should be analyzed in order to reduce the potentially significant environmental impacts. The identified additional information, data, analyses, or discussions are of such a magnitude that they should have full public review at a draft stage. This rating indicates EPA&#039;s belief that the draft EIS does not meet the purposes of NEPA and/or the Section 309 review, and thus should be formally revised and made available for public comment in a supplemental or revised draft EIS.&lt;!-- #BeginLibraryItem &quot;/Library/returntotop.lbi&quot; --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2015 21:55:47 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cschae02</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">74009 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>EPA Review Process under Section 309 of the Clean Air Act </title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/nepa/epa-review-process-under-section-309-clean-air-act</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;EPA reviews all draft Environmental Impact Statements (EIS) prepared by other federal agencies, as well as other certain federal actions, as required by &lt;a href=&quot;https://ceq.doe.gov/laws-regulations/laws.html&quot;&gt;Section 309 of the Clean Air Act&lt;/a&gt;. Section 309 also requires that EPA make these reviews public, and EPA does this by posting EPA comment letters on EISs in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://cdxnodengn.epa.gov/cdx-enepa-public/action/eis/search&quot;&gt;EIS database&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA&#039;s reviews are primarily concerned with identifying and recommending appropriate measures to avoid and mitigate significant environmental impacts associated with the proposal. EPA also evaluates the adequacy of the information presented in the EIS. As part of EPA&#039;s review, EPA rates all draft EISs submitted using a two-prong rating system:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;A rating for the environmental impacts of the proposed action and&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;A rating for the adequacy of the information presented in the EIS.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Learn more about &lt;a href=&quot;/nepa/environmental-impact-statement-rating-system-criteria&quot;&gt;EPA&#039;s Rating System Criteria&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA also conducts reviews of final EISs to ensure that the lead agency has taken EPA&#039;s comments into account. If the project remains environmentally unsatisfactory, EPA may refer the matter to the Council on Environmental Quality (CEQ). Learn more about &lt;a href=&quot;https://ceq.doe.gov/docs/nepa-practice/referrals-to-ceq-dec-2016.pdf&quot;&gt;CEQ&#039;s referral process (PDF)&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(4 pp, 40 K, &lt;a href=&quot;/home/pdf-files&quot;&gt;About PDF&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA has prepared a detailed manual that explains the policies and procedures for carrying out its review responsibilities under the National Environmental Policy Act and Section 309 of the Clean Air Act.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Read more about &lt;a href=&quot;/nepa/policy-and-procedures-review-federal-actions-impacting-environment-under-section-309-clean-air&quot;&gt;EPA&#039;s Policy and Procedures for 309 Reviews&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
     <pubDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2015 19:55:18 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cschae02</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">73247 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>EPA Region 5 Environmental Information Document Template</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/nepa/epa-region-5-environmental-information-document-template</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;For Special Appropriation Grants from Congress, EPA Region 5 strongly advises grant applicants to complete the environmental review process before beginning construction. This environmental information document template is used by Special Appropriation Project grant applicants to provide information about the proposed project located in EPA Region 5.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt; &lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-107291&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-01/documents/region_5_eid200907.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=90966&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;EPA Region 5 Environmental Information Document Template (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(19 pp, 91 K, 
  July 2009)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 29 Jan 2015 18:43:49 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cschae02</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">73047 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Submitting Copies of Environmental Impact Statements to EPA Regional Offices</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/nepa/submitting-copies-environmental-impact-statements-epa-regional-offices</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	A federal agency must submit the environmental impact statement (EIS) to the appropriate EPA regional office no later than the date that agency files and submits the EIS in &lt;em&gt;e-NEPA&lt;/em&gt;. EISs should be sent to the EPA region where the project is located.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table summary=&quot;EPA Region Address to mail environmental impact statements&quot;&gt;&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;Region / State&lt;/th&gt;
			&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;Address&lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/nepa/national-environmental-policy-act-epa-region-1&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Region 1- &lt;/strong&gt;(Connecticut, Maine, Massachusetts,&lt;br /&gt;
				New Hampshire, Rhode Island, Vermont)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;Please submit two paper copies to:&lt;/p&gt;

				&lt;p&gt;Office of Environmental Review&lt;br /&gt;
					U.S. EPA Region 1&lt;br /&gt;
					5 Post Office Square, Suite 100 (Mail code: ORA-17-1)&lt;br /&gt;
					Boston, MA 02109-3912&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/nepa/national-environmental-policy-act-epa-region-2&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Region 2 - &lt;/strong&gt;(New Jersey, New York,&lt;br /&gt;
				Puerto Rico, US Virgin Islands)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;Please submit one paper copy and two CDs to:&lt;/p&gt;

				&lt;p&gt;Environmental Review Section&lt;br /&gt;
					U.S. EPA Region 2&lt;br /&gt;
					290 Broadway&lt;br /&gt;
					New York, NY 10007-1866&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/nepa/national-environmental-policy-act-epa-region-3&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Region 3- &lt;/strong&gt;(Delaware, District of Columbia, Maryland,&lt;br /&gt;
				Pennsylvania, Virginia, and West Virginia)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;Please submit two paper copies and one CD to:&lt;/p&gt;

				&lt;p&gt;NEPA Team Leader&lt;br /&gt;
					Office of Environmental Programs (3EA30)&lt;br /&gt;
					U.S. EPA Region 3&lt;br /&gt;
					1650 Arch Street&lt;br /&gt;
					Philadelphia, PA 19106&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/nepa/national-environmental-policy-act-epa-region-4&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Region 4 &lt;/strong&gt;- (Alabama, Florida, Georgia, Kentucky,&lt;br /&gt;
				Mississippi, North Carolina, South Carolina, Tennessee)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;Please submit two paper copies to:&lt;/p&gt;

				&lt;p&gt;NEPA Program Office&lt;br /&gt;
					U.S. EPA Region 4&lt;br /&gt;
					61 Forsyth Street, SW&lt;br /&gt;
					Atlanta, GA 30303&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/nepa/national-environmental-policy-act-epa-region-5&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Region 5 &lt;/strong&gt;- (Illinois, Indiana, Michigan, Minnesota,&lt;br /&gt;
				Ohio, Wisconsin)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;Please submit two paper copies and one CD to:&lt;/p&gt;

				&lt;p&gt;NEPA Implementation Section (Mail Code E-19J)&lt;br /&gt;
					U.S. EPA Region 5&lt;br /&gt;
					77 W. Jackson Blvd.&lt;br /&gt;
					Chicago, IL 60604&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/nepa/national-environmental-policy-act-epa-region-6&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Region 6 &lt;/strong&gt;- (Arkansas, Louisiana, New Mexico,&lt;br /&gt;
				Oklahoma, Texas)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;Please submit two paper copies to:&lt;/p&gt;

				&lt;p&gt;U.S. EPA Region 6&lt;br /&gt;
					1445 Ross Avenue, Suite 1200&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span&gt;Mail Code:&lt;/span&gt; 6EN&lt;br /&gt;
					Dallas, TX 75202-2733&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/nepa/national-environmental-policy-act-epa-region-7&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Region 7 &lt;/strong&gt;- (Iowa, Kansas, Missouri, Nebraska)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;Please submit two paper copies to:&lt;/p&gt;

				&lt;p&gt;U.S. EPA Region 7&lt;br /&gt;
					11201 Renner Blvd.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span&gt;Mail Code:&lt;/span&gt; ENSVNEPA&lt;br /&gt;
					Lenexa, KS 66219&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/nepa/national-environmental-policy-act-epa-region-8&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Region 8 &lt;/strong&gt;- (Colorado, Montana, North Dakota,&lt;br /&gt;
				South Dakota, Utah, Wyoming)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;Please submit two paper copies and one CD to:&lt;/p&gt;

				&lt;p&gt;NEPA Compliance and Review Program&lt;br /&gt;
					U.S. EPA Region 8 (8EPR-N)&lt;br /&gt;
					1595 Wynkoop Street&lt;br /&gt;
					Denver, CO 80202-1129&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/nepa/national-environmental-policy-act-epa-region-9&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Region 9 &lt;/strong&gt;- (Arizona, California, Hawaii,&lt;br /&gt;
				Nevada, Pacific Islands)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;Please submit one paper copy to:&lt;/p&gt;

				&lt;p&gt;Environmental Review Section (Mail Code: ENF-4-2)&lt;br /&gt;
					U.S. EPA Region 9&lt;br /&gt;
					75 Hawthorne Street&lt;br /&gt;
					San Francisco, CA 94105&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/nepa/national-environmental-policy-act-epa-region-10&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Region 10 &lt;/strong&gt;- (Alaska, Idaho, Oregon, Washington)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;Please submit one paper copy and one CD to:&lt;/p&gt;

				&lt;p&gt;EIS Review Coordinator&lt;br /&gt;
					U.S. EPA Region 10&lt;br /&gt;
					1200 Sixth Avenue, Suite 900 (ETPA-202)&lt;br /&gt;
					Seattle, WA 98101&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;</description>
     <pubDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2015 20:36:25 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cschae02</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">72617 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Air Quality Guidance for National Environmental Policy Act Reviews</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/nepa/air-quality-guidance-national-environmental-policy-act-reviews</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Memorandum of Understanding on the Air Quality Analyses and Mitigation for Federal Oil and Gas Decisions Through the National Environmental Policy Act (NEPA) Process &lt;/em&gt;sets forth the expectations and agreements for addressing air quality analyses and mitigation measures through the NEPA process related to federal oil and gas planning, leasing, or field development decisions. This MOU is signed by the U.S. Department of Agriculture, U.S. Department of the Interior, and EPA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Using MOVES and EMFAC Emissions Models in NEPA Evaluations &lt;/em&gt;provides information for assessing criteria air pollutant impacts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Reflecting the Revised PM 2.5 National Ambient Air Quality Standard in NEPA Evaluation&lt;/em&gt; provides information on how to reflect the revised PM 2.5 National Ambient Air Quality Standard in NEPA evaluations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-82033&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2014-08/documents/air-quality-analyses-mou-2011.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=1865050&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Memorandum of Understanding on the Air Quality Analyses and Mitigation for Federal Oil and Gas Decisions Through the NEPA Process (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(27 pp, 2 MB)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-82035&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2014-08/documents/using-the-moves-and-emfac-emissions-models-in-nepa-evaluations-pg.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=695199&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Using the MOVES and EMFAC Emissions Models in NEPA Evaluations (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(3 pp, 695 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-82037&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2014-08/documents/revised-pm2-5-naaqs-nepa-pg.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=94992&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Reflecting the Revised PM 2.5 National Ambient Air Quality Standard in NEPA Evaluations (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(2 pp, 95 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 27 Aug 2014 22:25:33 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cschae02</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">61535 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  </channel>
</rss>

<!-- Page cached by Boost @ 2017-01-26 04:14:13, expires @ 2017-01-26 16:14:13, lifetime 12 hours -->