<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?><rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.epa.gov/feed/104989/rss.xml" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/" xmlns:og="http://ogp.me/ns#" xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#" xmlns:sioc="http://rdfs.org/sioc/ns#" xmlns:sioct="http://rdfs.org/sioc/types#" xmlns:skos="http://www.w3.org/2004/02/skos/core#" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#">
  <channel>
    <title>Emergency Response to Gold King Mine Release</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/feed/104989/rss.xml</link>
    <description>Updated Emergency Response to Gold King Mine Release content from the US Environmental Protection Agency</description>
    <language>en</language>
     <atom:link href="https://www.epa.gov/feed/104989/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      <item>
    <title>In the Rearview Mirror: Implementation of the Gold King Mine After-Action Review</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/goldkingmine/rearview-mirror-implementation-gold-king-mine-after-action-review</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;An assessment of the EPA&#039;s response to Gold King Mine incident, includes recommendations to improve the agency&#039;s readiness to address future emergency incidents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-345891&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2017-01/documents/gkm-after-action-review-implementation-report.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=1520497&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;In the Rearview Mirror: Implementation of the Gold King Mine After-Action Review (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(31 pp, 2 MB)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Fri, 13 Jan 2017 12:44:42 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cedstrom</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">169027 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Decision on Federal Tort Claims Act Claims</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/goldkingmine/decision-federal-tort-claims-act-claims</link>
    <description>&lt;div class=&quot;box multi related-info right&quot;&gt;
	&lt;h2 class=&quot;pane-title&quot;&gt;Contact Us&lt;/h2&gt;

	&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;Media Inquiries: &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:stclair.christie@epa.gov&quot;&gt;Christie St. Clair&lt;/a&gt;, stclair.christie@epa.gov, (202) 564-2880&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;Claimant Inquiries: &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:sisson.ann@epa.gov&quot;&gt;Ann Sisson&lt;/a&gt;, sisson.ann@epa.gov, (202) 564-5469&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On January 13, 2017, the independent claims officer within the Environmental Protection Agency – guided by the U.S. Department of Justice – made a decision on the administrative claims brought under the Federal Tort Claims Act (FTCA) in connection with the Aug. 5, 2015 Gold King Mine release. After careful analysis, the claims officer concluded that the agency is not legally able to pay compensation for the claims.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When passing the FTCA, Congress wanted to encourage government agencies to take action without the fear of paying damages in the event something went wrong while taking the action. So the act does not authorize federal agencies to pay claims resulting from government actions that are discretionary – that is, acts of a governmental nature or function and that involve the exercise of judgment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because the agency was conducting a site investigation at the Gold King Mine under the Comprehensive Environmental Response, Compensation, and Liability Act, the agency’s work is considered a “discretionary function” under this law. Therefore, the circumstances surrounding the Gold King Mine incident unfortunately do not meet the conditions necessary to pay claims.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, those who have filed claims and whose claims have been denied may challenge this decision with the United States District Court within six months of the date of the denial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The EPA has taken responsibility for the Gold King Mine incident, including providing financial support, continued water treatment and monitoring, developing and implementing a permanent remedial plan for the broader mining region, and research to improve our understanding of how contaminants move through complex river systems.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Fri, 13 Jan 2017 00:53:03 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cedstrom</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">169025 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Peer Review Materials for “Analysis of the Transport and Fate of Metals Released from The Gold King Mine in the Animas and San Juan Rivers”</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/goldkingmine/peer-review-materials-analysis-transport-and-fate-metals-released-gold-king-mine-animas</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;Peer Review Materials for “Analysis of the Transport and Fate of Metals Released from The Gold King Mine in the Animas and San Juan Rivers”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;roomy&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cfpub.epa.gov/si/si_public_file_download.cfm?p_download_id=530069&quot;&gt;External Letter for Peer Reviewers (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(132pp, 1M, &lt;a href=&quot;/home/pdf-files&quot;&gt;About PDF&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cfpub.epa.gov/si/si_public_file_download.cfm?p_download_id=530071&quot;&gt;Response to Peer Review Comments (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(84pp, 4.6M, &lt;a href=&quot;/home/pdf-files&quot;&gt;About PDF&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cfpub.epa.gov/si/si_public_file_download.cfm?p_download_id=529139&quot;&gt;Peer Review Plan (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(2pp, 32.7K, &lt;a href=&quot;/home/pdf-files&quot;&gt;About PDF&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cfpub.epa.gov/si/si_public_file_download.cfm?p_download_id=529481&quot;&gt;Peer Review Panel (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(1pp, 40.5K, &lt;a href=&quot;/home/pdf-files&quot;&gt;About PDF&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cfpub.epa.gov/si/si_public_file_download.cfm?p_download_id=530070&quot;&gt;Panel Member Curriculum Vitae (CVs) (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(44pp, 745.95K, &lt;a href=&quot;/home/pdf-files&quot;&gt;About PDF&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;More data will be available soon. If you have technical questions, please contact &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:mattas-curry.lahne@epa.gov&quot;&gt;Lahne Mattas-Curry&lt;/a&gt;, mattas-curry.lahne@epa.gov&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jan 2017 18:56:30 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cedstrom</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">168453 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Data used to support the EPA report</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/goldkingmine/data-used-support-epa-report</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;More data will be available soon. If you have technical questions, please contact &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:mattas-curry.lahne@epa.gov&quot;&gt;Lahne Mattas-Curry&lt;/a&gt;, mattas-curry.lahne@epa.gov&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cfpub.epa.gov/si/si_public_file_download.cfm?p_download_id=530073&quot;&gt;Appendices (PDF)&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(198pp, 13M, &lt;a href=&quot;/home/pdf-files&quot;&gt;About PDF&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Appendix B Annex contains tables of data to parameterize the Gold King WASP model for each of the scenarios performed in the analyses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-343475&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2017-01/documents/goldking-fatetransport-appendixb-annex.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=2518012&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Appendix B Annex contains tables of data to parameterize the Gold King WASP model for each of the scenarios performed in the analyses. (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(85 pp, 3 MB)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jan 2017 14:58:32 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cedstrom</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">168383 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Water Quality Since the Gold King Mine Acid Mine Drainage Release</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/goldkingmine/water-quality-gold-king-mine-acid-mine-drainage-release</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;Gold King Mine Acid Mine Drainage Release – Analysis of Fate and Transport of Metals in the Animas and San Juan Rivers&lt;br /&gt;
	Water Quality Since the Release Event August&lt;br /&gt;
	2015 to November 2016&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-343467&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2017-01/documents/ord-gold-king-analysis_pre_release_jan32017.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=2651239&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Gold King Mine Acid Mine Drainage Release – Analysis of Fate and Transport of Metals in the Animas and San Juan Rivers | Water Quality Since the Release Event August 2015 to November 2016 (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(20 pp, 3 MB)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jan 2017 13:46:03 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cedstrom</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">168379 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Fate &amp; Transport Analysis</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/goldkingmine/fate-transport-analysis</link>
    <description>&lt;div class=&quot;box multi related-info right&quot;&gt;
	&lt;h2 class=&quot;pane-title&quot;&gt;Contact Us&lt;/h2&gt;

	&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;Media inquiries: &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:stclair.christie@epa.gov&quot;&gt;Christie St. Clair&lt;/a&gt;, stclair.christie@epa.gov&lt;br /&gt;
			Technical inquiries: &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:mattas-curry.lahne@epa.gov&quot;&gt;Lahne Mattas-Curry&lt;/a&gt;, mattas-curry.lahne@epa.gov&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;January 6, 2017: EPA&#039;s Office of Research and Development has finalized the report “Analysis of the Transport and Fate of Metal Released from the Gold King Mine in the Animas and San Juan Rivers.” The report is a scientific analysis that focuses on understanding the river conditions before the GKM release; the movement of the GKM release through the river system; and what has happened to water quality in the river since the time of the GKM release.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The research supports EPA’s earlier statements that water quality in the affected river system returned to the levels that existed prior to the GKM release and contamination of metals from the release have been moved through the river system to Lake Powell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;roomy&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cfpub.epa.gov/si/si_public_file_download.cfm?p_download_id=530075&quot;&gt;Executive Summary (PDF)&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(6pp, 510K, &lt;a href=&quot;/home/pdf-files&quot;&gt;About PDF&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;, “Analysis of the Transport and Fate of Metals Released from The Gold King Mine in the Animas and San Juan Rivers”&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cfpub.epa.gov/si/si_public_file_download.cfm?p_download_id=530074&quot;&gt;Full Report (PDF)&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(328pp, 23M, &lt;a href=&quot;/home/pdf-files&quot;&gt;About PDF&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;, “Analysis of the Transport and Fate of Metals Released from The Gold King Mine in the Animas and San Juan Rivers”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Summary of key findings from the fate and transport of the GKM event:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;roomy&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;This river system has a long history of leaking mine waste contamination from hundreds of old and abandoned mines throughout the region.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;EPA analysis indicates as of Fall 2016 contamination of metals from the GKM release have been transported through the Animas and San Juan River system to Lake Powell.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;The GKM release included aluminum, iron, manganese, lead, copper, arsenic, zinc, cadmium, and a small amount of mercury.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;The Gold King Mine release was equivalent to four to seven days of ongoing GKM acid mine drainage. The total amount of metals entering the Animas River following the 9-hour release was comparable to the amount of metals carried by the river in one to two days of high spring runoff. However, the concentrations of metals were higher than historical acid mine drainage.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Samples collected did not exceed EPA’s recreational screening levels. Some metal concentrations contributed to sporadic exceedances of state and tribal water quality criteria at times for 9 months in some locations. EPA and states establish water quality standards based on the use of the water to protect human health and aquatic life. In addition to these factors, tribal standards also consider tribal cultural uses, and are often more stringent than state or federal standards. Thus, tribal standards were exceeded more often, even during average flow periods because of historical background contamination. Metals from the GKM release also may have contributed to some exceedances during the 2016 spring snow melt. Other exceedances may reflect longstanding issues of mining wastes in the region as well as natural levels of common elements such as aluminum and iron in soils and rocks in the area. EPA will continue to work with states and tribes to interpret and respond to these findings.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;The 2016 spring snowmelt remobilized the metals that had settled in the sediment throughout the river system. This was expected based on historic observations. Some of the metals were due to the GKM release. Concentrations of metals in both sediment and water returned to pre-event concentrations by the end of the snowmelt period.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Ground water modeling suggests that a few wells located in the floodplain within 100 meters of the Animas River had the potential to draw river water, possibly including dissolved metals, during the time the GKM release plume passed. Most ground water in the affected area flows towards the river rather than from the river toward the wells. The concentrations of metals in well-water samples collected after the plume passed did not exceed federal drinking water standards.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Results from this analysis will inform future monitoring by EPA, states and tribes, including decisions about what is monitored; where monitoring takes place; and when monitoring takes place.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;EPA is committed to working with States and Tribes in the areas affected by the Gold King Mine release to ensure the protection of public health and the environment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Additional Materials&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;roomy&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/goldkingmine/data-used-support-epa-report&quot;&gt;Supporting data&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/goldkingmine/peer-review-materials-analysis-transport-and-fate-metals-released-gold-king-mine-animas&quot;&gt;Peer review materials&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/goldkingmine/water-quality-gold-king-mine-acid-mine-drainage-release&quot;&gt;Stakeholder presentations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/newsreleases/epa-releases-final-analysis-metals-released-gold-king-mine-animas-and-san-juan-rivers&quot;&gt;Press Release&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;colorbox-youtube&quot; href=&quot;/sites/production/files/2017-01/gkmtotal_metals_20160805-2.gif&quot;&gt;View an animation of the Gold King Mine plume&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot; &quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/2017-01/gkmtotal_metals_20160805-2.gif&quot; width=&quot;1062&quot; height=&quot;821&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;colorbox-inline&quot; href=&quot;#colorbox-hidden&quot;&gt;View a text version of this animation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id=&quot;hidden-content&quot;&gt;
	&lt;div class=&quot;colorbox-hidden&quot; id=&quot;colorbox-hidden&quot;&gt;
		&lt;h3 id=&quot;dialog-title&quot;&gt;Text Version of Animation “Simulated Total Metals in Water Column Resulting from Gold King Mine Release”&lt;/h3&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;On August 5, 2015, a field investigation of the Gold King Mine (GKM) near Silverton, CO, inadvertently triggered an estimated release of 3 million gallons of acidic, mine-impacted waters into the Animas River. The animation shows that release initially with total metal load of 1500-23379 mg/L. One percent of the total metals came from the acid mine drainage that was pressurized inside the mine, and 99 percent came from the historic mine waste that had been piled up outside the mine and was scoured away from the hillslope and into the river system by the force of the GKM release.&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;As the river flows into Cement Creek and then into the Animas River, the plume of Gold King release metals mixes with river water and the total metals concentration begins to decrease. As the GKM plume flows downstream, it maintains a 90-1500 mg/L of metals mass until approximately reaching the San Juan River hear Farmington, NM. From there through the remaining miles of the river system, the metals decrease again to between 6-90mg/L. The metals mass flows into Lake Powell and the river system has returned to pre-event conditions by approximately August 13, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Previously Released Draft Materials&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/goldkingmine/peer-review-comments-epas-fate-and-transport-study&quot;&gt;Read peer review comments on the draft final report&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/goldkingmine/updated-draft-fate-transport-analysis-documents&quot;&gt;View stakeholder webinars on the draft final report&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/goldkingmine/epas-draft-analysis-fate-and-transport-metals-animas-and-san-juan-rivers&quot;&gt;Read the initial draft analysis&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 29 Dec 2016 14:42:59 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cedstrom</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">167963 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Final Decision Notification Letters to Stakeholders Regarding Response Cost Requests</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/goldkingmine/final-decision-notification-letters-stakeholders-regarding-response-cost-requests</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;EPA has completed its review of response cost requests submitted by a number of entities impacted by the Aug. 5, 2015 Gold King Mine release, and sent notification letters to stakeholders regarding the final decisions. The notification documentation contains specific information on what costs were disallowed, and the basis for these decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA’s evaluation of costs is consistent with the Agency’s legal authorities and the requirements under the Comprehensive Environmental Response, Compensation, and Liability Act (CERCLA) or Superfund. The agency can only reimburse documented and allowable incurred response costs submitted by government partners. Examples of reimbursable costs include field evaluations, sampling, laboratory analysis, and personnel. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notification letters were sent to the following entities: Southern Ute Indian Tribe, San Juan County/Town of Silverton, La Plata County, City of Durango, the San Juan Basin Health Department, New Mexico and Navajo Nation. The agency is still reviewing reimbursements for Utah and Colorado.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-338433&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-12/documents/city_of_durango_gold_king_mine_cooperative_agreement_v96836501_reimburs.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=362741&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;City of Durango Gold King Mine Cooperative Agreement (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(5 pp, 363 K, 
  December 8, 2016)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-338431&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-12/documents/la_plata_county_gold_king_mine_cooperative_agreement_v96836201_reimburs.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=317423&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;La Plata County Gold King Mine Cooperative Agreement (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(5 pp, 317 K, 
  December 8, 2016)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-338423&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-12/documents/gkmcoopaglettertonavajonation12.8.16.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=385566&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Navajo Nation GKM Cooperative Letter (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(7 pp, 386 K, 
  December 8, 2016)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-338419&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-12/documents/nmed_gkm_memo_dec_8_2016.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=441519&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;New Mexico Environment Department GKM Memo (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(3 pp, 442 K, 
  December 8, 2016)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-338429&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-12/documents/san_juan_basin_health_department_gold_king_mine_cooperative_agreement_v.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=320654&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;San Juan Basin Health Department Gold King Mine Cooperative Agreement (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(4 pp, 321 K, 
  December 8, 2016)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-338417&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-12/documents/san_juan_county_gold_king_mine_cooperative_agreement_v96836101_reimburs.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=320789&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;San Juan County Gold King Mine Cooperative Agreement (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(5 pp, 321 K, 
  December 8, 2016)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-338427&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-12/documents/southern_ute_indian_tribe_gold_king_mine_cooperative_agreement_v9683630.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=237895&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Southern Ute Indian Tribe Gold King Mine Cooperative Agreement (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(8 pp, 238 K, 
  December 8, 2016)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 14 Dec 2016 00:21:51 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>jmarruff</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">167085 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Gold King Mine: CERCLA Reimbursements and CWA Grants (August 5, 2016 version)</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/goldkingmine/gold-king-mine-cercla-reimbursements-and-cwa-grants-august-5-2016-version</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;This information is no longer current. The current reimbursement information is on &lt;a href=&quot;/goldkingmine/frequent-questions-related-gold-king-mine-response&quot;&gt;Frequently Asked Questions&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Updated August 5, 2016&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gold King Mine: CERCLA Reimbursements and CWA Grants&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table style=&quot;width:100%&quot;&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th&gt;
				
			&lt;/th&gt;
			&lt;th&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CERCLA reimbursements&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/th&gt;
			&lt;th&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recertified Tribal Funds&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/th&gt;
			&lt;th&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Clean Water Act funds (Section 106 and 319) &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/th&gt;
			&lt;th&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TOTAL&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Utah&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td style=&quot;width:111px&quot;&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;$258,000&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td style=&quot;width:83px&quot;&gt;
				
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td style=&quot;width:81px&quot;&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;$465,000&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td style=&quot;width:89px&quot;&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;$723,000&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=&quot;width:121px&quot;&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Colorado&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td style=&quot;width:111px&quot;&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;$161,000&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td style=&quot;width:83px&quot;&gt;
				
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td style=&quot;width:81px&quot;&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;$465,000&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td style=&quot;width:89px&quot;&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;$626,000&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=&quot;width:121px&quot;&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Southern Ute Indian Tribe&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

				
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td style=&quot;width:111px&quot;&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;$222,372&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td style=&quot;width:83px&quot;&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;$159,900&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td style=&quot;width:81px&quot;&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;$103,100&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td style=&quot;width:89px&quot;&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;$485,372&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=&quot;width:121px&quot;&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ute Mountain Ute&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td style=&quot;width:111px&quot;&gt;
				
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td style=&quot;width:83px&quot;&gt;
				
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td style=&quot;width:81px&quot;&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;$40,000&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td style=&quot;width:89px&quot;&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;$40,000&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=&quot;width:121px&quot;&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;La Plata County&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td style=&quot;width:111px&quot;&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;$369,578&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td style=&quot;width:83px&quot;&gt;
				
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td style=&quot;width:81px&quot;&gt;
				
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td style=&quot;width:89px&quot;&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;$369,578&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=&quot;width:121px&quot;&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;San Juan County/Silverton&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td style=&quot;width:111px&quot;&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;$269,196&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td style=&quot;width:83px&quot;&gt;
				
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td style=&quot;width:81px&quot;&gt;
				
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td style=&quot;width:89px&quot;&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;$269,196&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=&quot;width:121px&quot;&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;San Juan Basin Health Department&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td style=&quot;width:111px&quot;&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;$72,540&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td style=&quot;width:83px&quot;&gt;
				
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td style=&quot;width:81px&quot;&gt;
				
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td style=&quot;width:89px&quot;&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;$72,540&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=&quot;width:121px&quot;&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Durango&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td style=&quot;width:111px&quot;&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;$45,471&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td style=&quot;width:83px&quot;&gt;
				
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td style=&quot;width:81px&quot;&gt;
				
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td style=&quot;width:89px&quot;&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;$45,471&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=&quot;width:121px&quot;&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Navajo Nation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td style=&quot;width:111px&quot;&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;$602,756&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td style=&quot;width:83px&quot;&gt;
				
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td style=&quot;width:81px&quot;&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;$465,000&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td style=&quot;width:89px&quot;&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;$1,067,756&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=&quot;width:121px&quot;&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Arizona&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td style=&quot;width:111px&quot;&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;$19,460&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td style=&quot;width:83px&quot;&gt;
				
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td style=&quot;width:81px&quot;&gt;
				
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td style=&quot;width:89px&quot;&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;$19,460&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=&quot;width:121px&quot;&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;New Mexico&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td style=&quot;width:111px&quot;&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;$1,072,585&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td style=&quot;width:83px&quot;&gt;
				
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td style=&quot;width:81px&quot;&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;$465,000&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td style=&quot;width:89px&quot;&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;$1,537,585&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=&quot;width:121px&quot;&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TOTAL&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td style=&quot;width:111px&quot;&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;$3,092,958&lt;/p&gt;

				
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td style=&quot;width:83px&quot;&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;$159,900&lt;/p&gt;

				
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td style=&quot;width:81px&quot;&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;$2,003,100&lt;/p&gt;

				
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td style=&quot;width:89px&quot;&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;$5,255,958&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is EPA doing to address the financial needs of the states, tribes and local governments impacted by the release?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA takes responsibility for the cleanup of the Aug. 5, 2015 Gold King Mine release. To date, EPA has dedicated more than $29 million to address the Gold King Mine incident, including more than $2 million in Clean Water Act grants and $3,092,958 in reimbursements for emergency response expenses under CERCLA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additional details:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;Allocated $2 million in Clean Water Act funding to support states’ and tribes’ monitoring plans. Utah, New Mexico, Southern Ute Indian Tribe, Ute Mountain Ute Tribe, Navajo Nation, and Colorado are eligible and may apply those funds to spring monitoring and preparedness planning as well. Some entities have applied and some have not.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;Agreed to contribute an additional $628,000 in Clean Water Act funds to enable states and tribes to fund a real-time water-quality monitoring alert system. This real-time monitoring would also serve to ensure successful coordination and implementation of notification and preparedness activities for communities downstream.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;Provided $197,792 to La Plata County through a pre-existing cooperative agreement with the Colorado Department of Public Health and Environment (CDPHE). These funds were a reimbursement for the County’s allowable removal response expenses related to the Gold King Mine release.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;Provided an additional $72,786 to La Plata County through a Superfund Cooperative Agreement awarded on April 1, 2016. EPA is in the process of evaluating additional expenses requested by La Plata County, and expects to reimburse additional allowable response costs under the cooperative agreement soon.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;Provided $220,667 to San Juan County/Town of Silverton through a pre-existing cooperative agreement with CDPHE. These funds were reimbursement for the county’s and town’s allowable removal response expenses related to the Gold King Mine release.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;Provided an additional $5,529 to San Juan County/Town of Silverton through a Superfund Cooperative Agreement awarded on April 1, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;Provided $2,471 to the City of Durango through a Superfund Cooperative Agreement awarded on April 1, 2016. EPA is in the process of evaluating additional expenses requested by the City of Durango and expects to reimburse additional allowable response costs under the cooperative agreement soon.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;Provided $71,571 to San Juan Basin Health through a pre-existing cooperative agreement with CDPHE and an additional $969 through a Superfund Cooperative Agreement awarded on April 1, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;Provided $157,000 through a cooperative agreement with Navajo Nation government agencies for costs incurred during the response to the August 2015 Gold King Mine release, and requested additional information from the Navajo Nation about remaining reimbursement requests to determine their eligibility under the EPA&#039;s response authorities and federal grant principles. The Tribe submitted additional documentation in late July, and EPA is reviewing that documentation now. These cooperative agreement funds are in addition to more than $1.1 million spent by the agency in response costs on the Navajo Nation immediately following the release to provide hay and agricultural water to Navajo Nation farmers and ranchers.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;Reimbursed the Southern Ute Indian Tribe $116,372 for costs incurred during the response. EPA is in the process of evaluating additional expenses requested by the Southern Ute Indian Tribe and expects to reimburse additional allowable response costs.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;Provided $19,460 in funding through a cooperative agreement with Arizona for costs incurred during the response to the August 2015 Gold King Mine release. EPA is reviewing requests from Arizona for reimbursement of additional costs.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;Allocated an additional $159,900 of recertified tribal funds to the Southern Ute Indian Tribe to further support their water quality monitoring plans.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;EPA has funded about $1.64 million in reimbursements and monitoring costs for New Mexico, including $1,072,585 for costs incurred during the response. We continue to review additional requests and will expedite payments for allowable costs. New Mexico also has $5.67 million available in unallocated federal funds - of which $108,000 has already been approved to fund real-time monitors in the river.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 13 Dec 2016 23:23:18 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>jmarruff</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">167083 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Identifying Tribal Emergency Response Contacts for Tribal Governments</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/goldkingmine/identifying-tribal-emergency-response-contacts-tribal-governments</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;September 27, 2016 Update:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	Documents related to tribal stakeholder notifications:&lt;br /&gt;
	Identifying Tribal Emergency Response Contacts for Tribal Governments&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-322217&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-10/documents/tribalnotificationmemo_9-12-16_signed.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=427400&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Identifying Tribal Emergency Response Contacts for Tribal Governments (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(2 pp, 427 K)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;field field-name-field-document-description field-type-text field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    EPA HQ request to Regional Administrators to ensure their offices develop a plan to maintain updated information for tribal emergency response contacts.  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Fri, 07 Oct 2016 15:34:56 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>pnelso02</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">162273 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  </channel>
</rss>

<!-- Page cached by Boost @ 2017-01-26 12:18:28, expires @ 2017-01-27 12:18:28, lifetime 1 day -->