<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?><rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.epa.gov/feed/91867/rss.xml" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/" xmlns:og="http://ogp.me/ns#" xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#" xmlns:sioc="http://rdfs.org/sioc/ns#" xmlns:sioct="http://rdfs.org/sioc/types#" xmlns:skos="http://www.w3.org/2004/02/skos/core#" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#">
  <channel>
    <title>Reporting Pesticide Incidents</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/feed/91867/rss.xml</link>
    <description>Updated Reporting Pesticide Incidents content from the US Environmental Protection Agency</description>
    <language>en</language>
     <atom:link href="https://www.epa.gov/feed/91867/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      <item>
    <title>Pesticide Safety Tips</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/pesticide-incidents/pesticide-safety-tips</link>
    <description>&lt;div class=&quot;box multi related-info right&quot;&gt;
	&lt;h2 class=&quot;pane-title&quot;&gt;Related Information&lt;/h2&gt;

	&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Questions On Pesticides?&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://npic.orst.edu/&quot;&gt;National Pesticide Information Center (NPIC)&lt;/a&gt;  1-800-858-7378 &lt;br /&gt;&lt;!-- #BeginLibraryItem &quot;/Library/exit.lbi&quot; --&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/pesticide-incidents/first-aid-case-pesticide-exposure&quot;&gt;First Aid in Case of Pesticide Exposure&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although pesticides can be useful, they also can be dangerous if used carelessly or are not stored properly. Here are some tips for safer pest control:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;roomy&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;The most effective way to reduce risks posed by pesticides is to use non-chemical control methods to reduce or eliminate pest problems. Around the home, such measures include:
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;removing sources of food and water (such as leaky pipes); and&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;destroying pest shelters and breeding sites (such as litter and plant debris).&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;If you decide you must use pesticides, always read the label first and follow the directions to the letter, including all precautions and restrictions.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Don&#039;t use products for pests that are not indicated on the label and don&#039;t use more pesticide than directed by the label. Don&#039;t think that twice the amount will do twice the job.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Use protective measures when handling pesticides as directed by the label, such as wearing impermeable gloves, long pants, and long-sleeve shirts. Change clothes and wash your hands immediately after applying pesticides.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Before applying a pesticide (indoors or outdoors), remove children, toys and pets from the area and keep them away until the pesticide has dried or as recommended by the label.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Remove or cover food during indoor applications.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Don&#039;t spray outdoors on windy or rainy days. Take precautions to keep the pesticide from drifting or running off into the vegetable garden, pool or neighbor&#039;s yard.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;If using a commercial applicator or lawn care service, ask for information about potential risks and safety precautions to take.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Don&#039;t buy more pesticides than you will need. If you have leftover pesticides, check with your local government to determine whether your community has a household hazardous waste collection program or other program for disposing of pesticides. If no community program exists, follow label directions and any state or local regulations regarding disposal.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Keep the telephone number of your area Poison Control Center near your telephone: 1-800-222-1222.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/safepestcontrol/reduce-your-childs-chances-pesticide-poisoning&quot;&gt;View tips to follow if you have children or if children visit your house or yard&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/pesticide-incidents/first-aid-case-pesticide-exposure&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;IN CASE OF AN EMERGENCY&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 05 Aug 2015 13:31:46 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cgesalma</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">102589 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>How to Report Pesticide Incidents</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/pesticide-incidents/how-report-pesticide-incidents</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;Everyone has a responsibility to report incidents related to harm from pesticides. For some, the responsibility is a legal requirement. For others, reporting is not required, but taking time to report can lead to changes where warranted that can help prevent future incidents. For more information about pesticide incident reporting, see the links under the group to which you belong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On this page:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#public&quot;&gt;Consumers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#health&quot;&gt;Health care professionals&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#veterinarian&quot;&gt;Veterinarians&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#wildlife&quot;&gt;Wildlife biologists&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#registrant&quot;&gt;Pesticide manufacturers or registrants&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;public&quot; name=&quot;public&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Consumers&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In all cases of pesticide incidents, please notify the product&#039;s manufacturer who is required by law to submit reports of adverse effects to EPA. Their contact information is on the product’s label.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Depending on the type of incident and your reason for reporting, it may be appropriate to report to a number of different organizations. The &lt;a href=&quot;http://npic.orst.edu/incidents.html&quot;&gt;National Pesticide Information Center&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt; is a good place to start for more information on different types of incidents and your various options for reporting. When reporting a pesticide incident, please follow the guidance given below for the following types of incidents:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;roomy&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/pesticide-incidents/how-report-pesticide-incident-involving-exposures-people&quot;&gt;Harm to people from pesticide exposure&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/pesticide-incidents/report-pesticide-exposure-incidents-affecting-pets-or-domestic-animals&quot;&gt;Incidents from pet flea and tick products&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/pesticide-incidents/report-spills-and-environmental-violations&quot;&gt;Chemical spills and illegal pesticide use&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/pesticide-incidents/how-report-pesticide-incidents-involving-wildlife-or-environment&quot;&gt;Wildlife and environmental incidents&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;health&quot; name=&quot;health&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Health Care Professionals&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Find information about identifying and responding to pesticide poisoning in &lt;a href=&quot;/pesticide-worker-safety/recognition-and-management-pesticide-poisonings&quot;&gt;Recognition and Management of Pesticide Poisoning&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/pesticide-incidents/how-report-pesticide-incident-involving-exposures-people&quot;&gt;Learn about reporting human health incidents&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;veterinarian&quot; name=&quot;veterinarian&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Veterinarians&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/pesticide-incidents/report-pesticide-exposure-incidents-affecting-pets-or-domestic-animals&quot;&gt;Report pet incidents&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/pets&quot;&gt;Information about protecting pets from fleas and ticks&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;wildlife&quot; name=&quot;wildlife&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Wildlife Biologists&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/pesticide-incidents/how-report-pesticide-incidents-involving-wildlife-or-environment&quot;&gt;Reporting incidents related to wildlife and environmental exposures&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/pollinator-protection/report-bee-kills&quot;&gt;Report bee kills&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;registrant&quot; name=&quot;registrant&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Pesticide Manufacturers or Registrants&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/pesticide-incidents/incident-reporting-pesticide-manufacturers-registrants&quot;&gt;Incident reporting (FIFRA 6(a)(2))&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jul 2015 18:52:34 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>ctran</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">97339 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>First Aid in Case of Pesticide Exposure</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/pesticide-incidents/first-aid-case-pesticide-exposure</link>
    <description>&lt;h2&gt;Human Exposure&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If someone has swallowed or inhaled a pesticide or gotten it in the eyes or on the skin:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Call 911 if the person is unconscious, having trouble breathing or having convulsions.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Check the label for directions on first aid for that product.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Call the Poison Control Center at (800) 222-1222 for help with first aid information.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://npic.orst.edu/ingred/index.html&quot;&gt;The National Pesticide Information Center&lt;/a&gt; (NPIC) (800) 858-7378 also can provide information about pesticide products and their toxicity. &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;EPA&#039;s publication, &lt;a href=&quot;/pesticide-worker-safety/recognition-and-management-pesticide-poisonings&quot;&gt;Recognition and Management of Pesticide Poisoning&lt;/a&gt; provides information about symptoms caused by poisoning with specific pesticides and treatment information.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2&gt;General First Aid Guidelines&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Swallowed poison&lt;/strong&gt;. Induce vomiting ONLY if emergency personnel on the phone or the product label tells you to do so. It will depend on what the person has swallowed; some petroleum products or caustic poisons will cause more damage if the person is made to vomit. Always keep Syrup of Ipecac on hand (1 ounce for each child in the household) to use to induce vomiting if recommended by emergency personnel. Be sure the date is current.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Poison in eye&lt;/strong&gt;. Eye membranes absorb pesticides faster than any other external part of the body; eye damage can occur in a few minutes with some types of pesticides. If poison splashes into an eye, hold the eyelid open and wash quickly and gently with clean running water from the tap or a gentle stream from a hose for at least 15 minutes. If possible, have someone else contact a Poison Control Center for you while the victim is being treated. Do not use eye drops or chemicals or drugs in the wash water.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Poison on skin&lt;/strong&gt;. If pesticide splashes on the skin, drench area with water and remove contaminated clothing. Wash skin and hair thoroughly with soap and water. Later, discard contaminated clothing or thoroughly wash it separately from other laundry.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Inhaled poison&lt;/strong&gt;. Carry or drag victim to fresh air immediately. If you think you need protection such as a respirator and one is not available to you, call the Fire Department and wait for emergency equipment before entering the area. Loosen victim&#039;s tight clothing. If the victim&#039;s skin is blue or the victim has stopped breathing, give artificial respiration (if you know how) and call rescue service for help. Open doors and windows so no one else will be poisoned by fumes.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jul 2015 17:46:21 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>dcoleman</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">97123 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Incident Reporting by Pesticide Manufacturers/ Registrants </title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/pesticide-incidents/incident-reporting-pesticide-manufacturers-registrants</link>
    <description>&lt;div class=&quot;box multi related-info right&quot;&gt;
	&lt;h2 class=&quot;pane-title&quot;&gt;Enhanced Reporting Pilot for Pet Spot-on Incidents&lt;/h2&gt;

	&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;EPA has developed a draft standard template to be used by registrants submitting information on incidents involving spot-on pet products to ensure the submission of data in a consistent format using consistent terminology. The standardized template will allow the Agency to review incidents more efficiently and, if concerns are raised, give us the necessary information on which to act. &lt;a href=&quot;/pesticides/pilot-test-new-template-enhanced-pet-spot-product-incident-reporting&quot;&gt;More information about the pilot, including the template&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pesticide registrants are required to inform us about harmful effects of their products under federal law:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/laws-regulations/summary-federal-insecticide-fungicide-and-rodenticide-act&quot;&gt;Federal Insecticide, Fungicide, and Rodenticide Act (FIFRA)&lt;/a&gt;, section (6)(a)(2): “If at any time after the registration of a pesticide the registrant has additional factual information regarding unreasonable adverse effects on the environment of the pesticide, the registrant shall submit such information to the Administrator.”&lt;br /&gt;
	 &lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Adverse effect information they must report includes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;New information derived from scientific studies (e.g., unexpected levels of toxicity).&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Reports of incidents of harmful effects resulting from the use of their pesticide products.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;We consider incident information submitted by registrants and all others in evaluating the safety of pesticide products.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How to Report Incidents&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fifra6a2.com/&quot;&gt;Voluntary Incident Reporting Forms and Instructions&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;  We accept any information format that meets the requirements of the regulations. We are providing these forms, which were developed by pesticide registrants and trade association representatives, as a convenience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;U.S. mailing address for 6(a)(2) submissions by pesticide registrants:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Document Processing Desk -6(a)(2)&lt;br /&gt;
	Office of Pesticide Programs- 7504P&lt;br /&gt;
	U.S. Environmental Protection Agency&lt;br /&gt;
	William Jefferson Clinton Building&lt;br /&gt;
	1200 Pennsylvania Ave., NW&lt;br /&gt;
	Washington, DC 20460-0001&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	Courier services are to deliver to this address:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Document Processing Desk - 6(a)(2)&lt;br /&gt;
	Office of Pesticide Programs&lt;br /&gt;
	Document Processing Room S-4900&lt;br /&gt;
	One Potomac Yard&lt;br /&gt;
	2777 S. Crystal Drive&lt;br /&gt;
	Arlington, VA 22202&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;For More Information&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ecfr.gov/cgi-bin/text-idx?SID=680dff323249c84b0f88ddd044793a71&amp;amp;mc=true&amp;amp;node=pt40.24.159&amp;amp;rgn=div5&quot;&gt;Federal regulations on registrant reporting requirements:  40 CFR part 159&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA’s Pesticide Registration Notices (PR Notice) provide technical guidance on what, when, and how registrants are to report:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;roomy&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/pesticide-registration/prn-98-3-guidance-final-fifra-6a2-regulations-pesticide-product-registrants&quot;&gt;PR Notice 98-3&lt;/a&gt;: Guidance on Final FIFRA Section 6(a)(2) Regulations for Pesticide Product Registrants (1998). PRN 98-3 provides guidance topics including the role of agents, aggregate reporting of incidents, definitions of incident severity categories, waiver requests and property damage incidents.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/pesticide-registration/prn-98-4-additional-guidance-final-fifra-section-6a2-regulations-pesticide&quot;&gt;PR Notice 98-4&lt;/a&gt;: Additional Guidance on Final FIFRA Section 6(a)(2) Regulations for Pesticide Product Registrants (1998). PRN 98-4 provides guidance on topics such as the definition of “registrant’, reporting timeframes and required information.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/pesticide-registration/prn-2000-8-reportability-attorneys-opinions-and-conclusions-under-40-cfr-part&quot;&gt;PR Notice 2000-8&lt;/a&gt;: Reportability of Attorney&#039;s Opinions and Conclusions under 40 CFR Part 159 and FIFRA Section 6(a)(2) (2000). PRN 2000-8 contains EPA&#039;s opinion about the reporting of attorney professional legal judgments.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;For questions about the 6(a)(2) regulations and guidance, contact &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:miller.robert@epa.gov&quot;&gt;Robert Miller&lt;/a&gt;, miller.robert@epa.gov. &lt;/p&gt;


</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 02 Jul 2015 14:57:22 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>morganic</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">95521 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>How to Report Pesticide Incidents Involving Wildlife or the Environment</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/pesticide-incidents/how-report-pesticide-incidents-involving-wildlife-or-environment</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;Wildlife and environmental incidents can be reported for all wildlife, including mammals, birds, fish, shell fish, reptiles, amphibians, insects including bees and other pollinators, plants, and for soil and water suspected or known to be related to pesticide exposures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;roomy&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;Do not touch or disturb dead animals. Poisoned animals that are still alive may be taken to a veterinarian or &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wildliferehabinfo.org/&quot;&gt;wildlife rehabilitation center&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt; for treatment. It is best to call the local animal control or Humane Society office for assistance. &lt;span&gt;Rescue of ill animals should be attempted only by trained personnel who are properly protected from pesticide contamination and are knowledgeable about state and federal regulations related to the collection of wildlife. In addition, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span&gt;injured animals can be frightened and aggressive.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;NPIC’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://pi.ace.orst.edu/erep/&quot;&gt;Ecological Incident Reporting Portal&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;collects information from government organizations, the public, academia, wildlife rehabilitation centers, conservation societies, and bee keepers. NPIC provides reports to EPA on incidents, but does not collect information for enforcement.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Contact your &lt;a href=&quot;http://npic.orst.edu/reg/state_agencies.html#map&quot;&gt;state pesticide regulatory agency&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;especially if you are concerned about a possibly illegal use of a pesticide. States generally have primary enforcement responsibility for pesticide misuse violations and for investigating possible instances of pesticide misuse.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;For incidents involving fish or wildlife, &lt;a href=&quot;/home/health-and-environmental-agencies-us-states-and-territories&quot;&gt;contact your state’s department that is responsible for protecting fish, game, and natural resources&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Learn about &lt;a href=&quot;/pollinator-protection/report-bee-kills&quot;&gt;specific reporting options for possible pollinator incidents&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;If you suspect that federal pesticide regulations have been violated, &lt;a href=&quot;/enforcement/report-environmental-violations&quot;&gt;submit a report to EPA&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Tell the product&#039;s manufacturer, who is required by law to submit reports of adverse effects to EPA. Their contact information is on the product label.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;mailto:Report.Incident@epa.gov&quot;&gt;For any non-registrant wanting to report incidents that may not involve violations of pesticide laws and regulations, send us an email&lt;/a&gt;. 
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;For wildlife exposures, useful information, if available, includes:
				&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;the type and number of animals exposed;&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;the condition of the animals;&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;the pesticide involved (EPA registration number if available);&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;and any other pertinent information. &lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;For environmental exposures affecting soils, plants, streams, rivers, and other bodies of water, useful information, if available, includes:
				&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;information on the pesticide involved (EPA registration number if available);&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;number of plants, fish, other aquatic organisms exposed;&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;the condition of the plants, fish and other aquatic organisms; and&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;any other pertinent information.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 02 Jul 2015 13:52:20 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cgesalma</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">95487 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Report Pesticide Exposure Incidents Affecting Pets or Domestic Animals</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/pesticide-incidents/report-pesticide-exposure-incidents-affecting-pets-or-domestic-animals</link>
    <description>&lt;div class=&quot;box multi related-info right&quot;&gt;
	&lt;h2 class=&quot;pane-title&quot;&gt;Enhanced Reporting Pilot Information&lt;/h2&gt;

	&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;EPA has developed a draft standard template to be used by registrants submitting information on incidents involving spot-on pet products to ensure the submission of data in a consistent format using consistent terminology. The standardized template will allow the Agency to review incidents more efficiently and, if concerns are raised, give us the necessary information on which to act. &lt;a href=&quot;/pesticides/pilot-test-new-template-enhanced-pet-spot-product-incident-reporting&quot;&gt;More information about the pilot, including the template&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Options for Reporting by Pet Owners&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;roomy&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;If your animal needs medical attention right now, call your local veterinarian, a local emergency clinic, or the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.aspca.org/pet-care/animal-poison-control&quot;&gt;National Animal Poison Control Center&lt;/a&gt; (NAPCC) at (888) 426-4435. &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt; NAPCC may charge a fee, unless you contact them via the National Pesticide Information Center.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Tell the product&#039;s manufacturer, who is required by law to submit reports of adverse effects to EPA. Their contact information is on the product label. &lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;For non-emergencies, you can call the &lt;a href=&quot;http://npic.orst.edu/incidents.html#anim&quot;&gt;National Pesticide Information Center&lt;/a&gt; (NPIC) at (800) 858-7378 &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt; to find out more about reporting a possible pesticide exposure or illness. NPIC also provides summary reports to EPA on incidents, but does not collect information for enforcement.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Contact your &lt;a href=&quot;http://npic.orst.edu/reg/state_agencies.html#map&quot;&gt;state pesticide regulatory agency&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt; especially if you are concerned about a possibly illegal use of a pesticide. States generally have primary enforcement responsibility for pesticide misuse violations and for investigating possible instances of pesticide misuse.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/enforcement/report-environmental-violations&quot;&gt;Submit a report to EPA&lt;/a&gt; if you suspect that federal pesticide regulations have been violated.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;mailto:Report.Incident@epa.gov&quot;&gt;For any non-registrant wanting to report incidents involving pets or domestic animals that may not involve violation of pesticide regulations, send us an email&lt;/a&gt;. If available, useful information includes:
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Type and number of animals exposed.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Size, breed and age of the animal.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Condition of the animal, e.g., symptoms exhibited, current health status.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;The pesticide involved (include EPA registration number if available).&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Any other pertinent information.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Reporting by Veterinarians&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;roomy&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;NPIC offers an online &lt;a href=&quot;http://pi.ace.orst.edu/vetrep/&quot;&gt;Veterinary Pesticide Incident Reporting Portal&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;where veterinarians and their staff can submit reports to NPIC, for surveillance purposes (not enforcement). NPIC staff are also available to veterinarians for general pesticide-related questions regarding animal exposures.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jul 2015 17:54:19 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cgesalma</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">95345 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>How to Report a Pesticide Incident Involving Exposures to People</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/pesticide-incidents/how-report-pesticide-incident-involving-exposures-people</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;If someone has been exposed to a pesticide and has been harmed by that exposure, there are several actions you can take. The first priority, of course, is the health and safety of the affected person. Once that is ensured, you can report the incident in one of several ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On this page:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#info&quot;&gt;Information for everyone&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#additional&quot;&gt;Additional information for physicians and health care providers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;info&quot; name=&quot;info&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Information for Everyone&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;roomy&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/pesticide-incidents/first-aid-case-pesticide-exposure&quot;&gt;Emergency information&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Non-emergency Reporting&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;roomy&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;You may want to start by calling the &lt;a href=&quot;http://npic.orst.edu/incidents.html#hum&quot;&gt;National Pesticide Information Center&lt;/a&gt; (NPIC) &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt; at 1-800-858-7378 to find out more about reporting pesticide exposure or illness. NPIC also provides summary reports to EPA on incidents, but does not collect information for enforcement nor do they provide EPA with any personal identifying information.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Call your &lt;a href=&quot;http://npic.orst.edu/reg/state_agencies.html#map&quot;&gt;state pesticide regulatory agency&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt; especially if you are concerned about a possible illegal use of a pesticide. States generally have primary enforcement responsibility for pesticide misuse violations and for investigating possible instances of pesticide misuse.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;If you suspect that federal pesticide regulations have been violated, &lt;a href=&quot;/enforcement/report-environmental-violations&quot;&gt;submit a report to EPA&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;mailto:Report.Incident@epa.gov&quot;&gt;For incidents that may not involve violations of pesticide laws and regulations, send us an email&lt;/a&gt;. If available, useful information includes:
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;when, where and how the exposure occurred;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;any medical outcome;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;the number of people exposed;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;the pesticide involved (EPA registration number if available); and&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;any other pertinent information.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Tell the product&#039;s manufacturer who is required by law to submit reports of adverse effects to EPA. Their contact information is on the product label.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;For exposures at the workplace, you may also want to contact your local Occupational Health and Safety Administration office. NPIC offers &lt;a href=&quot;http://npic.orst.edu/mlrDetail.html?lang=en&amp;amp;to=SPE&amp;amp;state=IL#osha&quot;&gt;a listing of resources on different state agencies&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;additional&quot; name=&quot;additional&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Additional Information for Physicians and Health Care Providers&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By law, pesticide-related illness is a reportable condition in several states.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.migrantclinician.org/issues/occupational-health/pesticides/reporting-illnesses.html&quot;&gt;Migrant Clinicians Network&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;offers resources for clinicians on pesticide incident management and reporting.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul class=&quot;roomy&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;NPIC also offers &lt;a href=&quot;http://npic.orst.edu/mcapro/index.html&quot;&gt;Medical Case Profiles&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;http://npic.orst.edu/mcapro/PesticideIncidentReporting.pdf&quot;&gt;Pesticide Incident Reporting (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(3 pp, 329.55 K, &lt;a href=&quot;/home/pdf-files&quot;&gt;About PDF&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt; NPIC has a medical toxicologist who is available to provide information and consult with physicians about non-emergency pesticide exposure cases.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Some products applied to people or animals are considered drugs (pharmaceuticals). Adverse reactions to drugs should be reported to the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fda.gov/Safety/MedWatch/HowToReport/default.htm&quot;&gt;Food and Drug Administration (FDA)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Patients can be advised of the options listed above for reporting a pesticide exposure incident.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jul 2015 17:30:30 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cgesalma</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">95331 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Common Causes of Pesticide Incidents</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/pesticide-incidents/common-causes-pesticide-incidents</link>
    <description>&lt;div class=&quot;box multi related-info right&quot;&gt;
	&lt;h2 class=&quot;pane-title&quot;&gt;Related Information&lt;/h2&gt;

	&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/pesticide-incidents/pesticide-safety-tips&quot;&gt;Pesticide Safety Tips&lt;/a&gt; -- ways to help avoid pesticide incidents.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;There are many types and causes of pesticide incidents. EPA staff analyze pesticide incident reports involving people (including children and farm workers), pets, domestic animals, wildlife including bees and other pollinators, and the environment (air, soil, and water). &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;Incidents can result from use according to label directions as well as when a pesticide is misused or used incorrectly. &lt;/span&gt;People can experience unintentional pesticide exposures in a number of ways, including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;roomy&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;Not following label instructions.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Applying too much pesticide product.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Applying pesticide product in breezy conditions.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Not following label safety instructions when using a pesticide. Wearing rubber gloves and protective eyewear can prevent over-exposure.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Improperly using a pesticide. For example, staying in the rooms where foggers are used, or using outdoor use products inside your house.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Bringing pesticides into your home on your clothing after working in treated fields.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Storing pesticides in an unsecured place that children and pets can access.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Other accidental exposures, such as from spills.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Not wearing recommended personal protective equipment (for example, rubber gloves, protective eyewear, long pants, long-sleeved shirts).&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Equipment malfunction.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Accidental exposure from aerial treatment or spray drift.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Post-application exposure from a treated area.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Pets, domestic animals and wildlife (such as mammals, birds, fish, insects and plants) can experience unintentional exposure to pesticides. Examples of how this can happen include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;roomy&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;When too much pesticide is applied to pets or domestic livestock.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;When wildlife consume pesticide contaminated water or food.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;When agricultural pesticide runs off or drifts from the agricultural area into water or other wildlife habitat.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The environment (air, soil and water) can be contaminated by pesticide overuse, spills, leaking storage tanks, rainwater runoff from over-treated areas, spray drift, and improper disposal of pesticides, among other ways. Pesticides can enter ground and surface waters (streams, rivers) that people and wildlife use for drinking water and can also harm aquatic life (e.g., plants, fish, crabs, shellfish).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jul 2015 17:10:04 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cgesalma</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">95323 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Introduction to Pesticide Incidents</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/pesticide-incidents/introduction-pesticide-incidents</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;EPA defines a pesticide incident as any exposure or effect from a pesticide’s use that is not expected or intended. Pesticide incidents may involve humans, wildlife, plants, domestic animals (e.g., pets) and bees. Pesticide spills can also be a type of incident.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why Report Pesticide Incidents&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before registering a pesticide (i.e., licensing a pesticide for use), EPA must make a determination that the pesticide is safe for humans and the environment. Pesticide incident reports tell EPA if there are problems with a pesticide and any adverse effects on people, pets, domestic animals, wildlife, or the environment (air, soil, water). Reporting a pesticide incident helps provide EPA the most robust information on the effects and consequences of exposures to pesticides affecting people and the environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How EPA Uses Incident Reports&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA considers incident information when evaluating the risks from exposure to a pesticide. Incident reports help EPA determine whether:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;The pesticide’s application directions need to be clarified&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;We should restrict uses of the pesticide.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;We should require additional protective safety equipment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;If risks associated with exposures to a pesticide cannot be reduced, EPA can remove it from the marketplace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sources of Pesticide Incident Information&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA uses information related to pesticide incidents from a variety of sources, including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;roomy&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://npic.orst.edu/incidents.html&quot;&gt;National Pesticide Information Center (NPIC)&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt; Anyone can contact NPIC for information on pesticides and to report possible pesticide incidents (e.g., general public, veterinarians, physicians, wildlife organizations). The NPIC program currently operates under a cooperative agreement between EPA and Oregon State University.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cdc.gov/niosh/topics/pesticides/overview.html&quot;&gt;SENSOR-Pesticides&lt;/a&gt;. NIOSH’s Sentinel Event Notification System for Occupational Risk (SENSOR) is the only aggregated pesticide surveillance program in existence. Besides tabulating numbers of acute occupational pesticide-related cases, SENSOR-supported surveillance systems perform in-depth investigations for case confirmation and develop preventive interventions aimed at particular industries or pesticide hazards. The SENSOR-Pesticides program is useful for timely identification of outbreaks and emerging pesticide problems.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Manufacturers of pesticide products (also known as registrants). Pesticide manufacturers are required by law to submit to the EPA reports of adverse effects from their products.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.aapcc.org/&quot;&gt;American Association of Poison Control Centers&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt; AAPCC compiles information from state poison control centers.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Information submitted directly to EPA.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Voluntary reporting by the public through various methods.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jul 2015 16:13:52 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>morganic</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">95303 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  </channel>
</rss>

<!-- Page cached by Boost @ 2017-01-25 16:36:02, expires @ 2017-01-26 04:36:02, lifetime 12 hours -->