<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?><rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.epa.gov/feed/80795/rss.xml" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/" xmlns:og="http://ogp.me/ns#" xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#" xmlns:sioc="http://rdfs.org/sioc/ns#" xmlns:sioct="http://rdfs.org/sioc/types#" xmlns:skos="http://www.w3.org/2004/02/skos/core#" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#">
  <channel>
    <title>Sustainable Management of Food</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/feed/80795/rss.xml</link>
    <description>Updated Sustainable Management of Food content from the US Environmental Protection Agency</description>
    <language>en</language>
     <atom:link href="https://www.epa.gov/feed/80795/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      <item>
    <title>U.S. Food Loss and Waste 2030 Champions Activity Form</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/sustainable-management-food/us-food-loss-and-waste-2030-champions-activity-form</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;To join the U.S. Food Loss and Waste 2030 Champions, organizations complete and submit the 2030 Champions form, in which they commit to reduce food loss and waste in their own operations and periodically report their progress on their website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-333621&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-11/documents/u.s._food_loss_and_waste_champions_activity_form_-_september_2016_epa_logo_0.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=207643&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;U.S. Food Loss and Waste 2030 Champions Activity Form (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(1 pg, 208 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 22 Nov 2016 15:36:37 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>esundin</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">165547 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>About the 2016 Food Recovery Challenge Award Winners</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/sustainable-management-food/about-2016-food-recovery-challenge-award-winners</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;The 2016 Food Recovery Challenge national award winners shared details and quotes about their wasted food prevention and diversion activities, and about their awards with EPA. Read about their accomplishments and how they achieved them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On this page:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Sprouts&quot;&gt;Sprouts Farmers Markets 205 and 286&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Ursinus&quot;&gt;Ursinus College&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Lanikai&quot;&gt;Lanikai School&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Chumash&quot;&gt;Chumash Casino Resort&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#OrtegaNationalParks&quot;&gt;Ortega National Parks, LLC - Carlsbad Caverns Trading Company&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Goodkind&quot;&gt;Goodkind&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#NewPaltz&quot;&gt;Town of New Paltz&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#UCDavis&quot;&gt;University of California, Davis&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Sodexo&quot;&gt;Sodexo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#FoodForward&quot;&gt;Food Forward&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#NERC&quot;&gt;Northeast Recycling Council &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Ramona&quot;&gt;Ramona High School &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;Sprouts&quot; name=&quot;Sprouts&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Sprouts Farmers Markets 205 and 286&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg right view-mode-medium&quot; style=&quot;width:448px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Image depicting Shoppers filling up a box of produce at Sprouts Market&quot; height=&quot;299&quot; width=&quot;448&quot; class=&quot;right media-element file-medium right&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/medium/public/2016-11/img_0769.jpg&quot; title=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sprouts Farmers Market: 205, Data-driven Winner, Grocers&lt;br /&gt;
	Sprouts Farmers Market: 286, Data-driven Winner, Newcomer&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sprouts is committed to zero food waste, taking responsibility for preserving the resources that go into getting food from farm to store including the soil, water, packaging and transportation. To combat hunger and reduce food waste, in 2015, all Sprouts stores donated more than 14 million pounds of fresh food to local hunger relief agencies through their Food Rescue Program. Sprouts also diverted another 5.5 million pounds of food to composting facilities and to local farms to feed animals. By working with the EPA’s Food Recovery Challenge and organizations like Feeding America, Sprouts is able to reduce the impact of hunger in their communities and contribute to a cleaner environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;Ursinus&quot; name=&quot;Ursinus&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Ursinus College&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Data-driven Winner, Colleges and Universities&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ursinus College Dining Services, managed by Sodexo, has worked collaboratively with faculty, staff and students to implement various waste diversion initiatives including waste reduction during preparation, food donations, composting, recycling and trash to energy. By utilizing the Sustainable Materials Management Data Management System, they have been able to track diversion efforts, create goals from their baseline and track and measure results. In addition to participating in the Food Recovery Challenge, Ursinus College is a member school of the Pennsylvania Environmental Resource Consortium.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;Lanikai&quot; name=&quot;Lanikai&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Lanikai School&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Data-driven Winner, K-12 Schools&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;box multi related-info right&quot;&gt;
	&lt;h2 class=&quot;pane-title&quot;&gt;The Story of the Lanikai School&#039;s Efforts&lt;/h2&gt;

	&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dropbox.com/s/5ymnjivrc2b7vam/ZeroWaste_FINAL3_3.mp4?dl=0&quot;&gt;Watch a video about the Lanikai&#039;s School&#039;s food waste recovery program&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lanikai Elementary Public Charter School, on the Island of Oahu, Hawaii, has enthusiastically adopted the philosophy and practice of Zero Waste, where all discarded materials are regarded not as trash but as valuable resources. Now in the second full year of 100% food waste recovery, Lanikai students collect, sort and separate lunch and snack food and process all organics – food, paper, cardboard and green waste (yard waste and food waste)– right in the middle of campus, with children at every grade level involved with operations. Kitchen preparation waste feeds worms, a hot compost array handles mixed plate scrapings, and bokashi fermentation (anaerobic fermentation process) for heavy proteins rounds out the suite of processing technologies that converted 14,433 pounds of food waste into rich soil amendments in 2015.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	Using these inputs, Lanikai students create magnificent, incredibly productive gardens. This past year, on-site processing transformed food waste into 16 cubic yards of rich compost and 1,320 pounds of valuable vermicasts (worm manure or “castings”). Half of the recovered food waste was used in the gardens, and half shared with growers in the community. Growing more food than the school community can consume, surplus produce is boxed for Aloha Harvest, an agency that distributes food to the needy. While all students, staff, and faculty participate daily in Zero Waste practices, the program was designed and is managed by a full-time professional Resource Recovery Specialist who is funded by a private grant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg center view-mode-medium caption&quot; style=&quot;width:448px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;this is an image of students working in the garden&quot; height=&quot;336&quot; width=&quot;448&quot; class=&quot;center media-element file-medium center&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/medium/public/2016-11/lanikaischool.jpg&quot; title=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;figcaption&quot;&gt;Students at Lanikai School&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;Chumash&quot; name=&quot;Chumash&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Chumash Casino Resort&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Data-driven Winner, Sports and Entertainment Venues&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Chumash Casino Resort is dedicated to the sustainable health of people, the planet and their company. They promote sustainable business practices and social responsibility by using resources responsibly in daily operations and through the entire supply chain. The Casino Resort has set a goal to be a zero waste property by 2019. A major component of this goal is food waste, comprising 40 percent of the waste stream at the resort. The resort’s onsite kitchens recycle organic waste by teaming up with local composters and adding tools like a pulper, dehydrator and liquefier to help reduce and recycle waste. The resort has also teamed up with a waste hauler and composting facility where scraps from the kitchen are composted with the property&#039;s bio-solids from its wastewater treatment plant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;OrtegaNationalParks&quot; name=&quot;OrtegaNationalParks&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Ortega National Parks, LLC – Carlsbad Caverns Trading Company&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Data-driven Winner, Hotels, Resorts, and Lodging&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ortega National Parks and Carlsbad Caverns Trading Company are committed to the conservation and preservation of our nation’s wonderful parks -- &quot;America&#039;s Best Idea.&quot; They increased their food waste diversion efforts throughout 2015 on several fronts. Careful inventory management and analysis of guests&#039; dining choices, coupled with tracking food waste on a monthly basis, allowed them to select vendor products and make menu design and serving decisions with a goal to reduce food waste, while still offering guests a satisfying and healthy range of dining options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ortega National Parks and Carlsbad Caverns Trading Company constantly seek to improve their environmental efforts. Their environmental management system is certified to the ISO 14001 standard, and as an organization, they place the utmost importance on the proper stewardship of environmental resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;Goodkind&quot; name=&quot;Goodkind&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Goodkind&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Data-driven Winner, Restaurants and Food Service Providers&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; “We would like to express our thanks to Compost Crusader for helping us achieve these goals and to encourage our entire community to participate in the programs that Melissa at Compost Crusader has initiated. Composting from a food business standpoint is a no-brainer and has really helped us minimize our waste overall. It&#039;s simple and rewarding. We hope composting becomes as accessible and easy as trash and recycling in the future. It should just be a way of life.” -- William Seidel, Co-Owner, Goodkind&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;NewPaltz&quot; name=&quot;NewPaltz&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Town of New Paltz&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Data-driven Winner, Other Sector&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg right view-mode-medium&quot; style=&quot;width:448px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;this is a picture of composting bins at Town of New Paltz event&quot; height=&quot;304&quot; width=&quot;448&quot; class=&quot;right media-element file-medium right&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/medium/public/2016-12/event_compostingcropped.jpg&quot; title=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;The New Paltz Food Recovery Program has naturally transitioned to match several components of EPA’s Food Recovery Hierarchy. In 2011, during the early stages of the New Paltz program, the town held public interactive workshops as part of a zero waste initiative partnership with EPA. Attendees made it clear that composting was one of the most important initiatives. By 2012, the New Paltz ReUse and Recycling Center received approval from the state regulatory agency, New York State’s Department of Environmental Conservation, to begin taking in commercial food waste for composting. Since opening in 2012, the center has diverted over 1,380 tons of source separated food waste.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New Paltz has established itself as a model for other small capacity composting sites, i.e., registered for up to 1,000 cubic yards per year. Ulster County, which is home to New Paltz, now has five registered composting sites which are operated by both public and private sector companies. The food recovery program then began a grass roots transition to include food recovery for animal feed as part of its efforts. Several local food chains (retail and warehouses) including a grocery retailer, donate food for both human consumption that is collected weekly for a soup kitchen, and for animal feed. Finally, a snack food franchise donates food waste to a local pig and chicken farmer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until recently, the Town of New Paltz worked solely with the SUNY New Paltz campus dorm cleanout effort to donate excess, wholesome food to hungry people. Now though, New Paltz has partnered with multiple key players in the Hudson Valley Food Hub to donate food to hungry people and added a freezer/cooler at the ReUse and Recycling Center. The cooler will be part of a food recovery hub that connects distribution warehouses with local food pantries. The cooler will provide additional storage so that pantries can manage distribution of perishable produce, reduce transportation and carbon dioxide emissions, and encourage additional donations from farms that overproduce or are gleaning. The second phase of this collaboration will be to store food prepared at restaurants and/or by caterers until it can be transported to soup kitchens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“The most important factor to the success of any program is volunteers, business partnerships and churches to support and implement our Zero Waste efforts. Without these components, none of the programs at the ReUse Center would be possible.”&lt;/em&gt; -- Laura Petit, Recycling Coordinator for the Town of New Paltz&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;UCDavis&quot; name=&quot;UCDavis&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;University of California, Davis&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Narrative Category Winner, Source Reduction&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg right view-mode-medium caption&quot; style=&quot;width:448px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Students at University of California, Davis reducing food waste &quot; height=&quot;627&quot; width=&quot;448&quot; class=&quot;right media-element file-medium right&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/medium/public/2016-11/ucdavis.jpg&quot; title=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;figcaption&quot;&gt;Students on campus reducing food waste.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;The University of California, Davis (UC Davis) is a leading sustainable institution with numerous innovative programs. As a global food leader ranked first in the nation and second in the world in agriculture and forestry, UC Davis proudly implements various efforts to actively prevent and reduce food waste on the Davis campus and at the UC Davis Medical Center. University leaders proactively gather, track and analyze metrics on a regular basis to identify opportunities to reduce waste further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few examples of UC Davis’ innovative food waste reduction practices:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Just-Ask&lt;/em&gt; program gives dining hall guests the option to remove unwanted ingredients from their dishes, to prevent them from going to waste.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Try-A-Taste&lt;/em&gt; program provides guests with the option to sample a menu item before taking a full portion of the dish.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Interactive waste audits and displays educate guests about how much edible food is wasted during a meal period.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;The student-run Coffee House intentionally repurposes scraps from food preparation for other meals – such as taking the ends of bread and turning them into croutons.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Since 2008, trayless meals in the dining halls have significantly decreased food waste by more than 30 percent.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;The UC Davis Medical Center recently centralized its kitchens to one main location and switched to similar menus to reduce food inventory and waste.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The university has a long tradition of embracing sustainability standards that advance leading practices in higher education and beyond. But even more importantly, UC Davis is committed to educating empowered students who can take the things they learn and experience back to their communities to help our world thrive in the midst of environmental challenges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;Sodexo&quot; name=&quot;Sodexo&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Sodexo&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Narrative Category Winner, Leadership&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an endorser of the Food Recovery Challenge, Sodexo actively fights to reduce food waste. Sodexo started a Waste Skills Training at client partner locations across the country. The client partner site is used as a learning laboratory for area Sodexo team members and clients. The interactive training, conducted in collaboration with the EPA, includes classroom education and a waste sort followed by analysis and problem solving using the waste sort data. This type of training easily translates to immediate implementation once attendees travel back to their own sites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last April, Sodexo announced their commitment to eliminate waste to the landfill by 2025. To achieve this ambitious goal, they focus at the top of the EPA Food Recovery Hierarchy focusing first on preventing food waste all together and then donating recovered food. Sodexo is committed to playing a role in achieving this waste goal and is strengthening their efforts to eliminate food waste at every client site through programs that focus on raising awareness and influencing the behaviors of customers and employees, continuously improving back-of-house processes and upgrading equipment in the kitchen, measuring impact, and sharing expertise with clients and external industry partners to drive fundamental change on the issue of food waste.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sodexo delivers more than 100 services across North America that enhance organizational performance, contribute to local communities and improve quality of life. The global Fortune 500 Company is a leader in delivering sustainable, integrated facilities management and food service operations. Learn more about the company at its corporate blog, Soxexo Insights. &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; “Receiving the Leadership Award from the EPA is a great honor. Reducing food waste and fighting hunger have long been approaches through which we live our mission on improving the quality of life in the communities we serve. We look forward to continued collaboration with the EPA and accomplishing great strides to reduce wasted food.” -- Christy Cook, Director Sustainability Performance and Field Support Sodexo North America&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;FoodForward&quot; name=&quot;FoodForward&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Food Forward&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg right view-mode-medium caption&quot; style=&quot;width:448px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Unpacking produce at Food Forward &quot; height=&quot;299&quot; width=&quot;448&quot; class=&quot;right media-element file-medium right&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/medium/public/2016-11/foodforward.jpg&quot; title=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;figcaption&quot;&gt;Packing produce.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Narrative Category Winner, Innovation&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Food Forward is a second time Food Recovery Challenge awardee. By nearly doubling their food recovery efforts from 2014 to 2015, their staff and more than 7,000 volunteers have recovered over 200 varieties of produce every day of the year. Their innovative model, which mixes high-impact wholesale recovery with massive civic engagement, creates an average of over 150 volunteer-powered food recovery events every month and delivers meaningful results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The crux of Food Forward’s efforts is a Farmers Market Recovery (FMR) Program that combines gleaning of fresh produce, in coordination with receiving agencies that ensure the food goes to feed those in need. Food Forward’s glean teams recover an average of 8,300 pounds of produce per week, mostly in Los Angeles and Ventura Counties, reaching those in need across eight Southern California counties - from Santa Barbara down to the Mexico border.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2015, 3,012 FMR program volunteers, including 157 individual glean team leaders attended 743 events at 17 markets, collecting 448,585 pounds of excess produce and serving 63 individual receiving agencies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;NERC&quot; name=&quot;NERC&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Northeast Recycling Council&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Narrative Category Winner, Endorsers&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg left view-mode-medium&quot; style=&quot;width:448px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;this is a picture of a NERC official demonstrating waste sorting at a school in VT&quot; height=&quot;298&quot; width=&quot;448&quot; class=&quot;left media-element file-medium left&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/medium/public/2016-12/nerc_presentsmonument_school_bennington_vt_cr_derick_carson_bennington_banner.jpg&quot; title=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;Through its food scrap management work, the Northeast Recycling Council (NERC) provides technical assistance, trainings, and resources advancing wasted food reduction, recovery, and composting. NERC works with communities, residents, schools, and businesses around the Northeast. In 2015, NERC provided technical assistance resulting in food scrap composting at Jay Peak Resort’s five full-service restaurants and at four schools in Southern Vermont, presented on food scrap management at two conferences and on two webinars, and published an article on food scrap composting at schools. Through its email bulletin, social media, and other avenues, NERC’s outreach promoting EPA’s Food Recovery Hierarchy and the Food Recovery Challenge has reached thousands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“NERC is very committed to advancing wasted food reduction, recovery, and composting throughout the Northeast. NERC is well known and regarded for its work around the Northeast due to its staff expertise, demonstrated success with various projects, events, technical assistance, resource material development, and speaking engagements. This multi-faceted approach serves to engage a wide range of people; whether it is through hands-on meetings and technical assistance or through its presentations and written materials, NERC successfully gains its audience attention.” - Robert C. Isner, Director, Waste Engineering and Enforcement Division, Bureau of Materials Management and Compliance Assurance, Connecticut Department of Energy and Environmental Protection and NERC Board President&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;Ramona&quot; name=&quot;Ramona&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Ramona High School&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Narrative Category Winner, Education and Outreach&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Eco-Leaders at Ramona High School are a small group of students who participate in a Functional Skills program and are committed to making change in the world. Led by their teacher, Gloria Quinn, and in collaboration with the County of San Diego, they run a district-wide food waste reduction and composting program. Students weigh, measure, chart and keep accurate data from eight school sites. This data is sent electronically to the County each day. The Eco-Leaders are the first high school students in California (and the fourth in the nation) to participate in the EPA&#039;s Food Recovery Challenge. The program follows the EPA’s Food Recovery Hierarchy of source reduction, food donation, and animal feed methods which are employed to maximize community and environmental value. Academic subjects are brought to life and connected to the community, while developing independent living skills and purpose. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a model program, the students at Ramona High School and their teacher have given numerous presentations and on-site demonstrations believing that everyone can &quot;save the world.” Guests have included representatives from municipalities, school districts, class clubs, teachers, government agencies, and advisory committees. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg center view-mode-medium caption&quot; style=&quot;width:448px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Food Scraps from the Eco-Leader Program&quot; height=&quot;378&quot; width=&quot;448&quot; class=&quot;center media-element file-medium center&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/medium/public/2016-11/eco_leader_program_food_scraps.jpg&quot; title=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;figcaption&quot;&gt;Food Scraps from the Eco-Leader Program&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Mon, 21 Nov 2016 17:58:05 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>carcari</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">165491 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>United States Food Loss and Waste 2030 Champions</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/sustainable-management-food/united-states-food-loss-and-waste-2030-champions</link>
    <description>&lt;div class=&quot;box multi related-info right&quot;&gt;
	&lt;h2 class=&quot;pane-title&quot;&gt;Helpful Links&lt;/h2&gt;

	&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Join the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.usda.gov/oce/foodwaste/Champions/index20161108.htm&quot;&gt;U.S. Food Loss and Waste 2030 Champions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;to make a public commitment to reduce food loss and waste in your own operations in the United States by 50 percent by the year 2030.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Join the &lt;a href=&quot;/sustainable-management-food/food-recovery-challenge-frc&quot;&gt;Food Recovery Challenge&lt;/a&gt; and benefit from EPA&#039;s technical assistance to set specific quantitative food-waste goals and attain them.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Join the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.usda.gov/oce/foodwaste/join.htm&quot;&gt;U.S. Food Waste Challenge&lt;/a&gt; and post activities/objectives your organization will undertake in the next year to reduce, recover, and recycle food waste in the United States.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On this page:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#about&quot;&gt;About the U.S. Food Loss and Waste 2030 Champions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#list&quot;&gt;List of Champions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#frequent&quot;&gt;Frequent Questions about the U.S. Food Loss and Waste 2030 Champions&lt;/a&gt;
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#q1&quot;&gt;What is a Food Loss and Waste 2030 Champion?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#q2&quot;&gt;How Does a Company Become a 2030 Champion?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#q3&quot;&gt;Does USDA or EPA verify the Champions&#039; food loss and waste reduction estimates?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#q4&quot;&gt;How is food loss and waste defined and measured?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#q5&quot;&gt;Does USDA or EPA provide technical support to measure food loss and waste?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#q6&quot;&gt;Are there any government recognition programs for businesses that are not ready to commit to a 50 percent reduction goal, but are working to reduce, recover and recycle food loss and waste in their operations?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#q7&quot;&gt;Why did USDA and EPA establish the U.S. Food Loss and Waste 2030 Champions and how is it different than the U.S. Food Waste Challenge?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#q8\&quot;&gt;What are the three food loss and waste recognition programs maintained by USDA and EPA?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;about&quot; name=&quot;about&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;About the U.S. Food Loss and Waste 2030 Champions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In November 2016, the U.S. Department of Agriculture (USDA) and the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) announced the formation of the U.S. Food Loss and Waste 2030 Champions group and presented the first set of &lt;em&gt;2030 Champions&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;U.S. Food Loss and Waste 2030 Champions are businesses and organizations that have made a public commitment to reduce food loss and waste in their own operations in the United States by 50 percent by the year 2030.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The staggering amount of wasted food in the United States has far-reaching impacts on food security, resource conservation and climate change. To help galvanize national efforts to reduce food loss and waste, &lt;a href=&quot;/sustainable-management-food/united-states-2030-food-loss-and-waste-reduction-goal&quot;&gt;USDA and EPA announced the United States’ first-ever food loss and waste reduction goal&lt;/a&gt; in September 2015, calling for a 50-percent reduction by 2030. Government alone cannot reach this goal. It will require effort and action from the entire food system. The 2030 Champions have heard the &lt;a href=&quot;/sustainable-management-food/call-action-stakeholders-united-states-food-loss-waste-2030-reduction&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Call to Action&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and are committed to do their part to help the nation reach this critical goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;list&quot; name=&quot;list&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;List of U.S. Food Loss and Waste 2030 Champions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following is a list of our current U.S. Food Loss and Waste 2030 Champions who have committed to reduce food loss and waste in their own operations in the United States by 50 percent by the year 2030:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Ahold USA&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Blue Apron&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Bon Appetit Management Company&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Conagra Brands&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Delhaize America&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;General Mills, Inc.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;PepsiCo&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Weis Markets&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Kellogg Company&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Campbell Soup Company&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Sodexo&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Walmart and Sam&#039;s U.S.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Wegmans Food Markets, Inc.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Unilever&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;YUM! Brands&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;frequent&quot; name=&quot;frequent&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Frequent Questions About the U.S. Food Loss and Waste 2030 Champions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following are frequent questions about the Food Loss and Waste 2030 Champions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;q1&quot; name=&quot;q1&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;1. What is a U.S. Food Loss and Waste 2030 Champion?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;U.S. Food Loss and Waste 2030 Champions are businesses and organizations that have made a public commitment to reduce food loss and waste in their own operations in the United States by 50 percent by the year 2030.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;q2&quot; name=&quot;q2&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;2. How does a company become a U.S. Food Loss and Waste 2030 Champion?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To join the U.S. Food Loss and Waste 2030 Champions, organizations complete and submit the &lt;a href=&quot;/sustainable-management-food/us-food-loss-and-waste-2030-champions-activity-form&quot;&gt;U.S. Food Loss and Waste 2030 Champions Activity Form&lt;/a&gt;, in which they commit to reduce food loss and waste in their own operations and periodically report their progress on their website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;q3&quot; name=&quot;q3&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;3. Does USDA or EPA verify the Champions’ food loss and waste reduction estimates? &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No, neither USDA nor EPA verify or audit the Champions’ food loss and waste estimates. 2030 Champions are responsible for setting their own baselines and measuring their own food loss and waste reductions. They commit to reporting on their progress on their websites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;q4&quot; name=&quot;q4&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;4. &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How is food loss and waste defined and measured?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The exact definition of food loss and waste could vary by country, business and consumer. U.S. Food Loss and Waste 2030 Champions are encouraged to consult the &lt;a href=&quot;http://flwprotocol.org/&quot;&gt;Food Loss and Waste Protocol&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt; for information on defining and transparently measuring food loss and waste. It is at the Champion’s discretion whether to calculate the 50% reduction on an absolute or per customer/consumer basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;q5&quot; name=&quot;q5&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;5. Does USDA or EPA provide technical support to measure food loss and waste?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;U.S. Food Loss and Waste 2030 Champions can join EPA’s &lt;a href=&quot;/sustainable-management-food/food-recovery-challenge-frc&quot;&gt;Food Recovery Challenge&lt;/a&gt; to access technical assistance for measuring food waste and assessing the positive environmental benefits of waste reduction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;q6&quot; name=&quot;q6&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;6. Are there any government recognition programs for businesses that are not ready to commit to a 50 percent reduction goal but are working to reduce, recover and recycle food loss and waste in their operations?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Businesses that are not ready to make the 50-percent reduction commitment but are engaged in efforts to reduce food loss and waste in their operations can be recognized for their efforts by either joining &lt;a href=&quot;/sustainable-management-food/food-recovery-challenge-frc&quot;&gt;Food Recovery Challenge&lt;/a&gt; or the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.usda.gov/oce/foodwaste/&quot;&gt;U.S. Food Waste Challenge&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;q7&quot; name=&quot;q7&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;7. Why did USDA and EPA establish the U.S. Food Loss and Waste 2030 Champions and how is it different than the U.S. Food Waste Challenge?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;USDA and EPA launched the U.S. Food Waste Challenge in 2013 as a way to raise awareness about food loss and waste in the United States and about steps that businesses and organizations are taking to reduce it. More than 4,000 entities have signed up for the U.S. Food Waste Challenge, demonstrating the growing momentum around this issue in the United States. Reaching the new national goal of cutting food loss and waste in half by 2030, which was announced in 2015, is going to require renewed commitments to aggressively cut food loss and waste. USDA and EPA established the U.S. Food Loss and Waste 2030 Champions initiative as a way of ramping up national efforts to meet this goal. The U.S. Food Loss and Waste 2030 Champions initiative is about recognizing those organizations that have committed to cutting food loss and waste in their own operations in half by 2030 and periodically report on their progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;q8\&quot; id=&quot;q8\&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;8. What are the three food loss and waste recognition programs maintained by USDA and EPA?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.usda.gov/oce/foodwaste/Champions/index20161108.htm&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;U.S. Food Loss and Waste 2030 Champions&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Launched in 2016, &lt;em&gt;U.S. Food Loss and Waste 2030 Champions&lt;/em&gt; are businesses and organizations that have made a public commitment to reduce food loss and waste in their own operations in the United States by 50 percent by the year 2030.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/sustainable-management-food/food-recovery-challenge-frc&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Food Recovery Challenge&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Launched in 2011, the &lt;em&gt;Food Recovery Challenge&lt;/em&gt; (FRC) is designed for organizations seeking to track their food waste reduction activities. Members can join as participants if they are generating food waste or as endorsers if they are not generating their own food waste but can help others reduce their waste (i.e., organizations looking to help educate or recruit for the FRC) with requirements to provide data or report activities/accomplishments to the challenge. Members are eligible for awards based on their accomplishments which are given annually. EPA provides technical assistance and a free climate report to participants. The FRC currently has more than 800 participants and has prevented and diverted millions of tons of food since it started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.usda.gov/oce/foodwaste/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;U.S. Food Waste Challenge&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Launched in 2013, the &lt;em&gt;U.S. Food Waste Challenge&lt;/em&gt; is designed for organizations seeking to make a public pledge/disclosure of their activities to reduce food waste. Participants make a one-time pledge with their name and activities listed on USDA’s website. The goal of the &lt;em&gt;U.S. Food Waste Challenge&lt;/em&gt; is to disseminate information about best practices to reduce, recover, and recycle food loss.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Fri, 23 Sep 2016 14:58:52 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>esundin</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">161041 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Links and Resources About Food Recovery in San Diego Area</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/sustainable-management-food/links-and-resources-about-food-recovery-san-diego-area</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg right view-mode-medium&quot; style=&quot;width:448px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Food Recovery Hierarchy, food waste, composting, waste management, recycle, source reduction&quot; title=&quot;Image of EPA&amp;#039;s Food Recovery Hierarchy&quot; height=&quot;395&quot; width=&quot;448&quot; class=&quot;right media-element file-medium right&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/medium/public/2016-01/fd_reccvry_hierachy_550pxw.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;Learn about some food recovery alternatives in the San Diego Area. EPA’s Food Recovery Hierarchy prioritizes these food waste strategies from most to least preferable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On this page:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#source&quot;&gt;Source Reduction&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#donations&quot;&gt;Feed Hungry People (Donations)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#animals&quot;&gt;Feed Animals&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#industrial&quot;&gt;Industrial Uses&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#composting&quot;&gt;Composting&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#successes&quot;&gt;Successes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
		 &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;source&quot; name=&quot;source&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Source Reduction&lt;!--3--&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Source reduction is the strategy of preventing food from becoming waste in the first place. There are many resources able to tackle source reduction:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;U.S. EPA Food Recovery Website:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
		Toolkits and resources on this website include:
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/sustainable-management-food/tools-assessing-wasted-food#packaging&quot;&gt;Food and Packaging Waste Prevention Tool&lt;/a&gt; - Excel spreadsheet to identify patterns of waste.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/sustainable-management-food/resources-assessing-wasted-food&quot;&gt;Reducing Wasted Food &amp;amp; Packaging: A Guide for Food Services&lt;/a&gt;- Provides guidelines on using the prevention tool tracking results to save money and reduce waste.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/sustainable-management-food/resources-assessing-wasted-food&quot;&gt;Food Waste Assessment Guidebook&lt;/a&gt; - Shows how to do a one-time snapshot wasted food assessment.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;National Restaurant Association Con Serve Program&lt;/strong&gt; - The &lt;a href=&quot;https://conserve.restaurant.org&quot;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt; connects restaurant owners or managers to tools and information to reduce waste.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Leanpath&lt;/strong&gt;: Company assists foodservice operations in reducing food waste, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.leanpath.com/&quot;&gt;website provides many free tools, videos and case studies.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Save the Food&lt;/strong&gt; - The &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.savethefood.com&quot;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt; provides food storage tips and other waste reduction strategies for households, as part of a national campaign.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3&gt;San Diego Resources&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;City of San Diego&lt;/strong&gt; has a Zero Waste resolution, and is working toward diverting more and more waste from the landfill. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sandiego.gov/mayor/pdf/2015/ZeroWastePlan.pdf&quot;&gt;Learn more&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;. The City offers &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sandiego.gov/environmental-services/miramar/greenery/foodwaste&quot;&gt;information&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt; on food waste diversion and a commercial food scrap composting program.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The County of San Diego&lt;/strong&gt; provides ways to minimize food waste and maximize source reduction. The County also offers technical assistance to businesses and schools in the unincorporated areas of the county that want to reduce, donate or divert organics, including food waste. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sandiegocounty.gov/content/sdc/dpw/recycling/Food.html &quot;&gt;Learn more&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The City of Chula Vista&lt;/strong&gt; offers tips for shopping and food storage to help households to minimize food waste. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.chulavistaca.gov/departments/public-works/environmental-fiscal-sustainability/environmental-services/food-waste&quot;&gt;Learn more&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The City of Oceanside&lt;/strong&gt; is on the Road to Zero Waste with a goal is of reaching a 75-90% diversion/recycling rate by 2020.The City also offers technical assistance to businesses within their jurisdiction. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ci.oceanside.ca.us/gov/water/services_programs/recycling/&quot;&gt;Learn more&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;donations&quot; name=&quot;donations&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Feed Hungry People (Donations)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Help curb hunger in our region. Businesses and others can help by donating surplus food. See below for organizations that help fight hunger in San Diego.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Ways to Donate&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Food Banks&lt;/strong&gt; - Food banks collect, store, and distribute food to networks of food pantries, homeless shelters, and other charities that rely on donations. Some provide food directly to the hungry. The larger food banks can help donors to find local charities that can accept their food donations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Food Pantries and Soup Kitchen&lt;/strong&gt;s - San Diego County has hundreds of local, small scale, charitable organizations that provide food directly to those in need. This may be perishable food, packaged food or meals that are prepared in their kitchens. Often they have limited space to store food donations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gleaning&lt;/strong&gt; - Gleaning is the act of picking the excess fruit or vegetables that are left on trees or plants after the owners or farmers have harvested what they want to eat, or what they can sell. San Diego gleaning groups organize volunteers to harvest produce from backyards, orchards, and farms. Donors may claim tax deductions. Why let this fresh food go to waste?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Organizations Accepting Food Donations&lt;/strong&gt; The food banks in San Diego County are listed in the table below, along with other organizations able to accept large donations of food.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;Donation Center&lt;/th&gt;
			&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;Location&lt;/th&gt;
			&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;Website/ Contact&lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Feeding America Food Bank&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
					9445 Waples St. Suite 135&lt;br /&gt;
					San Diego, CA 92121&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://feedingamericasd.org/&quot;&gt;Website&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
					(858) 527-1419&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;San Diego Food Bank&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
					9850 Distribution Avenue&lt;br /&gt;
					San Diego, CA 92121-2320&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://sandiegofoodbank.org/&quot;&gt;Website&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
					(858) 452-3663&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;San Diego Food Bank - North County&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
					680 Rancheros Road Suite 100&lt;br /&gt;
					San Marcos, CA 92069&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://sandiegofoodbank.org/&quot;&gt;Website&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
					(858) 452-3663&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Catholic Charities: Food Resource Centers &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
					 &lt;/p&gt;

				&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;FRC- Downtown&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
					 &lt;/p&gt;

				&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;FRC – College Area&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

				&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;FRC – El Centro&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;FRC – Vista&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
					349 Cedar Street, Room 102&lt;br /&gt;
					San Diego, CA 92101&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
					6360 El Cajon Blvd, Suite B&lt;br /&gt;
					San Diego, CA 92115&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
					250 West Orange Avenue&lt;br /&gt;
					El Centro, CA 92243&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
					917 East Vista Way&lt;br /&gt;
					Vista, CA 92084&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ccdsd.org/programs/&quot;&gt;Website&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Downtown &lt;/strong&gt;(619) 231-2828 x102&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;College Area&lt;/strong&gt; (619) 286-1100&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;El Centro &lt;/strong&gt; (760) 353-6823&lt;/p&gt;

				&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vista&lt;/strong&gt;  (760) 631-4792&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Community Resource Center North County&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
					650 Second Street&lt;br /&gt;
					Encinitas, CA 92024&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://crcncc.org/&quot;&gt;Website&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
					(760) 753-2200&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Interfaith Services&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
					 &lt;/p&gt;

				&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Inland&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
					Coastal&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
					Veterans&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
					 &lt;/p&gt;

				&lt;p&gt;550 W. Washington Ave.&lt;br /&gt;
					Escondido, CA 92025&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
					4700 North River Road&lt;br /&gt;
					Oceanside, CA 92057&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
					1617 Mission Ave.&lt;br /&gt;
					Oceanside, CA 92058&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.interfaithservices.org/contact/&quot;&gt;Website&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
					(760) 489-6380&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
					(760) 721-2117&lt;/p&gt;

				&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
					(760) 529-9979&lt;/p&gt;

				
			&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;San Diego Rescue Mission&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
					5150 University Ave.&lt;br /&gt;
					San Diego, CA 92105&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sdrescue.org/our-programs/hunger-relief/partners-for-hunger-relief/&quot;&gt;Website&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

				&lt;p&gt;(888) SDRESCUE&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kitchens for Good&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
					404 Euclid AveSan Diego, CA 92114&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://kitchensforgood.org/&quot;&gt;Website&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
					(619) 450-4040&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;United Services Organization (USO) San Diego&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;3350 E Street&lt;br /&gt;
				San Diego, CA 92102&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://my.neighbor.org/&quot;&gt;Website&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Father Joe’s Villages&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
					3350 E Street&lt;br /&gt;
					San Diego, CA 92102&lt;br /&gt;
					(619) 446-2100&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://my.neighbor.org/&quot;&gt;Website&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
					(619) 446-2100&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Got Your Back San Diego&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
					4061 Oceanside Blvd. Ste E&lt;br /&gt;
					Oceanside, CA 92056&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gybsd.org/&quot;&gt;Website&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
					(760) 575-4571&lt;/p&gt;
				net&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Tools for Finding Food Charities&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2-1-1 San Diego:&lt;/strong&gt; Serving San Diego County, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.211sandiego.org/new/&quot;&gt;2-1-1 San Diego&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt; connects you with community, health and disaster services through a free, 24/7 stigma-free phone service and searchable database. Simply dial 2-1-1 or search their online database.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;San Diego Food Bank – Food Pantry Zip Code Search: &lt;/strong&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://sandiegofoodbank.org/get-help/need-food-zip-code-search/&quot;&gt;Food Bank&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt; offers a ‘zip code finder’ search for residents to use to find nonprofit partners who offer food assistance. Residents can also call at (866) 350-FOOD (3663).&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Feeding America San Diego – Food Distribution Partner Search&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href=&quot;https://feedingamericasd.org/need-help/&quot;&gt;Feeding America San Diego&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt; connects residents in need with their local partners or mobile pantry locations through a searchable map.  Residents can also call (858) 452-3663 or email  &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:info@feedingamericasd.org&quot;&gt;info@feedingamericasd.org&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I Love A Clean San Diego&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.WasteFreeSD.org&quot;&gt;ILACSD’s&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt; recycling database and call center is a one-stop resource which offers information on donating perishable and non- perishable food--as well as how to divert household items, recyclables, and household hazardous waste from our landfills. Easy access information connects to local resources that reduce waste. &lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ample Harvest “Find a Pantry”: &lt;/strong&gt;This &lt;a href=&quot;https://ampleharvest.org/find-pantry/&quot;&gt;national site&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt; provides a map tool for finding local food banks and pantries.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;County of San Diego - Soup Kitchens List&lt;/strong&gt;: The &lt;a href=&quot;http://sandiego.networkofcare.org/veterans/services/subcategory.aspx?tax=BD-5000.8300&quot;&gt;County of San Diego’s Health and Human Services&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt; website provides a list of soup kitchens as a resource for veterans.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gleaning Organizations&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;box multi related-info right&quot;&gt;
	&lt;h2 class=&quot;pane-title&quot;&gt;Good Samaritan Act&lt;/h2&gt;

	&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://media.law.uark.edu/arklawnotes/2013/08/08/the-legal-guide-to-the-bill-emerson-good-samaritan-food-donation-act/&quot;&gt;The Good Samaritan Act&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;span&gt;Exit &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt;was created to prevent good surplus food from going to waste by protecting donor companies from liability when donating to charitable organizations.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;LIABILITY OF PERSON OR GLEANER- A person or gleaner shall not be subject to civil or criminal liability arising from the nature, age, packaging, or condition of apparently wholesome food or an apparently fit grocery product the at the person or gleaner donates in good faith to a nonprofit organization for ultimate distribution to needy individuals.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Feeding America&lt;/strong&gt; - &lt;a href=&quot;https://feedingamericasd.org/get-involved/donate-food/residential-harvests/&quot;&gt;Feeding America&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt; sends requests for gleaning to local organizations (like the ones below) who can come out to farms, orchards, or backyards to pick the remaining crop for distribution to the hungry. Residents can also call 1-866-350-FOOD (3663) to access this information.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CropSwap&lt;/strong&gt; - Based in North County, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.producegood.org&quot;&gt;ProduceGood&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt; operates the CropSwap gleaning program which organizes teams of volunteers to pick fruit from private groves and orchards throughout San Diego County. Gleaned fruit is donated to food banks for distribution to the hungry.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Harvest CROPS&lt;/strong&gt; - Based in Lemon Grove, &lt;a href=&quot;https://harvestcrops.org/&quot;&gt;Harvest CROPS&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt; organizes teams of volunteers to pick fruit from backyards and orchards throughout San Diego County. The gleaned fruit is donated to local charities for distribution to the hungry.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Senior Gleaners&lt;/strong&gt; - These &lt;a href=&quot;https://seniorgleanerssdco.org/&quot;&gt;volunteer gleaners&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;, aged 55+, harvest from backyards and farms throughout San Diego County, and collect unsold food from grocery stores and restaurants. Gleaned food is distributed at no charge to agencies feeding low income residents.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;San Diego Roots Sustainable Food Project&lt;/strong&gt; - The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sandiegoroots.org/harvesting.php&quot;&gt;San Diego Roots Sustainable Food Project&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt; connects local tree farmers with food pantries who send volunteers out to get the fruit and bring it back to the people who really need it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Working Towards a Fuller Future&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These organizations coordinate efforts to reduce food waste and end hunger in San Diego County.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;San Diego Hunger Coalition&lt;/strong&gt; - The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sandiegohungercoalition.org/&quot;&gt;San Diego Hunger Coalition&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt; is working to remove barriers that make it difficult for families to receive CalFresh aid as well as helping to make the funds from the federal government more available to help more of the children who qualify for the free and reduced lunch programs.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;San Diego Food System Alliance&lt;/strong&gt; - The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sdfsa.org/&quot;&gt;Alliance&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt; is a collaborative that works to address several aspects of hunger and food waste in San Diego. They are striving towards making the food system sustainable, equally available, and economically feasible for all.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;North County Food Policy Alliance&lt;/strong&gt; - The purpose of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.regionalsolutions.net/#!food-policy-council/c5zn&quot;&gt;North County Food Policy Council&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt; is to find solutions to address the unmet food security needs of the residents of North County and to increase access to a secure and nutritionally quality food supply and food shed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;animals&quot; name=&quot;animals&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Feed Animals&lt;br /&gt;
	 &lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Food that is not suitable for donation to hungry people may be valuable for farmers with animals to feed. For instance, many breweries in San Diego donate their spent grain to farms and dairies in the region as well as out of state. The Ramona Unified School District uses food scraps from schools to feed animals in the agricultural program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;For information on which farms are in need of spent grain or other food donations, please contact the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sdfarmbureau.org&quot;&gt;San Diego County Farm Bureau&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt; - or call (760) 745-3023.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;industrial&quot; name=&quot;industrial&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Industrial Uses&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fats, Oils and Grease, also known as FOG, can be converted into fuel and has various industrial uses. There is increasing interest in finding effective means to obtain biofuel and bio-products from wasted food. San Diego regional options include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;New Leaf Biofuel&lt;/strong&gt; - The &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.newleafbiofuel.com/&quot;&gt;New Leaf Biofuel&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt; collects grease from restaurants, schools, hotels and other businesses to convert the cooking oil that would otherwise be discarded into biodiesel fuel.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Buster Biofuels&lt;/strong&gt; - The &lt;a href=&quot;http://busterbiofuels.com/&quot;&gt;Buster Biofuels&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt; partners with different businesses and corporations to collect and repurpose their used kitchen oils and grease to convert it into biofuel.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;composting&quot; name=&quot;composting&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Food Scraps Composting&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Composting turn food scraps into a nutrient-rich soil amendments and can be done on site in smaller amounts or on a larger scale at a municipal or commercial level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Composting Facilities&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The San Diego region has facilities that accept food scraps for composting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Miramar Greenery – City of San Diego&lt;/strong&gt; - The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sandiego.gov/environmental-services/miramar/greenery/foodwaste&quot;&gt;Miramar Greenery&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt; accepts commercial food scraps from pre-approved businesses to be taken to the Greenery and turned into compost. San Diego residents are allowed to take up to two cubic yard of compost for free. The Miramar Greenery website also list the uses for compost.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;El Corazon Compost Facility - City of Oceanside&lt;/strong&gt; - The City of Oceanside’s green waste program takes all green waste collected curbside to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.agriserviceinc.com/&quot;&gt;El Corazon Compost Facility&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt; to be composted. The El Corazon Compost Facility is also currently accepting vegetative food scraps from pre-approved businesses in Oceanside. Oceanside residents are allowed to pick up compost for free with proof of residency at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.oceansiderecycles.org&quot;&gt;Oceanside Solid Waste &amp;amp; Recycling Services&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;City of Chula Vista&lt;/strong&gt; - &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.chulavistaca.gov/departments/public-works/environmental-fiscal-sustainability/environmental-services&quot;&gt;Chula Vista&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt; is currently operating a pilot program where vegetative food waste is being collected from homes and businesses, and taken to the Otay Mesa Landfill Compost Facility.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;successes&quot; name=&quot;successes&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Food Recovery Successes:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The San Diego region has some notable successes in food recovery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Petco Park&lt;/strong&gt; - This large &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.petcoparkevents.com/&quot;&gt;public venue&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt; and home to the San Diego Padres donates large amounts of food to Feeding America for distribution to those in need. All concession stands and restaurants within Petco Park participate in a food waste diversion program. That includes the composting of food scraps at the conclusion of any game or major event. Petco Park’s food waste is then taken to the Miramar Greenery where it&#039;s turned into compost. The compost is periodically returned on site for use in the ballpark landscaping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;San Diego Airport Authority&lt;/strong&gt; - Since 2013 the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.san.org/Airport-Projects/Environmental-Affairs&quot;&gt;San Diego Airport Authority&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt; has had a food waste diversion program. Apart from donating food to feed people, they divert food scraps generated by the on-site food prep in all 40 of the airport’s restaurants, three prep kitchens, and the USO Airport Center, by composting it at the Miramar Greenery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;San Diego Zoo&lt;/strong&gt; - The &lt;a href=&quot;https://sandiegozoo.org/sdzglobal/&quot;&gt;San Diego Zoo&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt; donates unserved food after catered events, and composts animal food prep waste at their Children’s Zoo facility and all food waste from all their restaurants at the Miramar Greenery . The &lt;strong&gt;Safari Park&lt;/strong&gt; composts all main kitchen and restaurants food prep waste at the Miramar Greenery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Ramona Unified School District&lt;/strong&gt; - The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ramonausd.net/&quot;&gt;district&#039;s innovative program&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt; finds the highest and best uses for unserved food and food scraps. Unserved food is collected by a local pantry and donated to feed people; vegetative and bakery food scraps suitable for animal feed are delivered to the district’s agricultural program; and high school students compost other food scraps in an onsite Earth Tub composting unit. Landscape trimmings help provide the “brown” carbon materials needed in the composting process, and the finished compost is used in school landscapes and gardens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sharp Memorial Hospital&lt;/strong&gt; - &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sharp.com/hospitals/memorial/&quot;&gt;Sharp Memorial Hospital&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt; has been composting all their food waste at the Miramar Greenery since 2012, and in 2016 started donating their edible food to local charities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to those examples, many grocery stores, restaurants, hotels and caterers donate leftover or unsold food to hunger relief organizations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Disclaimer&lt;/strong&gt;: The information contained on these pages is intended to inform the public and does not establish or affect legal rights or obligations. Links to non-EPA sites do not imply any official EPA endorsement of, or responsibility for, the opinions, ideas, data or products presented at those locations, or guarantee the validity of the information provided. Reference to any specific commercial products, process or service by trade name, trademark, manufacturer, or otherwise, does not necessarily constitute or imply its endorsement, recommendation, or favoring by the United States Government and shall not be used for advertising or product endorsement purposes.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 22 Sep 2016 18:52:10 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>apage01</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">160983 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Food Loss Prevention Options for Grade Schools, Manufacturers, Restaurants, Universities and Grocery Stores</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/sustainable-management-food/food-loss-prevention-options-grade-schools-manufacturers-restaurants</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;Businesses and organizations can learn to effectively prevent wasted food by taking source reduction steps such as inventorying supplies, changing processes and buying less. EPA developed tip sheets for grade schools, food manufacturers, restaurants, universities and grocery stores that provide suggestions for ways these sectors can prevent food loss and waste.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-309925&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-08/documents/food_loss_prevention_options_grade_schools_august_2016.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=125949&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Food Loss Prevention Options for Grade Schools (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(1 pg, 126 K, 
  August 2016, 
  EPA-530-F-16-019-A)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-309919&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-08/documents/food_loss_prevention_options_manufacturers_august_2016.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=106109&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Food Loss Prevention Options for Manufacturers (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(2 pp, 106 K, 
  August 2016, 
  EPA-530-F-16-019-B)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-309929&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-08/documents/food_loss_prevention_options_restaurants_august_2016.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=160914&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Food Loss Prevention Options for Restaurants (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(2 pp, 161 K, 
  August 2016, 
  EPA-530-F-16-019-C)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-309923&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-08/documents/food_loss_prevention_options_universities_august_2016.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=161541&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Food Loss Prevention Options for Universities (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(2 pp, 162 K, 
  August 2016, 
  EPA-530-F-16-019-D)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-309935&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-08/documents/food_loss_prevention_tips_grocerystores_august_2016.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=157861&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Food Loss Prevention Options for Grocery Stores (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(2 pp, 158 K, 
  August 2016, 
  EPA-530-F-16-019-E)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Fri, 19 Aug 2016 13:24:53 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>carcari</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">157973 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Evaluation Report for Campaigns Using the Food: Too Good to Waste Toolkit</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/sustainable-management-food/evaluation-report-campaigns-using-food-too-good-waste-toolkit</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;This report presents the findings from &lt;em&gt;Food: Too Good to Waste &lt;/em&gt;(FTGTW), a partnership of Community-based Social Marketing (CBSM) campaigns aimed at reducing wasted food from households. The report includes an analysis of seventeen FTGTW campaigns conducted in ten states from October 2012 through December 2014. The campaigns focused on assisting households to make small shifts in how they shop, prepare and store food to prevent it from being wasted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The evaluation addresses both the effectiveness and the impact of the FTGTW campaigns. It confirms that CBSM campaigns can bring about a notable reduction in preventable food waste at the household level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-302429&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-07/documents/ftgtw_finalreport_7_19_16.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=1501074&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Food: Too Good to Waste, An Evaluation Report for the Consumption Workgroup of the West Coast Climate and Materials Management Forum (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(70 pp, 2 MB)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 21 Jul 2016 17:17:25 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>gharman</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">155483 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Wasted Food Programs and Resources Across the United States</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/sustainable-management-food/wasted-food-programs-and-resources-across-united-states</link>
    <description>&lt;div class=&quot;box multi related-info right&quot;&gt;
	&lt;h2 class=&quot;pane-title&quot;&gt;Resources Relevant to All Regions&lt;/h2&gt;

	&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#resources&quot;&gt;EPA compiled a list of national resources&lt;/a&gt; that can help you find information in your community about recycling, pollution prevention, food rescue, food donation and composting.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Food loss and waste is a growing problem in our modern society. The amount of food Americans throw away each year is staggering. In 2014 alone, more than 38 million tons of food waste was generated, with only five percent diverted from landfills and incinerators. EPA estimates that more food reaches landfills and incinerators that any other single material in our everyday trash, constituting 21.6 percent of discarded municipal solid waste.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are growing efforts both to prevent wasted food from occurring in the first place and to divert if from landfills and incinerators. Choose your state or EPA region from the map below or scroll down to find information about state and/or EPA regional wasted food prevention and diversion efforts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#disclaimer&quot;&gt;Note:  Read a disclaimer about the information presented on this Web page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-gif center view-mode-full&quot; style=&quot;width:450px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Picture of EPA&amp;#039;s regional U.S. map&quot; title=&quot;EPA&amp;#039;s Regional U.S. Map&quot; height=&quot;340&quot; width=&quot;450&quot; class=&quot;center media-element file-full&quot; usemap=&quot;#m_us-regions&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/large/public/2016-03/us-regions_1.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;map name=&quot;m_us-regions&quot; id=&quot;m_us-regions&quot;&gt;&lt;area alt=&quot; Connecticut, Maine, Massachusetts, New Hampshire, Rhode Island, Vermont&quot; coords=&quot;390,46,362,40,373,3,426,7,449,42,450,96,419,96,412,84,398,91,394,67,392,65&quot; href=&quot;#1&quot; shape=&quot;poly&quot; title=&quot; Connecticut, Maine, Massachusetts, New Hampshire, Rhode Island, Vermont&quot; /&gt;&lt;area alt=&quot; New Jersey, New York, Puerto Rico, US Virgin Islands&quot; coords=&quot;351,87,356,74,378,51,389,47,392,66,395,67,399,92,412,85,417,99,433,99,433,302,247,302,246,257,348,257,348,303,433,302,433,109,416,110,394,116,388,106,393,101,390,95,391,90,387,90,385,83,352,90&quot; href=&quot;#2&quot; shape=&quot;poly&quot; title=&quot; New Jersey, New York, Puerto Rico, US Virgin Islands&quot; /&gt;&lt;area alt=&quot; Delaware, District of Columbia, Maryland, Pennsylvania, Virginia, West Virginia&quot; coords=&quot;351,86,345,89,349,105,345,119,340,121,336,131,339,134,342,143,331,150,365,146,396,138,407,152,425,152,426,111,408,111,394,115,388,105,394,99,389,94,392,89,387,89,384,83,352,88&quot; href=&quot;#3&quot; shape=&quot;poly&quot; title=&quot; Delaware, District of Columbia, Maryland, Pennsylvania, Virginia, West Virginia&quot; /&gt;&lt;area alt=&quot; Alabama, Florida, Georgia, Kentucky, Mississippi, North Carolina, South Carolina, Tennessee &quot; coords=&quot;335,130,319,126,318,133,314,131,308,138,294,142,292,148,289,150,292,152,284,157,276,170,279,174,272,185,270,199,274,205,270,221,282,219,288,225,377,268,387,251,398,145,395,138,363,146,330,151,342,142,340,134&quot; href=&quot;#4&quot; shape=&quot;poly&quot; title=&quot; Alabama, Florida, Georgia, Kentucky, Mississippi, North Carolina, South Carolina, Tennessee &quot; /&gt;&lt;area alt=&quot; Illinois, Indiana, Michigan, Minnesota, Ohio, Wisconsin&quot; coords=&quot;220,17,220,39,224,41,222,46,225,68,227,68,227,85,262,84,265,92,271,96,271,105,266,108,269,112,264,117,272,134,275,132,278,138,275,141,282,147,282,154,286,155,292,152,290,149,293,149,294,143,309,139,314,131,319,132,320,127,324,128,335,130,341,120,345,120,348,104,345,89,309,24&quot; href=&quot;#5&quot; shape=&quot;poly&quot; title=&quot; Illinois, Indiana, Michigan, Minnesota, Ohio, Wisconsin&quot; /&gt;&lt;area alt=&quot; Arkansas, Louisiana, New Mexico, Oklahoma, Texas&quot; coords=&quot;203,270,217,272,221,256,293,235,282,219,269,221,271,208,273,205,270,198,272,185,279,173,277,169,281,164,274,163,279,160,240,159,239,155,180,155,118,149,107,210,144,234,165,240,190,250&quot; href=&quot;#6&quot; shape=&quot;poly&quot; title=&quot; Arkansas, Louisiana, New Mexico, Oklahoma, Texas&quot; /&gt;&lt;area alt=&quot; Iowa, Kansas, Missouri, Nebraska&quot; coords=&quot;180,154,182,113,166,112,168,90,186,91,208,92,226,99,228,84,263,84,264,91,271,95,271,105,266,108,268,112,263,118,272,134,274,132,276,136,275,141,283,148,283,153,286,155,280,163,276,164,278,158,239,159,239,155&quot; href=&quot;#7&quot; shape=&quot;poly&quot; title=&quot; Iowa, Kansas, Missouri, Nebraska&quot; /&gt;&lt;area alt=&quot; Colorado, Montana, North Dakota, South Dakaota, Utah, Wyoming&quot; coords=&quot;89,8,83,31,88,43,90,44,91,46,88,50,88,54,91,55,97,65,107,67,111,70,107,95,85,90,76,142,117,149,179,152,181,111,165,110,169,90,207,91,226,97,226,84,226,67,224,66,222,48,223,40,219,36,220,32,219,16&quot; href=&quot;#8&quot; shape=&quot;poly&quot; title=&quot; Colorado, Montana, North Dakota, South Dakaota, Utah, Wyoming&quot; /&gt;&lt;area alt=&quot; Arizona, California, Hawaii, Nevada, Pacific Islands&quot; coords=&quot;85,92,10,73,4,86,4,316,86,316,86,244,108,210,117,150,76,142&quot; href=&quot;#9&quot; shape=&quot;poly&quot; title=&quot; Arizona, California, Hawaii, Nevada, Pacific Islands&quot; /&gt;&lt;area alt=&quot; Alaska, Idaho, Oregon, Washington&quot; coords=&quot;1,1,41,2,87,15,83,31,87,44,89,44,91,47,87,49,87,54,91,55,97,67,111,71,106,96,0,71,1,337,240,337,241,274,94,275,93,337,0,337&quot; href=&quot;#10&quot; shape=&quot;poly&quot; title=&quot; Alaska, Idaho, Oregon, Washington&quot; /&gt;&lt;/map&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;1&quot; name=&quot;1&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;EPA Region 1: Connecticut, Massachusetts, Maine, New Hampshire, Rhode Island and Vermont&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Current projects and grants awarded by the EPA New England Sustainable Food Management Program are listed below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Reduce and Recover Save Food for People Conference&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Reduce and Recover Save Food for People Conference was co-sponsored by U.S. EPA, Massachusetts Department of Environmental Protection and the Harvard Food Law and Policy Clinic on June 28-29, 2016. Read about the conference, view recordings of the sessions and more &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.chlpi.org/food-law-and-policy/reduce-and-recover-save-food-for-people/&quot;&gt;on the conference website&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Healthy Communities Grant Program&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www3.epa.gov/region1/eco/uep/hcgp.html&quot;&gt;Healthy Communities Grant Program&lt;/a&gt; is EPA New England&#039;s main competitive grant program to work directly with communities to reduce environmental risks, protect and improve human health and improve the quality of life. Below is a list of the organizations that received grant awards in the past three years to further wasted food reduction and diversion projects:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;2016 Awardees&lt;/th&gt;
			&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;2015 Awardees&lt;/th&gt;
			&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;2014 Awardee&lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;Center for Ecotechnology&lt;br /&gt;
					Waste Not Bridgeport&lt;br /&gt;
					$25,000&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;Sustainable America&lt;br /&gt;
					Implementing the Food Too Good to Waste Toolkit&lt;br /&gt;
					$25,000&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;Northeast Recycling Council&lt;br /&gt;
					Creating Healthy Communities through Food Recovery &amp;amp; Composting in Vermont&lt;br /&gt;
					$25,000&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;Charter Oaks Community Economic Development&lt;br /&gt;
					$25,000&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;Rhode Island Food Policy Council (Third Sector New England)&lt;br /&gt;
					The Food Too Good to Waste Ambassador Program&lt;br /&gt;
					$24,788&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;2016 New England Food Recovery Challenge Endorsers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA New England works with a number of organizations, called endorsers, that do not generate wasted food, but can provide resources to others to reduce their generation of wasted food. Below are the organizations that are participating in EPA&#039;s Food Recovery Challenge as endorsers: &lt;span class=&quot;disclaimer&quot;&gt;The following links exit the site &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bostongreentourism.org/&quot;&gt;Boston Green Tourism&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bu.edu/csc/community-service-center-programs/sfr/&quot;&gt;Boston University Community Service Center&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cetonline.org/&quot;&gt;Center for EcoTechnology&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://communityplates.org/&quot;&gt;Community Plates&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ct.gov/deep/cwp/view.asp?a=2714&amp;amp;q=531602&quot;&gt;Connecticut Department of Energy and Environmental Protection&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.foodforfree.org/&quot;&gt;Food For Free&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.growcompost.com/&quot;&gt;Grow Compost of Vermont&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lrswmd.org/&quot;&gt;Lamoille Regional Solid Waste Management District&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://lovinspoonfulsinc.org/&quot;&gt;Lovin Spoonfuls&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.manomet.org/program/sustainable-economies/grocery-stewardship-certification&quot;&gt;Manomet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mass.gov/eea/agencies/massdep/recycle/reduce/food-waste-ban.html&quot;&gt;Massachusetts Department of Environmental Protection&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nhha.org/index.php/nh-hospitals/nh-hospitals-for-a-healthy-environment-nh3e?highlight=WyJlbnZpcm9ubWVudCJd&quot;&gt;New Hampshire Hospital Association&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://nerc.org/&quot;&gt;Northeast Recycling Council&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nrra.net/&quot;&gt;Northeast Resource Recovery Association&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.newmoa.org/solidwaste/projects/food/&quot;&gt;Northeast Waste Management Officials Association&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://getphood.com/&quot;&gt;Phood LLC&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.foodspoileralert.com/&quot;&gt;Spoiler Alert&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wellesleyma.gov/pages/wellesleyma_sustenergy/index&quot;&gt;Town of Wellesley Sustainable Energy Committee&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://dec.vermont.gov/waste-management/solid/universal-recycling&quot;&gt;Vermont Department of Environmental Conservation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;State Agencies, Non-profits and Partnership Organizations&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below are links to state environmental agencies, non-profit organizations and partnership organizations that provide information about waste management and disposal, composting and food waste disposal bans in EPA Region 1 states:&lt;span class=&quot;disclaimer&quot;&gt;The following links exit the site &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;State&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/th&gt;
			&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;Organization&lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;New England&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.chlpi.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/Food-Waste-Toolkit_Oct-2016_smaller.pdf&quot;&gt;Harvard Food Law and Policy Clinic: Tool Kit Keeping Food out of the Landfill - Policy Ideas for States and Localities&lt;/a&gt; is a resource for state and local policymakers interested in reducing food waste. The toolkit brings together lessons in date labeling, tax incentives, liability protections, organic waste bans, leftovers for livestock as well as other food waste policies, to provide state and local policy makers with a comprehensive menu of policy options to reduce food waste.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.foodspoileralert.com/food-waste-resources-new-england&quot;&gt;Spoiler Alert: Food Waste Reduction &amp;amp; Food Donation Resources for New England&lt;/a&gt; is a resource for anyone who manages food that lists state-specific information on best practices for food donation, legal information on your state’s waste ban, how to find local food banks and rescue programs, and toolkits on managing organic waste and composting.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://nerc.org/documents/guidance_for_special_event_food_waste_diversion.pdf&quot;&gt;Northeast Recycling Council: Special Event Food Waste Diversion Guide&lt;/a&gt; is a guide for managing vendors and food waste disposal at outdoor fairs, concerts and other special events.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Connecticut&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ct.gov/deep/cwp/view.asp?a=2718&amp;amp;q=552676&amp;amp;deepNav_GID=1645&quot;&gt;Connecticut Department of Energy and Environmental Protection Commercial Organics Ban&lt;/a&gt; took effect on October 1, 2014 and states that a commercial food wholesaler or distributor, industrial food manufacturer or processor, supermarket, resort or conference center that generates a projected annual volume of 104 or more tons per year of source separated organic material, &lt;strong&gt;and is&lt;/strong&gt; located within 20 miles of a permitted recycling facility that can accept that material, then those materials must be recycled.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Maine&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://maine.gov/dep/sustainability/compost/index.html&quot;&gt;Maine Department of Environmental Protection Composting&lt;/a&gt; information provides resources and guidance developed by the State of Maine.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;Massachusetts&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mass.gov/eea/agencies/massdep/recycle/reduce/food-waste-ban.html&quot;&gt;Massachusetts Department of Environmental Protection Statewide Commercial Organics Disposal Ban&lt;/a&gt; took effect on October 1, 2014 and states that businesses and institutions that dispose of one ton or more of source separated organic materials per week divert food wastes from disposal to composting, conversion, recycling or reuse, recovery for donation or animal feed.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://recyclingworksma.com/&quot;&gt;Recyclingworks Massachusetts is a Statewide program that provides technical assistance to Massachusetts businesses and institutions&lt;/a&gt; is a state sponsored program that provides technical assistance to businesses and institutions to reduce waste including food waste.  A variety of tools and resources have been developed to support generators including food donation best management practices and other topics.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;New Hampshire&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://des.nh.gov/organization/divisions/waste/swmb/documents/bmp-food-composting.pdf&quot;&gt;New Hampshire Department of Environmental Services Best Management Practices for Food Waste Composting&lt;/a&gt; provides information for solid waste facilities in the state.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Rhode Island&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://ilsr.org/rule/food-scrap-ban/rhode-island-food-waste-recycling/&quot;&gt;Rhode Island Department of Environmental Management Food Waste Ban&lt;/a&gt; took effect on January 1, 2016 and applies only to organic waste producing institutions generating more than 104 tons per year (two tons per week). Food waste generators are exempt from recycling their materials if there is not a composting or anaerobic digestion facility within 15 miles of the institution’s location.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Vermont&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://dec.vermont.gov/waste-management/solid/universal-recycling&quot;&gt;Vermont Department of Environmental Conservation Universal Recycling Law&lt;/a&gt; (Act 148), effectively bans disposal of traditional recyclables, leaf and yard waste, and food scraps found in Vermonters&#039; trash bins. Specifically, food scrap (organic, compostable kitchen wastes) diversion began in a phased approach on July 1, 2014 targeting food scrap generators greater than 2 tons per week and located within 20 miles of certified (composting, anerobic digestion) facility. Diversion continues to ramp up by all size generators over time and by 2020, all food scraps, including those from households, must be diverted with no exemption for distance.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://dec.vermont.gov/waste-management/solid/materials-mgmt/food-donation&quot;&gt;Vermont Food Donation Guidance&lt;/a&gt; has been developed by the Vermont Department of Environmental Conservation,  the Vermont Department of Health and Vermont Agency of Education to promote food donation from businesses and institutions, as well as, kindergarten through grade 12 school share tables.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;2&quot; name=&quot;2&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;EPA Region 2: New Jersey, New York, Puerto Rico and the United States Virgin Islands&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below are links to state and local environmental agencies, non-profit organizations and universities that provide information about anaerobic digestion, composting, food donation and food rescue in New York and New Jersey: &lt;span class=&quot;disclaimer&quot;&gt;The following links exit the site &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;State&lt;/th&gt;
			&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;Resources&lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;New York&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dec.ny.gov/chemical/97612.html&quot;&gt;Information on anaerobic digestion from the state Department of Environmental Conservation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www1.nyc.gov/assets/dsny/zerowaste/residents/food-scraps-and-yard-waste.shtml&quot;&gt;Information on food scraps and yard waste disposal in New York City&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.grownyc.org/compost&quot;&gt;Information about composting food scraps at Greenmarket&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cityharvest.org/donate-food&quot;&gt;City Harvest Food Rescue in New York City&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.albanyny.org/Government/Departments/GeneralServices/TrashRecycling/CompostFacility.aspx&quot;&gt;Information about composting in the City of Albany&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.foodbankwny.org/&quot;&gt;Food Bank of Western New York&lt;/a&gt; (Serving Cattaraugus, Chautauqua, Erie, and Niagara Counties)&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;New Jersey&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.recyclingnj.com/recycle/garden/composting.html&quot;&gt;Information about state composting regulations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://ecocomplex.rutgers.edu/AnaerobicDigestion.pdf&quot;&gt;Overview on Anaerobic Digestion from Rutgers University&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Local food banks:&lt;/p&gt;

				&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.foodbankmoc.org/how-to-help/donate-food/&quot;&gt;FoodBank of Monmouth and Ocean Counties&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://foodbanksj.org/&quot;&gt;Food Bank of South Jersey&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cfbnj.org/&quot;&gt;Community FoodBank of New Jersey&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;3&quot; name=&quot;3&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;EPA Region 3: Delaware, Maryland, Pennsylvania, Virginia, West Virginia and the District of Columbia&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;box multi related-info right&quot;&gt;
	&lt;h2 class=&quot;pane-title&quot;&gt;Virginia Cooperative Extension Directory&lt;/h2&gt;

	&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://pubs.ext.vt.edu/452/452-230/452-230_pdf.pdf&quot;&gt;The Virginia Cooperative Extension directory&lt;/a&gt; of food waste composting facilities in the mid-Atlantic is intended to provide contact information for service and equipment suppliers, along with sources for information and education.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below are links to state environmental agencies, non-profit organizations and partnership organizations that provide information about composting, anaerobic digestion, organics product development and markets as well as solid waste management:  &lt;span class=&quot;disclaimer&quot;&gt;The following links exit the site &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;State&lt;/th&gt;
			&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;Resources&lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Delaware&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;“&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dnrec.delaware.gov/yardwaste/Pages/YardWasteHomeowners.aspx&quot;&gt;Composting University&lt;/a&gt;” from the Department of Natural Resources and Environmental Control&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Maryland&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mde.state.md.us/programs/Land/RecyclingandOperationsprogram/SpecialProjects/Pages/Programs/LandPrograms/Recycling/specialprojects/composting.aspx&quot;&gt;Overview of composting and regulations from the Department of the Environment&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.princegeorgescountymd.gov/DocumentCenter/View/3452&quot;&gt;How to compost&lt;/a&gt; in Prince George’s County&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.howardcountymd.gov/Departments/Public-Works/Bureau-Of-Environmental-Services/Recycling/Feed-the-Green-Bin&quot;&gt;How to compost&lt;/a&gt; in Howard County&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Pennsylvania&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://files.dep.state.pa.us/Waste/Bureau%20of%20Waste%20Management/WasteMgtPortalFiles/PA_Food_Waste_Composting_Facilities.pdf&quot;&gt;Food Waste Composting and Anaerobic Digestion Facilities locations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dep.pa.gov/Citizens/RecyclingDisposal/Composting/Pages/default.aspx&quot;&gt;Overview of composting and regulations from the Department of Environmental Protection&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://prc.org/learn-act/composting/&quot;&gt;Pennsylvania Resources Council runs composting workshops &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Find composting locations and learn more about the process from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://prrp.memberclicks.net/organics&quot;&gt;Professional Recyclers of Pennsylvania.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.pennrmc.org/organics/&quot;&gt;Pennsylvania Recycling Markets&lt;/a&gt; provides turnkey technical assistance that supports organics product development as well as new or existing market opportunities through their Organics Management Assistance Program.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Virginia&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.deq.virginia.gov/Programs/LandProtectionRevitalization/PermittingCompliance/WastePermits/SolidWasteCompostFacilityPermit.aspx&quot;&gt;Information on state composting permits&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;West Virginia&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dep.wv.gov/WWE/permit/solidwaste/Pages/default.aspx#docs&quot;&gt;Information on state composting permits&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.state.wv.us/swmb/&quot;&gt;State Solid Waste Management Board materials and meeting information&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;4&quot; name=&quot;4&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;EPA Region 4: Alabama, Florida, Georgia, Kentucky, Mississippi, North Carolina, South Carolina and Tennessee&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA worked with the Environmental Finance Center serving Region 4 at the University of Louisville to develop the Organics Recovery Program Development Tool for Colleges and Universities. The purpose of this tool is to assist post-secondary institutions with organizing new or expanding existing organics recovery programming with a special focus on composting. This introductory guide is organized by common practical composting methods from existing resources that is supported with school-specific examples and best practices.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://louisville.edu/cepm/organics-development-tool&quot;&gt;Check out the Organics Recovery Program Development Tool for Colleges and Universities &lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;5&quot; name=&quot;5&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;EPA Region 5: Illinois, Indiana, Michigan, Minnesota, Ohio and Wisconsin&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below are resources for sustainable food management in EPA Region 5:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;2015 Resource Guide on Food Scrap Compost Facility Training for Region 5 States and Operators&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/sustainable-management-food/assistance-development-information-resource-compost-facility-training&quot;&gt;This information resource guide&lt;/a&gt; was developed to discuss compost facility training needs and opportunities in EPA Region 5 states. This report:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Summarizes current EPA Region 5 state regulations relating to food scrap composting and requirements for operator training;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Identifies and describes key components of compost training resources available to EPA Region 5 state agency personnel and compost operators, especially those that accept food waste;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Provides a summary of interviews with EPA Region 5 compost operators regarding their experiences with available operator training; and&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Identifies key components that address the compost operational issues faced in EPA Region 5. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;State Agencies, Non-profit Organizations and Academic Institutions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below are links to state environmental and economic development agencies as well as other organizations that offer pollution prevention, waste exchanges, solid waste, recycling and composting resources in EPA Region 5 states:&lt;span class=&quot;disclaimer&quot;&gt;The following links exit the site &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;State&lt;/th&gt;
			&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;State Environmental Agency Website&lt;/th&gt;
			&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;Resources&lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;Illinois&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/hwgenerators/links-hazardous-waste-programs-and-us-state-environmental-agencies#il&quot;&gt;Illinois Environmental Protection Agency&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://illinoiscomposts.org/&quot;&gt;The Illinois Food Scrap Coalition&lt;/a&gt; is a group of solid waste agencies, counties, community and government organizations, businesses, schools, institutions, service providers, and processors dedicated to advancing food scrap composting in Illinois through program implementation, policy, and advocacy.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.illinoisrecycles.org&quot;&gt;Illinois Recycling Association&lt;/a&gt; has more than 100 members and acts as the collective voice for recycling on critical waste management issues at the state level.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.epa.illinois.gov/Assets/iepa/waste-management/composting/regulatoryrequirementsforcompostingfacilities.pdf&quot;&gt;Overview of regulatory requirements for composting facilities&lt;/a&gt; from the state’s Environmental Protection Agency&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;Indiana&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/hwgenerators/links-hazardous-waste-programs-and-us-state-environmental-agencies#in&quot;&gt;Indiana Department of Environmental Management&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://indianarecycling.org/&quot;&gt;The Indiana Recycling Coalition&lt;/a&gt; represents the Indiana Food Scrap Initiative, a multi-stakeholder group which explores the issues behind wasted food and supports the reduction of wasted food across the state.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.in.gov/idem/recycle/2353.htm&quot;&gt;Overview of composting from&lt;/a&gt; the Department of Environmental Management&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;Michigan&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/hwgenerators/links-hazardous-waste-programs-and-us-state-environmental-agencies#mi&quot;&gt;Michigan Department of Environmental Quality&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.michiganrecycles.org/&quot;&gt;The Michigan Recycling Coalition&lt;/a&gt; and its committee, the Michigan Organics Council, represents recycling and composting interests statewide as a recognized authority on waste reduction, beneficial utilization, recycling, and composting.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.michigan.gov/deq/0,1607,7-135-3312_4123---,00.html&quot;&gt;Overview of solid waste information and regulations from&lt;/a&gt; the Department of Environmental Quality&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Minnesota&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/hwgenerators/links-hazardous-waste-programs-and-us-state-environmental-agencies#mn&quot;&gt;Minnesota Pollution Control Agency &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mncompostingcouncil.org/&quot;&gt;The Minnesota Composting Council&lt;/a&gt; is dedicated to the development, expansion, and promotion of the composting industry based upon sound science, principles of sustainability, and economic viability.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://recycleminnesota.org/&quot;&gt;The Recycling Association of Minnesota&lt;/a&gt; is committed to promoting resource conservation through waste prevention, reuse, recycling, composting and purchasing practices using the most cost effective and environmentally sound methods available in Minnesota.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Minnesota Pollution Control Agency’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.pca.state.mn.us/waste/recycling-and-composting&quot;&gt;information on recycling and composting&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Ohio&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/hwgenerators/links-hazardous-waste-programs-and-us-state-environmental-agencies#oh&quot;&gt;Ohio Environmental Protection Agency&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ohiocompost.org/&quot;&gt;Organic Recycling Association of Ohio&lt;/a&gt; is a nonprofit organization that promotes the growth of the organics recycling industry in Ohio by encouraging further study, research, advancement, and development of composting and organic recycling through professionalism, education, training, information exchange and networking within the industry and with regulatory agencies.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://epa.ohio.gov/dmwm/Home/food_scrap.aspx&quot;&gt;Overview of the Ohio Food Scraps Recovery Initiative&lt;/a&gt; from the state’s Environmental Protection Agency&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;Wisconsin&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/hwgenerators/links-hazardous-waste-programs-and-us-state-environmental-agencies#wi&quot;&gt;Wisconsin Department of Natural Resources&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://dnr.wi.gov/topic/waste/studygroup.html&quot;&gt;The Wisconsin Department of Natural Resources Food and Organics Residual Reduction Management Subgroup&lt;/a&gt;. This subgroup is studying, developing and recommending a course of action for managing organics and specifically food waste in Wisconsin, including recommending potential operational practices and regulatory and legislative actions that could be undertaken.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://dnr.wi.gov/topic/recycling/&quot;&gt;Overview of the composting and recycling processes and regulations&lt;/a&gt; from the Department of Natural Resources  &lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;6&quot; name=&quot;6&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;EPA Region 6: Arkansas, Louisiana, New Mexico, Oklahoma and Texas&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coming soon!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;7&quot; name=&quot;7&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;EPA Region 7: Iowa, Kansas, Missouri and Nebraska&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;State Agencies, Non-profit Organizations and Academic Institutions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below are links to state environmental agencies, non-profit organizations and universities that provide information about composting, recycling, food rescue, source reduction, food donation and waste reduction in Region 7 states: &lt;span class=&quot;disclaimer&quot;&gt;The following links exit the site &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;State&lt;/th&gt;
			&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;State Environmental Agency&lt;/th&gt;
			&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;Organizations&lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Iowa&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.iowadnr.gov/Environmental-Protection/Land-Quality/Waste-Planning-Recycling/Composting-Organics&quot;&gt;Iowa Department of Natural Resources&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.iowadnr.gov/Environmental-Protection/Land-Quality/Waste-Planning-Recycling/Composting-Organics&quot;&gt;Overview of composting guidelines and resources&lt;/a&gt; from the Department of Natural Resources&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.iowarecycles.org/&quot;&gt;The Iowa Recycling Association&lt;/a&gt; is a statewide nonprofit that seeks to advance effective recycling by sharing resources, education and advocacy opportunities.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://foodrescueqc.org/how-to-get-started/epa-food-recovery-challenge/&quot;&gt;The Food Rescue Partnership&lt;/a&gt; is a community-focused coalition committed to rescuing food throughout the Quad Cities that would otherwise be thrown away, by informing and engaging the public and by fostering partnerships among food establishments, the Foodbank, food pantries, meal sites, and shelters.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Information from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.icgov.org/foodwaste&quot;&gt;Johnson County Solid Waste District and Iowa City website&lt;/a&gt; about local composting and strategies for reducing wasted food.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Kansas&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.kdheks.gov/waste/about_composting.html&quot;&gt;Kansas Department of Health and Environment&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://kansasrecycles.org/&quot;&gt;Kansas Recycles&lt;/a&gt; provides users with an easy and comprehensive destination to locate recycling options in all areas of Kansas based on a database and interactive map technology.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://kabtopsh.org/&quot;&gt;Keep Kansas Beautiful &lt;/a&gt;is the local affiliate of the national Keep America Beautiful organization, with information on recycling and composting opportunities.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Map of food diversion facilities from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sbeap.org/services-programs/food-recovery&quot;&gt;Kansas State University&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Overview of home composting and its benefits from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.kskor.org/recycling/composting&quot;&gt;Kansas Organization of Recyclers &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Missouri&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://dnr.mo.gov/env/swmp/composting/index.html&quot;&gt;Missouri Department of Natural Resources&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://greendiningalliance.org/resources/&quot;&gt;The Green Dining Alliance&lt;/a&gt; is a restaurant sustainability certification program that works with restaurants to reduce their environmental impact by completing an on-site audit that evaluates all areas of operations, and setting personalized goals.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;An overview on the process and benefits of composting from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.marc.org/Environment/Water-Resources/Landscaping-and-Lawn-Care/Composting&quot;&gt;Mid-America Regional Council&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mora.org/food-waste.html&quot;&gt;Missouri Recycling Association&lt;/a&gt; seeks to reduce waste and promote recycling.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Information on state &lt;a href=&quot;https://oa.mo.gov/general-services/missouri-state-recycling-program&quot;&gt;recycling statutes and services&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.coam-mo.com/about/&quot;&gt;The Composting and Organics Association of Missouri&lt;/a&gt; is dedicated to the development, expansion and promotion of the composting and organics industry throughout Missouri.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.missouribotanicalgarden.org/sustainability/sustainability/about-sustainability.aspx&quot;&gt;Earthways Center for Sustainability&lt;/a&gt; composts and reuses almost 100 percent of their plant and food waste.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Nebraska&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.deq.state.ne.us/&quot;&gt;Nebraska Department of Environmental Quality&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.recyclenebraska.org/&quot;&gt;Nebraska Recycling Association&lt;/a&gt; provides technical and grant assistance to recycling programs and communities state-wide.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.knb.org/&quot;&gt;Keep Nebraska Beautiful&lt;/a&gt; works to inspire Nebraskans to take actions that improve and beautify our communities.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wastecapne.org/&quot;&gt;WasteCap Nebraska&lt;/a&gt; is a statewide, member-based, nonprofit organization providing education, training and services to help businesses and communities reach their full potential to eliminate waste.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://savinggracefoodrescue.org/past-events/&quot;&gt;Saving Grace-Feeding the 5000&lt;/a&gt; collects perishable food from local food purveyors to local nonprofits that feeds hungry people, while raising awareness and providing education about food waste and hunger.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://producefromtheheart.org/&quot;&gt;Produce from the Heart&lt;/a&gt; collects donated edible produce from farmers and gardeners across Nebraska and redistributes it to pantries, homeless shelters and soup kitchens.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Past Recognition Events&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;&lt;em&gt;Newton, Kansas - Sand Creek Station Golf Course, June 24, 2013&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Region 7 presented an award to the City of Newton, Kansas, for efforts to reduce waste and recycle materials at the city-owned Sand Creek Station Golf Course. Among other achievements in 2012, the City of Newton diverted approximately 24 tons of waste from landfills through waste prevention and recycling programs at the golf course. &lt;a href=&quot;http://yosemite.epa.gov/opa/admpress.nsf/0/5F5A31E273A58EA185257B94006935F5&quot;&gt;Learn more.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;&lt;em&gt;St Louis Cardinals, April 29, 2013&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Region 7 recognized the St. Louis Cardinals baseball club for efforts to divert, donate and compost food waste around Busch Stadium in an on-field ceremony prior to the Cardinals-Reds game. &lt;a href=&quot;http://yosemite.epa.gov/opa/admpress.nsf/0/8D5F115FD1CB089185257B59006EFA5B&quot;&gt;Learn more.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kansas City Chiefs, April 8, 2013&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Region 7 and the Kansas City Chiefs announced Extra Yard for the Environment, the football club&#039;s sustainability initiative. The program is designed to devise and implement new green policies for the Kansas City Chiefs while raising awareness for green efforts at Arrowhead Stadium, the University of Kansas Hospital Training Complex, and for fans at home. &lt;a href=&quot;http://yosemite.epa.gov/opa/admpress.nsf/0/DCBF0D7F3D02D78785257B4700796197&quot;&gt;Learn more.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;&lt;em&gt;Haskell Indian Nations University, November 10, 2015&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Region 7 and Haskell Indian Nations University conducted a food waste sort as a part of the University’s ongoing food recovery efforts.  &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.epa.gov/blog/2015/11/food-for-thought-haskell-indian-nations-university-conducts-food-waste-audits/&quot;&gt;Learn More.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Watch Region 7&#039;s Food Recovery Stories&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=jn64ctB56T0&quot;&gt;Johnson County Solid Waste District and Iowa City’s video about Food: Too Good To Waste pilot project with EPA&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=nciqfJ8wz0g&quot;&gt;Iowa Waste Reduction Center food waste video&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Sign up for the Region 7 Community Digest Newsletter&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Region 7 Community Digest Newsletter contains information about upcoming events, webinars, grant opportunities and more. &lt;a href=&quot;/communities/communities-information-digest&quot;&gt;Check out the latest edition and learn how to subscribe to this newsletter.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;8&quot; name=&quot;8&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;EPA Region 8: Colorado, Montana, North Dakota, South Dakota, Utah and Wyoming&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below are links to state and local environmental agencies, non-profit organizations and partnership organizations that provide information about food recovery, food rescue, food donation, community gardens, sustainability and recycling in Region 8 states: &lt;span class=&quot;disclaimer&quot;&gt;The following links exit the site &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;State&lt;/th&gt;
			&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;Resources&lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Colorado&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.foodrecoverynetwork.org/colorado&quot;&gt;Colorado Food Recovery Network&lt;/a&gt; recovers meals from college dining halls and delivers them to local partners to distribute to the community.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thegrowingproject.org/food-finders.html&quot;&gt;The Growing Project: Food Finders&lt;/a&gt; addresses food insecurity by making fresh, nourishing, regional food more accessible to all.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Garfield County provides information about food rescue and resources through their &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.garfield-county.com/livewell&quot;&gt;LiveWell program&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.boulderfoodrescue.org&quot;&gt;Boulder Food Rescue&lt;/a&gt; is a nonprofit organization whose goal is to create a more just and less wasteful food system. They completed a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.boulderfoodrescue.org/index.php/food-waste-audit&quot;&gt;Food Waste Audit&lt;/a&gt; in 2016 to provide information about the state of food waste in Boulder.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.DICP.org&quot;&gt;Denver Inner City Parish&lt;/a&gt; has one of the original and longest running programs offered by the Denver Inner City Parish.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.foragedfeast.org&quot;&gt;Foraged Feast&lt;/a&gt; is a Denver-based nonprofit that collects locally grown food that would otherwise go unused or wasted and connects those nutritional food sources with the underserved of our community.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.boulderfoodrescue.org/index.php/food-rescue-alliance/&quot;&gt;Food Rescue Alliance&lt;/a&gt; is a nonprofit organization whose goal is to create a more just and less wasteful food system. They redistribute food “waste” to agencies who serve hungry, homeless and low-income individuals while educating communities about food justice.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.denverfoodrescue.org&quot;&gt;Denver Food Rescue&lt;/a&gt; is a nonprofit focused on improving health equity outcomes by increasing access to healthy foods in low income areas.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;As an innovative provider of food for the hungry, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wedontwaste.org/&quot;&gt;We Don’t Waste&lt;/a&gt; collects excess food from venues, caterers, restaurants, and other food purveyors and distributes the food to Denver’s under-served populations.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.produceforpantries.com&quot;&gt;Produce for Pantries&lt;/a&gt; encourages home, school and community gardeners to plant, grow and share produce with food pantries and hunger-relief organizations in their neighborhoods.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.careandshare.org&quot;&gt;Care and Share Food Bank for Southern Colorado&lt;/a&gt; exists to ensure that the one in seven Southern Coloradoans at risk of hunger have access to enough healthy and nutritious food to thrive.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.coloradospringsfoodrescue.org&quot;&gt;Colorado Springs Food Rescue&lt;/a&gt; volunteers sustainably recover food seven days a week from donor businesses around the Pikes Peak region and deliver it directly to local nonprofit partnership programs.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://yardharvest.org/&quot;&gt;Denver Yard Harvest&lt;/a&gt; brings fresh produce that would otherwise go waste to people who might otherwise go without it, building community and learning more about the importance of healthy food and reducing waste.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Montana&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://ecotrust.org/project/foodhub/&quot;&gt;Ecotrust Food Hub&lt;/a&gt; is an online platform that connects farmers, ranchers, fishermen and specialty producers with wholesale food buyers in their region.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://growmontana.ncat.org/&quot;&gt;Grow Montana&lt;/a&gt; is a broad-based food policy coalition whose common purpose is to promote community economic development and education policies that support sustainable Montana-owned food production, processing, and distribution, and that improve everyone’s access to healthy Montana foods.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://helenagardens.org/&quot;&gt;Helena Community Gardens&lt;/a&gt; builds gardens, provides the tools and knowledge to grow food, and increases access to healthy and affordable food.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.westernsustainabilityexchange.org/montana-farm-to-restaurant/&quot;&gt;Montana to Farm Restaurant Connection&lt;/a&gt; works to increase the visibility of local producers that use sustainable agricultural techniques and the business establishments that carry their products.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://mfbn.org/&quot;&gt;Montana Food Bank Network&lt;/a&gt; is a nonprofit that works to end hunger in Montana through food acquisition and distribution, education and advocacy.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.homegrownmontana.org/&quot;&gt;Montana Sustainable Growers Union&lt;/a&gt; is a group of local farmers who all farm within a 75 mile radius of Missoula and market in the state to promote buying homegrown goods.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;North Dakota&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Information about Holy Cross Daily Bread Food Bank &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.foodpantries.org/li/holy_cross_daily_bread_58078&quot;&gt;from Food Pantries.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nd.gov/ndda/program-info/local-foods-initiative/hunger-free-nd-garden-project&quot;&gt;Hunger Free North Dakota Garden Project&lt;/a&gt; is committed to addressing the hunger issue in North Dakota through the local foods initiative. They encourage farmers and gardeners to plant an extra acre or row of produce and donate fresh fruits and vegetable to food pantries, soup kitchens, and other charitable community programs.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.greatplainsfoodbank.org/&quot;&gt;Great Plains Food Bank&lt;/a&gt; works to end hunger in North Dakota and western Minnesota through community partnerships.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;South Dakota&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://feedingsouthdakota.org/&quot;&gt;Feeding South Dakota&lt;/a&gt; (multiple chapters) works to eliminate hunger in South Dakota by working with communities, distributing food to those in need, and advocating at the state and federal level on behalf of the hungry.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Utah&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.foodrecoverynetwork.org/utah&quot;&gt;Utah Food Recovery Network&lt;/a&gt; recovers meals from college dining halls and delivers them to local partners to distribute to the community.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.utahfoodbank.org/grocery-rescue&quot;&gt;Utah Food Bank Grocery Rescue Program&lt;/a&gt; is a strategic business alliance between Utah Food Bank and Utah retailers that provides a safe and efficient donation outlet for food that is nearing its expiration date, but is still safe, healthy and wholesome to eat.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://utah.momentumrecycling.com/foodwaste/&quot;&gt;Wasatch Food Waste Recovery&lt;/a&gt; works with hotels, restaurants, and other food waste producing companies to turn food waste into energy and fertilizer using anaerobic digestion.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://ecoscraps.com/pages/our-story&quot;&gt;EcoScraps &lt;/a&gt; recycles food scraps into organic and sustainable lawn and garden products.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Wyoming&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.holefoodrescue.org&quot;&gt;Hole Food Rescue&lt;/a&gt; is a nonprofit organization that works to reduce food waste and food insecurity in their community.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.foodbankrockies.org/&quot;&gt;Wyoming Food Bank of the Rockies&lt;/a&gt; provides food and supplies to more than 500 hunger-relief programs.&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;9&quot; name=&quot;9&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;EPA Region 9: Arizona, California, Hawaii, Nevada, Guam and American Samoa&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Food recovery work in southern Nevada, food recovery guides for certain cities, partnering organization websites and key contacts for EPA Region 9 are listed below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Southern Nevada Food Recovery Work&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On September 30, 2015, a Southern Nevada Food and Organics Recovery Workshop was hosted by U.S. EPA, the Nevada Department of Environmental Protection, the Environmental Finance Center West and the Regional Transportation Commission of Southern Nevada, in Las Vegas. This workshop brought together 36 representatives from the private sector, government agencies, non-profit organizations and academia to explore opportunities and barriers to the recovery of wasted food and other organic wastes generated in Southern Nevada.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/sustainable-management-food/final-report-and-analysis-2015-southern-nevada-food-and-organics&quot;&gt;Read about the workshop, outcomes, conclusions and more in the Final Report and Analysis &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Local Food Recovery Guides, Partnering Organizations and Key Contacts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below are food recovery guides for certain cities in Region 9 along with links to partner organizations and contact information for key Region 9 partners: &lt;span class=&quot;disclaimer&quot;&gt;The following links exit the site &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;State&lt;/th&gt;
			&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;Local Food Recovery Guides&lt;/th&gt;
			&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;Partnering Organizations and Key Contacts&lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Arizona&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/sustainable-management-food/links-and-resources-about-food-recovery-phoenix-area&quot;&gt;Local Food Recovery Guide in Phoenix&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.azdeq.gov/environ/waste/solid/index.html&quot;&gt;Arizona Department of Environmental Quality Waste Programs: Solid Waste Section&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

				&lt;p&gt;J.B. Shaw&lt;br /&gt;
					(602) 771-5613&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;mailto:js15@azdeq.gov&quot;&gt;js15@azdeq.gov&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;California&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/sustainable-management-food/links-and-resources-about-food-recovery-san-francisco-bay-area&quot;&gt;Local Food Recovery Guide in the Bay Area&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/sustainable-management-food/links-and-resources-about-food-recovery-los-angeles&quot;&gt;Local Food Recovery Guide in Los Angeles&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/sustainable-management-food/links-and-resources-about-food-recovery-san-diego-area&quot;&gt;Local Food Recovery Guide in San Diego area&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.calrecycle.ca.gov/organics/&quot;&gt;California&#039;s Department of Resources Recycling and Recovery (CalRecycle) Organic Materials Management&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

				&lt;p&gt;Bob Horowitz&lt;br /&gt;
					(916) 341-6452&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;mailto:Robert.Horowitz@CalRecycle.ca.gov&quot;&gt;Robert.Horowitz@CalRecycle.ca.gov&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Hawaii&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;
						&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/sustainable-management-food/links-and-resources-about-food-recovery-honolulu&quot;&gt;Local Food Recovery Guide in Honolulu&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
					&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://health.hawaii.gov/shwb/solid-waste/&quot;&gt;Hawaii Department of Health Office of Solid Waste Management&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

				&lt;p&gt;Lene Ichinotsubo&lt;br /&gt;
					(808) 586-7497&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;mailto:lene.ichinotsubo@doh.hawaii.gov&quot;&gt;lene.ichinotsubo@doh.hawaii.gov&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Nevada&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/sustainable-management-food/links-and-resources-about-food-recovery-las-vegas&quot;&gt;Local Food Recovery Guide in Las Vegas&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/sustainable-management-food/links-and-resources-about-food-recovery-reno-nevada&quot;&gt;Local Food Recovery Guide in Reno&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://ndep.nv.gov/bwm/solid.htm&quot;&gt;Nevada Division of Environmental Protection Bureau of Waste Management&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

				&lt;p&gt;Northern Nevada Recycling Coordinator: Patricia Moen&lt;br /&gt;
					(775) 687-9466&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;mailto:pmoen@dcnr.nv.gov&quot;&gt;pmoen@dcnr.nv.gov&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

				&lt;p&gt;Southern Nevada Recycling Coordinator: Rachel Lewison&lt;br /&gt;
					(702) 486-2850 x268&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;mailto:rlewison@dcnr.nv.gov&quot;&gt;rlewison@dcnr.nv.gov&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Pacific Islands&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;None available&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/aboutepa/epa-pacific-islands&quot;&gt;U.S. EPA Region 9 Pacific Islands Office&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

				&lt;p&gt;John McCarroll&lt;br /&gt;
					(415) 972-3774&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;mailto:mccarroll.john@epa.gov&quot;&gt;mccarroll.john@epa.gov&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;10&quot; name=&quot;10&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;EPA Region 10: Alaska, Idaho, Oregon and Washington&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coming soon!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;resources&quot; name=&quot;resources&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Resources Relevant to All Regions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below are links to resources that may help you find information in your community about recycling, pollution prevention, food rescue, food donation and composting:&lt;span class=&quot;disclaimer&quot;&gt;The following links exit the site &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ampleharvest.org/find-pantry.php&quot;&gt;Ample Harvest&lt;/a&gt; allows you to search food pantries by zip code and shows the location on an interactive map.  &lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.campuskitchens.org/&quot;&gt;The Campus Kitchen Project&lt;/a&gt; partners with high schools, colleges and universities to share on-campus kitchen space, recover food from cafeterias and engage students as volunteers who prepare and deliver meals to the community.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.1800cleanup.org/&quot;&gt;Earth’s 911&lt;/a&gt; provides local resources on recycling, pollution prevention and environmental information based on your zip code.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.feedingamerica.org/find-your-local-foodbank/&quot;&gt;Feeding America&lt;/a&gt; has a map of their own Feeding America member food banks. Some of these food banks might have a minimum donation size requirement for pick up.  &lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.findacomposter.com/&quot;&gt;Find a Composter&lt;/a&gt; near you using this tool.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.findafoodpantry.org/&quot;&gt;Find a Food Pantry&lt;/a&gt; near you using this tool.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.foodconnectgroup.com/&quot;&gt;Food Connect&lt;/a&gt; helps organizations with excess food find local charities who can use the food.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://foodcowboy.com/&quot;&gt;Food Cowboy&lt;/a&gt; connects wholesalers to charities to recover rejected food deliveries.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.foodrecoverynetwork.org/&quot;&gt;The Food Recovery Network&lt;/a&gt; recovers meals from college dining halls and delivers them to local partners to distribute to the community.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;This &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.homelessshelterdirectory.org/&quot;&gt;Homeless Shelter Directory&lt;/a&gt; allows you to search homeless shelters and services by city.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.meansdatabase.com/&quot;&gt;MEANS&lt;/a&gt; is a live match making map where donors can post donations and non-profits can get alerts.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Rock and Wrap It Up’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://rockandwrapitup.org/hungerpedia/&quot;&gt;Hungerpedia&lt;/a&gt; is a live downloadable directory of agencies in need of contributions.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Find your &lt;a href=&quot;/home/health-and-environmental-agencies-us-states-and-territories&quot;&gt;state&#039;s health and environmental agencies&lt;/a&gt; for more information.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://sustainableamerica.org/foodrescue/&quot;&gt;Sustainable America&lt;/a&gt; has a live interactive map of food rescue non-profits that can take your donations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;disclaimer&quot; name=&quot;disclaimer&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Disclaimer of Endorsement&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reference herein to any specific commercial products, process, or service by trade name, trademark, manufacturer, or otherwise, does not necessarily constitute or imply its endorsement, recommendation, or favoring by the United States Government. The views and opinions of authors expressed herein do not necessarily state or reflect those of the United States Government, and shall not be used for advertising or product endorsement purposes. The examples included in the following sections are for informational purposes only.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Mon, 23 May 2016 16:43:59 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>carcari</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">150225 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>A Call to Action by Stakeholders: United States Food Loss &amp; Waste 2030 Reduction Goal</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/sustainable-management-food/call-action-stakeholders-united-states-food-loss-waste-2030-reduction</link>
    <description>&lt;div class=&quot;box multi related-info right&quot;&gt;
	&lt;h2 class=&quot;pane-title&quot;&gt;Helpful Links&lt;/h2&gt;

	&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;Join the&lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/sustainable-management-food/food-recovery-challenge-frc&quot;&gt; Food Recovery Challenge&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span&gt; and benefit from EPA’s technical assistance to set specific quantitative food-waste goals and attain them!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;Join the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.usda.gov/oce/foodwaste/join.htm&quot;&gt;U.S. Food Waste Challenge&lt;/a&gt;, and post activities/objectives your organization will undertake in the next year to reduce, recover, and recycle food waste in the United States.&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;Check out the recent conference we co-hosted with Harvard Law School on June 28-29, 2016. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.chlpi.org/food-law-and-policy/reduce-and-recover-save-food-for-people/&quot;&gt;Reduce and Recover: Save Food For People&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The federal government, led by EPA and the United States Department of Agriculture (USDA), is seeking to work with communities, organizations and businesses along with our partners in state, tribal and local government to reduce food loss and waste by 50 percent over the next 15 years. As an important stride in reaching the 2030 food reduction goal, EPA hosted the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.serdc.org/Program&quot;&gt;Food Recovery Summit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt; where organizations across the food chain, from manufacturers to consumers, met to discuss the key challenges in reducing food loss and waste. Based on this summit and continued input, EPA, USDA and stakeholders from across the food chain have developed a collaborative Call to Action, which identifies current opportunities and challenges in reducing food loss and waste in the United States.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On this page:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#objectives&quot;&gt;Objectives&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#activities&quot;&gt;Key Activities Identified by Stakeholders&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#opportunities&quot;&gt;Opportunities and Actions Identified by Stakeholders&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;objectives&quot; name=&quot;objectives&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Objectives&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The purposes of this Call to Action are to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;collect and synthesis key opportunities and issues identified at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.serdc.org/Program&quot;&gt;2015 Food Recovery Summit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt; and subsequent meetings,&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;establish a cohesive list of actions available to businesses, organizations, governments, and general public to reduce food loss and waste, and&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;inspire new innovations and actions from the stakeholder community to further progress towards the 2030 food loss and waste reduction goal.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p&gt;EPA and USDA offer this Call to Action in order to highlight and share the assessments of outside experts and representatives of the food system about current opportunities and challenges. As stakeholders across the food supply chain voluntarily initiate actions to reduce food loss and waste, this Call to Action can help them identify opportunities and gaps. EPA and USDA are very interested in learning more about new actions and accomplishments that reflect the nation’s achievements, opportunities and ongoing challenges to reduce food loss and waste.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stakeholders will determine their own actions or any other input and will not be limited by the content of this Call to Action. EPA’s and USDA’s role is to act as a convener, help facilitate discussion, provide leadership, and compile actions and conversations of individual companies, organizations and stakeholders. The federal government is not seeking consensus advice or recommendations from stakeholders through this Call to Action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;activities&quot; name=&quot;activities&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Key Activities Identified by Stakeholders&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Participants at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.serdc.org/Program&quot;&gt;2015 Food Recovery Summit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;identified the following key activities as the core of a successful strategy that would result in wide-scale and sustained reductions in food loss and waste.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Seek Prevention Strategies and Use the Food Recovery Hierarchy:&lt;/strong&gt; By focusing interventions on the prevention of wasted food and following the principles outlined in the &lt;a href=&quot;/sustainable-management-food/food-recovery-hierarchy&quot;&gt;Food Recovery Hierarchy&lt;/a&gt;, businesses, individuals and organizations can maximize economic gains while increasing social and environmental benefits&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Increase Public Awareness:&lt;/strong&gt; Increase consumer and industry awareness of the scale of the food waste problem along with the environmental, social, and economic benefits of reducing wasted food. Furthering food stewardship, donation and waste reduction begins with education and outreach about the collective effects of food waste and providing replicable best practices.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Improve the Data:&lt;/strong&gt; Encourage companies and organizations in the private and public sectors to measure their contribution to food loss and waste and their associated reduction efforts. By collecting valid data, businesses can justify sustainable food management investments, tailor their reduction programs, and gain new insights on opportunities to prevent and reduce food loss and waste.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Forge New Partnerships and Expand the Existing Ones:&lt;/strong&gt; Leverage existing or create new partnerships to divert excess food to new and/or secondary markets and/or recover food waste that has historically been destined for disposal. When organizations collaborate they are able to share existing infrastructures, resources and expertise, which could help them efficiently restructure food management towards a more sustainable operation.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Clarify Date Labels and Food Safety:&lt;/strong&gt; Use clear terminology and phrasing to help consumers and secondary users make better decisions about discarding food. Date labeling, when clearly communicated, can be an effective tool to provide consumers with recommendations from a food manufacturer/producer about the viability or quality of a particular item. However, too often, date labels are ambiguous on what characteristic they are speaking to (e.g., quality or safety), leading consumers, food banks, and others to make an independent assessment on the viability of a product. Understandably, decisions are often made on the conservative side and items are discarded.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Build Food Loss and Waste Infrastructures:&lt;/strong&gt; Effectively divert excess food to new markets and recover wasted food by creating new options and incentives to individuals and companies. Increase investments to establish or expand new recovery and/or diversion operations and promote development of new technologies and innovation for food waste recovery. By supporting transportation and processing of excess food, communities can capitalize on the economic opportunities of a sustainable food management system while reducing the cost and environmental burdens associated with landfilling food waste.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;opportunities&quot; name=&quot;opportunities&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Opportunities and Actions Identified by Stakeholders&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;box multi related-info right&quot;&gt;
	&lt;h2 class=&quot;pane-title&quot;&gt;Note&lt;/h2&gt;

	&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;While the sectors of the food system are segregated, it is important to note that many strategies as well as actors (e.g., producers, manufacturers, retailers, etc.) will find relevant factors to consider in multiple areas.&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stakeholders across the supply chain, including participants at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.serdc.org/Program&quot;&gt;2015 Food Recovery Summit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;, have identified specific opportunities and actions across the food system to reduce FLW. This section divides the food system into focus areas (Production, Manufacturing, Retail/Food Service, Consumers and Donation, Recovery/Recycling, and Regulators/Policy Makers) and identifies opportunities and actions within each area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the tables below, opportunities are areas of action with high prospects for reducing food loss and waste. If these opportunities are realized through action, progress will be made in achieving the 2030 FLW reduction goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Key Stakeholders&lt;/strong&gt; are those stakeholders that are particularly, though not exclusively, associated with a specific area of the food system.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Demonstrated Practices &lt;/strong&gt;are ongoing or past interventions identified that have had success in reducing food waste.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Actions&lt;/strong&gt; towards progress are suggestions from stakeholders, primarily from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.serdc.org/Program&quot;&gt;Food Recovery Summit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;, and are incorporated into this document for reaction and additional comments.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;table&gt;&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;
				&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Disclaimer of Endorsement&lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;: Reference herein to any specific commercial products, process, or service by trade name, trademark, manufacturer, or otherwise, does not necessarily constitute or imply its endorsement, recommendation, or favoring by the United States Government. The views and opinions of authors expressed herein do not necessarily state or reflect those of the United States Government, and shall not be used for advertising or product endorsement purposes. The examples included in the following sections are for informational purposes only.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;div id=&quot;tabs&quot;&gt;
	&lt;ul class=&quot;tabs&quot; id=&quot;tabsnav&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;menu-internal&quot; href=&quot;#tab-1&quot;&gt;Production&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;menu-internal&quot; href=&quot;#tab-2&quot;&gt;Manufacturing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;menu-internal&quot; href=&quot;#tab-3&quot;&gt;Retail/Food Services&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;menu-internal&quot; href=&quot;#tab-4&quot;&gt;Consumers and Donation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;menu-internal&quot; href=&quot;#tab-5&quot;&gt;Recovery/Recycling&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;menu-internal&quot; href=&quot;#tab-6&quot;&gt;Regulators/Policy Makers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;div id=&quot;tab-1&quot;&gt;
		&lt;h2 class=&quot;highlighted&quot;&gt;Production&lt;/h2&gt;

		&lt;h3&gt;Key Stakeholders&lt;/h3&gt;

		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Farmers&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Ranchers&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Aquaculture&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Plantations/Greenhouses&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Community Gardens&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Transporters&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Retail (grocers, restaurants, vendors, etc.)&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Opportunities Highlighted by Stakeholders&lt;/h3&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;Feed people with wholesome, excess food and recovering/recycling inedible portions.&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;For crops that are not harvested, due to cost or other constraints, but are wholesome for human or animal consumption, explore partnerships and opportunities with secondary markets, feed operations, or non-profit/volunteer groups to reduce or eliminate cost, transport, and/or labor barriers.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;For produce that is harvested/collected and safe to eat, but may not be marketable due to visual or size defects, develop strategies and infrastructure for utilization.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;For produce, byproducts, and other food materials that are inedible or unsafe for human or animal consumption and on-site composting is unavailable, assess the potential to partner with commercial composters or anaerobic digesters.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;For livestock and aquaculture operations, establish relationships with local growers as well as food manufacturers (e.g., breweries) and retailers (e.g., grocers, restaurants, vendors, cafeterias, food banks) to use wasted food, as allowed under federal and state law, as a feed stock.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;For produce and meat products, work with downstream users (retailers, manufacturers, consumers/food banks) to determine if slight changes in processing or packaging can help increase utilization of a food product or lengthen its viability.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Demonstrated Practices&lt;span class=&quot;disclaimer&quot;&gt;The following links exit the site &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

		&lt;table&gt;&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;Demonstrated Practices in Production&lt;/th&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;“Ugly” produce markets for off-spec/off-grade fruits and vegetables. See: &lt;a href=&quot;http://foodtank.com/news/2016/03/imperfect-teaming-up-with-whole-foods-market-to-sell-ugly-produce&quot;&gt;Food Tank and Whole Foods example&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Breweries spent grain to feed operations. See: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.brewersassociation.org/attachments/0001/1529/Sustainability_Manual_Solid_waste.pdf&quot;&gt;Brewers Solid Waste Reduction Manual &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;CropMobster platform, which provides a digital marketplace to connect producers, retailers, local businesses, donation centers, and others. See: &lt;a href=&quot;http://sfbay.cropmobster.com/&quot;&gt;CropMobster example&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Use off-spec peaches to create salsa. See: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.campbellsoupcompany.com/newsroom/news/2013/11/21/just-peachy-salsa/&quot;&gt; Peach Salsa example&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Community gardens donating excess food. See: &lt;a href=&quot;http://ampleharvest.org/&quot;&gt;Ample Harvest&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Philadelphia’s University City District food recycling program donating compost to community gardens. See: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.philabundance.org/university-city-food-recycling-project-brings-together-amtrak-epa-philabundance/&quot;&gt;Philabundance &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Farmers fighting hunger using gleaning programs. See: &lt;a href=&quot;http://blogs.usda.gov/2015/04/03/farmers-help-fight-food-waste-by-donating-wholesome-food/#more-57554&quot;&gt;New York State Farmer and City Harvest&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Actions Suggested by Stakeholders&lt;/h3&gt;

		&lt;table&gt;&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;Actions Suggested by Stakeholders in Production&lt;/th&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Develop relationships with volunteer organizations to establish gleaning opportunities. See: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.usda.gov/documents/usda_gleaning_toolkit.pdf&quot;&gt;USDA’s toolkit&lt;/a&gt; for suggestions and resources.&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Connect communities of food producers, users, and recovery/recycling operations through mobile technologies.&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Develop plans for off-spec produce (e.g., trimming, farmers markets) and explore donation opportunities.&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Optimize distribution networks to reduce transportation and storage cost.&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Work with downstream businesses to increase utilization and longevity of food products.&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;For animal feed operations, seek opportunities to use recovered/excess food.&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;For community gardens and growing operations, use locally produced compost.&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

	&lt;div id=&quot;tab-2&quot;&gt;
		&lt;h2 class=&quot;highlighted&quot;&gt;Manufacturing&lt;/h2&gt;

		&lt;h3&gt;Key Stakeholders&lt;/h3&gt;

		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Food Manufacturers&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Food Processors&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Transporters&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Opportunities Highlighted by Stakeholders&lt;/h3&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;Decrease the amount of food waste due to known ambiguity in date labeling and assess current processes to determine areas for increased efficiency and recovery.&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;For manufacturing processes, refine standard procedures to avoid loss and seek to replicate efficiency practices. Create a new mindset to treat excess and off-spec food as a resource.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;For final products, ensure clear labeling and packaging for preservation and longevity. Establish a “quality trumps quantity” ethos.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;For unavoidable excess or off-spec products, establish donation networks for feeding people and animals.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;For transportation and storage issues, seek out local options for excess food products (donation centers) and build supply chains, including local chains that optimize storage and reduce waste at every stage of the chain.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;For outreach programs aimed at consumers, provide clear messaging around date labeling and leverage technology and communication platforms to enhance consumer knowledge about food preservation and safety.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Demonstrated Practices&lt;span class=&quot;disclaimer&quot;&gt;The following links exit the site &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

		&lt;table&gt;&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;In processing:&lt;/th&gt;
					&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;In unavoidable excess or off spec products:&lt;/th&gt;
					&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;In outreach&lt;/th&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Change practices to make sure consecutive product runs are compatible with each other. See: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.conagrafoods.com/news-room/news-ConAgra-Foods-Conserves-97-Million-Gallons-of-Water--Optimizes-Packaging-to-Save-15-Million-Pounds-of-Material--and-Eliminates-58-700-Tons-Waste-2024707&quot;&gt;Blended Pudding&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Partner with local farms to create product from off spec produce and excess food from manufacturing process. See: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thefruitcycle.com/&quot;&gt;Fruit Cycle example &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Share a suggested practices guide. See: Food Waste Reduction Alliance’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.foodwastealliance.org/wp-content/uploads/2015/11/FINAL_FWRAToolkit_15.pdf&quot;&gt;Best Practices Guide&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Use manufacturing by-products first when developing new product ideas or seasonal items (fruit leather, beef jerky). See: Food Waste Reduction Alliance’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.foodwastealliance.org/wp-content/uploads/2015/11/FINAL_FWRAToolkit_15.pdf&quot;&gt;Best Practices Guide&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Use technology to make food storage easier and avoid spoilage. See: &lt;a href=&quot;http://blogs.usda.gov/2015/04/02/new-usda-foodkeeper-app-your-new-tool-for-smart-food-storage/&quot;&gt;FoodKeeper App&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Food Waste Reduction Alliance convening an industry effort to address date labeling in April 2016.&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Actions Suggested by Stakeholders&lt;/h3&gt;

		&lt;table&gt;&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;In products:&lt;/th&gt;
					&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;In unavoidable excess or off-spec products:&lt;/th&gt;
					&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;In outreach:&lt;/th&gt;
					&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;Miscellaneous:&lt;/th&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Work within the company and other manufacturers to ensure that labeling is clear when a printed product date relates to freshness/taste versus an actual, health and safety issue.&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Assess viability of excess or off-spec food products.&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Compile and share best practices.&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;In processing, &lt;a href=&quot;/sustainable-management-food/tools-assessing-wasted-food&quot;&gt;conduct a waste audit&lt;/a&gt; to identify where the largest quantity of wasted food is coming from in your process.&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Work to ensure consistency and standardization of terms – &lt;a href=&quot;http://blogs.harvard.edu/foodpolicyinitiative/files/2013/09/dating-game-IB.pdf&quot;&gt;what does “use by,” or “sell by” mean?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.feedingamerica.org/&quot;&gt;Work with donation centers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt; to ensure that the wholesome, nutritious food goes to feeding hungry people or work with local farms to ensure that the food can feed animals.&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Produce or work with other companies to create outreach materials, such as apps that consumers can use in their home or while shopping to understand how to read and use date labels.&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;In transportation, assess buying practices and improve storage to avoid food loss before manufacture.&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Create packaging that extends shelf life of products or preserves freshness longer (e.g. vacuum sealed meat).&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Analyze and choose packaging to create less wasted food (e.g. Tetra Paks versus glass jars).&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

	&lt;div id=&quot;tab-3&quot;&gt;
		&lt;h2 class=&quot;highlighted&quot;&gt;Retail/Food Services&lt;/h2&gt;

		&lt;h3&gt;Key Stakeholders&lt;/h3&gt;

		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Grocers&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Vendors&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Restaurants&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Cafeterias&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Food Pantries/Food Banks&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Transporters&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Opportunities Highlighted by Stakeholders &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;Employ programs that build awareness to increase food donations and recovery, better track food inputs and outputs to optimize waste prevention and create efficient management practices, such as the following:&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Capture excess food through expanded networks at the local and/or regional level (e.g., new local partners).&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Improve donation practices by establishing clear guidelines and/or policies for employees.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Better track the scope and size of food waste generation by creating standard procedures for measurement.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Reduce operating costs associated with food waste by employing efficiency standards and performance standards to improve inventory and cold supply chain management.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Increase program viability by engaging customers through outreach and marketing campaigns.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Demonstrated Practices&lt;span class=&quot;disclaimer&quot;&gt;The following links exit the site &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

		&lt;table&gt;&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;Holistic&lt;/th&gt;
					&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;Source Reduction&lt;/th&gt;
					&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;Excess Food to People&lt;/th&gt;
					&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;Feed to Animals&lt;/th&gt;
					&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;Digestion and Composting of Scraps&lt;/th&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.refed.com/&quot;&gt;ReFED developed a national economic study: Rethinking Food Waste through Economics and Data: A Roadmap to Reduce U.S. Food Waste by 20 Percent&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
					&lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt;Smart purchasing, staff training and other prep waste reduction controls. See: &lt;a href=&quot;http://serdc.org/resources/Documents/&#039;15%20Food%20Recovery%20Summit/Presentations/Cook%20-%20Processing%20of%20Commercial%20and%20Institutional%20Food%20Discards.pdf&quot;&gt;Sodexo&lt;/a&gt; example&lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt;Establish and institutionalize donation protocols. See: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.serdc.org/resources/Documents/&#039;15%20Food%20Recovery%20Summit/Presentations/Brunson%20-%20Processing%20of%20Commercial%20and%20Institutional%20Food%20Discards.pdf&quot;&gt;Publix example&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href=&quot;http://fortune.com/2016/03/22/starbucks-foodshare-donate-unsold-food/&quot;&gt;Starbucks example &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt;Work with local farms to sell or donate scraps/byproducts to animals. See: &lt;a href=&quot;http://serdc.org/resources/Documents/&#039;15%20Food%20Recovery%20Summit/Presentations/Chastain_Food%20Recovery%20Suummit_Nov%202015.pdf&quot;&gt;Spent grain to cows&lt;/a&gt; example&lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt;Commercial/Institutional Collection Partnerships. See: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.serdc.org/resources/Documents/&#039;15%20Food%20Recovery%20Summit/Presentations/Dangerfield,%20Jones,%20Koeckeritz%20%20Successful%20Commercial%20Institutional%20Parnerships.pdf&quot;&gt;College of Charleston&lt;/a&gt; example, &lt;a href=&quot;http://serdc.org/resources/Documents/&#039;15%20Food%20Recovery%20Summit/Presentations/Jonjevic%20-%20Successful%20.pdf&quot;&gt;Burtons Grill&lt;/a&gt; example&lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wri.org/our-work/project/food-loss-waste-protocol&quot;&gt;World Resources Institute&lt;/a&gt; (WRI) and a large group of stakeholders has developed and will release an accounting and reporting standard for quantifying food and associated inedible parts removed from the food supply chain on June 6, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;
					&lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt;Trayless dining, taste tests, portion size reduction and other incentives for plate waste reduction. See: &lt;a href=&quot;/sites/production/files/2015-08/documents/reducing_wasted_food_pkg_tool.pdf&quot;&gt;University of Maine at Farmington&lt;/a&gt; example; &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.epa.gov/blog/2015/11/food-for-thought-haskell-indian-nations-university-conducts-food-waste-audits/&quot;&gt;Haskell Indians Nations University example &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;p&gt;Utilize Peer-to-Peer matching software that links potential donators with food banks. See: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.meansdatabase.com/&quot;&gt;MEANS Database example&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
					&lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt;Source separation and collection of food scraps. See: &lt;a href=&quot;/sustainable-management-food/about-2015-food-recovery-challenge-award-winners&quot;&gt;Pearl City High School&lt;/a&gt; example&lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;p&gt;Waste audits/measurement and tracking. See: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.serdc.org/resources/Documents/&#039;15%20Food%20Recovery%20Summit/Presentations/Shakman%20-%20Business%20of%20Food%20Recovery_v6.pdf&quot;&gt;LeanPath&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/sustainable-management-food/tools-assessing-wasted-food#packaging&quot;&gt;EPA’s Reducing Wasted Food &amp;amp; Packaging Toolkit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
					&lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;p&gt;Offer haul-out service to catering or other off site service clients. See: &lt;a href=&quot;/sustainable-management-food/about-2015-food-recovery-challenge-award-winners&quot;&gt;Serendipity Catering&lt;/a&gt; example&lt;/p&gt;
					&lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt;Retain food recovery service to ensure donation of excess catered and other food. &lt;a href=&quot;http://foodshift.net/events/big-win-airbnb-hires-food-shift-manage-recovery/&quot;&gt;See: Convention&lt;/a&gt; example&lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Require sustainable food management and closed loop systems in dining service requests for proposals. See: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.biocycle.net/2012/04/25/serving-up-sustainable-food-service-options/http:/www.biocycle.net/2012/04/25/serving-up-sustainable-food-service-options/&quot;&gt;various universities and dining service providers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt;Utilize legal and policy tools to maximize food donations. See: &lt;a href=&quot;http://recyclingworksma.com/donate/&quot;&gt;Massachusetts&#039; RecyclingWorks Comprehensive Donation Guidelines and Harvard&#039;s Food Law and Policy Clinic Fact Sheets&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Consumer/guest campaigns and other awareness raising activities. See: &lt;a href=&quot;http://dining.ucdavis.edu/documents/LoveFoodHateWasteWasteAuditFA12Report_001.pdf&quot;&gt;UC Davis Love Food example&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ivaluefood.com/&quot;&gt;I Value Food&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.foodprotect.org/guides-documents/comprehensive-guidance-for-food-recovery-programs/&quot;&gt;Comprehensive Guidance for Food Recovery Programs &lt;/a&gt;from Conference for Food Protection&lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;p&gt;Sports venues and concessionaires across the country are moving toward environmentally preferable food service to help build a healthier and more sustainable food program. &lt;a href=&quot;http://greensportsalliance.org/resources/ChampionsofGameDayFoodReport.pdf&quot;&gt;Find resources on the Green Sports Alliance website.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
					&lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt;To learn more about new tax incentives for businesses that donate food (as of Dec. 2015), see Harvard’s Food Law and Policy Clinic’s, University of Arkansas&#039;, and Food Recovery Project’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.chlpi.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/Food-Donation-Fed-Tax-Guide-for-Pub-2.pdf&quot;&gt;Tax Deduction for Food Donation: a legal guide&lt;/a&gt; (see Disclaimer of Endorsement statement above)&lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Actions Suggested by Stakeholders&lt;/h3&gt;

		&lt;table&gt;&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;Actions Suggested by Stakeholders in Retail/Food Services:&lt;/th&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Provide successful model programs, example policies and guidelines to share with others in your sector.&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Implement pilot programs and expand successful efforts.&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Capture data on food donation levels, quantity of waste, and reasons for waste within retailer’s inventory management systems to better inform forecasting.&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Use available resources and tools to measure and track the amount, type of, and the source of the food and packaging waste. See: &lt;a href=&quot;/sustainable-management-food/resources-assessing-wasted-food&quot;&gt;Resources for Assessing Wasted Food&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;If contracting with a food service provider, include provisions to drive food recovery at every level of the hierarchy (e.g. inventory control from source reduction, excess food to people, etc.)&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Support value-added processing of imperfect produce, surplus product and byproducts (i.e. work with suppliers/marketing orders and federal grading standards to allow more variance in grades and eliminate any restrictions of sale).&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Partner with other industries to leverage more weight in driving markets (i.e., compost development).&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Join &lt;a href=&quot;/sustainable-management-food/food-recovery-challenge-frc&quot;&gt;EPA’s Food Recovery Challenge&lt;/a&gt; to benchmark progress toward waste reduction goals and get recognition for more sustainable food management.&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Improve practices to ensure wholesome, nutritious, excess food gets to people (e.g., develop institutional protocols, allocate infrastructure, and partner with food recovery service to consistently pick up food).&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Develop on-site solutions where feasible (e.g., shared fridge approach for employees/students, redistribute excess food to students in need on site, in-vessel composting options for institutional food services).&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Provide incentives for guest/client food waste prevention.&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Educate guests/clients on ways they can help prevent waste at retail/food service establishments.&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Develop industry-wide standardized measurement methodology to track food waste and a mechanism to aggregate and disseminate information gathered.&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

	&lt;div id=&quot;tab-4&quot;&gt;
		&lt;h2 class=&quot;highlighted&quot;&gt;Consumers and Donation&lt;/h2&gt;

		&lt;h3&gt;Key Stakeholders&lt;/h3&gt;

		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Individual Consumers or Groups&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Soup Kitchens&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Food Banks&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Schools/Institutions&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Faith-Based Organizations&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Non-profit/Advocacy Organizations&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Opportunities Highlighted by Stakeholders&lt;/h3&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;Reduce wasted food by tailoring purchase and preparation practices and providing the public with clear information about the wholesomeness of food as well as the importance of food stewardship.&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;Opportunities for Individuals:&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Reduce wasted food due to spoilage through behavior change:
				&lt;ul style=&quot;list-style-type:circle&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;Tailor purchases around meal planning;&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;Reduce plate waste by preparing meals according to recommended serving sizes; and&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;Conduct frequent pantry and refrigerator checks (i.e., shop your refrigerator first).&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Participate in residential, community or home compost projects where available.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Opportunities for Groups:&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Provide education and outreach for targeted audiences with clear, consistent definitions and messaging.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Educate households on proper food storage focusing on fresh produce.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Provide information to clients, customers, and the public about date labeling and food safety as well as tips on recipes and storage to maximize food usage.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Improve training and training tools for those working and volunteering at donation centers (e.g., food safety, handling and storage, quality of products, applicable guidelines).&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Explore opportunities to recover (animal feed) or recycle (compost, industrial uses) food waste.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Demonstrated Practices&lt;span class=&quot;disclaimer&quot;&gt;The following links exit the site &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

		&lt;table&gt;&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;Demonstrated Practices for Consumers and Donation&lt;/th&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;NRDC/Ad Council launch a national &lt;a href=&quot;http://adcouncil.org/Our-Campaigns/Family-Community/Reducing-Food-Waste&quot;&gt;public service campaign&lt;/a&gt; to reduce wasted food. See: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.savethefood.com/&quot;&gt;Save The Food&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Mobile technologies for consumers. See: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fsis.usda.gov/wps/portal/fsis/topics/food-safety-education/featured-campaign&quot;&gt;FoodKeeper App&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Public awareness campaign. See: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.unep.org/NEWSCENTRE/default.aspx?DocumentId=2702&amp;amp;ArticleId=9377&quot;&gt;2013 Think Eat Save Campaign&lt;/a&gt; (FAO &amp;amp; UNEP)&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Recipes to reduce food waste. See: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nrdc.org/food/wastefreekitchen&quot;&gt;Waste Free Kitchen Handbook&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;EPA’s tips for consumers to reduce food waste. See: &lt;a href=&quot;/recycle/reducing-wasted-food-home#planning&quot;&gt;Reducing Wasted Food at Home&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Nashville Food Project and NRDC &amp;amp; Zero Waste Pilot. See: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.tennessean.com/story/life/2015/12/04/cutting-food-waste-helps-solve-hunger-problem/76626138/&quot;&gt;Tennessean article&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Faith-based organization work on gleaning. See: &lt;a href=&quot;http://endhunger.org/&quot;&gt;Society of St. Andrew&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;See UDSA’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.serdc.org/resources/Documents/&#039;15%20Food%20Recovery%20Summit/Presentations/Nguyen%20-%20Campaigns%20to%20Engage%20Consumers.pdf&quot;&gt;Helping Students to Eat Healthier &amp;amp; Reduce Wasted Food&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;See EPA’s &lt;a href=&quot;/sustainable-management-food/food-too-good-waste-implementation-guide-and-toolkit&quot;&gt;Food: Too Good To Waste Implementation Guide and Toolkit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;See Sustainable America’s awareness and education tool: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ivaluefood.com&quot;&gt;I Value Food&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;NRDC/Ad Council launched a national &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.serdc.org/resources/Documents/&#039;15%20Food%20Recovery%20Summit/Presentations/Hill-Campaigns%20to%20Engage%20Consumers.pdf&quot;&gt;public service campaign&lt;/a&gt; to reduce wasted food.&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;The American Chemistry Council is investigating the role of food packaging to reduce food loss and waste at the household level, and potentially throughout the food system.&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Actions Suggested by Stakeholders&lt;span class=&quot;disclaimer&quot;&gt;The following links exit the site &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

		&lt;table&gt;&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;For Individuals:&lt;/th&gt;
					&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;For Groups:&lt;/th&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Create new routines before going grocery shopping such as “shopping your refrigerator first” and meal mapping to tailor your grocery list.&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;For foodbanks distributing items nearing past their prime, provide clients simple and nutritious recipes that help lengthen the viability of the food and that are also easily portioned.&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Prior to freezing proteins (e.g., meat, seafood) or other perishable items portion and store them based on serving sizes. See: USDA’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.choosemyplate.gov/&quot;&gt;Choose My Plate&lt;/a&gt; for easy to use tools to plan meals, improve your diet and reduce wasted food.&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Target specific groups to amplify messages (e.g., faith organizations, millennials).&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Tailor recipes and meals to best use food nearing their prime. See: Love Food Hate Waste &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lovefoodhatewaste.com/&quot;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lovefoodhatewaste.com/content/download-our-love-food-hate-waste-app-free&quot;&gt;app&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Create rescue organization network to combine efforts and share information on best practices, networks, safety protocols/procedures. See examples like the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mygfsi.com/schemes-certification/overview.html&quot;&gt;Global Food Safety Initiative&lt;/a&gt; for cold chain management.&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;For perishable food or prepared foods (e.g., leftovers, takeout, store prepared items) as well as other items in your pantry, use resources like the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.foodsafety.gov/keep/foodkeeperapp/&quot;&gt;FoodKeeper app&lt;/a&gt; for guidelines on how long items keep under certain conditions (e.g., frozen, refrigerated, dry storage).&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Share fleet resources, analyze routes and combine stops where possible.&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;To learn more about new tax incentives for businesses that donate food (as of Dec. 2015), see Harvard’s Food Law and Policy Clinic’s, University of Arkansas&#039;, and Food Recovery Project’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.chlpi.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/Food-Donation-Fed-Tax-Guide-for-Pub-2.pdf&quot;&gt;Tax Deduction for Food Donation: a legal guide&lt;/a&gt; (see Disclaimer of Endorsement statement above).&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

	&lt;div id=&quot;tab-5&quot;&gt;
		&lt;h2 class=&quot;highlighted&quot;&gt;Recovery/Recycling&lt;/h2&gt;

		&lt;h3&gt;Key Stakeholders&lt;/h3&gt;

		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Composters&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Energy Recovery/Anaerobic Digestion&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Industrial Uses&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Transporters&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Animal Feed Operators&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Opportunities Highlighted by Stakeholders&lt;/h3&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;Bolster and improve recovery and recycling operations by creating partnerships that reduce business expenses, improve education and outreach, and create new markets.&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;Opportunities for Recovery Operations:&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;For animal feed operations, increase the usage of food waste and food byproducts, as allowable under federal, state and local law.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Publicize food recovery programs to recognize partnering businesses and organizations.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Reduce transportation cost by developing co-ops, partnerships or other relationships that reduce or distribute cost among several operations/organizations.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Opportunities for Recycling Operations:&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Develop partnerships and collaborations within the local area to optimize operations and build capacity.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;To maintain the viability of your operation, develop well researched business and operational practices. Make sure to fully account for siting, available technologies, training of staff, potential feedstocks and customers, nuisance issues (e.g., odor), community support, scalability of operations, applicable laws, and other key factors.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Build and maintain the support of the surrounding community to the operations.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Develop strategies to control feedstock contamination as well as other common physical (moisture) or chemical issues (pH) typical of composting or digestion operations.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Create opportunities by developing clear messages on benefits of food recovery and recycling.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Demonstrated Practices&lt;span class=&quot;disclaimer&quot;&gt;The following links exit the site &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

		&lt;table&gt;&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;Demonstrated Practices for Recovery/Recycling&lt;/th&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Successful pilot programs with Charleston County Schools (now 48 schools) and the College of Charleston (expanded to all dining facilities and small service counters). See: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wastefwd.com/&quot;&gt;Food Waste Disposal example&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Animal feed operation. See: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.serdc.org/resources/Documents/&#039;15%20Food%20Recovery%20Summit/Presentations/Hedrick%20-%20Role%20of%20Animal%20Feeding.pdf&quot;&gt;Organix Recycling example&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;See U.S. Compost Council’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.serdc.org/resources/Documents/&#039;15%20Food%20Recovery%20Summit/Presentations/Rattie%20-%20Compost%20and%20Digestate%20End%20Use.pdf&quot;&gt;Seal of Testing Assurance&lt;/a&gt; program.&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Commercial composting training videos. See: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0BMkgamqRjE&quot;&gt;SMART Recycling teams up with Low Country Local First&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Technologies to locate local composting operations. See: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.findacomposter.com/&quot;&gt;Find A Composter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Sustainable Packaging Coalition (SPC) is creating an on-package label that is clear and consistent on what to do with the package. See: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.serdc.org/resources/Documents/&#039;15%20Food%20Recovery%20Summit/Presentations/Goodrich%20-%20Grassroots%20Based%20Initiatives.pdf&quot;&gt;How2Compost Label&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Actions Suggested by Stakeholders&lt;/h3&gt;

		&lt;table&gt;&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;For Recovery Operations&lt;/th&gt;
					&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;For Recycling Operations&lt;/th&gt;
					&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;For Recovery and Recycling Operations&lt;/th&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Reach out to local businesses (e.g., grocery stores, caters, restaurants, brewers) and organizations (e.g., food banks, school cafeterias, soup kitchens) to establish formal programs with clear guidelines on acceptable sources/types of discarded/excess food.&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Continue to create toolkits and foster research to overcome common operational issues such as contamination of feedstock, odor, chemical issues (pH), physical issues (moisture level).&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Work with other recovery operations as well as local organic waste haulers to determine mutually beneficial arrangements to reduce transportation costs and other operational expenses.&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Create local media campaigns/recognition events to bolster existing partnerships and build public support.&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Create and share public education tools that can be used to inform surrounding residents of an organics recovery or recycling operation and other key stakeholders.&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Develop and share training protocols and programs for employees.&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

	&lt;div id=&quot;tab-6&quot;&gt;
		&lt;h2 class=&quot;highlighted&quot;&gt;Regulators/Policy Makers&lt;/h2&gt;

		&lt;h3&gt;Key Stakeholders&lt;/h3&gt;

		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Federal Government&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Local Government&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;StateGovernment&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Tribal Government&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Non-governmental Organizations&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Opportunities Highlighted by Stakeholders&lt;/h3&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;Promote the reduction of food loss and waste through policies, guidance and other tools that will strengthen communities and reduce the associated environmental, social, and economic impacts.&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;Federal:&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;To get a better understanding of the size and impacts of food loss and waste, help standardize measurement and data analysis tools.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Foster private and public collaboration to reduce food loss and waste and find new opportunities within local communities and regions.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;To increase food donation and recovery/recycling, provide clarity on laws and regulations related to food safety, food donations, and organic recycling and recovery operations.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Help to create and deliver effective and consistent messaging to the public about the importance of food stewardship and the need to address food loss and waste.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Provide grants to help secondary resellers expand to lower-income neighborhoods and eradicate food deserts.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Create opportunities to recognize leaders in private and public sectors taking action to reduce food loss and waste.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Convene meetings with stakeholders to improve the state of the food system and help craft new strategies to address food loss and waste.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Establish clear goals and strategic plans to achieve the 2030 FLW reduction goal.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Stake/Tribal/Local:&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Assist and support private and public collaborations to reduce food loss and waste.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;To increase food donation and recovery/recycling, provide clarity and consistency on regulations related to food safety, food donations, and organics recycling and recovery operations.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Work with community and local business leaders to develop messaging to the public on the importance of reducing wasted food and the need to address food loss and waste in your jurisdiction.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Create opportunities to recognize leaders in the private and public sectors taking action to reduce food loss and waste.&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;Convene meetings with stakeholders to improve the state of the industry and help craft new strategies to address food loss and waste.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Demonstrated Practices&lt;span class=&quot;disclaimer&quot;&gt;The following links exit the site &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

		&lt;table&gt;&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;Federal Laws:&lt;/th&gt;
					&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;Federal Efforts:&lt;/th&gt;
					&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;Federal Resources and Tools&lt;/th&gt;
					&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;State, Local, and Tribal Efforts&lt;/th&gt;
					&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;State, Local, and Tribal Resources and Tools&lt;/th&gt;
					&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;International Efforts&lt;/th&gt;
					&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;Non-governmental Organization Tools&lt;/th&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gpo.gov/fdsys/pkg/PLAW-104publ210/pdf/PLAW-104publ210.pdf&quot;&gt;Bill Emerson Good Samaritan Food Donation Act-&lt;/a&gt; was created to encourage the donation of food and grocery products to qualified nonprofit organizations and provides liability protection to food donors. Under this Act, as long as the donor has not acted with negligence or intentional misconduct, the company is not liable for damage incurred as the result of illness.&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;See EPA’s &lt;a href=&quot;/sustainable-management-food&quot;&gt;Sustainable Management of Food&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/sustainable-management-food/food-recovery-challenge-frc&quot;&gt;Food Recovery Challenge&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;/communityhealth/foodsteward&quot;&gt;Food Steward’s Pledge&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;See FDA’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fda.gov/Food/ResourcesForYou/Consumers/ucm197835.htm&quot;&gt;Surplus, Salvaged, and Donated Foods: Safety Tips&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Compost and organic recycling regulations. See State of South Carolina’s experience with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.serdc.org/resources/Documents/&#039;15%20Food%20Recovery%20Summit/Presentations/White%20-%20Regulations%20and%20Optimizing%20Food%20Recovery.pdf&quot;&gt;Compost Regulations&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;See &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.co.washington.or.us/hhs/swr/recycleatwork/upload/food-donation-flyer-2_2014.pdf&quot;&gt;Food Donation Guide for Washington County Oregon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;United Nations, Food and Agriculture Organization. See: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fao.org/food-loss-and-food-waste/en/&quot;&gt;Food Loss and Food Waste Program&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wri.org/our-work/project/food-loss-waste-protocol&quot;&gt;World Resources Institute&lt;/a&gt; (WRI) will develop a global accounting and reporting standard for quantifying food and associated inedible parts removed from the food supply chain.&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;For tax law related food donations, see the recently passed FY2016 Omnibus which expanded and made permanent certain tax deductions for donated food. For a discussion of the changes see &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.chlpi.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/12/Food-Donation-Fed-Tax-Guide-for-Pub-2.pdf&quot;&gt;Harvard’s Center for Health Law &amp;amp; Policy Innovation&lt;/a&gt; or read the &lt;a href=&quot;http://docs.house.gov/billsthisweek/20151214/121515.250_xml.pdf&quot;&gt;bill&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;See USDA’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.choosemyplate.gov/lets-talk-trash&quot;&gt;Choose My Plate&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;See EPA’s &lt;a href=&quot;/sustainable-management-food/food-too-good-waste-implementation-guide-and-toolkit&quot;&gt;Food: Too Good to Waste Implementation Guide and Toolkit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;State of Massachusetts efforts to reduce organics from MSW landfills. See their &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.serdc.org/resources/Documents/&#039;15%20Food%20Recovery%20Summit/Presentations/Fischer%20-%20Regulations%20and%20Optimizing%20Food%20Recovery.pdf&quot;&gt;commercial organics waste ban presentation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt;See the State of Massachusetts Economic Impact Analysis for their Commercial Food Waste Ban &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.mass.gov/eea/docs/dep/recycle/priorities/orgecon-study.pdf&quot;&gt;http://www.mass.gov/eea/docs/dep/recycle/priorities/orgecon-study.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;See &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wri.org/our-work/project/food-loss-waste-protocol&quot;&gt;Food Loss and Waste Measurement Protocol&lt;/a&gt;; &lt;a href=&quot;https://champions123.org/&quot;&gt;12.3 Champions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.refed.com/&quot;&gt;ReFED: Rethinking Food Waste through Economics and Data: A Roadmap to Reduce U.S. Food Waste by 20 Percent&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gpo.gov/fdsys/pkg/BILLS-110s2420enr/pdf/BILLS-110s2420enr.pdf&quot;&gt;U.S. Federal Food Donation Act of 2008&lt;/a&gt; specifies procurement contract language encouraging federal agencies and contractors of federal agencies to donate excess wholesome food to eligible nonprofit organizations to feed food-insecure people in the United States.&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;See EPA’s and USDA’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.usda.gov/oce/foodwaste/&quot;&gt;U.S. Food Waste Challenge&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;See EPA’s &lt;a href=&quot;/sustainable-management-food/tools-assessing-wasted-food&quot;&gt;Sustainable Management of Food Tools&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt;
						

						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Massachusetts Department of Environmental Protection’s industry assistance program for food waste. See: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.recyclingworksma.com&quot;&gt;RecyclingWorks Food Waste&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt;
						
					&lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Will host or help sponsor 2030 FLW reduction goal meetings and summits. Host/co-host one event annually with key stakeholders to discuss progress.&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;See EPA’s &lt;a href=&quot;/recycle/composting-home&quot;&gt;Composting at Home Basics; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/sustainable-management-food/types-composting-and-understanding-process&quot;&gt;Types of Compost and Understanding the Process &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Howard County, Maryland’s residential curbside collection of organics. See their experience with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.serdc.org/resources/Documents/&#039;15%20Food%20Recovery%20Summit/Presentations/Evans%20-%20Recovering%20Food%20from%20Residential%20Sources.pdf&quot;&gt;residential organics program&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Is initiating a wide range of programs to help make reducing food loss and waste the first-best option for farmers, businesses, organizations and consumers.&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;See EPA’s &lt;a href=&quot;/transforming-waste-tool&quot;&gt;Managing and Transforming Waste Streams-A Tool for Communities&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;See City of Calgary, Canada and their &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.serdc.org/resources/Documents/&#039;15%20Food%20Recovery%20Summit/Presentations/Bitz%20-%20Recovering%20Food%20From%20Residential%20Sources.pdf&quot;&gt;Green Cart Composing Pilot&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;See &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.usda.gov/oce/foodwaste/usda_commitments.html&quot;&gt;USDA’s Commitments&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;See Eastern Band of the Cherokee Indians’ &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fao.org/nr/sustainability/food-loss-and-waste/database/projects-detail/en/c/135015/&quot;&gt;Premier Food Waste Compost example&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Ongoing work with the World Resource Institute to develop a standard measuring protocol.&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt;
						
					&lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Actions as Suggested by Stakeholders&lt;/h3&gt;

		&lt;table&gt;&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;Federal&lt;/th&gt;
					&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt;State, Tribal, and Local&lt;/th&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Convene stakeholders including private sector, NGOs, agriculture, academia, government, and other relevant sectors and federal government.&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Meet with local food producers, retailers, transports, food banks, food advocacy groups (NGOs), faith leaders, and food recovery/recycling operations (e.g., composters, biogas producers), to identify local issues and opportunities surrounding food loss and waste.&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Help develop and make available a standard measurement tool.&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Where feasible and prudent, explore tailoring of regulations and policies to safely promote FLW reduction and recovery programs.&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Institute a process for documenting progress on the 2030 FLW reduction goal.&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Where available, explore funding FLW reduction community pilot programs as well as FLW recovery/recycling infrastructure investments.&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Where available, provide funding opportunities to help spur development of new FLW reduction programs and infrastructure.&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Provide technical assistance to donation and food recovery operations.&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;
						&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Support and promote pilot projects with potential to scale up.&lt;/li&gt;
						&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
					&lt;td&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
				&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 26 Apr 2016 21:17:49 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>carcari</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">147703 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>United States 2030 Food Loss and Waste Reduction Goal </title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/sustainable-management-food/united-states-2030-food-loss-and-waste-reduction-goal</link>
    <description>&lt;div class=&quot;box multi related-info right&quot;&gt;
	&lt;h2 class=&quot;pane-title&quot;&gt;Helpful Links&lt;/h2&gt;

	&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/sustainable-management-food/food-recovery-challenge-frc&quot;&gt;Food Recovery Challenge&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/communityhealth/foodsteward&quot;&gt;Food Steward&#039;s Pledge&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.usda.gov/oce/foodwaste/join.htm&quot;&gt;U.S. Food Waste Challenge&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/recycle/reducing-wasted-food-home&quot;&gt;Reducing Wasted Food at Home&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;In the United States, EPA estimates that more food reaches landfills and incinerators than any other single material in our everyday trash, about 21 percent of the waste stream. Reducing food waste will help the United States address climate change, as 20 percent of total U.S. methane emissions come from landfills. By keeping wholesome and nutritious food in our communities and out of our landfills, we can help address the 42 million Americans that live in food insecure households.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On this page:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#goal&quot;&gt;U.S. 2030 Food Loss and Waste Reduction Goal&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#measure&quot;&gt;Measuring the Success of the Goal&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#epa action&quot;&gt;How Does EPA Plan to Take Action on the Goal?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#you action&quot;&gt;How Can You Take Action?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;goal&quot; id=&quot;goal&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;U.S. 2030 Food Loss and Waste Reduction Goal&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On September 16, 2015, in alignment with &lt;a href=&quot;https://sustainabledevelopment.un.org/sdg12&quot;&gt;Target 12.3 of the UN Sustainable Development Goals&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot; class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt; the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.usda.gov/oce/foodwaste/#&quot;&gt;United States Department of Agriculture (USDA)&lt;/a&gt; and EPA announced the first ever &lt;a href=&quot;/newsreleases/epa-and-usda-join-private-sector-charitable-organizations-set-nations-first-goals&quot;&gt;domestic goal to reduce food loss and waste by half by the year 2030&lt;/a&gt;. By taking action on the U.S. 2030 Food Loss and Waste Reduction goal (2030 FLW reduction goal), the United States can help feed the hungry, save money for families and businesses and protect the environment. Led by USDA and EPA, the federal government is seeking to work with communities, organizations and businesses along with our partners in state, tribal and local government to reduce food loss and waste by 50 percent over the next 15 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;measure&quot; id=&quot;measure&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Measuring the Success of the Goal&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To measure and describe progress against the goal, the following two different, but equally important, baselines were chosen for the 2030 FLW reduction goal:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;For food waste in the United States, EPA’s “&lt;a href=&quot;/smm/advancing-sustainable-materials-management-facts-and-figures-report&quot;&gt;Advancing Sustainable Materials Management: Facts and Figures&lt;/a&gt;” provides an estimate of the amount of food going to landfills from residences, commercial establishments (e.g. grocery stores and restaurants), and institutional sources (e.g. school cafeterias). Preconsumer food generated during the manufacturing and packaging of food products is not included in EPA&#039;s food waste estimates. Using the available data, 2010 was selected as a baseline at 218.9 pounds of food waste per person sent for disposal. The 2030 FLW reduction goal aims to reduce food waste going to landfills by 50 percent to 109.4 pounds per person.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;For food loss in the United States, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ers.usda.gov/&quot;&gt;USDA’s Economic Research Service&lt;/a&gt; has estimated the amount of available food supply that went uneaten at the retail and consumer levels. In the baseline year of 2010, food loss was 31 percent of the food supply, equaling 133 billion pounds and an estimated value of $161.6 billion. The 2030 FLW reduction goal aims to cut food loss at the retail and consumer level in half, by approximately 66 billion pounds.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Over the next 15 years, we hope to see 50 percent reductions in both baseline measurements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;epa action&quot; id=&quot;epa action&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;How Does EPA Plan to Take Action on the Goal?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working with USDA and partners in the states and tribes, EPA plans to secure action on the 2030 FLW reduction goal by working with leaders in the food system (e.g., private, government, nonprofit, academia, faith) to promote action and bring more successful interventions and tools to advance the sustainable management of food.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA launched a &lt;a href=&quot;/sustainable-management-food/call-action-stakeholders-united-states-food-loss-waste-2030-reduction&quot;&gt;Call to Action by Stakeholders&lt;/a&gt; page, which identifies current opportunities and challenges in reducing food loss and waste in the United States. EPA will continue to help facilitate discussion by co-hosting summits where leaders in various sectors can exchange ideas and identify needed actions, provide leadership and technical assistance, conduct outreach and share information, develop new tools, and celebrate the successes of stakeholders. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;you action&quot; id=&quot;you action&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;How Can You Take Action?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone can take action to reduce food loss and waste in the United States, whether you are an individual, a business, a school, or a non-profit, community or faith-based organization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Individuals: &lt;/strong&gt;If you are an individual, &lt;a href=&quot;/recycle/reducing-wasted-food-home&quot;&gt;learn how to reduce wasted food at home&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Businesses and Organizations: &lt;/strong&gt;If you are a business or organization, join our &lt;a href=&quot;/sustainable-management-food/food-recovery-challenge-frc&quot;&gt;Food Recovery Challenge&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.usda.gov/oce/foodwaste/join.htm&quot;&gt;U.S. Food Waste Challenge&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Faith Organizations: &lt;/strong&gt;If you are a faith organization, take our &lt;a href=&quot;/communityhealth/foodsteward&quot;&gt;Food Steward&#039;s Pledge&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;All&lt;/strong&gt;: See the opportunities, demonstrated practices, and actions suggested by stakeholders in our &lt;a href=&quot;/sustainable-management-food/call-action-stakeholders-united-states-food-loss-waste-2030-reduction&quot;&gt;Call to Action&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 14 Apr 2016 16:46:54 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>DSulliva</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">142883 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  </channel>
</rss>

<!-- Page cached by Boost @ 2017-01-25 16:28:07, expires @ 2017-01-26 04:28:07, lifetime 12 hours -->