<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?><rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.epa.gov/feed/61829/rss.xml" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/" xmlns:og="http://ogp.me/ns#" xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#" xmlns:sioc="http://rdfs.org/sioc/ns#" xmlns:sioct="http://rdfs.org/sioc/types#" xmlns:skos="http://www.w3.org/2004/02/skos/core#" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#">
  <channel>
    <title>EPA in Illinois</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/feed/61829/rss.xml</link>
    <description>Updated EPA in Illinois content from the US Environmental Protection Agency</description>
    <language>en</language>
     <atom:link href="https://www.epa.gov/feed/61829/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      <item>
    <title>ACTION MEMORANDUM - Pillsbury Mills LLC Removal Site, Springfield, Sangamon County, Illinois (Site ID #C5BW)</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/il/action-memorandum-pillsbury-mills-llc-removal-site-springfield-sangamon-county-illinois-site-id</link>
    <description>&lt;div class=&quot;box multi related-info right&quot;&gt;
	&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/il/pillsbury-mills-llc-removal-site&quot;&gt;Pillsbury Mills LLC Removal Site&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ACTION MEMORANDUM - Request for Approval and Funding for a Time Critical Removal Action at the Pillsbury Mills LLC Removal Site, Springfield, Sangamon County, Illinois (Site ID #C5BW)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-339521&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-12/documents/pillsbury_am_final_scanned_0.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=13611094&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;ACTION MEMORANDUM - Request for Approval and Funding for a Time Critical Removal Action at the Pillsbury Mills LLC Removal Site (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(92 pp, 14 MB, 
  Sept. 2016)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Mon, 19 Dec 2016 16:46:31 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>josterme</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">167479 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>U.S. EPA Prepares for Cleanup in January: Pillsbury Mills LLC Removal Site Fact Sheet</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/il/us-epa-prepares-cleanup-january-pillsbury-mills-llc-removal-site-fact-sheet</link>
    <description>&lt;div class=&quot;box multi related-info right&quot;&gt;
	&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/il/pillsbury-mills-llc-removal-site&quot;&gt;Pillsbury Mills LLC Removal Site&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;U.S. EPA Prepares for Cleanup in January: Pillsbury Mills LLC Removal Site Fact Sheet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-341193&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-12/documents/pillsbury-mills-removal-fact-sheet-201612.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=552553&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;U.S. EPA Prepares for Cleanup in January: Pillsbury Mills LLC Removal Site Fact Sheet (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(2 pp, 553 K, 
  December 2016)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Mon, 19 Dec 2016 15:53:51 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>ypina</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">167475 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Pilsen Area Soils Past Site Updates</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/il/pilsen-area-soils-past-site-updates</link>
    <description>&lt;h2&gt; &lt;b&gt;September 2016 Update&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;box multi related-info right&quot;&gt;
	&lt;h2 class=&quot;pane-title&quot;&gt;Additional Information&lt;/h2&gt;

	&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/il/environmental-issues-chicagos-little-village-pilsen-neighborhoods&quot;&gt;Environmental Issues in Chicago&#039;s Little Village/Pilsen Neighborhood&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/il/pilsen-area-soil-site&quot;&gt;Pilsen Area Soil Site&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Sept. 22, 2016, EPA ordered H. Kramer &amp;amp; Co. to take immediate action to remove lead-contaminated soil from at least 54 residential yards in Chicago’s Pilsen neighborhood. H. Kramer has up to 30 days to comply with EPA’s unilateral administrative order and begin the cleanups. (See &lt;a href=&quot;http://semspub.epa.gov/src/document/05/931068&quot;&gt;Unilateral Administrative Order for Pilsen Soil Operable Unit 2 Residential Site&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To date, EPA has done lead testing at 58 Pilsen residences in a 25-acre area bounded by West 18th Place to the north, an alley between South Allport Street and South Racine Avenue to the east, West 21st Street to the south, and South Loomis Street to the west. Results from EPA tests in the spring of this year at 34 properties show that 30 have lead concentrations above the Agency’s 400 ppm action level for lead in surface soil. EPA has begun notifying residents of their test results. In 2013, EPA had notified Pilsen residents that test results at 24 of 25 properties showed lead concentrations above the action level. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2013 results prompted EPA to initiate a robust community involvement and information program to warn Pilsen residents about lead risks and advise them on how to avoid exposure to lead. EPA also negotiated a December 2015 legal agreement with H. Kramer requiring the company to expand lead testing to the rest of the area. EPA is seeking access to another 57 residences in the area to continue lead soil testing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt; &lt;b&gt;July 2016 Update&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://semspub.epa.gov/src/document/05/931061&quot;&gt;Operable Unit 1 (OU1)&lt;/a&gt;: EPA oversaw the removal by BNSF contractors of tracks and ties along the railway spur.  EPA also oversaw the excavation and disposal of lead-contaminated soil from the railroad spur and alley by H. Kramer contractors. Work was completed in Areas 1-2 and 4-10, which have been covered with either a compacted gravel cap or asphalt. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next steps: EPA will continue to work with the city of Chicago to address any concerns in portions of soil adjacent to Area 2.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://semspub.epa.gov/src/document/05/931062&quot;&gt;Operable Unit 2 (OU2)&lt;/a&gt;: Earlier this year EPA reached out to owners of 130 properties by mail, phone, and in person in an effort to gain access for soil sampling. Between a 2013 round of sampling and another one this year, EPA has sampled or has overseen the sampling of over 50 properties. There are a number of properties in OU2 that have been determined to have permanent covers with no exposure to bare soil. EPA continues to work with the city of Chicago and community organizations to identify and reach out to property owners about this project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; Next steps: Under the Administrative Settlement Agreement and Order on Consent for Removal Action, EPA and H. Kramer will review the data from samples collected this year. Once the sampling analysis report is finalized, EPA will continue working with H. Kramer and the city of Chicago to determine next steps in addressing lead concerns in OU2. Owners whose property was sampled this year should be getting their result letters later this summer.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


</description>
     <pubDate>Mon, 19 Dec 2016 15:28:21 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>josterme</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">167469 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Pillsbury Mills LLC Removal Site</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/il/pillsbury-mills-llc-removal-site</link>
    <description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;small&gt;On this page&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#site-update&quot;&gt;Site Update&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#documents&quot;&gt;Site Description&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#background&quot;&gt;Site Background&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#cleanup&quot;&gt;Documents&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;site-update&quot; name=&quot;site-update&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;December 2016 Update&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name=&quot;Text17&quot; id=&quot;Text17&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Beginning in January 2017, U.S. EPA plans to remove and properly dispose of asbestos-containing waste and hazardous substances.  This will stop the ongoing release of asbestos into the environment and protect the health of local residents.   U.S. EPA will also take measures to keep any asbestos-contaminated dust from blowing off-site. The air will be monitored to ensure the asbestos is under control. Security will also be provided around the clock to prevent trespassing.  The cleanup is scheduled to be completed in about five months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;documents&quot; name=&quot;documents&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Site Description&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Pillsbury Mills LLC removal site is located at 1525 E. Phillips St., Springfield, IL.  The site is a former food processing facility on about 18 acres of land.  At one point, it consisted of 26 structures including warehouses, office buildings, grain-mixing buildings, and grain storage silos. It is located in a residential and light industrial area next to rail lines. Vacant for about 10 years, Pillsbury Mills is surrounded by a fence, however, there is evidence of trespassing. &lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg left view-mode-medium caption&quot; style=&quot;width:448px;&quot;&gt;&lt;a
    href=&quot;/sites/production/files/2016-12/pillsbury.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img height=&quot;298&quot; width=&quot;448&quot; class=&quot;left media-element file-medium left&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/medium/public/2016-12/pillsbury.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; title=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;figcaption&quot;&gt;The Pillsbury Mills facility as it looks today.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;background&quot; name=&quot;background&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Site Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Illinois EPA referred Pillsbury Mills to U.S. EPA for an assessment and possible cleanup in March 2016. Prior to that, Illinois EPA referred the matter to the Illinois Attorney General’s Office. That office filed a complaint against the owner and others for asbestos-related violations. The owner/operator was required to secure the site and hire an asbestos professional to design a cleanup plan. Although steps were taken, including the removal of a small amount of asbestos-containing material outside the fence line, an acceptable cleanup plan was never submitted and a cleanup was never started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, Illinois EPA and the city of Springfield continue to monitor the site for improper activities and are trying to compel the owner to provide better security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;cleanup&quot; name=&quot;cleanup&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;indented&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/il/us-epa-prepares-cleanup-january-pillsbury-mills-llc-removal-site-fact-sheet&quot;&gt;U.S. EPA Prepares for Cleanup in January: Pillsbury Mills LLC Removal Site Fact Sheet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://semspub.epa.gov/src/collection/05/AR64846&quot;&gt;Technical and Legal Documents&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 07 Dec 2016 19:37:43 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>josterme</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">166601 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Wedron Groundwater Site Frequently Asked Questions 2013</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/il/wedron-groundwater-site-frequently-asked-questions-2013</link>
    <description>&lt;div class=&quot;box multi related-info right&quot;&gt;
	&lt;h2 class=&quot;pane-title&quot;&gt;Related Information&lt;/h2&gt;

	&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/il/wedron-groundwater-site-wedron-illinois&quot;&gt;Wedron Groundwater Site, Wedron, Illinois&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://semspub.epa.gov/src/collection/05/SC30194&quot;&gt;Superfund Records Collections for Wedron Groundwater Contamination&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Wedron Groundwater Site Frequently Asked Questions prepared in 2013&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. How many wells has EPA sampled? How many homes have wells that exceed the Maximum Contaminant Level for benzene?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA has tested 43 private wells in Wedron. Seven exceed the Maximum Contaminant Level, or MCL, for benzene of 5 parts per billion, while two were just below that level.  We are providing bottled water for these nine homes, and have installed temporary whole-house treatment units.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. What does EPA plan to do to help people with contaminated wells?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From our &lt;a href=&quot;https://semspub.epa.gov/src/document/05/446464&quot;&gt;November 16, 2012, Action Memo (PDF)&lt;/a&gt; (26pp, 13MB):&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;First,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; we will continue to provide bottled water to residents with contaminated wells until we put an alternative water source in place. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Second,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; we will continue to provide temporary whole-house treatment units until we choose a long-term option.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Third,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; we will evaluate three options:&lt;br /&gt;
	Option 1 – install whole-house treatment units that remove volatile organic compounds, or VOCs. We will maintain those units for one year, and then property owners must maintain them.&lt;br /&gt;
	Option 2 – drill a shared semi-private deep well that is double-cased to prevent contamination.&lt;br /&gt;
	Option 3 – tie affected homes into new semi-private deep wells outside the ground-water plume area. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Fourth,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; we will put one of these three options in place.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Fifth,&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; if we connect homes to new semi-private deep wells, we will close the contaminated wells according to state and local well abandonment procedures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. Who pays for maintenance?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Property owners would be responsible for maintenance of whole-house treatment units after one year. If EPA connects residences to a new semi-private deep well, they should create a legal agreement that covers maintenance issues and fees.  They should consider paying into an association fund to maintain the well, the pump and the water main, as well as to pay for sampling the well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. How long will it be before the EPA provides an alternative water supply to homes with well water contamination?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once any required legal agreements are done, we expect to complete the project in 90-120 days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5. Can there be legal problems among the residents connected to a shared well?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes.  So we recommend residents create a legal agreement to handle maintenance and set up ways to resolve disagreements. This should be done before we install the shared well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;6. Will it make a difference to other non-contaminated wells if a new well is built for the nine affected homes?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We may find contaminated drinking water in the future at additional homes close to the plume, so we’re evaluating what to do if that happens.  Our November 16, 2012 Action Memo says we intend to cover the cost of additional ground-water sampling and provide alternative water supply to as many as 10 additional homes if needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;7. If there is a possibility more homes may have their wells contaminated, couldn’t EPA provide more homes – besides the nine mentioned – access to a new communal well?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have funds to provide alternative water only to residents with wells that show contamination above or near the MCL. We’re evaluating what we might do to provide an alternative water supply to residents whose wells become contaminated in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;8. After the nine affected homes get an alternative water supply, will EPA test the water in those wells and in the rest of the community?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA has sampled the whole-house filters to make sure they are working properly, and results show they are. If the semi-private well is installed, we will sample the well on installation and for the first year.  The residents will be responsible for annual sampling after that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;9. How does benzene affect plumbing, water heaters and water softeners?  If my well water has benzene, will I need to replace my home’s plumbing and water heater?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We installed carbon filter units in homes with contaminated wells.  Granular carbon in combination with packed tower aeration has proven effective for removing benzene from water to below the MCL. Each homeowner will have to decide for themselves whether to replace any plumbing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;10. How is the carbon in whole-house treatment units disposed of? Is it considered hazardous waste?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once they have been used, some carbon filters may require hazardous waste handling and disposal.  We have reviewed carbon filter handling and disposal requirements with residents who have treatment units.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;11. What happened before when there were contaminated wells in Wedron?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wedron has a history of contamination in drinking water dating back to 1982. The Illinois Environmental Protection Agency and the Illinois Department of Public Health did an investigation from 1982-1985 and determined that seven private wells and a well at the former Martin Marietta Corp. facility were contaminated with VOCs and high levels of benzene.  In 1985, the Illinois Commerce Commission installed two new semi-private deep wells on the former Martin Marietta property near the existing Wedron Silica technical center, and seven residences were hooked up to the wells.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;12. Are there any problems with the wells installed in 1985?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neither of the wells installed in 1985 are contaminated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;13. What is the cause of the contamination? Will EPA address the cause?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In July and August 2012, EPA and Illinois EPA conducted an investigation to find possible sources of contamination and define the extent of the ground-water contamination plume.  We found several possible sources but there may be more. Current and former owners and operators of Wedron businesses may be responsible, including gas stations, fueling operations, farm supply businesses, laboratories, sand mining operations and railroad transport. We are still working to have the responsible parties conduct additional investigation on their properties to make sure we find all possible sources of the contamination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;14. How deep is the benzene plume? What area does it cover? Is it moving?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our July 2012 investigation found high benzene levels in soil samples above the first layer of sandstone, which is commonly found at 20-23 feet below the surface.  We found contamination in some wells drilled 140 feet or less in the plume area. Wells 180 feet deep or deeper have not shown contamination.  We will oversee a voluntary ground-water study by Fairmount Minerals Ltd. to gather additional information.  We have maps showing the plume and have shown the &lt;a href=&quot;/region5/cleanup/wedron/pdfs/wedron-maps.pdf&quot;&gt;maps (PDF)&lt;/a&gt; (9pp, 3MB) at public meetings.  The plume can move as a result of pumping, and depending on the elevation of the bedrock and ground water.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;15. Are there other environmental concerns in Wedron?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of its investigation, EPA will do samples for vapor intrusion of soil gas outside Wedron homes. If warranted, we will also check for vapor intrusion under basement concrete slabs, in crawl spaces and inside homes. (See &lt;a href=&quot;https://semspub.epa.gov/src/document/05/918995&quot;&gt;EPA’s Vapor Intrusion fact sheet&lt;/a&gt; (2pp 156KB)) During the 1982-1985 investigation, Illinois EPA and Illinois DPH found soil vapors on the former Martin Marietta scale house property, now owned by Wedron Silica Co.  We found VOC contamination in soil during the 2012 study on the right-of-way adjacent to the Hoxsey property and on property owned by the railroad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;16. How can wells that draw water from the same aquifer show different levels of benzene?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many factors can cause different benzene levels at wells that draw from the same aquifer, including the well casing, the depth and what geologic formation the well is drawing water from. Shallow wells within the plume generally are showing contamination while deeper wells are not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;17. Why doesn’t EPA use federal funds to clean up the ground water now?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our policy is to follow “the polluter pays” model for cleaning up contamination, and we will follow that model to secure funding for cleaning up the contamination in Wedron.  Also, sites that only have petroleum product contamination do not qualify for certain types of long-term cleanup funding under the Superfund program.  What we’ve found so far shows the contamination came from petroleum products, so we’re looking to other regulatory authorities – such as the Safe Drinking Water Act – to secure funding from potentially responsible parties and ultimately put a long-term solution in place.  We are still investigating possible contamination from non-petroleum products.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;18. What is EPA doing to clean up the contamination?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of our work is short-term:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Installing whole-house treatment units in homes with well contamination and possibly connecting those homes to new semi-private deep wells.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Conducting vapor intrusion studies.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Working with Illinois EPA on additional soil investigation on the Hoxsey property.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Overseeing Fairmount Minerals Ltd.’s voluntary ground-water study.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;While other actions are long-term:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Identifying long-term solutions to provide alternative water to all Wedron residents.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Identifying all parties with potential responsibility for the contamination.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Working to secure funding from responsible parties so we can ultimately put a long-term solution in place.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
     <pubDate>Mon, 07 Nov 2016 21:28:52 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>josterme</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">164793 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Site Updates Wedron Groundwater Site</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/il/site-updates-wedron-groundwater-site</link>
    <description>&lt;h2&gt;September 2016&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Site Status Change -&lt;/strong&gt;  The Wedron site is being switched between EPA programs. It has been determined the major source of pollution is leakage from petroleum underground storage tanks. Under existing regulations, the Superfund Petroleum Exclusion applies and EPA Superfund can no longer expend additional resources at the site. The Superfund Petroleum Exclusion requires Superfund to defer to the EPA Resource Conservation and Recovery Act (RCRA) Underground Storage Tank program to address petroleum releases. Corrective action activities going forward will be handled under EPA’s RCRA Underground Storage Tank program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;October 2015&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;box multi related-info right&quot;&gt;
	&lt;h2 class=&quot;pane-title&quot;&gt;Related Information&lt;/h2&gt;

	&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/il/wedron-groundwater-site-wedron-illinois&quot;&gt;Wedron Groundwater Site, Wedron, Illinois&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://semspub.epa.gov/src/collection/05/SC30194&quot;&gt;Superfund Records Collection for Wedron Groundwater Contamination&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another investigation report is final - In late Fall 2015, U.S. EPA accepted as final the &lt;a href=&quot;https://semspub.epa.gov/src/document/05/930375&quot;&gt;Illinois Railway Site Investigation Final Report (PDF)&lt;/a&gt; (510pp, 12MB) (Oct. 2015) that includes results from an investigation of locations on Illinois Railway property where underground storage tanks were located.  This report and two other reports contain the results of investigations into possible sources of soil and groundwater contamination in Wedron:    &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://semspub.epa.gov/src/document/05/930379&quot;&gt;Wedron Site Investigation Technical Memorandum by BP (PDF)&lt;/a&gt; (3506pp, 80.9MB) (May 2014) (for the former BP Terminal Property on the NE edge of Wedron)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;“&lt;a href=&quot;/node/163871&quot;&gt;Wedron Silica Company - Final Report – Administrative Order on Consent&lt;/a&gt;” (for their properties to the east and south of the residential area of Wedron)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Illinois Railway &lt;/strong&gt;also submitted a separate Site Investigation Completion Report to the Illinois EPA’s Leaking Underground Storage Tank (Leaking UST) Program in late Fall 2015 for investigations of former UST areas on Illinois Railway property.  The Illinois EPA is reviewing the report.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wedron Silica Company implemented an Illinois EPA-approved Leaking UST Corrective Action Plan&lt;/strong&gt; during Summer of 2015 to address contamination identified at a former UST area on its property.  The Company must submit an amended Corrective Action Completion Report to the Illinois EPA this Winter to address some additional work needed in the area.  This contamination has been thoroughly defined and is not considered to be one of the potential source areas for the Wedron residential area groundwater contamination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Private Well Sampling Completed&lt;/strong&gt; – The Wedron private water well sampling event (29 wells total) was completed in Summer 2015.  The Illinois Department of Public Health sent a letter with laboratory results and interpretations to each property owner and/or occupant household to explain their specific results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Likely Sources of Groundwater Contamination Identified&lt;/strong&gt; – An October 2014 U.S. EPA memorandum &lt;a href=&quot;https://semspub.epa.gov/src/document/05/930378&quot;&gt;Evaluation of the Wedron Groundwater Site’s Identified BTEX Source Areas and Their Relationship to BTEX Groundwater Contamination in the Village of Wedron, Illinois (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;  (3pp, 1.25MB) (Oct. 2014)  an April 2014 &lt;a href=&quot;https://semspub.epa.gov/src/document/05/930380&quot;&gt;Data Evaluation Report (PDF)&lt;/a&gt; (232pp, 24MB) and a July 2015 &lt;a href=&quot;https://semspub.epa.gov/src/document/05/930376&quot;&gt;Report Review - Data Evaluation Report, Wedron, LaSalle County, Illinois (PDF)&lt;/a&gt; (1p, 122K)  identify likely sources of the groundwater contamination in Wedron and are available under the technical documents tab on this webpage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next steps - Illinois EPA is working to have a contractor perform a late Fall/early Winter 2015 pumping test of the lower aquifer in Wedron to better understand hydraulic properties of that aquifer.  The pumping test results will help identify whether the uncontaminated lower aquifer will support additional new private wells and whether it is isolated from the upper aquifer.  With that critical  information in hand, the agencies will work to identify remediation technologies and cleanup options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;August 2015&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;July/August 2015&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Private Well Sampling&lt;/strong&gt; – The Wedron private water well sampling event (29 wells total) is scheduled for August.  Illinois EPA will assist the LaSalle Co. Health Dept. in collecting the water samples and the Illinois EPA’s laboratory will analyze them.  The laboratory results should be available within a month.  The Illinois Department of Public Health will interpret the results and prepare a letter for each property owner and/or occupant household to explain their specific results.&lt;br /&gt;
	  &lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;New technical documents available – &lt;/strong&gt;An October 2014 U.S. EPA memorandum &lt;a href=&quot;https://semspub.epa.gov/src/document/05/930378&quot;&gt;Evaluation of the Wedron Groundwater Site’s Identified BTEX Source Areas and Their Relationship to BTEX Groundwater Contamination in the Village of Wedron, Illinois (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;  (3pp, 1.25MB) (Oct. 2014)  an April 2014 &lt;a href=&quot;https://semspub.epa.gov/src/document/05/930380&quot;&gt;Data Evaluation Report (PDF)&lt;/a&gt; (232pp, 24MB) and a July 2015 &lt;a href=&quot;https://semspub.epa.gov/src/document/05/930376&quot;&gt;Report Review - Data Evaluation Report, Wedron, LaSalle County, Illinois (PDF)&lt;/a&gt; (1p, 122K)  identify likely sources of the groundwater contamination in Wedron and are available under the technical documents tab on this webpage. &lt;strong&gt;These documents identify likely source areas of the groundwater contamination in Wedron.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Two investigation reports are final&lt;/strong&gt; - In late winter 2015, two reports on investigations of possible sources of soil and groundwater contamination in Wedron were accepted as final by U.S. EPA and have also been added to the technical documents posted to the web page:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://semspub.epa.gov/src/document/05/930379&quot;&gt;Wedron Site Investigation Technical Memorandum by BP (PDF)&lt;/a&gt; (3506pp, 80.9MB) (May 2014) (for the former BP Terminal Property on the NE edge of Wedron)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;“&lt;a href=&quot;/node/163871&quot;&gt;Wedron Silica Company - Final Report – Administrative Order on Consent&lt;/a&gt;” (for their properties to the east and south of the residential area of Wedron)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Illinois Railway&lt;/strong&gt; submitted an updated report to U.S. EPA in May 2015, and the Agency is working with Illinois Railway to finalize it. The report includes results from an additional investigation that U.S. EPA asked Illinois Railway to perform this winter at locations on its property where underground storage tanks were located. The additional investigation was needed to fully characterize soil and groundwater contamination found during the initial investigation on Illinois Railway property.&lt;br /&gt;
	Also, Illinois Railway must submit a Site Investigation Completion Report to the Illinois EPA’s Leaking Underground Storage Tank (Leaking UST) Program for investigations of former UST areas on Illinois Railway property.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wedron Silica Company&lt;/strong&gt;’s UST cleanup plan approved &lt;strong&gt;– &lt;/strong&gt;The Illinois EPA has approved Wedron Silica Company’s Leaking UST Corrective Action Plan to address contamination identified at a former UST area on its property.  Implementation of the plan will begin during the Summer of 2015.  This contamination has been thoroughly defined and is not considered to be one of the potential source areas for the Wedron residential area groundwater contamination.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Next steps &lt;/strong&gt;- Illinois EPA is working to have a contractor perform a Fall 2015 pumping test of the lower aquifer in Wedron to better understand hydraulic properties of that aquifer.  The pumping test results will help identify whether the uncontaminated lower aquifer will support additional new private wells and whether it is isolated from the upper aquifer.  With that critical  information, the agencies will work to identify remediation technologies and cleanup options.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Air monitoring&lt;/strong&gt; – Air monitoring information collected under a U.S. EPA-approved air monitoring program for particulate matter on dust leaving Wedron Silica Company and Technisand operations in Wedron. &lt;a href=&quot;/il/air-monitoring-wedron-illinois&quot;&gt;Air Monitoring, Wedron, Ill.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;July 2015&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Private Well Sampling&lt;/strong&gt; – The Wedron private water well sampling event (29 wells total) is scheduled for August.  Illinois EPA will assist the LaSalle Co. Health Dept. in collecting the water samples and the Illinois EPA’s laboratory will analyze them.  The laboratory results should be available within a month.  The Illinois Department of Public Health will interpret the results and prepare a letter for each property owner and/or occupant household to explain their specific results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Illinois Railway&lt;/strong&gt; submitted an updated report to U.S. EPA in May 2015, and the Agency is working with Illinois Railway to finalize it. The report includes results from an additional investigation that U.S. EPA asked Illinois Railway to perform this winter at locations on its property where underground storage tanks were located. The additional investigation was needed to fully characterize soil and groundwater contamination found during the initial investigation on Illinois Railway property.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, Illinois Railway must submit a Site Investigation Completion Report to the Illinois EPA’s Leaking Underground Storage Tank (Leaking UST) Program for investigations of former UST areas on Illinois Railway property.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wedron Silica Company&lt;/strong&gt;’s UST cleanup plan approved &lt;strong&gt;– &lt;/strong&gt;The Illinois EPA has approved Wedron Silica Company’s Leaking UST Corrective Action Plan to address contamination identified at a former UST area on its property.  Implementation of the plan will begin during the Summer of 2015.  This contamination has been thoroughly defined and is not considered to be one of the potential source areas for the Wedron residential area groundwater contamination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Next steps &lt;/strong&gt;- Illinois EPA is working to have a contractor perform a Fall 2015 pumping test of the lower aquifer in Wedron to better understand hydraulic properties of that aquifer.  The pumping test results will help identify whether the uncontaminated lower aquifer will support additional new private wells and whether it is isolated from the upper aquifer.  With that critical  information, the agencies will work to identify remediation technologies and cleanup options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Air monitoring&lt;/strong&gt; – U.S. EPA has received air monitoring data for the months of February, March, and April 2015 under a U.S. EPA-approved air monitoring program for particulate matter.  The program provides data on dust leaving Wedron Silica Company and Technisand operations in Wedron.  The companies will continue to submit data to U.S. EPA each month under the approved air monitoring program until February 2016.  Data collection is being overseen by U.S. EPA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;April 2015&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Two reports are final&lt;/strong&gt; - In 2014, three reports on investigations of possible sources of soil and groundwater contamination in Wedron were submitted to EPA:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Illinois Railway&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;BP - &lt;strong&gt;accepted by EPA in late winter 2015&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Lockheed Martin, Technisand, and Wedron Silica Company - &lt;strong&gt;accepted by EPA in late winter 2015&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;llinois Railway&lt;/strong&gt; will submit an updated report to U.S. EPA. It will include results from additional investigation that EPA asked Illinois Railway to perform this winter at locations on its property where underground storage tanks were located. The additional investigation was needed to fully characterize soil and groundwater contamination found during the initial investigation on Illinois Railway property. EPA expects to work with Illinois Railway to finalize the report within the next few months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wedron Silica Company&lt;/strong&gt; also performed additional investigation on its property during the winter to further characterize contamination identified at a former UST area. Illinois EPA is reviewing the investigation results and will oversee any potential clean-up of the former UST area under its leaking underground storage tank program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Next steps &lt;/strong&gt;- U.S. EPA and Illinois EPA will consolidate all the investigation results to identify potential sources of contamination in Wedron. Then the agencies will work to identify remediation technologies and cleanup options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Well sampling&lt;/strong&gt; - U.S. EPA, LaSalle County Health Department and Illinois EPA have agreed on a sampling plan to sample private wells in Wedron until at least 2016. The LaSalle County Health Department will collect the next round of samples later this spring; Illinois EPA will analyze the samples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Illinois EPA is also working this year to have a contractor perform a pumping test of the lower aquifer in Wedron to better understand hydraulic properties of the lower aquifer to help identify whether the lower aquifer will support potential additional new wells.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Air monitoring&lt;/strong&gt; - In February 2015, Wedron Silica Company and Technisand began a U.S. EPA-approved air monitoring program for particulate matter to provide data on dust leaving the companies’ operations. The air monitoring for particulate matter will continue in Wedron for one year with U.S. EPA oversight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;November 2014&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;U.S. EPA and Illinois EPA have provided comments on reports for investigations of possible sources of soil and groundwater contamination in Wedron. Three reports were submitted to EPA:  one from Illinois Railway, one from BP, and one from Lockheed Martin, Technisand, and Wedron Silica Company.  EPA expects to work with these companies to finalize the reports in the next few months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;U.S. EPA and Illinois EPA are working together and coordinating their oversight of investigations of benzene and other volatile organic chemical contamination at the Wedron Groundwater site. Wedron Silica Company will perform additional investigation on its property in November 2014 to further characterize contamination identified at a former underground storage tank (UST) area.  U.S. EPA has also asked Illinois Railway to perform additional investigation at locations on its property where USTs were located.  These investigations are needed to fully characterize soil and groundwater contamination found during the initial investigations.  After the additional investigations are completed, the agencies will work to identify potential long-term remediation solutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;U.S. EPA also approved a work plan from Wedron Silica Company and Technisand to conduct air monitoring in Wedron for one year.  The monitoring will provide data on dust leaving the companies’ operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;August 2014&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA is reviewing reports and data submitted by BP, Illinois Railway, Lockheed Martin, Technisand, and Wedron Silica Company on their investigations of possible sources of soil and groundwater contamination in Wedron.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;BP conducted an investigation of the former Amoco bulk plant area in Wedron. The investigation consisted of sampling sub-surface soil at agreed upon locations. EPA collected split soil samples from some of the locations sampled by the BP contractors. Results from the investigation are showing little to no contamination in the area sampled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Illinois Railway (IR) conducted an investigation on a long stretch of IR&#039;s right of way property.  EPA collected split soil samples from some of the locations sampled by the IR contractors. Soil and groundwater results show multiple exceedances of Illinois TACO standards for benzene and other volatile organic chemicals (VOCs). (TACO is the Illinois EPA&#039;s method for developing remediation objectives for contaminated soil and groundwater. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.epa.state.il.us/land/taco/fact-sheet.html&quot;&gt;www.epa.state.il.us/land/taco/fact-sheet.html&lt;/a&gt;) Further review and investigation is needed to fully characterize the area and determine the extent of the contamination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;BP and Illinois Railway also conducted geophysical investigations on IR’s right of way to identify whether any additional underground storage tanks (USTs) remain on IR property where the soil and groundwater investigations occurred. Three USTs have been removed from this area since July of 2012.  The geophysical investigations did not identify any additional USTs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Soil sample results from an investigation conducted by Lockheed Martin, Technisand, and Wedron Silica Company on Wedron Silica Company and Technisand properties show some to no contamination in some areas, and multiple exceedances of Illinois TACO standards for benzene and other VOCs in an area where USTs were once located. Wedron Silica Company will install groundwater monitoring wells to determine whether the groundwater under the area with soil exceedances has been impacted.  EPA collected split soil samples from some of the areas sampled by the companies’ contractors. Further investigation is needed to fully characterize the area with soil exceedances on Wedron Silica Company property and determine the extent of contamination. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In December of 2013, the Illinois EPA determined that the Hoxsey property in Wedron should be considered a potential source of contamination.  Additional investigation is needed to fully characterize the extent of contamination at the Hoxsey property.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA and Illinois EPA are working together and coordinating their oversight of the investigations of the three likely source areas at the Wedron Groundwater site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the additional investigations to fully characterize the three likely source areas of contamination are complete, EPA and Illinois EPA will work to identify long-term remediation solutions to address Wedron&#039;s groundwater contamination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wedron Silica Company and Technisand are planning to conduct air monitoring in Wedron for one year under a soon to be approved workplan.  The companies will be ordering monitoring equipment as soon as possible after EPA approves the workplan. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;May 2014&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Water samples taken in March 2014 from the eight Wedron replacement wells that EPA installed this winter confirms that the water is safe to drink.  At the same time, EPA also tested other wells at homes that are adjacent to the groundwater plume. One of these wells showed a detection of benzene at a level close to the standards that are set by the EPA for drinking water quality. The detection in this well is not in excess of the EPA standards. This well was sampled over one year ago and did not show contamination at that time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA has communicated with the owner and the tenants to make sure that they use bottled water and do not drink from the well. EPA is working to install carbon filter units similar to the ones installed in eight Wedron wells in 2012 and 2013 before those wells were replaced because of benzene contamination. Granular activated carbon has proven effective for removing benzene from water to below the standards set by EPA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA is trying to identify sources of the groundwater contamination. To that end, EPA continues to oversee groundwater and soil investigations by BP, Illinois Railway, Lockheed Martin, Technisand, and Wedron Silica Company as agreed through Administrative Orders on Consent (AOCs) with the companies. Final reports for the investigations are expected in summer 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the groundwater and soil investigations are complete, EPA will work to identify long-term solutions to provide alternative water to Wedron residents who may become affected by the groundwater contamination.  The additional well with contamination will be included in that evaluation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA, LaSalle County Health Department and Illinois EPA have agreed on a long-term sampling plan to sample private wells in Wedron for a period of two years in order to take immediate response action to protect the public health if benzene is detected near or in excess of EPA standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;April 2014&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA collected additional water samples from the recently installed eight residential replacement wells in early April 2014. Previous sampling showed that the water is good quality. EPA expects to have the results from this second round of sampling in May 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA continues to oversee groundwater and soil investigations by BP, Illinois Railway, Lockheed Martin, Technisand, and Wedron Silica Company as agreed through Administrative Orders on Consent (AOCs) with the companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;The AOC are available in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://semspub.epa.gov/src/collection/05/SC30194&quot;&gt;Superfund Records Collections for Wedron Groundwater Contamination&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Harsh winter weather caused some delays with the investigations. Most of the soil investigation work is complete, and results from the soil investigations and the Hoxsey property investigation show there are multiple potential sources of the benzene contamination in Wedron.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA is overseeing remaining investigation work that will confirm the locations of the sources of contamination. Final reports for the investigations are expected in summer 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wedron Silica Company and Technisand are planning to perform air monitoring in Wedron for one year starting summer 2014. The air monitors will collect information on blowing sand in Wedron, and EPA will oversee the work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;December 2013&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA has completed the installation of eight private drinking water wells in Wedron to replace existing wells that had benzene contamination.  The wells were drilled into the lower New Richmond aquifer which provides potable water to many of the residents in LaSalle County.   The water from the new wells have been sampled and results show that it is good quality water. The Agency recommends that the residents with the newly installed wells upgrade their water softener in order to reduce traces of naturally occurring radium, which may appear in some of the water samples. The EPA will collect additional water samples from the new wells in March and April of 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The EPA also concluded vapor intrusion sampling in three Wedron homes this fall.  A subslab and indoor air sample were collected at each property for volatile organic compounds (VOCs).  The results showed that vapors inside the homes and under the subslab are below EPA&#039;s screening values and do not pose a health risk.  No further vapor intrusion sampling is planned at this time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Agency is overseeing groundwater and soil investigations by BP, Illinois Railway, Technisand, and Wedron Silica Company as agreed through Administrative Orders on Consent (AOCs) with the companies. An additional underground storage tank has been discovered during the initial phase of these investigations.  This makes the third tank that will have been removed since the beginning of EPA&#039;s activities in Wedron. The results of the investigations by these parties, which are expected in the Spring of 2014, should provide information on the possible sources of the benzene contamination in Wedron. The AOCs are available in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://semspub.epa.gov/src/collection/05/SC30194&quot;&gt;Superfund Records Collections for Wedron Groundwater Contamination&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Agency will conduct another round of water sampling in March 2014 at a limited number of Wedron locations on and near where the benzene plume has been located. &lt;a href=&quot;https://semspub.epa.gov/work/05/918992.pdf&quot;&gt;See map&lt;/a&gt; showing the approximate area of the groundwater contamination.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Illinois EPA has concluded field work for an investigation on the Hoxsey property to explore its role as a potential source of the groundwater contamination in Wedron.  IEPA is in the process of analyzing information it obtained during the field work in order to develop a draft report summarizing the results of that work. IEPA is coordinating this effort with U.S. EPA and is using state funds to pay for the investigation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;September 2013 &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;U.S. EPA plans to begin work this month to install individual replacement wells for eight private drinking water wells currently contaminated with benzene. The federal Agency is awaiting approvals from the LaSalle County Health Department before beginning the work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Agency also plans to install five additional monitoring wells in Wedron to further define the extent of the groundwater contamination plume and help determine sources of contamination. Based on the results of the soil gas sampling that we completed this summer, we will conduct limited vapor intrusion monitoring in 3-4 homes in coordination with ATSDR this fall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;U.S. EPA has reached agreements in principle with BP, Illinois Railway, Lockheed Martin, Technisand, and Wedron Silica Company to perform investigations in Wedron that will help the Agency identify potential sources of the contamination to the soil and groundwater. We anticipate finalizing the Administrative Orders on Consent and Work Plans in September 2013 so the investigations can begin in October 2013. The Agency is using its authority under the &lt;a href=&quot;/agriculture/lrca.html&quot;&gt;Resource Conservation and Recovery Act (RCRA)&lt;/a&gt; for these investigations. In addition, as part of an information request from the &lt;a href=&quot;/air/caa/index.html&quot;&gt;EPA under the Clean Air Act&lt;/a&gt;, Wedron Silica Company and Technisand are working with EPA to install air monitors in Wedron to study the impact of blowing sand in Wedron.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Illinois EPA is installing three monitoring wells on the Hoxsey property in September to further investigate the Hoxsey property as a potential source of the groundwater contamination. IEPA is coordinating this effort with U.S. EPA and is using state funds to pay for the investigation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The EPA has completed a &lt;a href=&quot;https://semspub.epa.gov/src/document/05/911118&quot;&gt;Community Involvement Plan&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://semspub.epa.gov/src/document/05/911118&quot;&gt; (PDF)&lt;/a&gt; (32pp, 364K) (Feb. 2014), to enhance communication between local residents and EPA as the investigation and cleanup at the site progress. EPA invites everyone to provide comments about the plan to &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:leon.heriberto@epa.gov&quot;&gt;Heriberto Leon&lt;/a&gt;, Community Involvement Coordinator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;April 2013&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last year, EPA sampled all but two of the 45 homes in Wedron. EPA is trying to get access to the remaining two properties. Nine homes tested positive for volatile organic compounds, including benzene, and these residents were offered bottled water.  In addition, EPA’s contractor installed filtration systems in these homes in February 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since last October, EPA has hosted community meetings every two months, and the most recent meeting was on April 3.  Health officials from the CDC’s Agency of Toxic Substances and Disease Registry have joined us at meetings and are a resource for residents with health concerns. The next EPA event will be an open house scheduled for early June, and it will be advertised on our website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This spring and summer EPA will continue efforts to investigate the sources of contamination and explore options for a long-term solution. These efforts include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Plans to conduct vapor intrusion sampling in homes in early May to determine whether indoor air is being impacted by the contamination.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Evaluating locations for two new semi-private deep wells that would serve the nine homes with contaminated wells.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Overseeing a groundwater study being voluntarily conducted by Fairmont Minerals this spring.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Continuing to work with Illinois EPA, which is conducting a soil investigation at the Hoxsey property in May 2013.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;July and August 2012&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In July 2012, EPA and Illinois EPA collected soil samples from 18 locations in Wedron using a special drilling rig called a geoprobe that can collect samples beneath soil surface. The results of the soil sampling also showed elevated levels of the VOCs benzene, chloroform, ethylbenzene, and xylenes. This investigation also identified several potential sources of the groundwater and soil contamination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also in July 2012, EPA, Illinois EPA and the Illinois Fire Marshal’s office oversaw the excavation and removal of an underground tank that was uncovered during a rail expansion along the Illinois Railway tracks bordering N. 2153 Road (LaSalle County 11). Illinois Railway hired a contractor to remove the liquid in the tank, clean the tank and remove the affected soil.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA oversaw an investigation conducted by Hoxsey property owners in August 2012 at the former Hoxsey gas station to determine if underground tanks or piping are still present. The investigation identified piping from the tanks on the property, but did not find tanks still underground. An additional investigation was set to be conducted by Illinois EPA at this property.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 03 Nov 2016 18:59:34 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>josterme</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">164507 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Air Monitoring Wedron, Illinois</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/il/air-monitoring-wedron-illinois</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;The following documents contain air monitoring data on for &lt;/span&gt;TEOM, PM 4 Particulate Matter and Crystalline Silica and PM 4 Crystalline Silica&lt;span&gt; from May 2015 - March 2016. The data was collected under a U.S. EPA-approved air monitoring program for particulate matter on dust leaving Wedron Silica Company and Technisand operations in Wedron. Data collection was overseen by U.S. EPA.  &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-328143&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-10/documents/air_monitoring_data_-_pm_4_crystalline_silica_data_summary_july_2015_-_march_2016.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=207586&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;PM 4 Crystalline Silica Data Summary May 2015 - March 2016 (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(11 pp, 208 K, 
  May 2015 - March 2016)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-328149&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-10/documents/pm4_particulate_matter_and_crystalline_silica_filter_data_august_2015_-_march_2016.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=3804706&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;PM4 Particulate Matter and Crystalline Silica Filter Data May 2015 - March 2016 (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(220 pp, 4 MB, 
  May 2015 - March 2016)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-328155&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-10/documents/teom_data_march_2016_-_may_2015.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=23781164&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;TEOM Data May 2015 - March 2016 (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(4725 pp, 24 MB, 
  May 2015 - March 2016)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Mon, 31 Oct 2016 14:57:47 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>josterme</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">163811 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Fact Sheet: Water Monitoring Reveals More Well Contamination</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/il/fact-sheet-water-monitoring-reveals-more-well-contamination</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;U.S. EPA, Illinois Environmental Protection Agency and the LaSalle County Health Department have been monitoring residential wells and groundwater in Wedron, Ill. In summer 2016, officials identified three private wells as having BTEX contamination. BTEX stands for petroleum-derived pollutants named benzene, toluene, ethylbenzene and xylene. The four contaminants are often found together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
	
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-327483&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-10/documents/wedron_clean_template_fact_sheet_v_10-25-16-oecedits_docxvi.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=158944&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Fact Sheet: Water Monitoring Reveals More Well Contamination (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(1 pg, 159 K, 
  Nov 2016)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 27 Oct 2016 19:37:00 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>dlambert</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">163695 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Wedron Groundwater Site in Wedron, Illinois</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/il/wedron-groundwater-site-wedron-illinois</link>
    <description>&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On this page:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Cleanup&quot;&gt;Cleanup Status&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Description&quot;&gt;Site Description&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Contaminants&quot;&gt;Contaminants at this Facility&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Communication&quot;&gt;Key Communication Documents&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Technical&quot;&gt;Key Technical Documents&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Updates&quot;&gt;Past Site Updates under Superfund&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;Cleanup&quot; name=&quot;Cleanup&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;box multi related-info right&quot;&gt;
	&lt;h2 class=&quot;pane-title&quot;&gt;Additional Site Information&lt;/h2&gt;

	&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
		&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Environmental Scientist&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;mailto:rudloff.gregory@epa.gov?subject=Wedron&quot;&gt;Greg Rudloff&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
				(rudloff.gregory@epa.gov)&lt;br /&gt;
				312-886-0455&lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Community Involvement Coordinator&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;mailto:Gonzalez.RafaelP@epa.gov?subject=wedron&quot;&gt;Rafael Gonzalez&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
				(gonzalez.rafaelp@epa.gov)&lt;br /&gt;
				312-886-0269&lt;/p&gt;

			&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://semspub.epa.gov/src/collection/05/SC30194&quot;&gt;Superfund Records Collection for Wedron Groundwater Contamination&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;li&gt;More Information from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://oaspub.epa.gov/enviro/efsystemquery.fii_retrieve?fac_search=handler_id&amp;amp;fac_value=PAD002344463&amp;amp;fac_search_type=Beginning+With&amp;amp;postal_code=&amp;amp;location_address=&amp;amp;add_search_type=Beginning+With&amp;amp;city_name=&amp;amp;county_name=&amp;amp;state_code=&amp;amp;epa_region_code=&amp;amp;naic_code_desc=&amp;amp;naic_code=&amp;amp;all_programs=YES&amp;amp;univ_search=0&amp;amp;univA=FULL_ENFORCEMENT&amp;amp;univB=LQG&amp;amp;LIBS=&amp;amp;proc_group=0&amp;amp;procname=&amp;amp;program_search=2&amp;amp;report=3&amp;amp;page_no=1&amp;amp;output_sql_switch=TRUE&amp;amp;database_type=RCRAINFO&quot;&gt;Envirofacts database&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cleanup Status - Nov. 2016&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Site Status Change -&lt;/strong&gt;  The Wedron site is being switched between EPA programs. It has been determined the major source of pollution is leakage from petroleum underground storage tanks. Under existing regulations, the Superfund Petroleum Exclusion applies and EPA Superfund can no longer expend additional resources at the site. The Superfund Petroleum Exclusion requires Superfund to defer to the EPA Resource Conservation and Recovery Act (RCRA) Underground Storage Tank program to address petroleum releases. Corrective action activities going forward will be handled under EPA’s RCRA Underground Storage Tank program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Private Well Sampling&lt;/strong&gt; – During the summer of 2016, three private wells were identified as having BTEX contamination. BTEX stands for petroleum-derived pollutants named benzene, toluene, ethylbenzene and xylene. One of the wells previously had detections, one of the wells was previously nondetect, and one of the wells was sampled for the first time. IEPA is suppling bottled water to one home that exceeded maximum contaminant levels (MCLs), and to another home below MCLs that had children present. Illinois EPA is leading the effort to get the homes being supplied with bottled water and a third home using carbon filtration, connected to a nearby deep replacement well that was installed by US EPA as part of the EPA Superfund removal action. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A recent private water well sampling event (21 wells total) took place in Wedron on Sept. 27. The LaSalle County Health Department assisted Illinois EPA in collecting the water samples, and Illinois EPA’s laboratory analyzed the samples. The Illinois Department of Public Health will interpret the results and prepare a letter for each property owner and/or occupant household to explain their specific results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wedron Monitoring Well Sampling&lt;/strong&gt; - In October 2016, Illinois EPA sampled six monitoring wells in and around Wedron and one deep well installed by EPA to identify if contamination has reached these locations. The Illinois EPA laboratory analyzed the groundwater samples. The results were nondetect for all wells. “Groundwater” is an environmental term for underground supplies of fresh water.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Investigation report status&lt;/strong&gt; – Final reports for groundwater and soil investigations by BP, Illinois Railway, Lockheed Martin, Technisand and Wedron Silica Co. have been completed and are available under &lt;a href=&quot;#Technical&quot;&gt;Key Technical Documents&lt;/a&gt;. These investigations were completed as agreed through Administrative Orders on Consent (AOCs) with the companies. Since the investigations required under the AOCs have been completed, EPA is evaluating the AOCs for termination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;LUST Investigation&lt;/strong&gt; – Illinois Railway submitted a revised Site Investigation Completion Report to Illinois EPA’s Leaking Underground Storage Tank Program in August 2016 for investigations of former UST areas on Illinois Railway property. Illinois EPA is currently reviewing the report.   &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Air monitoring&lt;/strong&gt; – Wedron Silica completed a year-long ambient air monitoring study with U.S. EPA oversight. Data were compiled to estimate the annual average concentration of crystalline silica in the ambient air at both monitoring locations – one about three miles south of the Wedron Silica facility (South Monitor) and one directly north of the facility, near Wedron Silica’s main office (North Monitor). Because there is no regulatory standard for crystalline silica concentration in ambient air, the results were compared against a health-based criteria value of 3.0 µg/m&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt; (3.0 micrograms of crystalline silica per cubic meter of air). This value, as a long-term average, is the level at which several state and local health and environmental agencies have determined that long-term exposure (on the order of years) at or above could potentially cause adverse health effects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the North Monitor, the average crystalline silica concentration, which is the arithmetic mean of all samples collected over the duration of the study, was 1.45 µg/m&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;. Approximately 37 percent of samples had crystalline silica concentrations below the level that the laboratory method is capable of detecting and measuring, which is 0.3 µg/m&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;. These “nondetects” were assigned a value of 50 percent of the detection level (0.15 µg/m&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;) for the purposes of calculating the long-term average.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the South Monitor, around 85 percent of the samples collected showed crystalline silica concentrations below the detection level. The remaining detectable-level samples were all at or below 0.69 µg/m&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The data files are available under &lt;a href=&quot;/il/air-monitoring-wedron-illinois&quot;&gt;Air Monitoring Data&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Next steps&lt;/strong&gt; – In July 2016, Illinois EPA hired a contractor to perform a pumping test of the lower aquifer in Wedron to better understand hydraulic properties of that underground water body. The pumping test results will help identify whether the uncontaminated lower aquifer will support additional new private wells and whether it is isolated from the upper aquifer. With this information in hand, Illinois EPA and EPA will work to identify remediation technologies and cleanup options. A report on the pump test results was received by IEPA on Oct. 7, 2016, and is currently under review.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/il/wedron-reports-and-documents&quot;&gt;Fact Sheet: Water Monitoring Reveals More Well Contamination&lt;/a&gt; (Nov. 2016)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;Description&quot; name=&quot;Description&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Site Description&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In April 1982, several complaints of gasoline-type odors in Wedron residents’ private well water were received at the Illinois Department of Public Health. A groundwater investigation was started by the Illinois EPA. In 2009, benzene was detected in two private wells in Wedron (town of ~47 homes) at concentrations above the MCL of 5 ppb. In 2011, IEPA and IDPH sampled private wells in Wedron and found wells contaminated with BTEX constituents. The benzene detected in private wells exceeded the MCL, with levels as high as 2,800 ppb. Samples collected confirmed the presence of chemicals found in gasoline. IEPA referred the site to EPA in 2011. In 2014, EPA installed eight replacement drinking water wells pursuant to a CERCLA removal action. The wells were drilled into a lower uncontaminated aquifer (New Richmond Aquifer).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, investigations of several possible sources of pollution beyond a former gas station were completed. No additional major sources were found. The major source of pollution seems to be leakage from petroleum underground storage tanks. Therefore, the Superfund Petroleum Exclusion applies, and Superfund can no longer expend additional resources at the site. The Superfund Petroleum Exclusion requires Superfund to defer to the Resource Conservation and Recovery Act (RCRA) Underground Storage Tank program to address petroleum releases. Corrective action activities going forward, will be addressed under the RCRA Underground Storage Tank program. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	In 2009, benzene was detected in two private wells in Wedron (town of 47 homes) at concentrations above the MCL of 5 ppb. In 2011, IEPA and IDPH sampled private wells in Wedron and found wells contaminated with BTEX constituents. The benzene detected in private wells exceeded the MCL, with levels as high as 2,800 ppb. IEPA referred the site to EPA in 2011. In 2014, EPA installed eight replacement drinking water wells pursuant to a CERCLA removal action. The wells were drilled into a lower uncontaminated aquifer (New Richmond Aquifer).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;Contaminants&quot; name=&quot;Contaminants&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contaminants at this Facility&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Major contaminants of concern are benzene, toluene, ethylbenzene, and xylene (BTEX) in groundwater.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;Communication&quot; name=&quot;Communication&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Key Communication Documents&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are some of the key communication documents. More are included in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://semspub.epa.gov/src/collection/05/SC30194&quot;&gt;Superfund Records Collection for Wedron Groundwater Contamination&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/il/fact-sheet-water-monitoring-reveals-more-well-contamination&quot;&gt;Fact Sheet: Water Monitoring Reveals More Well Contamination&lt;/a&gt; (Nov. 2016)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://semspub.epa.gov/src/document/05/911118&quot;&gt;Community Involvement Plan&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://semspub.epa.gov/src/document/05/911118&quot;&gt; (PDF)&lt;/a&gt; (32pp, 364K) (Feb. 2014) &lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://semspub.epa.gov/src/document/05/908843&quot;&gt;EPA Explores Alternative Water Source (PDF)&lt;/a&gt; (2pp, 310K) (June 2013)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://semspub.epa.gov/src/document/05/918981&quot;&gt;EPA Considers Options for Contaminated Wells (PDF)&lt;/a&gt; (2pp, 113K) (Feb. 2013)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/il/wedron-groundwater-site-frequently-asked-questions-2013&quot;&gt;Wedron FAQs prepared in 2013&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://semspub.epa.gov/src/document/05/908840&quot;&gt;EPA Looking for Pollution Source in Underground Water (PDF)&lt;/a&gt; (2pp, 265K) (Oct. 2012)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://semspub.epa.gov/src/document/05/918995&quot;&gt;What You Should Know about the Problem of Vapor Intrusion (PDF)&lt;/a&gt; (2pp, 561K) (Jan. 2012)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;Technical&quot; name=&quot;Technical&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Key Technical Documents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are some of the key technical and legal documents. More are included in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://semspub.epa.gov/src/collection/05/SC30194&quot;&gt;Superfund Records Collection for Wedron Groundwater Contamination.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://semspub.epa.gov/src/document/05/929116&quot;&gt;BTEX Screening Map (PDF)&lt;/a&gt; (1p, 614K) (Oct. 2015)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://semspub.epa.gov/src/document/05/929521&quot;&gt;Wedron Silica Company Corrective Action Completion Report Submitted to Illinois Environmental Protection Agency (PDF)&lt;/a&gt; (195pp, 14.3MB) (Aug. 2015)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://semspub.epa.gov/src/document/05/930375&quot;&gt;Illinois Railway Site Investigation Final Report (PDF)&lt;/a&gt; (510, 12MB) (Oct. 2015)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://semspub.epa.gov/src/document/05/930376&quot;&gt;Report Review - Data Evaluation Report, Wedron, LaSalle County, Illinois (PDF)&lt;/a&gt; (1p, 122K)  (April 2015)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://semspub.epa.gov/src/document/05/930377&quot;&gt;Wedron Silica Company - Final Report - Administrative Order on Consent (PDF)&lt;/a&gt; (490pp, 61MB) (Nov. 2015)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/sites/production/files/2016-10/documents/wedron_clean_template_fact_sheet_v_10-25-16-oecedits_docxvi.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=158944&quot;&gt;Site Investigation Completion Report LUST Incident #20130463 Illinois Railway Property (PDF)&lt;/a&gt; (Aug. 2015)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://semspub.epa.gov/src/document/05/930379&quot;&gt;Wedron Site Investigation Technical Memorandum by BP (PDF)&lt;/a&gt; (3506pp, 80.9MB) (May 2014)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://semspub.epa.gov/src/document/05/913498&quot;&gt;Administrative Order on Consent Docket No. RCRA-05-2013-0011 (PDF)&lt;/a&gt; (35pp, 3MB) (Sept. 2013)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://semspub.epa.gov/src/document/05/930378&quot;&gt;Evaluation of the Wedron Groundwater Site’s Identified BTEX Source Areas and Their Relationship to BTEX Groundwater Contamination in the Village of Wedron, Illinois&lt;/a&gt; (3pp, 1MB) (Oct. 2014)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://semspub.epa.gov/src/document/05/918957&quot;&gt;Site Investigation Report, Hoxsey Property (PDF)&lt;/a&gt; (298pp, 10.7MB) (Dec. 2013)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;Updates&quot; name=&quot;Updates&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Past Site Updates under Superfund&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/il/site-updates-wedron-groundwater-site&quot;&gt;Site activities from July 2012 - Oct. 2015&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;pagetop&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#main-content&quot;&gt;Top of Page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 27 Oct 2016 19:24:27 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>josterme</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">163691 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  </channel>
</rss>

<!-- Page cached by Boost @ 2017-01-25 16:30:37, expires @ 2017-01-26 04:30:37, lifetime 12 hours -->