<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?><rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.epa.gov/feed/58269/rss.xml" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/" xmlns:og="http://ogp.me/ns#" xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#" xmlns:sioc="http://rdfs.org/sioc/ns#" xmlns:sioct="http://rdfs.org/sioc/types#" xmlns:skos="http://www.w3.org/2004/02/skos/core#" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#">
  <channel>
    <title>Health Research</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/feed/58269/rss.xml</link>
    <description>Updated Health Research content from the US Environmental Protection Agency</description>
    <language>en</language>
     <atom:link href="https://www.epa.gov/feed/58269/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      <item>
    <title>Community Support Fact Sheets</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/healthresearch/community-support-fact-sheets</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;EPA develops community support tools that help citizens and decision makers take action to protect community health and promote sustainability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-326767&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-10/documents/c-port_beta_fact_sheet_mm_edits.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=479597&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;The Community modeling system for near-PORT (C-PORT) Tool (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(2 pp, 480 K)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;field field-name-field-document-description field-type-text field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    C-PORT provides a platform for air quality modeling and visualization that can inform interested users about ways that emissions from commercial ports can impact local air quality.   &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-326771&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-10/documents/c-ferst_fact_sheet_mmedits.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=161806&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;EPA’s Community-Focused Exposure and Risk Screening Tool (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(2 pp, 162 K)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;field field-name-field-document-description field-type-text field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    C-FERST is a web-based tool that provides information to help users identify environmental issues in their communities, learn about issues, and explore risk reduction options.  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 25 Oct 2016 18:08:25 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>mmcguinn</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">163411 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Asthma Research Discoveries</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/healthresearch/asthma-research-discoveries</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;A large body of research has been published in peer-reviewed journal articles by EPA and EPA-funded scientists on the link between air pollution and asthma. Highlights of recent discoveries show how research is improving our understanding of the contribution of air pollution to the health problem of asthma. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cfpub.epa.gov/si/si_lab_search_results.cfm?searchAll=asthma&amp;amp;subject=asthma&amp;amp;sortBy=revisionDate&amp;amp;showCriteria=2&quot;&gt;Full list of asthma-related publications from EPA’s Science Inventory&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Near-road air monitoring tool R-LINE&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;EPA researchers have updated its dispersion model called R-LINE (v.1.2) to better capture temporal and spatial variability of mobile source-related concentrations in the near-road environment. The modeling system provides information on exposure to traffic-related air pollutants, and model outputs are matched to the desired temporal and spatial resolution needed for the health study.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;R-Line is available to the public and can be found on the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cmascenter.org/r-line&quot;&gt;Community Modeling &amp;amp; Analysis System&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;. The site is a forum for air quality modelers and others to use R-LINE and contribute to the improvement and future development of this model.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Children’s lung development and exposure to air pollution&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Lung function development in children with and without asthma improved with declines in air pollution from 1994-2011, according to a study by the University of Southern California. Researchers found that respiratory health in children improved as air pollution decreased over each four-year study period in southern California. The study is partially funded by the Health Effects Institute (HEI), an independent research organization funded by EPA and industry partners to investigate the health effects of air pollution.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nejm.org/doi/full/10.1056/NEJMoa1414123&quot;&gt;Association of Improved Air Quality with Lung Development in Children&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;, published in the &lt;em&gt;New England Journal of Medicine&lt;/em&gt;, March 2015.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Size of particulate matter effect on asthma&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;EPA researchers have found links between the size of particulate matter and its relationship to allergic asthma. Downwind coarse particulate matter increased inflammation indicators related to asthma more than upwind coarse PM. In contrast, upwind fine PM increased indicators related to inflammation more than the downwind fine PM. This finding supports previous research showing that source as well as size of PM contribute to PM health effects.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://pubs.acs.org/doi/abs/10.1021/es506048k&quot;&gt;Differential Effects of Particulate Matter Upwind and Downwind of an Urban Freeway in an Allergic Mouse Model&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;, published in &lt;em&gt;Environmental Science and Technology&lt;/em&gt;, February 2015.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Ozone exposure and asthma in rural areas&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;EPA researchers are working to improve the ability to conduct research on the health effects of air pollution in rural areas. Rural areas are difficult to study because of the limited data from regulatory air monitoring networks, which are located in metropolitan cities. Using the Community Multiscale Air Quality (CMAQ) model, researchers have studied associations between asthma emergency department visits and short term ozone exposure.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;The results support a link between short-term ozone exposures and asthma emergency department visits and suggest that children and individuals living in counties with poorer health status are at increased risk of asthma-related visits to the emergency department following ozone exposure.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://ehp.niehs.nih.gov/1306940/&quot;&gt;Influence of Urbanicity and County Characteristics on the Association between Ozone and Asthma Emergency Department Visits in North Carolina&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;, published in &lt;em&gt;Environmental Health Perspectives&lt;/em&gt;, May 2014.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 09 Aug 2016 19:19:23 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cbooker</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">156995 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Community-LINE Source Model (C-LINE) to estimate roadway emissions</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/healthresearch/community-line-source-model-c-line-estimate-roadway-emissions</link>
    <description>&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is the Community-LINE Source Model (C-LINE)?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;C-LINE is a web-based model that estimates emissions and dispersion of toxic air pollutants for roadways in the U.S. This reduced-form air quality model can examine what-if scenarios for changes in emissions, such as traffic volume, fleet mix and vehicle speed. C-LINE accesses inputs, performs atmospheric dispersion calculations, visualizes results, provides options to manipulate input variables, and performs basic data analysis to present model results in an interpretable manner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What are the benefits of using C-LINE?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;C-LINE can identify potentially at-risk populations located near roadways and effects that changes in traffic activity may have on those populations. Currently, C-LINE is capable of modeling any region of the U.S. and can be applied to a number of community-scale applications such as assessing air quality by schools located near busy highways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Who should use C-LINE?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;C-LINE is intended to support local communities and planners to get an initial assessment of near-source air quality impacts of transportation-related sources using national-scale input databases, and reduced-form modeling approaches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How does C-LINE work?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;C-LINE computes air quality concentrations of primary mobile source pollutants using analytical version of R-LINE dispersion model. Specific emissions for each road link are calculated by combining national database information on traffic volume and fleet mix with emissions factors from EPA’s MOtor Vehicle Emission Simulator (MOVES) modeling system. Users can modify emissions for each road link by changing traffic composition, speed and/or volume. C-LINE is currently capable of modeling any region of the United States&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Download Now:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;C-LINE 2.0 can be downloaded from the Community Modeling and Analysis System (CMAS).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA instituted the CMAS website in 2001 to provide community air quality modeling support, sharing of ideas and techniques through communication, and to encourage the growth of the community. It is currently operated under contract by the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill’s Institute for the Environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cmascenter.org/c-tools/&quot;&gt;CMAS&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Related Links:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cmascenter.org/r-line/&quot;&gt;R-LINE model&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Technical Contacts:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Vlad Isakov (&lt;a href=&quot;mailto:Isakov.Vlad@epa.gov&quot;&gt;Isakov.Vlad@epa.gov&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Tim Barzyk (&lt;a href=&quot;mailto:Barzyk.Timothy@epa.gov&quot;&gt;Barzyk.Timothy@epa.gov&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 03 Nov 2015 20:56:46 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>akocer</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">124595 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Gerena School Health Impact Assessment (HIA) Final Report</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/healthresearch/gerena-school-health-impact-assessment-hia-final-report</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;This is the final report of the EPA-led Gerena Community School HIA, which aims to provide valuable health-focused information to help the City of Springfield narrow down and prioritize renovation actions at the school that best address the existing environmental conditions and reduce the potential negative health impacts to students, faculty, staff, and community members who use the facility.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-218047&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-10/documents/final_gerena_school_hia_report.updated.508compliant.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=8220006&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Gerena School Health Impact Assessment (HIA) Final Report (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(308 pp, 8 MB)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 22 Oct 2015 19:40:49 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cbooker</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">122373 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Regional Sustainable Environmental Science (RESES) to promote sustainable and healthy communities</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/healthresearch/regional-sustainable-environmental-science-reses-promote-sustainable-and-healthy</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;The Regional Sustainable Environmental Science (RESES) program focuses on forming regional research partnerships to enable effective, efficient and socially responsible solutions to commonly faced resource sustainability problems. RESES combines practical field measures with effective, long-term community involvement by using the best available tools and science to assign value to ecosystem goods and services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ecosystem goods and services are the many life-sustaining benefits we receive from nature: clean air and water, fertile soil for crop production, pollination, and flood control. Ecosystems regulate air and water quality, provide protection from storms and floods, produce food and essential material, and provide opportunities for recreation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;RESES is meant to be a flexible, evolving, broadly inclusive method to help quickly address challenging regional environmental issues. The program creates partnerships within EPA, other federal and state agencies, non-governmental organizations and communities to demonstrate case study applications to inform decision making.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, 15 RESES projects are underway across all 10 EPA regions to demonstrate the value of this type of fully collaborative community-based approach. Although these demonstration projects span a range of geographically and scientifically distinct remediation challenges, and some deal almost exclusively with how to share important environmental policy, the driving force in each case is how to gain a realistic evaluation of a shared environmental resource, whether that is a physical setting, a renewable commodity or an issue of social fairness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Current RESES Projects:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Supporting Communities using EPA Science Tools (R10)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Research and development of National Waste to Biogas Mapping Tool – Creating an Organic Resources Exchange (R9)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Real-Time Monitoring of Domestic Water Consumption in Concert with Real-Time Energy Measurement in Multifamily Housing (R8)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Development of Sustainability Tool for Tribal Housing Decision Making (R8)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Preparing Communities for Disruptive Climate Events in Southern Massachusetts (R1)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Solution-Oriented Cumulative Risk and Near-Source Air Quality Assessments in Five Communities (R2, R3, R4, R5)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Community Resilience Planning and Decision Making Framework for Coastal (R4)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;A Health Impact Assessment (HIA) in Springfield, Mass., Environmental Justice Community Elementary School to Evaluate Proposed Remediation Scenarios for Indoor Sources and Near-Roadway Transportation Exposures (R1)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Conducting an HIA in the Proctor Creek District of Atlanta, Ga., to assess the distribution of both environmental and health impacts as Green Infrastructure approaches to Community Revitalization move forward (R4)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Inland Port Community Resilience Transportation Analysis in Mississippi (R4)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Using Green Infrastructure to Address Climate Change: A Case Study in N. Birmingham, Ala. (R4)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Parking lot Strategies to Mitigate Storm Water Quality/Volume and Urban Heat Island Effect Using Trees in Green Infrastructure (R6)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Citizen Monitoring of Water Quality and Sanitation in a Rural Puerto Rico Watershed (R2)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Development and Implementation of Bioavailability Tools to Link with C-FERST, Community Involvement and Inform Community Decisions (R2, R9)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Working with Communities to Develop Practical Measures of Sustainability (R1, R2, R4, R7) &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 30 Sep 2015 18:39:29 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>akocer</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">118795 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Contact Us About Aging</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/healthresearch/forms/contact-us-about-aging</link>
    <description>&lt;div class=&quot;box right&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;box left&quot; href=&quot;/enforcement/report-environmental-violations&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Report an environmental violation&quot; src=&quot;/sites/all/themes/epa/img/badge.gif&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

	&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/enforcement/report-environmental-violations&quot;&gt;Report a Violation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

	&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;Report possible violations of environmental laws and regulations.&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Please use the form below to send us comments or questions. Be sure to include your e-mail address if you’d like a response.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Send e-mail to:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:Sykes.Kathy@epa.gov&quot;&gt;Kathy Sykes&lt;/a&gt; (Sykes.Kathy@epa.gov)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mailing Address:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Office of Research and Development&lt;br /&gt;
	1300 Pennsylvania Ave NW&lt;br /&gt;
	Mail code 8101R&lt;br /&gt;
	Washington, D.C. 20460&lt;/p&gt;




</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 22 Sep 2015 18:22:25 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cbooker</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">115891 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Aging Factsheets in  French (Français)</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/healthresearch/aging-factsheets-french-francais</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;The Aging Initiative is working to protect the environmental health of older adults through the coordination of research, prevention strategies and public education.  These are factsheets in French (Français) translation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-184499&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-08/documents/ahbe-french-2007-07.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=108879&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Age Healthier, Breathe Easier (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(2 pp, 109 K, 
  EPA-100-F-07-013)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-189705&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-09/documents/pcmp_french_100-f-09-007.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=230995&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Carbon Monoxide Poisoning Prevention (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(4 pp, 231 K, 
  EPA-100-F-09-007)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-189707&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-09/documents/deh_french_100-f-07-050.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=287742&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Diabetes and Environmental Hazards (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(4 pp, 288 K, 
  EPA-100-F-07-050)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-189711&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-09/documents/echp_french_2007_08.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=113618&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Effective Control of Household Pests (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(2 pp, 114 K, 
  EPA-100-F-07-017)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-189715&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-09/documents/ehwhh_french_2007_08.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=140635&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Environmental Hazards Weigh Heavy on the Heart (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(2 pp, 141 K, 
  EPA-100-F-07-018)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-189719&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-09/documents/heour_french_100-f-10-014.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=306861&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Health Effects of Ultraviolet Radiation (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(4 pp, 307 K, 
  EPA 100-F-10-014)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-189733&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-09/documents/itdhpfehe_french_2007.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=142765&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;It&amp;#039;s Too Darn Hot&amp;quot; - Planning for Excessive Heat Events (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(2 pp, 143 K, 
  EPA-100-F-07-019)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-189739&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-09/documents/ww_french_2006_11.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=238809&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Water Works (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(4 pp, 239 K, 
  EPA-100-F-06-013)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-189745&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-09/documents/weh_french_100-f-08-005.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=334431&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Women and Environmental Health (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(4 pp, 334 K, 
  EPA-100-F-08-005)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 09 Sep 2015 19:26:24 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cbooker</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">112091 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Aging Factsheets in Vietnamese (Tiếng Việt)</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/healthresearch/aging-factsheets-vietnamese-tieng-viet</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;The Aging Initiative is working to protect the environmental health of older adults through the coordination of research, prevention strategies and public education.  These are factsheets in Vietnamese (Tiếng Việt) translation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-184539&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-08/documents/ahbe-vietnamese-2004-1101.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=117456&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Age Healthier, Breathe Easier (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(2 pp, 117 K, 
  EPA-100-F-04-020)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-190133&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-09/documents/pcmp_vietnamese_100-f-09-009.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=400929&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Carbon Monoxide Poisoning Prevention (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(4 pp, 401 K, 
  EPA-100-F-09-009)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-190139&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-09/documents/deh_vietnam_100-f-07-029.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=2510600&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Diabetes and Environmental Hazards (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(4 pp, 3 MB, 
  EPA-100-F-07-029)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-190143&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-09/documents/echp_vietnamese_2005.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=127780&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Effective Control of Household Pests (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(2 pp, 128 K, 
  EPA-100-F-04-021)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-190145&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-09/documents/ehwhh_vietnamese_2007_04.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=3788082&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Environmental Hazards Weigh Heavy on the Heart (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(4 pp, 4 MB, 
  EPA-100-F-06-017)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-190149&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-09/documents/heour_vietnamese_100-f-10-018.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=348445&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Health Effects of Ultraviolet Radiation (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(4 pp, 348 K, 
  EPA 100-F-10-018)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-190153&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-09/documents/itdhpfehe_vietnamese_2005_09.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=709199&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;It&amp;#039;s Too Darn Hot&amp;quot; - Planning for Excessive Heat Events (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(4 pp, 709 K, 
  EPA-100-F-05-048)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-190155&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-09/documents/ww_vietnamese_2007_04.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=526614&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Water Works (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(4 pp, 527 K, 
  EPA-100-F-06-016)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-190165&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-09/documents/weh_vietnamese_100-f-08-012.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=459667&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Women and Environmental Health (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(4 pp, 460 K, 
  EPA-100-F-08-012)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 09 Sep 2015 19:24:35 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cbooker</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">112089 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Aging Factsheets in Thai | ภาษาไทย</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/healthresearch/aging-factsheets-thai-phaasaaaithy</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;The Aging Initiative is working to protect the environmental health of older adults through the coordination of research, prevention strategies and public education.  These are factsheets in Thai (ภาษาไทย) translation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-184533&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-08/documents/ahbe-thai-100-f-08-011.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=255496&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Age Healthier, Breathe Easier (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(2 pp, 255 K, 
  EPA-100-F-09-011)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-190179&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-09/documents/pcmp_thai_100-f-09-018.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=344403&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Carbon Monoxide Poisoning Prevention (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(4 pp, 344 K, 
  EPA 100-F-09-018)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-190181&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-09/documents/deh_thai_100-f-09-023.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=312091&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Diabetes and Environmental Hazards (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(4 pp, 312 K, 
  EPA-100-F-09-023)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-190187&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-09/documents/echp_thai_100-f-08-074.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=1535668&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Effective Control of Household Pests (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(2 pp, 2 MB, 
  EPA-100-F-08-074)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-190191&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-09/documents/ehwhh_thai_100-f-08-045.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=4617224&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Environmental Hazards Weigh Heavy on the Heart (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(4 pp, 5 MB, 
  EPA-100-F-08-045)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-190199&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-09/documents/itdhpfehe_thai_100-f08-075.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=2957889&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt; &amp;quot;It&amp;#039;s Too Darn Hot&amp;quot; - Planning for Excessive Heat Events (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(4 pp, 3 MB, 
  EPA-100-F-08-075)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-190205&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-09/documents/ww_thai_100-f-08-060.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=485771&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Water Works (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(4 pp, 486 K, 
  EPA-100-F-08-060)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-190211&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-09/documents/weh_thai_100-f-09-026.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=329185&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Women and Environmental Health (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(4 pp, 329 K, 
  EPA-100-F-09-026)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 09 Sep 2015 19:21:13 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cbooker</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">112083 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  </channel>
</rss>

<!-- Page cached by Boost @ 2017-01-25 18:11:28, expires @ 2017-01-26 06:11:28, lifetime 12 hours -->