<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?><rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.epa.gov/feed/61873/rss.xml" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/" xmlns:og="http://ogp.me/ns#" xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#" xmlns:sioc="http://rdfs.org/sioc/ns#" xmlns:sioct="http://rdfs.org/sioc/types#" xmlns:skos="http://www.w3.org/2004/02/skos/core#" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#">
  <channel>
    <title>EPA in Iowa</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/feed/61873/rss.xml</link>
    <description>Updated EPA in Iowa content from the US Environmental Protection Agency</description>
    <language>en</language>
     <atom:link href="https://www.epa.gov/feed/61873/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      <item>
    <title>PCE Chestnut Street Superfund Site, Atlantic, Cass County, Iowa - Fact Sheet, January 2017</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/ia/pce-chestnut-street-superfund-site-atlantic-cass-county-iowa-fact-sheet-january-2017</link>
    <description>&lt;h2 class=&quot;highlighted&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;EPA Region 7 to Host Public Availability Session&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;INTRODUCTION&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The U.S. Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) Region 7 is holding a Public Availability Session to provide information related to the PCE Chestnut Street Superfund Site in Atlantic, Iowa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The session will be held:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tuesday, Jan. 24, 2017&lt;br /&gt;
	6:00 - 7:30 p.m.&lt;br /&gt;
	Atlantic Municipal Utilities&lt;br /&gt;
	15 W. 3rd Street&lt;br /&gt;
	Atlantic, IA 50022&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA will present historical site information, discuss ongoing sampling activities, and provide insight regarding vapor mitigation units installed at the site. The presentation will also include information regarding the contaminant of concern, tetrachloroethylene (PCE), and vapor intrusion issues found at several buildings at the site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on available data, EPA has determined there is a vapor intrusion plume of PCE at the site. EPA first detected the plume in March 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA is conducting a site investigation that includes the collection of soil, groundwater, and soil gas samples to define the extent of the site-related contamination. Site-related contaminants include PCE and its degradation products, primarily trichloroethylene (TCE). EPA is assessing whether PCE and/or TCE vapors have migrated into any additional buildings within the site area. As a result, indoor air and soil vapor samples continue to be collected from inside buildings in the downtown Atlantic area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ABOUT THE CONTAMINATION&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PCE is a chlorinated hydrocarbon solvent commonly used as a dry cleaning fluid and spot remover in dry cleaning operations, and as a degreaser in manufacturing plants. The levels of PCE vapors already found in buildings at the site present a health threat due to the inhalation hazards. Therefore, EPA installed vapor mitigation systems in affected buildings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additional information regarding PCE is available &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.atsdr.cdc.gov/toxfaqs/tfacts18.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;online&lt;/a&gt;. For information regarding vapor intrusion, including vapor mitigation systems, visit &lt;a href=&quot;/sites/production/files/2015-04/documents/a_citizens_guide_to_vapor_intrusion_mitigation_.pdf&quot;&gt;EPA’s website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ADDITIONAL INFORMATION&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA assessed the ability of the public to access documents for the site through an Internet-based repository and determined that the local community has this ability. Documents for the site are available online for anyone with an Internet connection, and also at the Atlantic Public Library by internet connections. Please visit &lt;a href=&quot;https://semspub.epa.gov/src/collection/07/AR63845&quot;&gt;EPA’s website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CONTACTS&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have questions or need additional information about any aspect of the site, please contact:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pamela Houston&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	Community Engagement Specialist&lt;br /&gt;
	Enforcement Coordination Office&lt;br /&gt;
	EPA Region 7&lt;br /&gt;
	11201 Renner Boulevard&lt;br /&gt;
	Lenexa, KS 66219&lt;br /&gt;
	Toll-free: 1-800-223-0425&lt;br /&gt;
	Email: &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:houston.pamela@epa.gov&quot;&gt;houston.pamela@epa.gov&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Susan Fisher&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	On-Scene Coordinator&lt;br /&gt;
	Response and Removal, North Section&lt;br /&gt;
	Superfund Division&lt;br /&gt;
	EPA Region 7&lt;br /&gt;
	11201 Renner Boulevard&lt;br /&gt;
	Lenexa, KS 66219&lt;br /&gt;
	Phone: 816-718-4285&lt;br /&gt;
	Email: &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:fisher.susan@epa.gov&quot;&gt;fisher.susan@epa.gov&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jeff Pritchard&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	On-Scene Coordinator&lt;br /&gt;
	Response and Removal, North Section&lt;br /&gt;
	Superfund Division&lt;br /&gt;
	EPA Region 7&lt;br /&gt;
	11201 Renner Boulevard&lt;br /&gt;
	Lenexa, KS 66219&lt;br /&gt;
	Toll-free: 1-800-223-0425&lt;br /&gt;
	Email: &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:pritchard.jeffrey@epa.gov&quot;&gt;pritchard.jeffrey@epa.gov&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 24 Jan 2017 20:51:19 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>mkessler</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">169961 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>PCE Former Dry Cleaner Superfund Site, Atlantic, Cass County, Iowa - Fact Sheet, January 2017</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/ia/pce-former-dry-cleaner-superfund-site-atlantic-cass-county-iowa-fact-sheet-january-2017</link>
    <description>&lt;h2 class=&quot;highlighted&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;EPA Region 7 to Host Public Availability Session&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;INTRODUCTION&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The U.S. Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) Region 7 is holding a Public Availability Session to provide information related to the PCE Former Dry Cleaner Superfund Site in Atlantic, Iowa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The session will be held:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tuesday, Jan. 24, 2017&lt;br /&gt;
	6:00 - 7:30 p.m.&lt;br /&gt;
	Atlantic Municipal Utilities&lt;br /&gt;
	15 W. 3rd Street&lt;br /&gt;
	Atlantic, IA 50022&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA will present historical site information, and provide plans for addressing the source area and containing the groundwater contaminant plume. EPA will implement electric resistivity heating (ERH) to reduce the tetrachloroethylene (PCE) contamination at the source area. EPA will implement groundwater extraction and treatment by air stripping to prevent additional impacts to the municipal supply wells.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For additional information regarding in-situ thermal treatment, including ERH, visit &lt;a href=&quot;/remedytech/situ-thermal-treatment-chlorinated-solvents-fundamentals-and-field-applications&quot;&gt;EPA’s website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;BACKGROUND&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The site contains a groundwater plume of PCE first detected in the 1980s. EPA completed a site investigation to determine the potential source areas and trace migration pathways to define the vertical and horizontal extent of the PCE groundwater plume.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The removal action will consist of the use of ERH technology to treat contamination in the source area, which is planned to begin in early 2017 and will take approximately one year to complete. A separate Removal Action will consist of installing two groundwater extraction wells and an air stripper to remove PCE contamination from the groundwater. Construction of this system is planned to begin in mid-2017.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ABOUT THE CONTAMINANT&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PCE is a chlorinated hydrocarbon solvent commonly used in dry cleaning operations, and as a degreaser in manufacturing plants. PCE is characterized by EPA as “likely to be carcinogenic to humans” by all routes of exposure. Additional information is available &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.atsdr.cdc.gov/toxfaqs/tfacts18.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;online&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ADDITIONAL INFORMATION&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA assessed the ability of the public to access documents for the site through an Internet-based repository and determined that the local community has this ability. Documents for the site are available online for anyone with an Internet connection, and also at the Atlantic Public Library by Internet connections. Please visit &lt;a href=&quot;https://cumulis.epa.gov/supercpad/cursites/csitinfo.cfm?id=0700145&quot;&gt;EPA’s website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CONTACTS&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have questions or need additional information about any aspect of the site, please contact:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pamela Houston&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	Community Engagement Specialist&lt;br /&gt;
	Enforcement Coordination Office&lt;br /&gt;
	EPA Region 7&lt;br /&gt;
	11201 Renner Boulevard&lt;br /&gt;
	Lenexa, KS 66219&lt;br /&gt;
	Toll-free: 1-800-223-0425&lt;br /&gt;
	Email: &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:houston.pamela@epa.gov&quot;&gt;houston.pamela@epa.gov&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Susan Fisher&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	On-Scene Coordinator&lt;br /&gt;
	Response and Removal, North Section&lt;br /&gt;
	Superfund Division&lt;br /&gt;
	EPA Region 7&lt;br /&gt;
	11201 Renner Boulevard&lt;br /&gt;
	Lenexa, KS 66219&lt;br /&gt;
	Phone: 816-718-4285&lt;br /&gt;
	Email: &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:fisher.susan@epa.gov&quot;&gt;fisher.susan@epa.gov&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bo Hull&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	Remedial Project Manager&lt;br /&gt;
	Site Remediation Branch&lt;br /&gt;
	Superfund Division&lt;br /&gt;
	EPA Region 7 &lt;br /&gt;
	11201 Renner Boulevard&lt;br /&gt;
	Lenexa, KS 66219&lt;br /&gt;
	Phone: 913-551-7226&lt;br /&gt;
	Email: &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:hull.owens@epa.gov&quot;&gt;hull.owens@epa.gov&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 24 Jan 2017 20:10:15 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>mkessler</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">169951 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>PCE Former Dry Cleaner Superfund Site and PCE Chestnut Street Superfund Site, Atlantic, Cass County, Iowa – Public Notice</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/ia/pce-former-dry-cleaner-superfund-site-and-pce-chestnut-street-superfund-site-atlantic-cass-county</link>
    <description>&lt;h2 class=&quot;highlighted&quot;&gt;EPA Region 7 to Host Public Availability Session&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The U.S. Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) Region 7 will host a Public Availability Session to provide site status updates for the PCE Former Dry Cleaner Superfund Site and the PCE Chestnut Street Superfund Site, both in Atlantic, Iowa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Public Availability Session will be held:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tuesday, Jan. 24, 2017&lt;br /&gt;
	6:00 - 7:30 p.m.&lt;br /&gt;
	Atlantic Municipal Utilities&lt;br /&gt;
	15 W. 3rd Street&lt;br /&gt;
	Atlantic, IA 50022&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;EPA has assessed the ability of the public to access site information through an Internet-based repository and has determined that the local community has this ability. Additional site information is available online for anyone with an Internet connection, and also at the Atlantic Public Library by Internet connections. Please visit the following EPA websites: &lt;a href=&quot;https://cumulis.epa.gov/supercpad/cursites/csitinfo.cfm?id=0700145&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;PCE Former Dry Cleaner Superfund Site&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://semspub.epa.gov/src/collections/07/AR63845&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;PCE Chestnut Street Superfund Site&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;For reasonable accommodation, please contact Jonathan Cooper at 1-800-223-0425 or &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:cooper.jonathan@epa.gov&quot;&gt;cooper.jonathan@epa.gov&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Questions or requests for site information can be submitted to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;Pamela Houston&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;Community Engagement Specialist&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;EPA Region 7&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;11201 Renner Boulevard&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;Lenexa, KS 66219&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;Toll-free: 1-800-223-0425&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;Email: &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:houston.pamela@epa.gov&quot;&gt;houston.pamela@epa.gov&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;


</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 24 Jan 2017 19:52:00 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>mkessler</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">169945 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>M&amp;R Holdings, LLC d/b/a Brandon’s Reserve Residential Development - Clean Water Act Public Notice</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/ia/mr-holdings-llc-dba-brandons-reserve-residential-development-clean-water-act-public-notice</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;UNITED STATES ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION AGENCY&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In accordance with Section 309(g) of the Clean Water Act (“CWA”), 33 U.S.C. § 1319 (g), and 40 C.F.R. §§ 22.50-22.52 of the Consolidated Rules of Practice Governing the Administrative Assessment of Civil Penalties, Issuance of Compliance or Corrective Action Orders, Revocation, Termination or Suspension of Permits (“Consolidated Rules”), the Environmental Protection Agency (“EPA”) is providing notice of an Administrative Penalty Assessment in the form of an Expedited Storm Water Settlement Agreement against M&amp;amp;R Holdings, LLC d/b/a Brandon’s Reserve Residential Development, a business located at 15602 Wilden Drive, Urbandale, Iowa 50323, for alleged violations at 1010 Warrior Lane, Waukee, Iowa 50263.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under Section 309(g) of the Clean Water Act, 33 U.S.C. § 1319 (g), the EPA is authorized to issue orders assessing civil penalties for various violations of the Clean Water Act. The EPA may issue such orders after filing a Complaint commencing a Class I penalty proceeding.  Any person who, without authorization, discharges a pollutant to a navigable water, as those terms are defined in Section 502 of the CWA, 33 U.S.C. § 1362, may be administratively assessed a Class I civil penalty up to a maximum penalty of $51,570 by EPA.  The EPA provides notice of the proposed assessment of a Class I proceeding pursuant to the EPA’s Consolidated Rules, 64 Fed. Reg. 40138 (July 23, 1999)(Part 22), including Rules related to Administrative Proceedings Not Governed by § 554 of the Administrative Practices Act, 40 C.F.R. §§ 22.50-22.52 (64 Fed. Reg. 40138, 40190).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this case, the EPA alleges that M&amp;amp;R Holdings, LLC d/b/a Brandon’s Reserve Residential Development violated the requirements of its NPDES permit (Permit #IA-28073-27824), in violation of Section 301 of the Clean Water Act, 33 U.S.C. § 1311.  Respondent has reached agreement with the EPA on the terms of the proposed Expedited Storm Water Settlement Agreement.  Respondent will pay a civil penalty of $8,350.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The EPA will receive written comments on the proposed Expedited Storm Water Settlement Agreement for a period of thirty (30) days from the date of publication of this notice.  All such comments shall be submitted to the Regional Hearing Clerk at the address provided below.  The procedures by which the public may submit written comments on a proposed Class I order or participate in a Class I proceeding, and the procedures by which a respondent may request a hearing, are set forth in the Consolidated Rules.  Persons wishing to obtain additional information on the proceeding, receive a copy of the EPA’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gpo.gov/fdsys/pkg/CFR-2003-title40-vol1/pdf/CFR-2003-title40-vol1.pdf&quot;&gt;Consolidated Rules&lt;/a&gt;, review the proposed Expedited Storm Water Settlement Agreement, comment upon the proposed penalty assessment, or otherwise participate in the proceeding should contact Kathy Robinson, Regional Hearing Clerk, U.S. Environmental Protection Agency, Region 7, 11201 Renner Blvd, Lenexa, KS 66219.  Please reference Docket No. CWA-07-2017-0018.  In order to provide opportunity for public comment, the EPA will issue no final order assessing a penalty in this proceeding prior to forty (40) days from the date of this notice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
			&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=&quot;vertical-align:top; width:50%&quot;&gt;1-12-17&lt;br /&gt;
				Date&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td style=&quot;vertical-align:top; width:50%&quot;&gt;/s/&lt;br /&gt;
				Karen Flournoy&lt;br /&gt;
				Director&lt;br /&gt;
				Water, Wetlands, and Pesticides Division&lt;br /&gt;
				U.S. EPA, Region 7&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;box multi related-info right&quot;&gt;
	&lt;h2 class=&quot;pane-title&quot;&gt;How to Comment&lt;/h2&gt;

	&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Comments due date&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
			02/17/2017&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;div&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How to comment&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
			Persons wishing to obtain additional information on the proceeding, receive a copy of EPA’s Consolidated Rules, review the prorposed Consent Agreement/Final Order, comment upon the proposed penalty assessment, or otherwise participate in the proceeding should contact Kathy Robinson, Regional Hearing Clerk, U.S. Environmental Protection Agency, Region 7, 11201 Renner Boulevard, Lenexa, Kansas, 66219.  Please reference Docket No. CWA-07-2017-0018.&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Summary&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The EPA is providing notice of an Administrative Penalty Assessment in the form of an Expedited Storm Water Settlement Agreement against M&amp;amp;R Holdings, LLC d/b/a Brandon’s Reserve Residential Development, a business located at 15602 Wilden Drive, Urbandale, IA 50323, for alleged violations at 1010 Warrior Lane, Waukee, IA 50263.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;​&lt;strong&gt;Program/Statute:&lt;/strong&gt;  Clean Water Act (CWA)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Applicant/Respondent(s):&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;M&amp;amp;R Holdings, LLC d/b/a Brandon’s Reserve Residential Development&lt;br /&gt;
	Waukee, Iowa&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Proposed action:&lt;/strong&gt; Public Notice of Clean Water Act Adminstrative Penalty Settlement&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Docket ID: &lt;/strong&gt;CWA-07-2017-0018&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-346797&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2017-01/documents/brandons-reserve-esa.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=210711&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;M&amp;amp;R Holdings, LLC d/b/a Brandon’s Reserve Residential Development proposed Consent Agreement Final Order (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(1 pg, 211 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2017 13:17:50 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>mpropst</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">169355 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Region 7 States Air Quality Monitoring Plans - Iowa</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/ia/region-7-states-air-quality-monitoring-plans-iowa</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;Iowa, Kansas, Missouri, and Nebraska; Annual Monitoring Network Plans, Five-Year Monitoring Network Assessments, and approval documentation. Each year, states are required to submit an annual monitoring network plan to EPA. The network plans provide for the creation and maintenance of monitoring stations, in accordance with EPA monitoring requirements specified in 40 CFR (Code of Federal Regulations) Part 58.  For Five Year Monitoring Network Assessments, as stated at 40 CFR (Code of Federal Regulations) Part 58, each state is required to perform and submit to EPA an assessment of its air quality monitoring network every five years. At a minimum, this “five-year assessment” is meant to determine: if the existing network meets the monitoring objectives defined in Appendix D of 40 CFR Part 58; whether new sites are needed; whether existing sites are no longer needed and can be terminated; and whether new technologies are appropriate for incorporation into the ambient air monitoring network. For PM2.5 (particulate &amp;lt; 2.5 micrometers), the assessment also must identify needed changes to population-oriented sites. The first five-year assessment was due to EPA by July 1, 2010, and each assessment thereafter will be due in five-year increments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-342071&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-12/documents/ia_5yr_networkassessment2015.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=14957056&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Iowa DNR 2015 Five-Year Ambient Monitoring Network Assessment (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(137 pp, 15 MB)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-342073&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-12/documents/ia_network_plan_2015.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=6637497&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Iowa Department of Natural Resources; Air Quality Bureau; Iowa Ambient Air Monitoring 2015 Network Plan (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(85 pp, 7 MB)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-342075&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-12/documents/ia_5yrand2015approvalletter_12_21_15.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=86521&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Letter to Iowa dated December 21, 2015; DNR Approval of 2015 Ambient Air Monitoring Network Plan and Five-Year Network Assessment (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(1 pg, 87 K, 
  12/21/2015)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 29 Dec 2016 13:47:05 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>mpropst</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">167955 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Aluminum Company of America Alcoa and Mississippi River Pool #15 Superfund Sites, Bettendorf, Scott County, Iowa - Fact Sheet, October 2016</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/ia/aluminum-company-america-alcoa-and-mississippi-river-pool-15-superfund-sites-bettendorf-scott</link>
    <description>&lt;h2 class=&quot;highlighted&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;EPA Provides Update on Cleanup Action&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;INTRODUCTION&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In response to requests from the public, the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) Region 7 is providing this update of information related to the Aluminum Company of America Alcoa and the Mississippi River Pool #15 Superfund sites in Bettendorf, Iowa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SITE BACKGROUND&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Alcoa Davenport Works facility is an active aluminum sheet and plate rolling mill that has been in operation since 1948. Aluminum production and waste management activities have resulted in groundwater contamination at the Alcoa site. The primary contaminants of concern in the groundwater are classified as volatile organic compounds (VOCs), semi-VOCs, polychlorinated biphenyls (PCBs), and metals. The VOCs include compounds associated with degreasing solvents that were used to clean aluminum prior to entering the finishing process. Prior waste management activities have also resulted in historical releases of PCBs to Mississippi River Pool #15.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SITE UPDATE&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA is currently conducting the first five-year review for both sites, required by the Superfund law to verify that the remedy selected continues to protect human health and the environment. This five-year review is scheduled to be completed by June 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fish sampling occurred in September at the Mississippi River Pool #15 site. Results of that sampling will be available in spring 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ADDITIONAL INFORMATION&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA has assessed the ability of the public to access the five-year review through an Internet-based repository and has determined that the local community has this ability. As a result, documents regarding both sites can be assessed through the following websites:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://semspub.epa.gov/src/collection/07/AR11444&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Aluminum Company of America Alcoa site document collection&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://semspub.epa.gov/src/collection/07/AR4583&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Mississippi River Pool #15 site document collection&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have questions or need additional information, please contact:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pamela Houston&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	Community Engagement Specialist&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;Enforcement Coordination Office&lt;br /&gt;
	EPA Region 7&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;11201 Renner Boulevard&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;Lenexa, KS 66219&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;Email: &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:houston.pamela@epa.gov&quot;&gt;houston.pamela@epa.gov&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;Phone: 913-551-7699 or&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;Toll-free: 1-800-223-0425&lt;br /&gt;
	 &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Erin McCoy, P.G.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	Remedial Project Manager&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;Superfund Division&lt;br /&gt;
	EPA Region 7&lt;br /&gt;
	11201 Renner Boulevard&lt;br /&gt;
	Lenexa, KS 66219&lt;br /&gt;
	Email: &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:mccoy.erin@epa.gov&quot;&gt;mccoy.erin@epa.gov&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	Phone: 913-551-7977 or &lt;br /&gt;
	Toll-free: 1-800-223-0425&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt; &lt;/div&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Fri, 07 Oct 2016 21:09:19 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>mkessler</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">162317 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>North Cascade Road Developers, LLC - Dubuque, Iowa - Clean Water Act Public Notice</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/ia/north-cascade-road-developers-llc-dubuque-iowa-clean-water-act-public-notice</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;UNITED STATES ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION AGENCY&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;In accordance with Section 309(g)(4)(A) of the Clean Water Act (“CWA”), 33 U.S.C. § 1319(g)(4)(A), and 40 C.F.R. § 22.45 of the Consolidated Rules of Practice Governing the Administrative Assessment of Civil Penalties and the Revocation/Termination or Suspension of Permits (“Consolidated Rules”), the Environmental Protection Agency (“EPA”) is providing notice of a proposed Administrative Penalty Assessment against North Cascade Road Developers, LLC, a business located at 1800 Manson Road, Dubuque, Iowa 52003, for alleged violations at the Timber-Hyrst Estates Residential Development located on North Cascade Road between Creekwood Road to the east and Miners Lane to the west, in Dubuque, Iowa 52003.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under Section 309(g) of the Clean Water Act, 33 U.S.C. § 1319(g), the EPA is authorized to issue orders assessing civil penalties for various violations of the Clean Water Act.  The EPA may issue such orders after filing a Complaint commencing either a Class I or Class II penalty proceeding.  The EPA provides notice of the proposed assessment of a Class II civil penalty pursuant to 33 U.S.C. § 1319(g)(4)(A).  Class II proceedings are conducted under the EPA’s Consolidated Rules, 40 C.F.R. Part 22.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this case, the EPA alleges that Respondent violated the requirements of its NPDES permit (Permit # IA-14559-14349), in violation of Section 402 of the Clean Water Act, 33 U.S.C. § 1342.  The EPA alleges that Respondent failed to adequately implement a storm water pollution prevention plan on a residential development construction site and to conduct site inspections in accordance with the site’s NPDES permit issued by the Iowa Department of Natural Resources, the state agency with the authority to administer the federal NPDES program in Iowa.  Respondent has reached agreement with the EPA on the terms of a proposed Consent Agreement/Final Order which would resolve this matter.  Under the proposed Consent Agreement/Final Order, Respondent will pay a civil penalty of $50,000.  Final approval of the proposed Consent Agreement/Final Order is subject to the requirements of 40 C.F.R. § 22.45.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The EPA will receive written comments on the proposed Administrative Penalty Assessment for a period of thirty (30) days from the date of publication of this notice.  All such comments shall be submitted to the Regional Hearing Clerk at the address provided below.  The procedures by which the public may submit written comments on a proposed Class II order or participate in a Class II proceeding, and the procedures by which a respondent may request a hearing, are set forth in the Consolidated Rules.  Persons wishing to obtain additional information on the proceeding, receive a copy of the EPA’s Consolidated Rules, review the proposed Consent Agreement/Final Order, comment upon the proposed penalty assessment, or otherwise participate in the proceeding should contact Kathy Robinson, Regional Hearing Clerk, U.S. Environmental Protection Agency, Region 7, 11201 Renner Blvd, Lenexa, KS 66219.  Please reference Docket No. CWA-07-2016-0033.  In order to provide opportunity for public comment, the EPA will issue no final order assessing a penalty in this proceeding prior to forty (40) days from the date of this notice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
			&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=&quot;vertical-align:top; width:50%&quot;&gt;9/30/16&lt;br /&gt;
				Date&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td style=&quot;vertical-align:top; width:50%&quot;&gt;/s/ Jeffery Robichaud    for&lt;br /&gt;
				Karen A. Flournoy&lt;br /&gt;
				Director&lt;br /&gt;
				Water, Wetlands, and Pesticides Division&lt;br /&gt;
				U.S. EPA, Region 7&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;box multi related-info right&quot;&gt;
	&lt;h2 class=&quot;pane-title&quot;&gt;How to Comment&lt;/h2&gt;

	&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Comments due date&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
			11/3/2016&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;div&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How to comment&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
			Persons wishing to obtain additional information on the proceeding, receive a copy of EPA’s Consolidated Rules, review the prorposed Consent Agreement/Final Order, comment upon the proposed penalty assessment, or otherwise participate in the proceeding should contact Kathy Robinson, Regional Hearing Clerk, U.S. Environmental Protection Agency, Region 7, 11201 Renner Boulevard, Lenexa, Kansas, 66219.  Please reference Docket No. CWA-07-2016-0033.&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Summary&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;he EPA is providing notice of a proposed Administrative Penalty Assessment against North Cascade Road Developers, LLC, a business located at 1800 Manson Rd., Dubuque, IA 52003, for alleged violations at the Timber-Hyrst Estates Residential Development located on North Cascade Rd. between Creekwood Rd. to the east and Miners Lane to the west, in Dubuque, IA 52003.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;​&lt;strong&gt;Program/Statute:&lt;/strong&gt;  Clean Water Act (CWA)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Applicant/Respondent(s):&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;North Cascade Road Developers, LLC&lt;br /&gt;
	Dubuque, Iowa&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Proposed action:&lt;/strong&gt; Public Notice of Clean Water Act Adminstrative Penalty Settlement&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Docket ID: &lt;/strong&gt;CWA-07-2016-0033&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-320931&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-10/documents/north-cascade-road-developers-cafo.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=1402205&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;North Cascade Road Developers, LLC proposed Consent Agreement Final Order (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(13 pp, 1 MB)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 04 Oct 2016 12:34:36 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>mpropst</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">161917 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Agri Star Meat &amp; Poultry, LLC - Postville, Iowa - Clean Water Act Public Notice</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/ia/agri-star-meat-poultry-llc-postville-iowa-clean-water-act-public-notice</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;UNITED STATES ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION AGENCY&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In accordance with Section 309(g)(4)(A) of the Clean Water Act (“CWA”), 33 U.S.C. § 1319(g)(4)(A), and 40 C.F.R. § 22.45 of the Consolidated Rules of Practice Governing the Administrative Assessment of Civil Penalties and the Revocation/Termination or Suspension of Permits (“Consolidated Rules”), the Environmental Protection Agency (“EPA”) is providing notice of a proposed Administrative Penalty Assessment against Agri Star Meat &amp;amp; Poultry, LLC, for alleged violations at its facility located at 220 West Street, Postville, Iowa 52162.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under Section 309(g) of the Clean Water Act, 33 U.S.C. § 1319(g), the EPA is authorized to issue orders assessing civil penalties for various violations of the Clean Water Act.  The EPA may issue such orders after filing a Complaint commencing either a Class I or Class II penalty proceeding.  The EPA provides notice of the proposed assessment of a Class II civil penalty pursuant to 33 U.S.C. § 1319(g)(4)(A).  Class II proceedings are conducted under the EPA’s Consolidated Rules, 40 C.F.R. Part 22.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this case, the EPA alleges that Respondent violated the requirements of its National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System permit for stormwater associated with industrial activities (Permit No. IA-10124-9928), in violation of Section 402 of the Clean Water Act, 33 U.S.C. § 1442.  The EPA alleges that Respondent failed to: have a copy of its Stormwater Pollution Prevention Plan (“SWPPP”) available at its facility; develop and update, as appropriate, an adequate SWPPP; conduct employee stormwater training during 2014; control non-stormwater pollutant discharges; and follow proper sampling procedures.  Respondent has reached agreement with the EPA on the terms of a proposed Consent Agreement/Final Order which would resolve this matter.  Under the proposed Consent Agreement/Final Order, Respondent will pay a civil penalty of $43,000.  Final approval of the proposed Consent Agreement/Final Order is subject to the requirements of 40 C.F.R. § 22.45.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The EPA will receive written comments on the proposed Administrative Penalty Assessment for a period of thirty (30) days from the date of publication of this notice.  All such comments shall be submitted to the Regional Hearing Clerk at the address provided below.  The procedures by which the public may submit written comments on a proposed Class II order or participate in a Class II proceeding, and the procedures by which a respondent may request a hearing, are set forth in the Consolidated Rules.  Persons wishing to obtain additional information on the proceeding, receive a copy of the EPA’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gpo.gov/fdsys/pkg/CFR-2003-title40-vol1/pdf/CFR-2003-title40-vol1.pdf&quot;&gt;Consolidated Rules&lt;/a&gt;, review the proposed Consent Agreement/Final Order, comment upon the proposed penalty assessment, or otherwise participate in the proceeding should contact Kathy Robinson, Regional Hearing Clerk, U.S. Environmental Protection Agency, Region 7, 11201 Renner Blvd, Lenexa, KS 66219.  Please reference Docket No. CWA-07-2016-0079.  In order to provide opportunity for public comment, the EPA will issue no final order assessing a penalty in this proceeding prior to forty (40) days from the date of this notice.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;table&gt;&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
			&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=&quot;vertical-align:top; width:50%&quot;&gt;9-27-16&lt;br /&gt;
				Date&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td style=&quot;vertical-align:top; width:50%&quot;&gt;/s/&lt;br /&gt;
				Karen A. Flournoy&lt;br /&gt;
				Director&lt;br /&gt;
				Water, Wetlands, and Pesticides Division&lt;br /&gt;
				U.S. EPA, Region 7&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;box multi related-info right&quot;&gt;
	&lt;h2 class=&quot;pane-title&quot;&gt;How to Comment&lt;/h2&gt;

	&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Comments due date&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
			10/29/2016&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;div&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How to comment&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
			Persons wishing to obtain additional information on the proceeding, receive a copy of EPA’s Consolidated Rules, review the prorposed Consent Agreement/Final Order, comment upon the proposed penalty assessment, or otherwise participate in the proceeding should contact Kathy Robinson, Regional Hearing Clerk, U.S. Environmental Protection Agency, Region 7, 11201 Renner Boulevard, Lenexa, Kansas, 66219.  Please reference Docket No. CWA-07-2016-0079.&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Summary&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The EPA is providing notice of a proposed Administrative Penalty Assessment against Agri Star Meat &amp;amp; Poultry, LLC, for alleged violations at its facility located at 220 West St, Postville, IA 52162.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;​&lt;strong&gt;Program/Statute:&lt;/strong&gt;  Clean Water Act (CWA)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Applicant/Respondent(s):&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Postville, Iowa&lt;br /&gt;
	 &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Proposed action:&lt;/strong&gt; Public Notice of Clean Water Act Adminstrative Penalty Settlement&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Docket ID: &lt;/strong&gt;CWA-07-2016-0079&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-319529&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-09/documents/agri-star-cafo.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=1863587&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Agri Star Meat &amp;amp; Poultry, LLC proposed Consent Agreement Final Order (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(16 pp, 2 MB)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 29 Sep 2016 13:15:10 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>mpropst</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">161505 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>City of West Union, Iowa - Clean Water Act Public Notice</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/ia/city-west-union-iowa-clean-water-act-public-notice</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;UNITED STATES ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION AGENCY&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In accordance with Section 309(g)(4)(A) of the Clean Water Act (“CWA”), 33 U.S.C. § 1319(g)(4)(A), and 40 C.F.R. § 22.45 of the Consolidated Rules of Practice Governing the Administrative Assessment of Civil Penalties, Issuance of Compliance or Corrective Action Orders, and the Revocation, Termination or Suspension of Permits (“Consolidated Rules”), the Environmental Protection Agency (“EPA”) is providing notice of a proposed Administrative Penalty Assessment against the City of West Union, Iowa, a municipality, for alleged violations of its National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System (“NPDES”) permit (permit No. IA-0035378) for discharges from the City’s Publicly Owned Treatment Works (“POTW”) into Otter Creek. The POTW is located at 9875 Echo Valley Road, West Union, Iowa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under Section 309(g) of the Clean Water Act, 33 U.S.C. § 1319(g), the EPA is authorized to issue orders assessing civil penalties for various violations of the Clean Water Act.  The EPA may issue such orders after filing a Complaint commencing either a Class I or Class II penalty proceeding.  The EPA provides notice of the proposed assessment of a Class II civil penalty pursuant to 33 U.S.C. § 1319(g)(4)(A).  Class II proceedings are conducted under EPA’s Consolidated Rules, 40 C.F.R. Part 22.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this case, the EPA alleges that the City of West Union violated the requirements of its NPDES permit, in violation of Sections 301(a) and 402 of the Clean Water Act, 33 U.S.C. §§ 1311(a) and 1342.  Respondent has reached agreement with EPA on the terms of a proposed Consent Agreement/Final Order which would resolve this matter.  Under the proposed Consent Agreement/Final Order, Respondent will pay a civil penalty of $9,200.  Respondent will pay $5,520 in cash, and the remainder of the civil penalty will be mitigated through performance by Respondent of a Supplemental Environmental Project.  The Supplemental Environmental Project requires Respondent to spend $3,680 to replace the current City Hall parking lot surface with permeable pavers installed at the parking stalls.  The permeable pavers infiltrate water and direct it to the northeast corner of the parking lot.  In the northeast corner, additional depth of storage aggregate would be included to provide additional storage of storm water.  A drain tile will be located within the storage area to direct flow to the drainage ditch which flows to nearby Otter Creek.  The proposed project also includes construction of a rain garden on the northeast corner of City Hall that will collect and treat roof drainage.  The rain garden will contain an underdrain that would flow into the storage aggregate of the permeable pavers.  The Respondent anticipates the project will significantly improve water quality and reduce pollutants that enter Otter Creek in the areas of the improvements.  Final approval of the proposed Consent Agreement/Final Order is subject to the requirements of 40 C.F.R. § 22.45.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The EPA will receive written comments on the proposed Administrative Penalty Assessment for a period of thirty (30) days from the date of publication of this notice.  All such comments shall be submitted to the Regional Hearing Clerk at the address provided below.  The procedures by which the public may submit written comments on a proposed Class II order or participate in a Class II proceeding, and the procedures by which a respondent may request a hearing, are set forth in the Consolidated Rules.  Persons wishing to obtain additional information on the proceeding, receive a copy of EPA’s Consolidated Rules, review the proposed Consent Agreement/Final Order, comment upon the proposed penalty assessment, or otherwise participate in the proceeding should contact Regional Hearing Clerk, U.S. Environmental Protection Agency, Region 7, 11201 Renner Boulevard, Lenexa, Kansas, 66219.  Please reference Docket No. CWA-07-2016-0078.  In order to provide opportunity for public comment, EPA will issue no final order assessing a penalty in this proceeding prior to forty (40) days from the date of this notice.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;table&gt;&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
			&lt;th scope=&quot;col&quot;&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/thead&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=&quot;vertical-align:top; width:50%&quot;&gt;8-16-16&lt;br /&gt;
				Date&lt;/td&gt;
			&lt;td style=&quot;vertical-align:top; width:50%&quot;&gt;/s/&lt;br /&gt;
				Karen A. Flournoy&lt;br /&gt;
				Director&lt;br /&gt;
				Water, Wetlands, and Pesticides Division&lt;br /&gt;
				U.S. EPA, Region 7&lt;/td&gt;
		&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;box multi related-info right&quot;&gt;
	&lt;h2 class=&quot;pane-title&quot;&gt;How to Comment&lt;/h2&gt;

	&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
		&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Comments due date&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br /&gt;
			09/16/2016&lt;/p&gt;

		&lt;div&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How to comment&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
			Persons wishing to obtain additional information on the proceeding, receive a copy of EPA’s Consolidated Rules, review the prorposed Consent Agreement/Final Order, comment upon the proposed penalty assessment, or otherwise participate in the proceeding should contact Kathy Robinson, Regional Hearing Clerk, U.S. Environmental Protection Agency, Region 7, 11201 Renner Boulevard, Lenexa, Kansas, 66219.  Please reference Docket No. CWA-07-2016-0078.&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Summary&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The EPA is providing notice of a proposed Administrative Penalty Assessment against the City of West Union, IA, a municipality, for alleged violations of its National Pollutant Discharge Elimination System permit (permit No. IA-0035378) for discharges from the City’s Publicly Owned Treatment Works into Otter Creek. The POTW is located at 9875 Echo Valley Road, West Union, IA. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;​&lt;strong&gt;Program/Statute:&lt;/strong&gt;  Clean Water Act (CWA)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Applicant/Respondent(s):&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;City of West Union, Iowa&lt;br /&gt;
	West Union, Iowa&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Proposed action:&lt;/strong&gt; Public Notice of Clean Water Act Adminstrative Penalty Settlement&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Docket ID: &lt;/strong&gt;CWA-07-2016-0078&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-309407&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-08/documents/west-union-city-iowa-cafo.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=1496031&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;City of West Union, Iowa proposed Consent Agreement Final Order (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(15 pp, 1 MB)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 17 Aug 2016 13:23:15 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>mpropst</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">157709 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  </channel>
</rss>

<!-- Page cached by Boost @ 2017-01-25 16:25:44, expires @ 2017-01-26 04:25:44, lifetime 12 hours -->