<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?><rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.epa.gov/feed/66381/rss.xml" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/" xmlns:og="http://ogp.me/ns#" xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#" xmlns:sioc="http://rdfs.org/sioc/ns#" xmlns:sioct="http://rdfs.org/sioc/types#" xmlns:skos="http://www.w3.org/2004/02/skos/core#" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#">
  <channel>
    <title>RE-Powering America&#039;s Land</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/feed/66381/rss.xml</link>
    <description>Updated RE-Powering America&#039;s Land content from the US Environmental Protection Agency</description>
    <language>en</language>
     <atom:link href="https://www.epa.gov/feed/66381/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      <item>
    <title>Community Solar: An Opportunity to Enhance Sustainable Development on Landfills and Other Contaminated Sites</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/re-powering/community-solar-opportunity-enhance-sustainable-development-landfills-and-other</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;This discussion paper describes the linkage between the need for solar access for some sites, the mechanism of community solar and the opportunities for using formerly contaminated lands, landfills and mine sites for renewable energy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-337409&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-12/documents/epa_repowering_community_solar_discussion_paper_final_120716_508.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=3853266&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Community Solar: An Opportunity to Enhance Sustainable Development on Landfills and Other Contaminated Sites (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(29 pp, 4 MB)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 06 Dec 2016 21:12:27 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cbooker</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">166539 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>RE-Powering Evaluation Fact Sheet and Report</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/re-powering/re-powering-evaluation-fact-sheet-and-report</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;In July 2016, the Evaluation of the RE-Powering America’s Land Initiative Report was completed.  Links both to a summarizing fact sheet and the full report are below.  The report is organized into four chapters:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Chapter 1 presents an introduction&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Chapter 2 presents the methodology for conducting the evaluation&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Chapter 3 provides findings for each evaluation question&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Chapter 4 provides summary conclusions and opportunities for improvement, based on the findings&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Appendices present the evaluation’s interview guides, a literature review, and a summary of solar and wind cost components.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The evaluation has benefitted from interviews with a host of stakeholders.  Efforts to continue to reach out to stakeholders in a variety of ways will be ongoing, in order to help ensure that activities aimed to effectively encourage renewable energy on contaminated lands, landfills and mine sites are meaningful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-327439&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-10/documents/re_power_evaluation_fs_508_102716.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=71286&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Fact Sheet: Evaluation of the RE-Powering America’s Land Initiative (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(2 pp, 71 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-326697&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-10/documents/re-powering_final_evaluation_report.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=2829221&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Final Report: Evaluation of the RE-Powering America’s Land Initiative (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(60 pp, 3 MB)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-326699&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-10/documents/re-powering_final_report_appendices_a-c.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=251382&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Final Report: Appendices (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(53 pp, 251 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 25 Oct 2016 15:41:45 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cbooker</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">163377 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Evaluation of RE-Powering America’s Land Initiative</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/re-powering/evaluation-re-powering-americas-land-initiative</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;In October 2014, the final version of the RE-Powering America’s Land Initiative (the “Initiative”) Action Plan 2.0, was released, articulating the goals and objectives of the Initiative and the activities it expected to pursue over the next two years. In that plan, we committed to perform an evaluation of Initiative activities to help improve the usefulness of technical support, outreach and tools provided to communities, developers and other stakeholders involved in the Initiative. That work was done in two stages with the support of Industrial Economics, Inc.:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In April 2015, the first stage of the evaluation was to complete an &lt;a href=&quot;/re-powering/re-powering-evaluation-scoping-assessment&quot;&gt;evaluation scoping assessment&lt;/a&gt;. The assessment included a new logic model; posed questions of interest to assess resources, tools and knowledge products; and explored methods and data that would be used to answer such questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on the results of this scoping assessment, EPA identified several aspects of the Initiative to continue to evaluate and, in June 2015, began the next phase of the evaluation. In July 2016, the &lt;a href=&quot;/re-powering/re-powering-evaluation-fact-sheet-and-report&quot;&gt;Evaluation of the RE-Powering America’s Land Initiative Report&lt;/a&gt; was completed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The evaluation has benefitted from interviews with a host of stakeholders. Efforts to continue to reach out to stakeholders in a variety of ways will be ongoing, in order to help ensure that activities aimed to effectively encourage renewable energy on contaminated lands, landfills and mine sites are meaningful.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 25 Oct 2016 15:33:52 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cbooker</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">163375 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>RE-Powering Benefits Matrix</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/re-powering/re-powering-benefits-matrix</link>
    <description>&lt;div&gt;
	&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
		&lt;div class=&quot;clearfix&quot;&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;RE-Powering tracks the economic and environmental benefits associated with completed sites, as identified and reported by parties directly involved with their respective projects. Common benefits reported include revenues from land leases and taxes, electricity cost savings associated with the reduced need to purchase power from the grid, job creation, reduced greenhouse gas emissions, et al. This resource is for informational purposes only and may not be a comprehensive representation of all benefits realized by completed projects on contaminated lands.&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;/div&gt;
	&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-337193&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-12/documents/re_benefits_matrix_508_120716_web.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=4545629&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;RE-Powering Benefits Matrix (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(26 pp, 5 MB)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 25 May 2016 19:55:25 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cbooker</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">150463 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Renewable Energy Reuse and Protectiveness</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/re-powering/renewable-energy-reuse-and-protectiveness</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;EPA works collaboratively with states, tribes, local government, and other stakeholders to achieve its mission of assessing, cleaning up and restoring contaminated sites to set the stage for redevelopment or facilitate the continued use of the facility. For the Superfund Program, EPA directly oversees the cleanup activities.  Other EPA programs were designed by Congress to be delegated or authorized to states (e.g., RCRA Corrective Action, Underground Storage Tanks) or established as a grant program (Brownfields). The majority of site-specific cleanup decisions are made by the state-run or state-delegated programs, including decisions about protectiveness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Developers of renewable energy on formerly contaminated lands, as well as landfills and mining sites, have adopted strategies to cost effectively install such technology and maintain the integrity and protectiveness of the remedy.  The site owner, the developer and the overseeing agency, through collaboration, can develop approaches to accommodate a renewable energy reuse option. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Strategies have included:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Ballasted racking systems so that solar panels can rest on top of the surface without driving supporting anchors into the ground either puncturing the cap of a landfill or otherwise creating unwanted preferential pathways for stormwater to enter the subsurface;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Selecting certain sub-sections of the site for reuse where contamination was limited or non-existent;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Designing renewable energy structures that effectively use, enhance or complement aspects particular to the material contained on site (&lt;em&gt;e.g&lt;/em&gt;., mill tailings) without exacerbating  existing contamination;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Adjusting the locations of groundwater monitoring stations to places that maximize flat, open areas for solar panels, but still providing the necessary and spatially relevant information to monitor the site; or&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Minimizing soil disturbance in design, installation and operation of the renewable energy system;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;In these and other ways, it is possible for renewable energy to be developed consistent with the chosen remedy and not affect the protectiveness of the site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;For More Information&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To determine what uses would be appropriate for a particular property, and finding information on potentially useful site-specific institutional controls, please contact the appropriate regulatory Agency for this site-specific information.  The contact information for Superfund and Brownfields sites are listed on the programs web sites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Parties interested in learning more about how specific Federal programs address protectiveness are encouraged to see the following sources of information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;roomy&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;/cleanups/cleanups-my-community&quot;&gt;Cleanups in My Community&lt;/a&gt; portal has a great deal of information and links to either list or map sites of interest, which in turn link to Project Profile pages that provide site-specific cleanup documents and would list the applicable regulatory authority.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Each of the Federal and Federally delegated programs also has information about sites within their purview:
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Superfund
				&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://semspub.epa.gov/work/11/175197.pdf&quot;&gt;A Community Guide to EPA’s Superfund Program (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;Information on a Site’s Cleanup Status and Reuse Potential&lt;br /&gt;
						(See Question 2 of “&lt;a href=&quot;/enforcement/report-top-10-questions-ask-when-buying-superfund-site&quot;&gt;Top 10 Questions to Ask When Buying a Superfund Site&lt;/a&gt;”)&lt;/li&gt;
					&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/superfund/search-superfund-sites-where-you-live&quot;&gt;Search for Superfund Sites Where You Live&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
				&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;RCRA
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/hwgenerators/resource-conservation-and-recovery-act-rcra-orientation-manual&quot;&gt;RCRA Orientation Manual&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://nepis.epa.gov/Exe/ZyNET.exe/10000MAO.txt?ZyActionD=ZyDocument&amp;amp;Client=EPA&amp;amp;Index=2000%20Thru%202005&amp;amp;Docs=&amp;amp;Query=&amp;amp;Time=&amp;amp;EndTime=&amp;amp;SearchMethod=1&amp;amp;TocRestrict=n&amp;amp;Toc=&amp;amp;TocEntry=&amp;amp;QField=&amp;amp;QFieldYear=&amp;amp;QFieldMonth=&amp;amp;QFieldDay=&amp;amp;UseQField=&amp;amp;IntQFieldOp=0&amp;amp;ExtQFieldOp=0&amp;amp;XmlQuery=&amp;amp;File=D%3A%5CZYFILES%5CINDEX%20DATA%5C00THRU05%5CTXT%5C00000005%5C10000MAO.txt&amp;amp;User=ANONYMOUS&amp;amp;Password=anonymous&amp;amp;SortMethod=h%7C-&amp;amp;MaximumDocuments=1&amp;amp;FuzzyDegree=0&amp;amp;ImageQuality=r75g8/r75g8/x150y150g16/i425&amp;amp;Display=p%7Cf&amp;amp;DefSeekPage=x&amp;amp;SearchBack=ZyActionL&amp;amp;Back=ZyActionS&amp;amp;BackDesc=Results%20page&amp;amp;MaximumPages=1&amp;amp;ZyEntry=1&quot;&gt;25 Years of RCRA: Building on Our Past to Protect Our Future&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www3.epa.gov/epawaste/hazard/correctiveaction/facility/index.htm&quot;&gt;RCRA Corrective Action Facility Information&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Brownfields
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/brownfields/brownfields-overview-brochure&quot;&gt;Brownfields Overview&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/land-revitalization&quot;&gt;Land Revitalization&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;/brownfields/brownfields-grantee-reporting-assessment-cleanup-and-redevelopment-exchange-system-acres&quot;&gt;Brownfields Grantees&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 25 Feb 2016 20:29:28 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cbooker</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">136823 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>RE-Powering Accomplishment Highlights</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/re-powering/re-powering-accomplishment-highlights</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;Since its inception in 2008, the RE-Powering Initiative has promoted renewable energy investments on contaminated properties through a combination of tailored redevelopment tools, outreach and technical assistance. The Initiative uses a multi-pronged approach to combine cleanup and renewable energy development on contaminated land, with continuous community and stakeholder engagement. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To date, 190 renewable energy installations have been installed on contaminated lands, landfills, and mine sites, with a cumulative installed capacity of just over 1,172 megawatts (MW) and consistent growth in total installations since the inception of the program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, the RE-Powering team successfully has and continues to develop and identify resources and tools to meet stakeholder needs; provide access to crucial information and data; and promote a cohesive approach at the federal level to further RE-Powering goals. Harvard University recognized the efforts of RE-Powering by selecting the Initiative as one of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://yosemite.epa.gov/opa/admpress.nsf/d0cf6618525a9efb85257359003fb69d/c4094857fe9964f585257b5e0055523e!OpenDocument&quot;&gt;Top 25 Innovations&lt;/a&gt; in American Government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some specific activities and accomplishments achieved by RE-Powering include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#highlight_1&quot;&gt;Developing Mapping and Screening Tools&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#highlight_2&quot;&gt;Providing Assistance Regarding Liability Concerns&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#highlight_3&quot;&gt;Developing Handbooks, Best Practice Guides, and Case Studies&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#highlight_4&quot;&gt;Providing Site-Specific Technical Assistance and  Stakeholder Outreach&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#highlight_5&quot;&gt;Conducting Program Evaluation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;hr /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;highlight_1&quot; name=&quot;highlight_1&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Developing Mapping and Screening Tools&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;RE-Powering Mapper&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To assist stakeholders learn about the renewable energy potential of contaminated properties in their region, the Initiative expanded and enhanced its &lt;a href=&quot;/re-powering/re-powering-mapping-and-screening-tools&quot;&gt;RE-Powering Mapper&lt;/a&gt; tool, which has preliminarily screened more than 80,000 EPA- and state-tracked sites on more than 43 million acres for solar, wind, biomass, and geothermal potential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To develop the tool, RE-Powering partnered with the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nrel.gov/&quot;&gt;National Renewable Energy Lab&lt;/a&gt;, as well as collaborated with state agencies from California, Hawaii, Illinois, Massachusetts, New York, New Jersey, Oregon, Pennsylvania, Texas, Virginia, and West Virginia to screen for renewable energy potential at over 47,000 state-tracked sites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Electronic Decision Tree&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To aid stakeholders navigate the various issues to consider when trying to determine a renewable energy project’s feasibility, RE-Powering developed an &lt;a href=&quot;/re-powering/re-powerings-electronic-decision-tree&quot;&gt;electronic decision tree&lt;/a&gt; that guides users through a process for screening site suitability for solar photovoltaic (PV) or wind installations. The electronic decision tree:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Explores potentially contaminated sites (e.g., brownfields, RCRA-permitted, Superfund), landfills, and underutilized sites and rooftops;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Walks users through a series of Yes / No / Skip questions supplemented by tips and links to relevant tools and information resources;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Screens for site characteristics, redevelopment considerations, criteria specific to landfills and contaminated sites, energy load, and policies and financial considerations; and&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Generates reports of the screening results and user annotations that can be printed and/or copied into another document.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;highlight_2&quot; name=&quot;highlight_2&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Providing Assistance Regarding Liability Concerns&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hearing concerns about potential liability from reusing formerly contaminated properties, the Initiative developed documents that &lt;a href=&quot;/enforcement/guidance-treatment-tenants-under-cerclas-bona-fide-prospective-purchaser-bfpp-provision&quot;&gt;clarify liability&lt;/a&gt;, including new guidance, model comfort letters, and fact sheets that cover liability concerns and the treatment of tenants under the Bona Fide Prospective Purchaser Provisions of the Comprehensive Environmental Response, Compensation, and Liability Act.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Initiative has also provided site-specific assistance as appropriate to clarify liability in order to move projects forward.  For example, EPA provided a comfort letter to one of the co-owners of the DuPont Solar Farm in Newport, DE, which helped the developer secure the financing necessary to complete the project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;highlight_3&quot; name=&quot;highlight_3&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Developing Handbooks, Best Practice Guides, and Other Resources&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Understanding that planning for and development of renewable energy projects can be effectively integrated within ongoing cleanup activities, RE-Powering developed the &lt;a href=&quot;/re-powering/handbook-siting-renewable-energy-projects-while-addressing-environmental-issues&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Handbook on Siting Renewable Energy Projects While Addressing Environmental Issues&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.  This Handbook provides tools to help interested parties determine the overall feasibility of siting renewable energy production and some key considerations for integrating renewable energy development during all phases of typical cleanup processes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recognizing the growing trend of reusing former landfills as solar installations, the Initiative developed the &lt;a href=&quot;/re-powering/best-practices-siting-solar-photovoltaics-municipal-solid-waste-landfills&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Best Practices for the Installation of Solar Photovoltaics (PV) on Municipal Solid Waste Landfills&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; to provide assistance in addressing common technical challenges for siting solar PV projects on MSW landfills for solar developers and landfill owners as well as federal, state and local stakeholders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;highlight_4&quot; name=&quot;highlight_4&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Providing Site-Specific Technical Assistance and Stakeholder Outreach&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Receiving project inquiries from communities, property owners, developers, and other stakeholders, RE-Powering created a network of professionals across its headquarters and regional offices, known as the &lt;a href=&quot;/re-powering/forms/contact-us-about-re-powering-americas-land#rprt&quot;&gt;RE-Powering Response Team&lt;/a&gt;, to provide site-specific assistance and project support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To educate stakeholders about the potential opportunities to develop renewable energy on contaminated properties and help assess project feasibility, the Initiative also has provided &lt;a href=&quot;/re-powering/re-powering-feasibility-studies&quot;&gt;technical assistance&lt;/a&gt; through the Initiative’s interagency agreement with the National Renewable Energy Lab (NREL), as well as provided tutorials and assistance related to RE-Powering’s screening and mapping tools. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To create an open forum to share innovative ideas and best practices, RE-Powering has organized a series of stakeholder meetings and workshops, including a finance workshop, convening bankers, developers, communities, and insurance companies to discuss structuring deals to address environmental issues. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;RE-Powering has also produced a number of communication products that highlight activities, benefits and accomplishments, including success stories, case studies, and newsletters that keep RE-Powering’s stakeholders informed about progress, trends, and products related to renewable energy and contaminated lands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recognizing the value of sharing news of other successful projects, the Initiative regularly compiles and reports information on specific completed projects and identifies trends related to renewable energy development on contaminated lands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a id=&quot;highlight_5&quot; name=&quot;highlight_5&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Conducting Program Evaluation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recognizing that the Initiative has lessons to learn from its previous activities and efforts, the Initiative has begun a staged evaluation of its work.  As a first step, RE-Powering has completed an &lt;a href=&quot;/re-powering/re-powering-evaluation-scoping-assessment&quot;&gt;evaluation scoping assessment&lt;/a&gt; to identify methods and data that would be needed to assess the Initiative’s effectiveness.  The Initiative is now considering the results of this assessment and exploring the practicality of which aspects of the Initiative to continue to evaluate.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 23 Feb 2016 18:48:26 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cbooker</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">136461 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>RE–Powering News (2016)</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/re-powering/re-powering-news-2016</link>
    <description>&lt;p id=&quot;subjectField&quot;&gt;Quarterly news digest from EPA’s RE-Powering America’s Land Initiative&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-299763&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-07/documents/re-powering_quarterly_newsletter_july_2016.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=1034735&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;RE-Powering News - July 2016 (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(9 pp, 1 MB)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-256665&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-02/documents/re_powering_newsletter_feb_2016_508_021616.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=754687&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Re-Powering News - February 2016 (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(9 pp, 755 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 17 Feb 2016 19:13:26 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cbooker</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">135789 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>RE-Powering America’s Land Electronic Decision Tree (October 2015)</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/re-powering/re-powering-americas-land-electronic-decision-tree-october-2015</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;Overview of the RE-Powering America’s Land initiative’s Electronic Decision Tree.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-209465&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2015-10/documents/repower_technologies_decision_tree.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=268871&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;RE-Powering America’s Land Electronic Decision Tree Factsheet (October 2015) (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(1 pg, 269 K)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 06 Oct 2015 14:24:33 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cbooker</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">119807 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Receive Notifications and Updates Regarding RE-Powering&#039;s Electronic Decision Tree</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/re-powering/forms/receive-notifications-and-updates-regarding-re-powerings-electronic-decision-tree</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;Receive notifications and updates regarding RE-Powering&#039;s Electronic Decision Tree.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Mon, 05 Oct 2015 14:28:56 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cbooker</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">119369 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  </channel>
</rss>

<!-- Page cached by Boost @ 2017-01-25 17:30:10, expires @ 2017-01-26 05:30:10, lifetime 12 hours -->