<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?><rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.epa.gov/feed/79351/rss.xml" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/" xmlns:og="http://ogp.me/ns#" xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#" xmlns:sioc="http://rdfs.org/sioc/ns#" xmlns:sioct="http://rdfs.org/sioc/types#" xmlns:skos="http://www.w3.org/2004/02/skos/core#" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#">
  <channel>
    <title>Environmental Response Team</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/feed/79351/rss.xml</link>
    <description>Updated Environmental Response Team content from the US Environmental Protection Agency</description>
    <language>en</language>
     <atom:link href="https://www.epa.gov/feed/79351/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      <item>
    <title>ERT Compressed Gas Cylinder Analysis</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/ert/ert-compressed-gas-cylinder-analysis</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;ERT Compressed Gas Cylinders Identification, Assessment, and Treatment Alternatives&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ERT can assist with:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Identification of unknown compressed gas cylinders when DOT and/or Compressed Gas Association (CGA) codes are legible or indecipherable. &lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Assessment of the cylinders to safely determine if they still contain compressed gas and if the valves are still operable.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Determination of cost-effective and efficient treatment of cylinder content.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Determination of alternative methods of treatment, transportation, and disposal of compressed gas cylinders.  Specifically, a saddle technique for on-site treatment of typical compressed gases (acetylene, chlorine, anhydrous ammonia, and inert/non-flammable gases).  The saddle technique is an ERT modification of a technique used to tap pipelines under pressure. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/ert/forms/contact-us-about-environmental-response-team-ert&quot;&gt;Contact Us&lt;/a&gt; to ask a question, provide feedback, or report a problem.&lt;/p&gt;


</description>
     <pubDate>Tue, 03 Nov 2015 13:59:06 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cgallo</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">124385 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Environmental Response Team (ERT) Overview</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/ert/environmental-response-team-ert-overview</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;The Environmental Response Team’s mission is to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;box multi related-info right&quot;&gt;
	&lt;h2 class=&quot;pane-title&quot;&gt;Related Links&lt;/h2&gt;

	&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.epaosc.org/&quot;&gt;EPAOSC.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.epaosc.org/site/site_profile.aspx?site_id=2107&quot;&gt;ERT SOPs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epaosc.org/viper&quot;&gt;VIPER&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://ertvideo.org/&quot;&gt;ERTV&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;file-175865&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/sites/production/files/2015-08/documents/ert_overview_oemremovalhsoilsupport.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=1339082&quot;&gt;ERT Overview (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(24 pp, 1 MB)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Support the nation&#039;s response, cleanup and renewal of its contaminated land, water and air.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Provide high quality service and consultation to those requiring assistance around the world.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Promote the development of technology and procedures in relevant science and engineering areas.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Support EPA programs within OSWER.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Disseminate relevant environmental information.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nationwide, ERT deploys rapid-response, comprehensive services that protect healthy communities and advance environmental protection.  ERT’s offices in Edison (New Jersey), Cincinnati (Ohio), Las Vegas (Nevada), and Research Triangle Park (North Carolina) maintain around-the-clock readiness to provide expertise at the scene of a hazardous substance release or a long-term environmental cleanup.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	ERT can provide support for the full range of emergency response actions, including unusual or complex emergency incidents such as an underwater release. In such cases, the team can bring in special equipment with technically adept responders providing the on-site coordinator or remedial project manager with experience and advice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ERT is also recognized as a vehicle for the rapid generation of topic-specific Standard Operating Procedures (SOPs), technical bulletins, fact sheets, and analytical method development and evaluation.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 16 Sep 2015 14:52:42 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cgallo</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">114167 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Environmental Response Team (ERT) Oil Response</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/ert/environmental-response-team-ert-oil-response</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;ERT provides classroom and hands-on field training for responding to oil spills in slow and fast water incidents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;box multi related-info right&quot;&gt;
	&lt;h2 class=&quot;pane-title&quot;&gt;Related Links&lt;/h2&gt;

	&lt;div class=&quot;pane-content&quot;&gt;
		&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/emergency-response/national-contingency-plan-subpart-j&quot;&gt;Learn more about the NCP&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
			&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/oil-spills-prevention-and-preparedness-regulations&quot;&gt;Learn more about the OPA&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ERT consults with federal, state and local responders on oil type and characteristics during incidents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ERT provides instruction for the Shoreline Cleanup and Assessment Technique (SCAT) process, Special Monitoring of Applied Response Technologies (SMART), in-situ burning, dispersants, bioremediation, booming strategies, response equipment, disposal of oily waste and other alternative countermeasures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ERT labs assist with oil identification (i.e., fingerprinting for enforcement and response activities).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ERT provides National Contingency Plan/Oil Pollution Act (NCP/OPA) interpretations for responders to oil spills.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 09 Apr 2015 15:08:56 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cgallo</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">79879 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Environmental Response Team (ERT) Laboratory and Analytic Support</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/ert/environmental-response-team-ert-laboratory-and-analytic-support</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;ERT’s fixed and mobile laboratories provide a wide variety of environmental sample analysis support for site cleanup activities (remedial and removal), emergency responses and special events. These laboratories perform routine, non-routine and specialized inorganic and organic analyses for air, soil gas, soil/sediment, water, tissue and other matrices. The analyses are primarily for ongoing EPA/ERT projects (engineering/remediation, biology, geology, air monitoring and other field activities).&lt;/p&gt;


</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 09 Apr 2015 15:05:26 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>xbstephe</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">79877 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Environmental Response Team Information Management</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/ert/environmental-response-team-information-management</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;Through experiences in the field and site-related activities, a variety of utilities and tools have been developed to assist EPA On-Scene Coordinators (OSCs), Remedial Project Managers (RPMs), and Task Leaders, as well as field personnel, in managing and performing site-related duties. Examples of support tools developed by The Environmental Response Team (ERT) are described below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scribe is a software tool developed by ERT to assist in the process of managing environmental data.  The tool captures sampling, observational and monitoring field data. Examples of Scribe field tasks include soil sampling, water sampling, air sampling and biota sampling. Scribe can import Electronic Data Deliverable (EDD) files including Analytical Lab Result EDD files and Sampling Location data EDD files such as GPS data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scribe outputs include labels for collected samples, chain-of-custody generation and analytical lab result data reports. The tool provides a flexible user interface to manage, query and view this information. In addition, it supports exporting electronic data for user services such as GIS tools and spreadsheets, so sampling data may be further analyzed and incorporated into report writing and deliverables. Scribe&#039;s Quickmap feature exports data to KML files that can then be viewed spatially using programs such as ArcGIS and Google Earth. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ertsupport.org/Scribe&quot;&gt;Scribe download&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot; class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Removal Cost Management System (RCMS) is a cost accounting and reporting system used on removal sites to track costs and usage of personnel, equipment, subcontractors and purchases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ertsupport.org/RCMS&quot;&gt;RCMS download &lt;/a&gt;&lt;a title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot; class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.epaosc.org/viper&quot;&gt;VIPER &lt;/a&gt;&lt;a title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot; class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;is a wireless network-based communications system that enables real-time transmission of data from field sensors to a local computer, remote computer or enterprise server. The communications system also provides data management, analysis and visualization. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 09 Apr 2015 15:02:11 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cgallo</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">79873 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Environmental Response Team (ERT) Health &amp; Safety</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/ert/environmental-response-team-ert-health-safety</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;EPA&#039;s Health and Safety Program &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ERT&#039;s safety experts manage EPA’s Emergency Responder Health and Safety program, ensuring the health and safety of all. ERT maintains a database to track training and medical monitoring of field employees. ERT also maintains and distributes personal protective equipment required of EPA personnel during site visits. ERT safety specialists serve as EPA’s national experts for health and safety management and oversight at Superfund sites and hazardous fieldwork sites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Personal Protection&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ERT&#039;s safety experts are charged with implementing EPA&#039;s Worker Protection Standard. In addition, they assess potential risks to all personnel at sites. ERT personnel develop, implement and monitor a variety of sampling and study activities in conjunction with air surveillance activities. ERT provides on-site safety management, including establishment and initial setup of the Incident Command System (ICS) Safety Command function for emergency response operations and large national incidents. ERT provides operational safety guidance, respiratory fit testing, site safety plan reviews, site safety audits, protocols for personal protective equipment, and continuous training for all emergency responders. ERT develops agency safety and health policy, guidance and protocols to clarify regulations, facilitate compliance, and promote occupational health and safety. ERT provides technical assistance in health and safety to various research committees and advisory boards, and co-chairs the National Response Team (NRT) Worker Safety and Health Subcommittee with the Occupational Safety and Health Administration (OSHA). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gpo.gov/fdsys/granule/CFR-2011-title40-vol28/CFR-2011-title40-vol28-part311/content-detail.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;EPA&#039;s Worker Protection Standard 40 CFR 311&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Health and Safety Assistance&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ERT reviews, evaluates and offers guidance on existing site-specific health and safety plans, emergency response plans, contingency plans, safety equipment, protocols, and standards. ERT safety staff are available to conduct on-site field safety assistance and safety audits of work sites to ensure that safety programs are set up and managed properly to provide worker protection. ERT serves as EPA&#039;s Safety-Health and Environmental Management Division&#039;s Center of Excellence for Health and Safety for Emergency Response.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/ERT/epas-safety-health-and-environmental-management-divisions-center-excellence-health-and-safety&quot;&gt;EPA&#039;s Safety-Health and Environmental Management Division&#039;s Center of Excellence for Health and Safety for Emergency Response&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 09 Apr 2015 14:58:19 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cgallo</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">79867 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Environmental Response Team (ERT) Risk Assessment</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/ert/environmental-response-team-ert-risk-assessment</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;The Environmental Response Team provides nationwide expertise on human health and ecological risk assessment in the areas of removal, remedial and emergency response. ERT is able to provide assistance to On-Scene Coordinators (OSCs) and Remedial Project Managers (RPMs) conducting risk assessments. In addition, the team  provides internal support from experts as well as contractor support to risk assessors conducting assessments for the Superfund program. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ERT has conducted or provided contractor support at many sites, including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;GE-Pittsfield/Housatonic River&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Lower Passaic River Restoration Project&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Palmerton Zinc and Anniston PCB&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Tittabawassee River cleanup&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Hurricane Katrina response&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt; Cleanup in Libby, Montana&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Pearl Harbor Naval Complex&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Upper Columbia River&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Team assistance ranges from problem formulation to support on policy and final decision making. ERT also provides assistance on sampling design, standard operating procedures, conceptual site models, measurement and assessment endpoints as well as derivation of numerical preliminary remedial goals (PRGs). &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 09 Apr 2015 14:54:25 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cgallo</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">79865 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Environmental Response Team (ERT) Remediation</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/ert/environmental-response-team-ert-remediation</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;ERT provides technical advice and field support to EPA Regions for all types of remedial actions. Services include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Remedial technology selection and evaluation&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Feasibility studies&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Treatment system design and pilot testing&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Treatment system performance monitoring, troubleshooting and optimization&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;To expedite site closures and minimize remediation costs, ERT also provides real-time, direct-sensing techniques and data visualization services to delineate source areas, quantify system effectiveness and evaluate recalcitrant hot spots. Services include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Direct-sensing site investigation&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Data visualization and conceptual site model development&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Remedial technology selection and evaluation&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Treatment system design and pilot testing&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Treatment system performance monitoring and optimization&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 09 Apr 2015 14:50:26 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>xbstephe</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">79861 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Environmental Response Team (ERT) Training</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/ert/environmental-response-team-ert-training</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;/emergency-response/national-oil-and-hazardous-substances-pollution-contingency-plan-ncp-overview&quot;&gt;National Contingency Plan (NCP)&lt;/a&gt; mandates that ERT provide introductory and intermediate training courses to prepare response personnel. ERT meets this mandate through formal and informal training initiatives. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Formal training programs include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;The Environmental Response Training Program, which provides technical and health and safety courses, exercise support, webinars, online courses and the &lt;a href=&quot;http://ertpvu.org&quot;&gt;ERTPVU.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt; website.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Training for EPA Regions on ERT-developed tools such as Scribe, Viper and Removal Cost Management System (RCMS).&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Course development and presentation at EPA training events such as National Association of Remedial Project Managers (NARPM), On-Scene Coordinator (OSC) academies, and the Radiation Task Force Leaders Program.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Quality assurance and other training for EPA employees.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;A List of currently scheduled ERTP training courses can be found on &lt;a href=&quot;https://trainex.org/bypartner_view.cfm?partner=ERTP&quot;&gt;TrainEx&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot; title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;In addition, individual ERT members provide training through:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Hands-on support, setup assistance and training at sites, and exercises and pre-deployments on equipment, health and safety, radiation safety, data management, ERT tools, and other topics.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Presentations at EPA meetings such as Regional Response Team meetings and at national and international conferences such as the International Oil Spill Conference.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Special topic training with and for EPA’s state, tribal, local and international response partners. Recent examples include uranium mining/milling training with Region 9 and Navajo tribal members and air monitoring training for the Panama Canal Authority.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 09 Apr 2015 14:46:37 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>cgallo</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">79859 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  </channel>
</rss>

<!-- Page cached by Boost @ 2017-01-26 04:02:54, expires @ 2017-01-26 16:02:54, lifetime 12 hours -->