<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?><rss version="2.0" xml:base="https://www.epa.gov/feed/61803/rss.xml" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:foaf="http://xmlns.com/foaf/0.1/" xmlns:og="http://ogp.me/ns#" xmlns:rdfs="http://www.w3.org/2000/01/rdf-schema#" xmlns:sioc="http://rdfs.org/sioc/ns#" xmlns:sioct="http://rdfs.org/sioc/types#" xmlns:skos="http://www.w3.org/2004/02/skos/core#" xmlns:xsd="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema#">
  <channel>
    <title>EPA in West Virginia</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/feed/61803/rss.xml</link>
    <description>Updated EPA in West Virginia content from the US Environmental Protection Agency</description>
    <language>en</language>
     <atom:link href="https://www.epa.gov/feed/61803/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
      <item>
    <title>Protecting Source Water in West Virginia</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/wv/protecting-source-water-west-virginia</link>
    <description>&lt;h2&gt;Stories of Progress in Achieving Healthy Waters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;U.S. EPA Region 3 Water Protection Division&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Charleston, West Virginia • January 19, 2017&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA funds helped West Virginia residents and utilities engage in source water protection efforts and emergency planning in the wake of the Elk River chemical spill of 2014. The spill contaminated the water supply of nearly 300,000 people in the capitol city Charleston as well as multiple surrounding counties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The West Virginia Department of Environmental Protection (WVDEP) used $15,000 from its &lt;a href=&quot;/nps/319-grant-program-states-and-territories&quot;&gt;EPA Section 319 grant&lt;/a&gt; to support a community education and engagement project to involve citizens in plans to protect their drinking water sources. The $15,000 was the largest contribution to the $50,000 project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The “Safe Water for WV” project led by the West Virginia Rivers Coalition (WVRC) included a series of public forums, educational tools, local partner network building and technical assistance to provide citizens with information on source water planning and their role in the process. A key activity was the development of a “&lt;a href=&quot;https://3ed59980-a-62cb3a1a-s-sites.googlegroups.com/site/wvrivers/archive/SWPPToolkit.pdf?attachauth=ANoY7cpid-yC4OPQ-3-npZES3-VhQV1QdiWp6Cvn3Lrt70jgzuMaJkP1B_6ghzvv0EQOrlPoZwLL-T2ZzaJgQ9I7WFJhXsNLjGMfj4X6Ikctmc-pidaaEhlpmGjgoo4uFSdR_Zk5K42yURiVzB-WYRC8gGVlxn7j1MbLmfTvoq46xdP2r7NDpZIHgzEngkHSL5VRME1kDuJcnIPSrGRxg46OS54J7XpKmfUqqocjtezGCLm8VA0jtfc%3D&amp;amp;attredirects=0&quot;&gt;Citizen’s Guide to Drinking Water Protection&lt;/a&gt;.” &lt;a title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot; class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A law passed by the state after the spill (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.legis.state.wv.us/Bill_Status/bills_text.cfm?billdoc=SB373%20SUB2%20ENR.htm&amp;amp;yr=2014&amp;amp;sesstype=RS&amp;amp;i=373&quot;&gt;SB 373&lt;/a&gt;) &lt;a title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot; class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt; required public water systems across the state to draft or update source water protection plans with the public’s involvement. The plans are designed to help manage pollution from general sources that could endanger drinking water supplies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Per WVRC, the Elk River chemical leak and ensuing water crisis was an awakening for many to the sources and vulnerability of their water supplies. It was the first time many people thought about where their drinking water comes from and the connection between watershed protection, public health and economic security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among the results of the Safe Water for WV project were five public forums attended by at least 345 community members, 72 local partners and 10 public water utilities. The Citizen’s Guide was distributed at the forum and was discussed in a statewide webinar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the education project, EPA’s Mid-Atlantic Region worked with the West Virginia Bureau of Public Health to hold five tabletop exercises around the state to improve emergency preparedness, response and source water protection. EPA also partnered with stakeholders in West Virginia to develop a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wvdhhr.org/oehs/eed/swap/documents/SB_373/Updated_2016/5_Supplemental%20Guide%20IV-EWMS_draft_1_26_16.pdf&quot;&gt;fact sheet&lt;/a&gt; on early warning and response to help utilities comply with the new source water protection legislation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The WVDEP will use funds from its 2017 319 grant to involve the public in a pilot project integrating Source Water Protection Plans and Watershed Based Plans in two watersheds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg view-mode-medium&quot; style=&quot;width:448px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;Map of West Virginia highlighted in yellow by counties affected by the Elk River spill, Putnam, Roane, Logan, Lincoln, Kanawha, Jackson, Clay, Cabell and Boone.&quot; height=&quot;346&quot; width=&quot;448&quot; class=&quot;media-element file-medium&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/medium/public/2017-01/wv_multiplecounties.jpg&quot; title=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 19 Jan 2017 13:54:34 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>nholomuz</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">169509 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Tentative Approval and Opportunity for Public Comment and Public Hearing for Public Water System Supervision Program Revision for West Virginia</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/wv/tentative-approval-and-opportunity-public-comment-and-public-hearing-public-water-system</link>
    <description></description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 12 Jan 2017 16:11:19 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>tscipion</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">168897 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Additional Documents Relating to the Tentative Approval for Public Water System Supervision Program Revision for West Virginia</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/wv/additional-documents-relating-tentative-approval-public-water-system-supervision-program-revision</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;Documents include the Primacy Revision Application from the West Virginia Department of Health and Human Resources which includes a crosswalk showing how the state rule is consistent with the Federal rule, an Attorney General Statement and other required documents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-345387&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2017-01/documents/letterfromstate.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=159226&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Cover Letter from State to EPA Regional Administrator (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(1 pg, 159 K, 
  September 30, 2015)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-345395&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2017-01/documents/agstatement.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=89774&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;West Virginia Attorney General&amp;#039;s Statement (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(1 pg, 90 K, 
  September 30, 2015)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-345405&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2017-01/documents/lettertostate_0.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=78154&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Letter to State for Receipt of Primacy Application (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(1 pg, 78 K, 
  December 7, 2015)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-345411&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2017-01/documents/memos.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=123571&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Memos to the file and other records documenting what EPA reviewed and found (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(2 pp, 124 K, 
  December 7, 2015 and January 12, 2016)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-345415&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2017-01/documents/orcmemo.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=75283&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;EPA Office of Regional Counsel Concurrence Memo (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(1 pg, 75 K, 
  January 29, 2016)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-345419&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2017-01/documents/ogwdwmemo.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=88068&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;EPA Office of Ground Water &amp;amp; Drinking Water&amp;#039;s Concurrence Memo (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(1 pg, 88 K, 
  August 4, 2016)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-345427&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2017-01/documents/tentativeapprovalletter.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=122793&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Letter to State on Tentative Approval of Primacy Revision (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(1 pg, 123 K, 
  2016)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 12 Jan 2017 15:53:55 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>tscipion</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">168889 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Action Resolves Hundreds of Coal Companies’ Violations</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/wv/action-resolves-hundreds-coal-companies-violations</link>
    <description>&lt;h2&gt;Stories of Progress in Achieving Healthy Waters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;U.S. EPA Region 3 Water Protection Division&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Appalachia• October 29, 2015&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A consent decree with a major coal company and its subsidiaries resolves Clean Water Act violations in five states and requires operational upgrades and other steps to ensure future compliance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arch Coal Inc., one of the nation’s largest coal companies, and 14 of its subsidiaries under the International Coal Group Inc. (ICG) agreed in a settlement with EPA and the U.S. Department of Justice to conduct comprehensive upgrades to their operations to ensure compliance with the Clean Water Act.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;/enforcement/arch-coal-inc-and-international-coal-group-subsidiaries-settlement&quot;&gt;settlement&lt;/a&gt; resolves hundreds of Clean Water Act violations related to illegal discharges of pollutants at the companies’ coal mines in Kentucky, Pennsylvania, Maryland, Virginia and West Virginia. The companies will also pay a $2 million civil penalty and must implement measures to ensure compliance and prevent future Clean Water Act violations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA Regional Administrator Shawn M. Garvin called the settlement “good news for water quality in the Appalachian region, and especially for the people living in the overburdened and underserved communities. It represents an important step forward by requiring these companies to take necessary actions to reduce pollution from their mining operations.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additional measures required by the settlement include: &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Developing and implementing a compliance management system. &lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Conducting internal and third-party environmental compliance audits.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Maintaining a database system to track violations, sampling data and compliance efforts.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Providing training for environmental managers and others responsible for the consent decree.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Paying escalating stipulated penalties if violations continue to occur.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;A government complaint filed concurrently with the settlement alleged that in the last six years, ICG operations violated discharge limits for aluminum, manganese, iron and total suspended solids in their state-issued National Pollution Discharge Elimination System permits on more than 1,200 occasions, resulting in over 8,900 days of violations. Of those violations, 700 had been previously resolved by state enforcement actions in Kentucky and West Virginia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA discovered the violations through inspections of ICG facilities and projects, reviewing information provided by the companies and coordinating with the affected state governments. The states of West Virginia, Virginia and Pennsylvania were co-plaintiffs in the settlement. The consent decree was lodged in the U.S. District Court for the Southern District of West Virginia on Aug. 6, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg left view-mode-medium&quot; style=&quot;width:399px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;A map showing the Appalachia region of the United States. &quot; height=&quot;264&quot; width=&quot;399&quot; class=&quot;left media-element file-medium left&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/medium/public/2016-11/appalachia_20151029.jpg&quot; title=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-334249&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-11/documents/multi_state_progress_-_action_resolves_hundreds_of_coal_companies_violations_-_20151029.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=618516&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Action Resolves Hundreds of Coal Companies’ Violations (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(1 pg, 619 K, 
  10/29/2015)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 23 Nov 2016 15:50:25 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>nholomuz</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">165639 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Martinsburg Plant Upgrade Helps Waters Near and Far</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/wv/martinsburg-plant-upgrade-helps-waters-near-and-far</link>
    <description>&lt;h2&gt;Stories of Progress in Achieving Healthy Waters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;U.S. EPA Region 3 Water Protection Division&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Martinsburg, West Virginia • October 27, 2016&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With key financial assistance from EPA, the City of Martinsburg, W.V., has revamped its wastewater treatment plant to achieve steep pollution reductions that will benefit local creeks and the Chesapeake Bay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project is the latest example of wastewater treatment upgrades that are helping the sector &lt;a href=&quot;/sites/production/files/2016-06/documents/wastewater_progress_report_06142016.pdf&quot;&gt;lead the way&lt;/a&gt; in meeting the Bay’s restoration goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA, through the West Virginia Department of Environmental Protection, provided nearly $30 million for the $53.3 million project in a 20-year, 1 percent low interest loan from the Clean Water State Revolving Fund.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The improvements increased the plant’s treatment capacity to a flow of 12 million gallons per day, helping to accommodate volume surges during heavy rains from the city’s older areas where stormwater and wastewater are not separated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Martinsburg Utilities Director Steve Knipe said in a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=oEzJ1hwNXOc&quot;&gt;YouTube video&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot; class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt; that the system could get a flow increase from 2 million to 10 million gallons per day “in a matter of hours” during a major storm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The upgrade to this Advanced Wastewater Treatment has led to deep drops in nitrogen and phosphorus levels in the plant’s effluent, benefitting the Tuscarora and Opequon creeks, as well as the Potomac River and the Bay. For example, Knipe said that nitrogen levels fell more than 80 percent from an average of 12,078 pounds per month early this year to 2,206 in September after the plant went online. Phosphorus dropped from an average 1,043 pounds to 290 in that same timeframe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Knipe praised the plant’s operating staff for meeting the challenges of keeping the facility running during three years of construction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Said EPA Regional Administrator Shawn M. Garvin, “The major pollution reductions resulting from this new plant will have a significant impact on local waters and the Chesapeake Bay. The City of Martinsburg is to be congratulated for its efforts to improve the quality of life for its residents and to help West Virginia do its share to meet the Bay pollution reduction goals.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg view-mode-medium&quot; style=&quot;width:448px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;A map of West Virginia highlighting the location of Martinsburg&quot; height=&quot;346&quot; width=&quot;448&quot; class=&quot;media-element file-medium&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/medium/public/2016-11/wv_martinsburg_20161025.jpg&quot; title=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-328897&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-11/documents/wv_progress_-_martinsburg_plant_upgrade_helps_waters_near_and_far.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=644024&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;Martinsburg Plant Upgrade Helps Waters Near and Far (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(1 pg, 644 K, 
  10/27/2016)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;field field-name-field-document-description field-type-text field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    With key financial assistance from EPA, the City of Martinsburg, W.V., has revamped its wastewater treatment plant to achieve steep pollution reductions that will benefit local creeks and the Chesapeake Bay.  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 02 Nov 2016 17:03:30 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>apruzins</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">164203 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>New Wastewater Plant Reduces Pollution in West Virginia</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/wv/new-wastewater-plant-reduces-pollution-west-virginia</link>
    <description>&lt;h2&gt;Stories of Progress in Achieving Healthy Waters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;U.S. EPA Region 3 Water Protection Division&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Romney, West Virginia • September 15, 2016&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A new state-of-the-art wastewater treatment plant in Romney, West Virginia, has made a “dramatic improvement” in reducing pollution to local waters and the Chesapeake Bay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nitrogen and phosphorous, along with other regulated pollutants, are down sharply since the $14 million plant began operation in 2015. Charts show that in just one month, nitrogen dropped from 16 mg/l to less than 3 mg/l and have been below 2 mg/l during some monitoring months. Phosphorus fell from 3 mg/l to below .25 mg/l, although the plant is working to control a recent rise in those levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reductions are designed to help the city meet state permit limits reflected in West Virginia’s Watershed Improvement Plan for the Chesapeake Bay. The city was under a consent order to meet the effluent limits by the end of 2015. The treated effluent discharges to Big Run of the South Branch of the Potomac River.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project received $5.6 million from EPA’s &lt;a href=&quot;/cwsrf&quot;&gt;Clean Water State Revolving Fund&lt;/a&gt; through the West Virginia Department of Environmental Protection, including $2 million as essentially a grant and $3.6 million in a low-interest loan. Funding was also provided through other federal, state and local sources, including a $500,000 EPA grant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The former plant, which was nearing its 500,000 gallons per day design capacity, had aging and failing equipment with pumps unable to handle sewage volumes during wet weather events, officials said. The new plant, built on the same site and serving more than 1,000 households, is rated to handle 750,000 gallons per day with room for at least one additional basin, providing capacity for new customers requesting sanitary sewer service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I’ve done a lot of water and sewer projects in my career. This is definitely one of the highlights,” said Daniel Ferrell, the project manager from the Thrasher Group. “We’ve seen a dramatic improvement in nitrogen, phosphorus, BOD (biological oxygen demand) and TSS (Total Suspended Solids).”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project included the rehabilitation of four lift stations, a new pretreatment works, two &lt;a href=&quot;https://www3.epa.gov/npdes/pubs/sbr_new.pdf&quot;&gt;Sequencing Batch Reactor (SBR)&lt;/a&gt; basins, two digesters, multiple chemical feed systems, a public works building, a laboratory/office/plant building, and other system improvements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The clarity (of the effluent) is unbelievable,” said Don Compton, the plant’s chief operator. “It’s just like water out of the tap.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg left view-mode-medium&quot; style=&quot;width:448px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;A map of West Virginia highlighting the location of Romney&quot; height=&quot;346&quot; width=&quot;448&quot; class=&quot;left media-element file-medium left&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/medium/public/2016-09/wv_romney.jpg&quot; title=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-323321&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-10/documents/wv_progress_-_new_wastewater_plant_reduces_pollution.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=626883&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;New Wastewater Plant Reduces Pollution in West Virginia (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(1 pg, 627 K, 
  09/15/2016)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;field field-name-field-document-description field-type-text field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    A new state-of-the-art wastewater treatment plant in Romney, West Virginia, has made a &amp;quot;dramatic improvement&amp;quot; in reducing pollution to local waters and the Chesapeake Bay.  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 13 Oct 2016 14:55:03 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>apruzins</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">162541 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>High Tech Systems Help Low-Income Families Deal with Sewage Problems</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/wv/high-tech-systems-help-low-income-families-deal-sewage-problems</link>
    <description>&lt;h2&gt;Stories of Progress in Achieving Healthy Waters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;U.S. EPA Region 3 Water Protection Division&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Lincoln County, West Virginia • March 19, 2015&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA-funded septic systems are making a difference in a distressed West Virginia community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Left Fork of the Mud River watershed – one of the poorest and most rural areas of West Virginia – old, failing septic tanks were causing major problems. Raw sewage was being discharged into streams and creeks, contributing to high levels of E. coli bacteria. In one case, sewage regularly ponded under a family home, spreading 30 feet into the yard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Magdalene Cunningham of the EPA Mid-Atlantic Region’s Water Protection Division recalls seeing a kids’ swing set in the middle of one of the impacted properties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, after five phases of work over 10 years with nearly $4 million in EPA funding, the 117th home in this area of Lincoln County is about to get one of the innovative septic systems that have improved water quality, reduced public health threats and drawn the community together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The majority of homes in the watershed are too close to creeks or don’t have enough room for conventional septic systems. Instead, the project involves installing high-tech systems that use peat as a secondary treatment and ultraviolet light as the final disinfectant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Residents who were once skeptical about whether the government funds would ever reach their doorsteps began lining up to be next after seeing that their neighbors “didn’t have septic in their yards and the creek didn’t smell bad anymore,” said Ric MacDowell, director of the Lincoln County Green Wastewater Project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, MacDowell said one of the biggest benefits of the project has been the residents’ involvement. They’ve formed a non-profit wastewater management association and pay $8 a month to have a contractor inspect their systems twice a year. If problems are found, the homeowner pays only 30 percent of the repair cost; the association picks up the rest. MacDowell said sampling has shown improvements in tributaries of the Left Fork. Water samples with acceptable levels of under 200 E. coli colonies per 100 ml rose from 34% between 2005 and 2010 to 57% between 2011 and 2013.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project has involved a partnership between the West Virginia Department of Environmental Protection, the state Department of Health and Human Resources, and the Lincoln County Commission. The EPA financing includes a $1 million grant (&lt;a href=&quot;http://water.epa.gov/infrastructure/septic/upload/mudriverwv_finalreport.pdf&quot;&gt;Phase 1&lt;/a&gt;) and then four rounds of Clean Water State Revolving Fund loans with 100 percent principal forgiveness totaling $2.86 million.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg left view-mode-medium&quot; style=&quot;width:448px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;A map of West Virginia highlighting the location of Lincoln County&quot; height=&quot;346&quot; width=&quot;448&quot; class=&quot;left media-element file-medium left&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/medium/public/2016-09/wv_lincolncounty_20160226.jpg&quot; title=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-319129&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-09/documents/wv_progress_-_high_tech_systems_help_low_income_families_deal_with_sewage_-_20150319.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=697669&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;High Tech Systems Help Low-Income Families Deal with Sewage Problems (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(1 pg, 698 K, 
  03/19/2015)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;field field-name-field-document-description field-type-text field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    EPA-funded septic systems are making a difference in a distressed West Virginia community  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2016 15:13:32 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>nholomuz</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">161373 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>EPA News and Events for West Virginia</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/wv/epa-news-and-events-west-virginia</link>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;Click on data points for more information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe width=&quot;930&quot; height=&quot;600&quot; title=&quot;West Virginia State Map&quot; src=&quot;https://epa.maps.arcgis.com/apps/Embed/index.html?webmap=1ace33f803044f5282c6f201d6238719&amp;amp;extent=-86.0885,35.8352,-73.6409,41.6807&amp;amp;zoom=true&amp;amp;scale=true&amp;amp;disable_scroll=true&amp;amp;theme=light&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Wed, 21 Sep 2016 18:36:26 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>jgrave04</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">160845 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>New Plant Tops Projections for Reducing Pollution to Bay, Local Waters</title>
    <link>https://www.epa.gov/wv/new-plant-tops-projections-reducing-pollution-bay-local-waters</link>
    <description>&lt;h2&gt;Stories of Progress in Achieving Healthy Waters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;U.S. EPA Region 3 Water Protection Division&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Moorefield, West Virginia • September 24, 2015&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A new wastewater treatment plant in West Virginia, considered a key to meeting the state’s commitment to help restore the Chesapeake Bay, is exceeding expectations for pollution reduction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Moorefield Regional Wastewater Treatment Plant is well below its discharge permit limits for nitrogen and phosphorus as it approaches the end of its annual monitoring period, according to Lucas Gagnon, president of the Moorefield/Hardy County Wastewater Authority.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The plant is contributing to the overall success of the wastewater sector in employing advanced treatment processes to reduce pollution to the Chesapeake Bay and local rivers and streams. The Moorefield plant is expected to remove more than 90,000 pounds of nitrogen and 93,000 pounds of phosphorus from West Virginia wastewater each year, accounting for a sizeable portion of the total nutrient reductions projected in the state’s Bay restoration plans. The plant replaced four older ones that would have needed costly upgrades, including two operated by poultry giant, Pilgrim’s Pride, a nearby major employer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EPA provided a bulk of the funding for the $40 million project - $18 million from the Clean Water State Revolving Fund (through the West Virginia State Revolving Fund) and a grant of $5.5 million.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Moorefield plant discharges to the South Branch of the Potomac River, a tributary of the Chesapeake Bay and a popular fishing and recreational resource. In a Bay Program &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.chesapeakebay.net/videos/clip/restoration_spotlight_wastewater_overhal_will_cut_pollution_in_west_virgini&quot;&gt;video,&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a title=&quot;EPA&#039;s External Link Disclaimer&quot; class=&quot;exit-disclaimer&quot; href=&quot;/home/exit-epa&quot;&gt;Exit&lt;/a&gt; Gagnon says that while local residents appreciate the need to reduce nutrients in the Bay, “the biggest benefit” is closer to home with a “cleaner, better river to enjoy.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While monitoring of stream health is underway, “there’s an obvious impact of having a discharge as clean as or cleaner than the river,” said Mike Warwick, an engineer for the West Virginia Department of Environmental Protection (WVDEP). “That wasn’t the case for the past 30 to 40 years. There will be a huge benefit.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the plant opened in November 2013, there was an adjustment period in knocking down phosphorus levels. “It took a while for the biological phosphorus bugs to circulate through the plant and get to work,” Gagnon said. But once they took hold, the numbers have been impressive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With four months to go in the reporting year, the treatment plant has discharged 13,978 pounds of nitrogen – far short of its 51,431 pound annual limit, according to Gagnon. For phosphorus, the data indicates a discharge of 2,084 pounds, well under the plant’s 5,221 pound limit. “Between the quality of construction and the operation of the system, we couldn’t be happier,” said Warwick of the WVDEP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
    class=&quot;figure image file file-image file-image-jpeg left view-mode-medium&quot; style=&quot;width:448px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;A map of West Virginia highlighting the location of Moorefield.&quot; height=&quot;346&quot; width=&quot;448&quot; class=&quot;left media-element file-medium left&quot; typeof=&quot;foaf:Image&quot; src=&quot;/sites/production/files/styles/medium/public/2016-07/wv_moorefield_20160226.jpg&quot; title=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class=&quot;field field-name-field-file field-type-file field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;

      &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;span id=&quot;file-302353&quot; class=&quot;file file-document file-application-pdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/sites/production/files/2016-07/documents/wv_progress_-_plant_exceeding_expectations_-_20150924.pdf&quot; type=&quot;application/pdf; length=634561&quot; class=&quot;file-link&quot;&gt;New Plant Tops Projections for Reducing Pollution to Bay, Local Waters (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;fileinfo&quot;&gt;(1 pg, 635 K, 
  09/24/2015)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;field field-name-field-document-description field-type-text field-label-hidden&quot;&gt;
    A new wastewater treatment plant in West Virginia, considered a key to meeting the state’s commitment to help restore the Chesapeake Bay, is exceeding expectations for pollution reduction.  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
     <pubDate>Thu, 21 Jul 2016 14:37:26 +0000</pubDate>
 <dc:creator>apruzins</dc:creator>
 <guid isPermaLink="false">155451 at https://www.epa.gov</guid>
  </item>
  </channel>
</rss>

<!-- Page cached by Boost @ 2017-01-26 04:04:27, expires @ 2017-01-26 16:04:27, lifetime 12 hours -->